PART TWO

9

While I was writing this book, out in New Salem, Illinois, my good friend Henry Pond, a local attorney, said to me a number of times:

“You ought to go and see Uncle Jimmy Miles, for one of his uncles, Herndon, was Lincoln's law partner, and one of his aunts ran a boarding-house where Mr. and Mrs. Lincoln lived for a while.”

That sounded like an interesting lead; so Mr. Pond and I climbed into his car one Sunday afternoon in July, and drove out to the Miles farm near New Salem—a farm where Lincoln used to stop and swap stories for a drink of cider while walking to Springfeld to borrow law-books.

When we arrived, Uncle Jimmy dragged a trio of rockingchairs out into the shade of a huge maple tree in the front yard; and there, while young turkeys and little ducks ran noisily through the grass about us, we talked for hours; and Uncle Jimmy related an illuminating and pathetic incident about Lincoln that has never been put into print heretofore. The story is this:

Mr. Miles's Aunt Catherine married a physician named Jacob M. Early. About a year after Lincoln arrived in Springfeld—during the night of March 11, 1838, to be exact—an unknown man on horseback rode up to Dr. Early's house, knocked, called the physician to the door, emptiedboth barrels of a shot-gun into his body, then leaped upon a horse and dashed away.

Small as Springfeld was at the time, no one was ever charged with the murder, and the killing remains a mystery to this day.

Dr. Early left a very small estate; so his widow was obliged to take in boarders to support herself; and, shortly after their marriage, Mr. and Mrs. Abraham Lincoln came to Mrs. Early's home to live.

Uncle Jimmy Miles told me that he had often heard his aunt, Dr. Early's widow, relate the following incident: One morning Mr. and Mrs. Lincoln were having breakfast when Lincoln did something that aroused the fiery temper of his wife. What, no one remembers now. But Mrs. Lincoln, in a rage, dashed a cup of hot coffee into her husband's face. And she did it in front of the other boarders.

Saying nothing, Lincoln sat there in humiliation and silence while Mrs. Early came with a wet towel and wiped off his face and clothes. That incident was probably typical of the married life of the Lincolns for the next quarter of a century.

Springfeld had eleven attorneys, and they couldn't all make a living there; so they used to ride horseback from one countyseat to another, following Judge David Davis while he was holding court in the various places throughout the Eighth Judicial District. The other attorneys always managed to get back to Springfeld each Saturday and spend the week-end with their families.

But Lincoln didn't. He dreaded to go home, and for three months in the spring, and again for three months in the autumn, he remained out on the circuit and never went near Springfeld.

He kept this up year after year. Living conditions in the country hotels were often wretched; but wretched as they were, he preferred them to his own home and Mrs. Lincoln's constant nagging and wild outburstsof temper. “She vexed and harassed the soul out of him—” that was what the neighbors said; and the neighbors knew, for they saw her, and they couldn't help hearing her.

Mrs. Lincoln's “loud shrill voice,” says Senator Beveridge, “could be heard across the street, and her incessant outbursts of wrath were audible to all who lived near the house. Frequently her anger was displayed by other means than words, and accounts of her violence are numerous and unimpeachable.”

“She led her husband a wild and merry dance,” says Herndon.

And Herndon felt he knew why “she unchained the bitterness of a disappointed and outraged nature.”

It was her desire for vengeance. “He had crushed her proud womanly spirit,” suggests Herndon, and “she felt degraded in the eyes of the world: Love fed at the approach of revenge.”

She was always complaining, always criticizing her husband; nothing about him was ever right: He was stoopshouldered, he walked awkwardly and lifted his feet straight up and down like an Indian. She complained that there was no spring to his step, no grace to his movements; and she mimicked his gait and nagged at him to walk with his toes pointed down, as she had been taught at Madame Mentelle's.

She didn't like the way his huge ears stood out at right angles from his head. She even told him that his nose wasn't straight, that his lower lip stuck out, that he looked consumptive, that his feet and hands were too large, his head too small.

His shocking indifference to his personal appearance grated on her sensitive nature, and made her woefully unhappy. “Mrs. Lincoln,” says Herndon, “was not a wildcat without cause.” Sometimes her husband walked down the street with one trouser leg stuffed inside his boot-top and the other dangling on the outside. His boots were seldom blackenedor greased. His collar often needed changing, his coat frequently needed brushing.

James Gourly, who lived next door to the Lincolns for years, wrote: “Mr. Lincoln used to come to our house, his feet encased in a pair of loose slippers, and with an old faded pair of trousers fastened with one suspender—” or “gallis” as Lincoln himself called it.

In warm weather he made extended trips “wearing a dirty linen duster for a coat, on the back of which the perspiration had splotched wide stains that resembled a map of the continent.”

A young lawyer who once saw Lincoln in a country hotel, getting ready for bed, and clad “in a home made yellow fannel night shirt” that reached “halfway between his knees and his ankles,” exclaimed, “He was the ungodliest fgure I ever saw.”

He never owned a razor in his life, and he didn't visit a barber as frequently as Mrs. Lincoln thought he should.

He neglected to groom his coarse, bushy hair, that stood out all over his head like horsehair. That irritated Mary Todd beyond words, and when she combed it, it was soon mussed again, by his bank-book, letters, and legal papers, which he carried in the top of his hat.

One day he was having his picture taken in Chicago, and the photographer urged him to “slick up” a bit. He replied that “a portrait of a slicked-up Lincoln wouldn't be recognized down in Springfeld.”

His table manners were large and free. He didn't hold his knife right, and he didn't even lay it on his plate right. He had no skill whatever in the art of eating fsh with a fork and a crust of bread. Sometimes he tilted the meat platter and raked or slid a pork chop off onto his plate. Mrs. Lincoln raised “merry war” with him because he persisted in using his own knife for the butter; and once when he put chicken bones on the side dish on which his lettuce had been served, she almost fainted.

She complained and scolded because he didn't stand up when ladies came into the room; because he didn't jump around to take their wraps, and didn't see callers to the door when they left.

He loved to read lying down. As soon as he came home from the offce, he took off his coat and shoes and collar and dropped his one “gallis” from his shoulder, turned a chair upside down in the hallway, padded its sloping back with a pillow, propped his head and shoulders against it, and stretched out on the foor.

In that position he would lie and read for hours—usually the newspapers. Sometimes he read what he considered a very humorous story about an earthquake, from a book entitled “Flush Times in Alabama.” Often, very often, he read poetry. And whatever he read, he read aloud. He had gotten the habit from the “blab” schools back in Indiana. He also felt that by reading aloud he could impress a thing on his sense of hearing as well as his sense of sight, and so remember it longer.

Sometimes he would lie on the floor and close his eyes and quote Shakspere or Byron or Poe; for example:

For the moon never beams without bringing me dreams
Of the beautiful Annabel Lee,
And the stars never rise, but I feel the bright eyes
Of the beautiful Annabel Lee.

A lady—a relative—who lived with the Lincolns two years says that one evening Lincoln was lying down in the hall, reading, when company came. Without waiting for the servant to answer the door, he got up in his shirtsleeves, ushered the callers into the parlor, and said he would “trot the women folks out.”

Mrs. Lincoln from an adjoining room witnessed the ladies' entrance, and overheard her husband's jocose expression. Her indignation was so instantaneous she made the situation exceedingly interesting for him, and he was glad to retreat from the mansion. He did not return until very late at night, and then slipped quietly in at a rear door.

Mrs. Lincoln was violently jealous, and she had little use for Joshua Speed. He had been her husband's intimate friend, and she suspected that he might have infuenced Lincoln to run away from his wedding. Before his marriage, Lincoln had been in the habit of ending his letters to Speed with “Love to Fanny.” But, after the marriage, Mrs. Lincoln demanded that that greeting be tempered down to “Regards to Mrs. Speed.”

Lincoln never forgot a favor. That was one of his outstanding characteristics; so, as a little gesture of appreciation, he had promised that the frst boy would be named Joshua Speed Lincoln. But when Mary Todd heard it she burst out in a storm. It was her child, and she was going to name it! And, what was more, the name was not going to be Joshua Speed! It was going to be Robert Todd, after her own father... and so on and so on.

It is hardly necessary to add that the boy was named Robert Todd. He was the only one of the four Lincoln children to reach maturity. Eddie died in 1850 at Springfeld—age 4. Willie died in the White House—age 12. Tad died in Chicago in 1871—age 18. Robert Todd Lincoln died in Manchester, Vermont, July 26, 1926—age 83.

Mrs. Lincoln complained because the yard was without flowers, shrubs, or color. So Lincoln set out a few roses, but he took no interest in them and they soon perished of neglect. She urged him to plant a garden, and one spring he did, but the weeds overran it.

Though he was not much given to physical exertion, he did feed and curry “Old Buck” ; he also “fed and milked his own cow and sawed his own wood.” And he continued to do this, even after he was electedPresident, until he left Springfeld.

However, John Hanks, Lincoln's second cousin, once remarked that “Abe was not good at any kind of work except dreamin'.” And Mary Lincoln agreed with him.

Lincoln was absent-minded, often sank into curious spells of abstraction, and appeared to be entirely oblivious of the earth and everything that was on it. On Sundays, he would put one of his babies into a little wagon and haul the child up and down the rough sidewalk in front of his house. Sometimes the little chap happened to roll overboard. But Lincoln pulled steadily ahead, his eyes fxed on the ground, unconscious of the loud lamentations behind him. He never knew what had happened until Mrs. Lincoln thrust her head out at the door and yelled at him in a shrill, angry voice.

Sometimes he came into the house after a day at the office and looked at her and apparently didn't see her and didn't even speak. He was seldom interested in food; after she had prepared a meal, she frequently had hard work to get him into the dining-room. She called, but he seemed not to hear. He would sit down at the table and stare off dreamily into space, and forget to eat until she reminded him of it.

After dinner he sometimes stared into the freplace for half an hour at a time, saying nothing. The boys literally crawled all over him and pulled his hair and talked to him, but he seemed unconscious of their existence. Then suddenly he would come to and tell a joke or recite one of his favorite verses:

Oh, why should the spirit of mortal be proud?
Like a swift-fleeting meteor, a fast-flying cloud,
A flash of the lightning, a break of the wave,
He passes from life to his rest in the grave.

Mrs. Lincoln criticized him for never correcting the children. But he so adored them that “he was blind and deaf to their faults.” “He never neglected to praise them for any of their good acts,” said Mrs. Lincoln, “and declared: It is my pleasure that my children are free and happy, and unrestrained by parental tyranny. Love is the chain whereby to bind a child to its parents.”

The liberties he allowed his children at times appear extraordinary. For example, once when he was playing chess with a judge of the Supreme Court, Robert came and told his father it was time to go to dinner. Lincoln replied, “Yes, yes.” But, being very fond of the game, he quite forgot that he had been called, and played on.

Again the boy appeared, with another urgent message from Mrs. Lincoln. Again Lincoln promised to come, again he forgot.

A third time Robert arrived with a summons, a third time Lincoln promised, and a third time he played on. Then, suddenly, the boy drew back and violently kicked the chess-board higher than the players' heads, scattering the chessmen in every direction.

“Well, Judge,” Lincoln said with a smile, “I reckon we'll have to fnish this game some other time.”

Lincoln apparently never even thought of correcting his son.

The Lincoln boys used to hide behind a hedge in the evening and stick a lath through the fence. As there were no street lights, passers-by would run into the lath and their hats would be knocked off. Once, in the darkness, the boys knocked off their father's hat by mistake. He didn't censure them, but merely told them that they ought to be careful, for they might make somebody mad.

Lincoln did not belong to any church, and avoided religious discussions even with his best friends. However, he once told Herndonthat his religious code was like that of an old man named Glenn, in Indiana, whom he had heard speak at a church meeting, and who said: “When I do good, I feel good, when I do bad I feel bad, and that's my religion.”

On Sunday mornings, as the children grew older, he usually took them out for a stroll, but once he left them at home and went to the First Presbyterian Church with Mrs. Lincoln. Half an hour later Tad came into the house and, missing his father, ran down the street and dashed into the church during the sermon. His hair was awry, his shoes unbuttoned, his stockings sagging down, and his face and hands were grimy with the black soil of Illinois. Mrs. Lincoln, herself elegantly attired, was shocked and embarrassed; but Lincoln calmly stretched out one of his long arms and lovingly drew Tad to him and held the boy's head close against his breast.

Sometimes on Sunday morning, Lincoln took the boys downtown to his offce. There they were permitted to run wild. “They soon gutted the shelves of books,” says Herndon, “rifed the drawers and riddled boxes, battered the point of my gold pen... threw the pencils into the spittoon, turned over the inkstands on the papers, scattered letters over the offce and danced on them.”

And Lincoln “never reproved them or gave them a fatherly frown. He was the most indulgent parent I have ever known,” Herndon concludes.

Mrs. Lincoln seldom went to the offce; but when she did, she was shocked. She had reason to be: the place had no order, no system, things were piled about everywhere. Lincoln tied up one bundle of papers and labeled it thus: “When you can't fnd it anywhere else, look in here.”

As speed said, Lincoln's habits were “regularly irregular.”

On one wall loomed a huge black stain, marking the place where one law student had hurled an inkstand at another one's head—and missed.

The office was seldom swept and almost never scrubbed. Some garden seeds that were lying on top of the bookcase had started to sprout and grow there, in the dust and dirt.

10

In most respects, there wasn't a more economical housewife in all Springfield than Mary Lincoln. She was extravagant chiefly in matters having to do with showing off. She bought a carriage when the Lincolns could ill afford it and paid a neighbor's boy twenty-fve cents an afternoon for driving her about town to make social calls. The place was a mere village, and she could have walked or hired a vehicle. But no, that would have been beneath her. And no matter how poor they were, she could always fnd money for clothes costing more than she could afford.

In 1844, the Lincolns paid ffteen hundred dollars for the home of the Rev. Charles Dresser who, two years before, had performed their marriage ceremony. The house had a livingroom, kitchen, parlor, bedrooms; and, in the back yard, there was a woodpile, an outhouse, and a barn where Lincoln kept his cow and Old Buck.

At frst the place seemed to Mary Lincoln an earthly paradise; and it was, in comparison with the bleak, bare rooms of the boarding-house she had just left. Besides, she had the new-found joy and pride of ownership. But its perfections soon began to fade, and she was forever fnding fault with the home. Her sister lived in a huge two-story house, and this one was only a story and a half high. She once told Lincoln that no man who ever amounted to much lived in a story-and-a-half house.

Usually, when she asked him for anything, he never inquired whether it was necessary. “You know what you want,” he would say, “so go and get it.” But in this instance, he rebelled: the family was small, and thehouse was entirely adequate. Besides, he was a poor man: he had only fve hundred dollars when they were married, and he had not added much to it since. He knew that they couldn't afford to enlarge the house; and she knew it also; but she kept on urging and complaining. Finally, in order to quiet her, he had a contractor estimate the cost, and Lincoln told him to make it high. He did, and Lincoln showed her the fgures. She gasped, and he imagined that settled the matter.

But he was too hopeful, for the next time he went away on the circuit she called in another carpenter, got a lower estimate, and ordered the work done at once.

When Lincoln returned to Springfeld and walked down Eighth Street, he hardly recognized his own house. Meeting a friend, he inquired with mock seriousness, “Stranger, can you tell me where Mr. Lincoln lives?”

His income from the law was not large; and he often had, as he put it, “hard scratching” to meet his bills. And now he had come home to fnd a large and unnecessary carpenter bill added to his burdens.

It saddened him, and he said so.

Mrs. Lincoln answered him in the only way that she knew how to react to a criticism—with an attack. She told him testily that he had no money sense, that he didn't know how to manage, that he didn't charge enough for his services.

That was one of her favorite grievances, and many people would have backed her stand on that. The other attorneys were constantly irritated and annoyed by Lincoln's trifing charges, declaring that he was impoverishing the whole bar.

As late as 1853, when Lincoln was forty-four years old and only eight years away from the White House, he handled four cases in the McLean Circuit Court for a total charge of thirty dollars.

Many of his clients, he said, were as poor as he, and he didn't havethe heart to charge them much.

Once a man sent him twenty-fve dollars; and Lincoln returned ten, saying he had been too liberal.

In another instance, he prevented a swindler from getting hold of ten thousand dollars' worth of property owned by a demented girl. Lincoln won the case in ffteen minutes. An hour later, his associate, Ward Lamon, came to divide their fee of two hundred and ffty dollars. Lincoln rebuked him sternly. Lamon protested that the fee had been settled in advance, that the girl's brother was entirely satisfed to pay it.

“That may be,” Lincoln retorted, “but I am not satisfed. That money comes out of the pocket of a poor, demented girl; and I would rather starve than swindle her in this manner. You return half this money at least, or I'll not take a cent of it as my share.”

In another instance, a pension agent had charged the widow of a Revolutionary soldier half the four hundred dollars to which her pension amounted, for getting her claim allowed. The old woman was bent with age, and in poverty. Lincoln had her sue the pension agent, won the case for her, and charged her nothing. Besides, he paid her hotel bill and gave her money to buy a ticket home.

One day the Widow Armstrong came to Lincoln in great trouble. Her son Duff was charged with having murdered a man in a drunken brawl, and she pleaded with Abe to come and save the boy. Lincoln had known the Armstrongs back in New Salem. In fact, he had rocked Duff to sleep when he was a baby in the cradle. The Armstrongs had been a wild, rough lot; but Lincoln liked them. Jack Armstrong, Duff's father, had been the leader of the Clary's Grove Boys, and the renowned athlete whom Lincoln vanquished in a wrestling-match that has gone down in history.

Old Jack was dead now. Lincoln gladly went before the jury and made one of the most moving and appealing addresses of his career, andsaved the boy from the gallows.

All the widowed mother had in the world was forty acres of land, which she offered to turn over to Lincoln.

“Aunt Hannah,” he said, “you took me in years ago when I was poor and homeless, and you fed me and mended my clothes, and I shan't charge you a cent now.”

Sometimes he urged his clients to settle out of court, and charged them nothing whatever for his advice. In one instance, he refused to take a judgment against a man, saying, “I am really sorry for him—poor and a cripple as he is.”

Such kindness and consideration, beautiful though it was, didn't bring in cash; so Mary Lincoln scolded and fretted. Her husband wasn't getting on in the world, while other lawyers were growing wealthy with their fees and investments. Judge David Davis, for example, and Logan. Yes, and Stephen A. Douglas. By investing in Chicago real estate, Douglas had amassed a fortune and even become a philanthropist, giving Chicago University ten acres of valuable land upon which to erect its buildings. Besides, he was now one of the most famous political leaders in the nation.

How often Mary Lincoln thought of him, and how keenly she wished she had married him! As Mrs. Douglas she would be a social leader in Washington, wear Paris clothes, enjoy trips to Europe, dine with queens, and some day live in the White House. So she probably pictured herself in vain day-dreams.

What was her future as Lincoln's wife? He would go on like this to the end: riding the circuit for six months out of the year, leaving her alone at home, lavishing no love on her, and giving her no attention.... How different, how poignantly different, the realities of life were from the romantic visions she had once dreamed at Madame Mentelle's in the long ago!

11

In most respects, as has been said, Mrs. Lincoln was economical, and took pride in the fact. She purchased supplies carefully and the table was set sparingly, very sparingly; there were just barely enough scraps left to feed the cats. The Lincolns had no dog.

She bought bottle after bottle of perfume, broke the seals, sampled them, and returned them, contending that they were inferior, that they had been misrepresented. She did this so often that the local druggist refused to honor her orders for more. His account-book may still be seen in Springfield with the penciled notations: “Perfume returned by Mrs. Lincoln.”

She frequently had trouble with the tradespeople. For example, she felt that Myers, the iceman, was cheating her with short weights; so she turned on him and berated him in such a shrill, loud voice that neighbors half a block away ran to their doors to look and listen.

This was the second time she had made this accusation, and he swore that he would see her sizzling in hell before he would sell her another piece of ice.

He meant it, and he stopped his deliveries. That was awkward. She had to have ice, and he was the only man in town who supplied it; so, for once in her life, Mary Lincoln humbled herself. But she didn't do it personally: she paid a neighbor a quarter to go downtown and salve over the wound and coax Myers to resume his deliveries.

One of Lincoln's friends started a little newspaper called “The Springfeld Republican.” He canvassed the town, and Lincoln subscribed for it. When the frst copy was delivered at the door, Mary Todd was enraged. What! Another worthless paper? More money thrown away when she was trying so hard to save every penny! She lectured and scolded; and, in orderto pacify her, Lincoln said that he had not ordered the paper to be delivered. That was literally true. He had merely said he would pay for a subscription. He hadn't specifcally said he wanted it delivered. A lawyer's fnesse!

That evening, unknown to her husband, Mary Todd wrote a fiery letter, telling the editor what she thought of his paper, and demanding that it be discontinued.

She was so insulting that the editor answered her publicly in a column of the paper, and then wrote Lincoln, demanding an explanation. Lincoln was so distressed by the publicity that he was positively ill. In humiliation, he wrote the editor, saying it was all a mistake, trying to explain as best he could.

Once Lincoln wanted to invite his stepmother to spend Christmas at his home, but Mary Todd objected. She despised the old folks, and held Tom Lincoln and the Hanks tribe in profound contempt. She was ashamed of them, and Lincoln feared that even if they came to the house she wouldn't admit them. For twenty-three years his stepmother lived seventy miles away from Springfeld, and he went to visit her, but she never saw the inside of his home.

The only relative of his that ever visited him after his marriage was a distant cousin, Harriet Hanks, a sensible girl with a pleasing disposition. Lincoln was very fond of her and invited her to live at his home while she attended school in Springfeld. Mrs. Lincoln not only made a servant of her but tried to turn her into a veritable household drudge. Lincoln rebelled at this, refused to countenance such rank injustice, and the whole thing resulted in a distressing scene.

She had incessant trouble with her “hired girls.” One or two explosions of her fery wrath, and they packed up and left, an unending stream of them. They despised her and warned their friends; so the Lincoln home was soon on the maids' black-list.

She fumed and fussed and wrote letters about the “wild Irish” she had to employ. But all Irish became “wild” when they tried to work for her. She openly boasted that if she outlived her husband, she would spend the rest of her days in a Southern State. The people with whom she had been brought up, back in Lexington, did not put up with any impudence from their servants. If a Negro did not mind, he was sent forthwith to the whipping-post in the public square, to be fogged. One of the Todds' neighbors fogged six of his Negroes until they died.

“Long Jake” was a well-known character in Springfeld at that time. He had a span of mules and an old dilapidated wagon, and he ran what he vaingloriously described as an “express service.” His niece, unfortunately, went to work for Mrs. Lincoln. A few days later, the servant and mistress quarreled; the girl threw off her apron, packed her trunk, and walked out of the house, slamming the door behind her.

That afternoon, Long Jake drove his mules down to the corner of Eighth and Jackson streets and told Mrs. Lincoln that he had come for his niece's baggage. Mrs. Lincoln few into a rage, abused him and his niece in bitter language, and threatened to strike him if he entered her house. Indignant, he rushed down to Lincoln's offce and demanded that the poor man make his wife apologize.

Lincoln listened to his story, and then said sadly:

“I regret to hear this, but let me ask you in all candor, can't you endure for a few moments what I have had as my daily portion for the last ffteen years?”

The interview ended in Long Jake's extending his sympathy to Lincoln and apologizing for having troubled him.

Once Mrs. Lincoln kept a maid for more than two years, and the neighbors marveled; they could not understand it. The explanation was very simple: Lincoln had made a secret bargain with this one. When she firstcame, he took her aside and told her very frankly what she would have to endure; that he was sorry, but it couldn't be helped. The girl must ignore it. Lincoln promised her an extra dollar a week, himself, if she would do so.

The outbursts went on as usual; but with her secret moral and monetary backing, Maria persisted. After Mrs. Lincoln had given her a tongue-lashing, Lincoln would watch his chance and steal out into the kitchen while the maid was alone and pat her on the shoulder, admonishing her:

“That's right. Keep up your courage, Maria. Stay with her. Stay with her.”

This servant afterward married, and her husband fought under Grant. When Lee surrendered, Maria hurried to Washington to obtain her husband's immediate release, for she and her children were in want. Lincoln was glad to see her, and sat down and talked to her about old times. He wanted to invite her to stay for dinner, but Mary Todd wouldn't hear of it. He gave her a basket of fruit and money to buy clothes, and told her to call again the next day and he would provide her with a pass through the lines. But she didn't call, for that night he was assassinated.

And so Mrs. Lincoln stormed on through the years, leaving in her wake a train of heartaches and hatred. At times she behaved as if insane.

There was something a trifle queer about the Todd family; and since Mary's parents were cousins, perhaps this queer streak had been accentuated by inbreeding. Some people—among others, her own physician—feared she was suffering from an incipient mental disease.

Lincoln bore it all with Christ-like patience, and seldom censured her. But his friends weren't so docile.

Herndon denounced her as a “wildcat” and a “she wolf.”

Turner King, one of Lincoln's warmest admirers, described her as “a hellion, a she devil,” and declared that he had seen her drive Lincoln outof the house time after time.

John Hay, as secretary to the President in Washington, called her a short, ugly name that it is best not to print.

The pastor of the Methodist Church in Springfield lived near the Lincoln house. He and Lincoln were friends; and his wife testifed that the Lincolns “were very unhappy in their domestic life, and that Mrs. Lincoln was seen frequently to drive him from the house with a broomstick.”

James Gourley, who lived next door for sixteen years, declared that Mrs. Lincoln “had the devil in her,” that she had hallucinations and carried on like a crazy woman, weeping and wailing until she could be heard all over the neighborhood, demanding that some one guard the premises, swearing that some rough character was going to attack her.

Her outbursts of wrath grew more frequent, more fiery, with the passing of time. Lincoln's friends felt deeply sorry for him. He had no home life, and he never invited even his most intimate companions to dine with him—not even men like Herndon and Judge Davis. He was afraid of what might happen. He himself avoided Mary as much as possible, spending his evenings spinning yarns with the other attorneys down at the law library or telling stories to a crowd of men in Diller's drugstore.

Sometimes he was seen wandering alone, late at night, through unfrequented streets, his head on his chest, gloomy and funereal. Sometimes he said, “I hate to go home.” A friend, knowing what was wrong, would take him to his house for the night.

No one knew more than Herndon about the tragic home life of the Lincolns; and this is what Herndon had to say on pages 430—434 of the third volume of his Lincoln biography:

Mr. Lincoln never had a confidant, and therefore never unbosomed himself to others. He never spoke of his trials to me or, so far as I knew, to any of his friends. It was a great burden to carry, but he bore it sadly enough and without a murmur. I could always realize when he was in distress, without being told. He was not exactly an early riser, that is, he never usually appeared at the office till about nine o'clock in the morning. I usually preceded him an hour. Sometimes, however, he would come down as early as seven o'clock—in fact, on one occasion I remember he came down before daylight. If, on arriving at the office, I found him in, I knew instantly that a breeze had sprung up over the domestic sea, and that the waters were troubled. He would either be lying on the lounge looking skyward, or doubled up in a chair with his feet resting on the sill of a back window. He would not look up on my entering, and only answered my “Good morning” with a grunt. I at once busied myself with pen and paper, or ran through the leaves of some book; but the evidence of his melancholy and distress was so plain, and his silence so significant, that I would grow restless myself, and finding some excuse to go to the court-house or elsewhere, would leave the room.

The door of the office opening into a narrow hallway was half glass, with a curtain on it working on brass rings strung on wire. As I passed out on these occasions I would draw the curtain across the glass, and before I reached the bottom of the stairs I could hear the key turn in the lock, and Lincoln was alone in his gloom. An hour in the clerk's office at the court-house, an hour longer in a neighboring store having passed, I would return. By that time either a client had dropped in and Lincoln was propounding the law, or else the cloud of despondency had passed away, and he was busy in the recital of an Indiana story to whistle off the recollections of the morning's gloom. Noon having arrived I would depart homeward for my dinner. Returning within an hour, I would find him still in the office, although his home stood but a few squares away, —lunching on a slice of cheese and a handful of crackers which, in my absence, he had brought up from a store below. Separating for the day at five or six o'clock in the evening, I would still leave him behind, either sitting on a box at the foot of the stairway, entertaining a few loungers, or killing time in the same way on the court-house steps. A light in the office after dark attested his presence there till late along in the night, when, after all the world had gone to sleep, the tall form of the man destined to be the nation's President could have seen strolling along in the shadows of trees and buildings, and quietly slipping in through the door of a modest frame house, which it pleased the world, in a conventional way, to call his home.

Some persons may insist that this picture is too highly colored. If so, I can only answer, they do not know the facts.

Once Mrs. Lincoln attacked her husband so savagely, and kept it up so long, that even he— “with malice toward none; with charity for all” —even he lost his self-control, and seizing her by the arm, he forced her across the kitchen and pushed her toward the door, saying: “You're ruining my life. You're making a hell of this home. Now, damn you, you get out of it.”

12

If Lincoln had married Ann Rutledge, in all probability he would havebeen happy, but he would not have been President. He was slow in thought and movement, and she was not the type that would have driven him to achieve political distinction. But Mary Todd, obsessed with an undying determination to live in the White House, was no sooner married to Lincoln than she had him out running for the Whig nomination for Congress.

The battle was a ferce one; and, incredible as it seems, his political enemies accused him of being an infdel because he belonged to no church, and denounced him as a tool of wealth and aristocracy because he had affiliated himself through marriage with the haughty Todd and Edwards families. Ridiculous as the charges were, Lincoln realized that they might hurt him politically. So he answered his critics: “Only one of my relatives has ever visited me since I came to Springfeld, and that one, before he got out of town, was accused of stealing a jew's-harp. Now, if that is being a member of a proud, aristocratic family, then I am guilty of the offense.”

When the election came, Lincoln was defeated. It was the first political setback of his career.

Two years later he ran again and won. Mary Lincoln was ecstatic; believing that his political triumphs had just begun, she ordered a new evening gown and polished up her French verbs. As soon as her husband reached the capital, she addressed her letters to “The Honorable A. Lincoln.” But he put a stop to that at once.

She wanted to live in Washington, too, she longed to bask in the social prestige that she was sure awaited her. But when she came East to join him, she found things vastly different from what she had anticipated. Lincoln was so poor that he had had to borrow money from Stephen A. Douglas to pay his expenses until he got his first salary check from the Government; so Mr. and Mrs. Lincoln stopped at Mrs. Spriggs's boardinghouse in Duff Green's Row. The street in front of Mrs. Spriggs's establishment was unpaved, the sidewalk was made of ashes and gravel, the rooms were bleak, and there was no plumbing. In her back yard Mrs. Spriggs had an outhouse, a goose-pen, and a garden; and, as the neighbors' hogs were constantly breaking in to eat her vegetables, her little boy had to run out at intervals with a club to drive the animals away.

The city of Washington did not trouble in those days to collect the garbage; so Mrs. Spriggs dumped her refuse in the back alley, and depended upon the cows, pigs, and geese that wandered about the streets at will, to come and devour it.

Mrs. Lincoln found the door to the exclusive society of Washington shut tightly against her. She was ignored, and left alone to sit in her bleak boarding-house bedroom, with her spoiled children and a headache—listening to Mrs. Spriggs's boy, shouting to drive the hogs out of the cabbage-patch.

Disappointing as that was, it was nothing in comparison with the political disaster that lurked around the corner. When Lincoln entered Congress, the country had been waging a war against Mexico for twenty months—a shameful war of aggression, deliberately provoked by the slave power in Congress in order that the nation might acquire more territory where slavery would flourish and from which pro-slavery senators would be elected.

America accomplished two things in that war. Texas had once belonged to Mexico and then seceded. We forced Mexico to renounce all of her claims to Texas; and, in addition, we deliberately robbed Mexico of half of all the territory she owned and carved it up into the States of New Mexico, Arizona, Nevada, and California.

Grant said it was one of the wickedest wars in all history, and that he could never forgive himself for having fought in it. A great many of the American soldiers rebelled and went over to the enemy; one famous battalion in Santa Anna's army was composed entirely of American deserters.

Lincoln stood up in Congress and did what many other Whigs had already done: he attacked the President for having started “a war of rapine and murder, a war of robbery and dishonor,” and declared that the God of heaven had “forgotten to defend the weak and innocent, and permitted the strong band of murderers and demons from hell to kill men, women, and children and lay waste and pillage the land of the just.”

The capital paid no attention whatever to this speech, for Lincoln was unknown. But back in Springfield, it raised a hurricane. Illinois had sent six thousand men to fight, as they believed, for the holy cause of liberty; and now their representative was standing up in Congress and calling their soldiers demons from hell, and accusing them of murder. In a rage, excited partizans held public meetings and denounced Lincoln as “base...” “dastardly...” “infamous...” “a reasonable guerilla...” “a second Benedict Arnold.”

At one meeting resolutions were adopted declaring that never until then had they “known disgrace so black.” ... “Such black odium and infamy heaped upon the living brave and illustrious dead can but excite the indignation of every true Illinoisan.”

The hatred was so bitter that it smoldered for more than a decade; and when Lincoln was running for the Presidency thirteen years later these denunciations were again hurled at his head.

“I have committed political suicide,” Lincoln confessed to his law partner.

He dreaded to go back home now and face his resentful constituents; so he tried to secure a position that would keep him in Washington, and maneuvered to secure an appointment as Commissioner of the Land Office, but he failed.

Then he tried to have himself named Governor of the Territory of Oregon, with the hope that he might be one of the first senators when it came into the Union, but he failed in that too.

So he returned to Springfield and his dirty law office. Once more he hitched up Old Buck to his ramshackle buggy, and again he started driving over the circuit of the Eighth Judicial District—one of the most dejected men in all Illinois.

He was determined now to forget all about politics, and devote himself to his profession. He realized that he had no method in his work, that he lacked mental discipline; and so, to train himself to reason more closely and to demonstrate a proposition, he bought a geometry and carried it with him as he rode the circuit.

Herndon records in his biography:

At the little country inns, we usually occupied the same bed. In most cases the beds were too short for Lincoln, and his feet would hang over the footboard, thus exposing a limited expanse of shin bone. Placing a candle on a chair at the head of the bed, he would read and study for hours. I have known him to study in this position until two o'clock in the morning. Meanwhile, I and others who chanced to occupy the same room would be safely and soundly asleep. On the circuit in this way he studied Euclid until he could with ease demonstrate all the propositions in the six books.

After he had mastered geometry, he studied algebra, then astronomy, then he prepared a lecture on the origin and growth of languages. But no other study interested him as did Shakspere. The literary tastes that Jack Kelso had nurtured in New Salem still persisted.

The most striking characteristic of Abraham Lincoln, from this time on to the end of his life, was a sadness so profound, a melancholy so deep that mere words can hardly convey its depths.

When Jesse Weik was helping Herndon prepare his immortal biography, he felt that surely the reports of Lincoln's sadness must be exaggerated. So he went and discussed this point at length with the men who had been associated with Lincoln for years—men such as Stuart, Whitney, Matheny, Swett, and Judge Davis.

Then Weik was firmly convinced “that men who never saw Lincoln could scarcely realize his tendency to melancholy,” and Herndon, agreeing with him, went farther, making the statement from which I have already quoted: “If Lincoln ever had a happy day in twenty years, I never knew of it. A perpetual look of sadness was his most prominent feature. Melancholy dripped from him as he walked.”

When he was riding the circuit he would frequently sleep in the same room with two or three other attorneys. They would be awakened early in the morning by the sound of his voice and find him sitting on the edge of the bed, mumbling incoherently to himself. Getting up, he would start a fire and sit for hours, staring into the blaze. Frequently, on such occasions, he would recite “Oh, why should the spirit of mortal be proud?”

Sometimes as he walked down the street, he was so deep in despair that he took no notice of those who met him and spoke to him. Occasionally he shook hands with people without knowing what he was doing.

Jonathan Birch, who all but worshiped Lincoln's memory, says:

When attending court at Bloomington, Lincoln would keep his hearers in the court room, office or on the street convulsed with laughter at one hour and the next hour be so deeply submerged in speculation that no one dared arouse him.... He would sit in a chair tilted against the wall, his feet on the lower rung, legs drawn up and knees level with his chin, hat tipped forward, hands clasped about knees, eyes infinitely sad, the very picture of dejection and gloom. Thus absorbed I have seen him sit for hours at a time, defying the interruption of even his closest friends.

Senator Beveridge, after studying Lincoln's career perhaps more exhaustively than any one else has ever done, came to the conclusion that “the dominant quality in Lincoln's life from 1849 to the end was a sadness so profound that the depths of it cannot be sounded or estimated by normal minds.”

Yet Lincoln's inexhaustible humor, his amazing capacity for telling stories, were as striking and inseparable a part of his personality as his sadness.

At times Judge Davis even stopped court to listen to his boisterous humor.

“Crowds thronged about him, crowds of two hundred and three hundred,” says Herndon, holding their sides and laughing the hours away.

One eye-witness declares that when Lincoln reached the “nub” of a good story, men “whooped” and rolled off their chairs.

Those who knew Lincoln intimately agreed that “his abysmal sadness” was caused by two things: his crushing political disappointments and his tragic marriage.

And so the poignant years of apparently permanent political oblivion dragged by—six of them—and then suddenly an event occurred that altered the whole course of Lincoln's life, and started him toward the White House.

The instigator and moving spirit behind this event was Mary Lincoln's old sweetheart, Stephen A. Douglas.

13

In 1854, a tremendous thing happened to Lincoln. It came about as a result of the repeal of the Missouri Compromise. The Missouri Compromise, in brief, was this:

In 1819, Missouri had wanted to come into the Union as a slave State. The North had opposed its doing so and the situation became serious. Finally, the ablest public men of that day arranged what is now known as the Missouri Compromise. The South got what it wanted: the admission of Missouri as a slave State. The North got what it wanted: thereafter slavery was never to be permitted in the West anywhere north of the southern boundary of Missouri.

People thought that would stop the quarreling about slavery, and it did—for a while. But now, a third of a century later, Stephen A. Douglas secured the repeal of the Compromise, and made it possible for a new area lying west of the Mississippi and equal in size to the original thirteen States, to be blighted with the curse of slavery. He fought long and hard in Congress for the repeal. The struggle lasted for months. Once during the bitter debates in the House of Representatives, members leaped on top of their desks, knives flashed, and guns were drawn. But finally, after an impassioned plea by Douglas, lasting from midnight until almost dawn, the Senate passed his bill on March 4, 1854. It was a tremendous event. Messengers ran through the streets of the slumbering city of Washington, shouting the news. Cannon in the Navy Yard boomed to salute the dawn of a new era—a new era that was to be drenched in blood.

Why did Douglas do it? No one seems to know. Historians in skullcaps are still arguing about it. Of this much, however, we are certain: Douglas hoped to be elected President in 1856. He knew this repeal would help him in the South.

But what of the North?

“By God, I know it will raise a hell of a storm there,” he declared.

He was right. It did. It raised a regular tornado that blew both the great parties into bits, and eventually whirled the nation into civil war.

Meetings of protest and indignation flared up spontaneously in hundreds of cities and villages and hamlets. Stephen Arnold Douglas was denounced as the “traitor Arnold.” People said that he had been named after Benedict Arnold. He was branded as a modern Judas, and presented with thirty pieces of silver. He was given a rope and told to hang himself.

The churches leaped into the fight with a holy frenzy. Three thousand and fifty clergymen in New England wrote a protest “in the name of Almighty God and in His presence,” and laid it before the Senate. Fiery and indignant editorials fed the flames of public indignation. In Chicago even the Democratic papers turned upon Douglas with vindictive fierceness.

Congress adjourned in August, and Douglas started home. Amazed at the sights that met his eyes, he declared afterward that he could have traveled all the way from Boston to Illinois by the light of burning effigies of himself hanging by the neck.

Daring and defiant, he announced that he was going to speak in Chicago. The hatred against him there, in his own home town, amounted to nothing less than fanaticism. The press assailed him, and wrathful ministers demanded that he never again be permitted to “pollute the pure air of Illinois with his perfidious breath.” Men rushed to the hardware stores, and, by sundown, there wasn't another revolver left for sale in all the city. His enemies swore that he should never live to defend his infamous deeds.

The moment Douglas entered the city, boats in the harbor lowered their flags to half-mast; and bells in a score of churches tolled, mourning the death of Liberty.

The night that he spoke was one of the hottest Chicago had ever known. Perspiration rolled down the faces of men as they sat idling in their chairs. Women fainted as they struggled to get out to the shore of the lake where they could sleep on the cool sands. Horses fell in their harness and lay dying in the streets.

But notwithstanding the heat, thousands of excited men, guns in their pockets, flocked to hear Douglas. No hall in Chicago could hold the throng. They packed a public square, and hundreds stood on balconies and sat astride the roofs of near-by houses.

The very first sentence that Douglas uttered was greeted with groans and hisses. He continued to talk—or, at least, he continued to try—and the audience yelled and booed and sang insulting songs and called him names that are unprintable.

His excited partizans wanted to start a fight. Douglas begged them to be quiet. He would tame the mob. He kept on trying, but he kept on failing. When he denounced the “Chicago Tribune,” the great gathering cheered the paper. When he threatened to stand there all night unless they let him speak, eight thousand voices sang: “We won't go home until morning. We won't go home until morning.”

It was a Saturday night. Finally, after four hours of futility and insult, Douglas took out his watch and shouted at the howling, bellowing, milling mob: “It is now Sunday morning, I'll go to church. And you can go to hell.”

Exhausted, he gave up and left the speaker's stand. The Little Giant had met humiliation and defeat for the first time in his life.

The next morning the papers told all about it; and down in Springfield, a proud, plump brunette, trembling on the brink of middle age, read it with peculiar satisfaction. Fifteen years before, she had dreamed of being Mrs. Douglas. For years she had watched him mount on wings until he had become the most popular and powerful leader in the nation, while her husband had gone down in humiliating defeat; and, deep in her heart, she resented it.

But now, thank God, the haughty Douglas was doomed. He had split his own party in his own State. And just before the election. This was Lincoln's chance. And Mary Lincoln knew it—his chance to win back the public favor that he had lost in 1848, his chance to reinstate himself politically, his chance to be elected to the United States Senate. True, Douglas still had four more years to serve. But his colleague was coming up for reelection in a few months.

And who was his colleague? A swaggering, pugnacious Irishman named Shields. Mary Lincoln had an old score to settle with Shields, too. Back in 1842, largely because of insulting letters that she herself had written, Shields had challenged Lincoln to a duel; and the two of them, armed with cavalry swords and accompanied by their seconds, had met on a sand-bar in the Mississippi River, prepared to kill each other. But, at the last moment, friends interceded and prevented bloodshed. Since that time, Shields had gone up in politics, but Lincoln had gone down.

But now Lincoln had struck bottom, and had started to rebound. The repeal of the Missouri Compromise had, as he said, “aroused” him. He could no longer remain quiet. He was determined to strike with all the vigor and conviction of his soul.

So he began preparing his speech, working for weeks in the State library, consulting histories, mastering facts, classifying, clarifying, studying all the hot debates that had been thundered back and forth across the Senate chamber during the stormy passage of this bill.

On October 3 the State Fair opened at Springfield. Thousands of farmers poured into town; men bringing their prize hogs and horses, their cattle and corn; women fetching their jellies and jam, their pies and preserves. But these displays were all but forgotten in the excitement of another attraction. For weeks it had been advertised that Douglas was to speak the opening day of the fair, and political leaders from all parts of the State had thronged there to hear him.

That afternoon he spoke for more than three hours, going over his record, explaining, defending, attacking. He hotly denied that he was trying either “to legislate slavery into a territory or to exclude it therefrom.” Let the people in a territory do whatever they pleased about slavery.

“Surely,” he shouted, “if the people of Kansas and Nebraska are able to govern themselves, surely they are able to govern a few miserable Negroes.”

Lincoln sat near the front, listening to every word, weighing every argument. When Douglas finished, Lincoln declared: “I'll hang his hide on the fence to-morrow.”

The next morning handbills were scattered all over town and the fair-grounds, announcing that Lincoln would reply to Douglas. The public interest was intense, and before two o'clock every seat was occupied in the hall where the speaking was to take place. Presently Douglas appeared and sat on the platform. As usual, he was immaculately attired and faultlessly groomed.

Mary Lincoln was already in the audience. Before leaving the house that morning she had vigorously brushed Lincoln's coat, had laid out a fresh collar and carefully ironed his best tie. She was anxious to have him appear to advantage. But the day was hot, and Lincoln knew the air in the hall would be oppressive. So he strode onto the platform without a coat, without a vest, without a collar, without a tie. His long, brown, skinny neck rose out of the shirt that hung loosely on his gaunt frame. His hair was disordered, his boots rusty and unkempt. One single knitted “gallis” held up his short, ill-fitting trousers.

At the first sight of him, Mary Lincoln flushed with anger and embarrassment. She could have wept in her disappointment and despair.

No one dreamed of it at the time, but we know now that this homely man, whose wife was ashamed of him, was starting out that hot October afternoon on a career that was to give him a place among the immortals.

That afternoon, he made the first great speech of his life. If all the addresses that he had made previously were collected and placed in one book, and those that he made from that afternoon on were placed in another volume, you could hardly believe that the same man was the author of them all. It was a new Lincoln speaking that day—a Lincoln stirred to the depths by a mighty wrong, a Lincoln pleading for an oppressed race, a Lincoln touched and moved and lifted up by moral grandeur.

He reviewed the history of slavery, and gave five fiery reasons for hating it.

But with lofty tolerance, he declared: “I have no prejudice against the Southern people. They are just what we would be in their situation. If slavery did not now exist among them, they would not introduce it. If it did now exist among us, we should not instantly give it up. When Southern people tell us they are no more responsible for the origin of slavery than we are, I acknowledge the fact. When it is said that the institution exists, and that it is very difficult to get rid of it in any satisfactory way, I can understand and appreciate the saying. I surely will not blame them for not doing what I should not know how to do myself. If all earthly power were given me, I should not know what to do with the existing institution.”

For more than three hours, with the perspiration rolling down his face, he continued to answer Douglas, revealing the senator's sophistry, showing the utter falseness of his position.

It was a profound speech, and it made a profound impression. Douglas winced and writhed under it. Time after time he rose to his feet and interrupted Lincoln.

The election wasn't far off. Progressive young Democrats were already bolting the ticket and attacking Douglas, and when the voters of Illinois cast their ballots, the Douglas Democrats were overwhelmed.

Senators were chosen in those days by the State legislatures; and the Illinois Legislature met in Springfield on February 8, 1855, for that purpose. Mrs. Lincoln had bought a new dress and hat for the occasion and her brother-in-law, Ninian W. Edwards, had with sanguine anticipation arranged for a reception to be given that night in Senator Lincoln's honor.

On the first ballot, Lincoln led all the other candidates, and came within six votes of victory. But he steadily lost after that; and on the tenth ballot he was definitely defeated, and Lyman W. Trumbull was elected.

Lyman Trumbull had married Julia Jayne, a young woman who had been bridesmaid at Mary Lincoln's wedding and probably had been the most intimate friend that Mrs. Lincoln ever had. Mary and Julia sat side by side in the balcony of the Hall of Representatives that afternoon, watching the senatorial election; and when the victory of Julia's husband was announced, Mrs. Lincoln turned in a temper and walked out of the building. Her anger was so fierce, and her jealousy was so galling, that from that day on, to the end of her life, she never again spoke to Julia Trumbull.

Saddened and depressed, Lincoln returned to his dingy law office with the ink-stain on the wall and the garden seeds sprouting in the dust on top of the bookcase.

A week later he hitched up Old Buck and once more started driving over the unsettled prairies, from one country courthouse to another. But his heart was no longer in the law. He talked now of little else but politics and slavery. He said that the thought of millions of people held in bondage continually made him miserable. His periods of melancholy returned now more frequently than ever; and they were more prolonged and more profound.

One night he was sharing a bed with another lawyer in a country tavern. His companion awoke at dawn and found Lincoln sitting in his nightshirt on the edge of the bed, brooding, dejected, mumbling to himself, lost in unseeing abstraction. When at last he spoke, the first words were:

“I tell you this nation cannot endure permanently half slave and half free.”

Shortly after this a colored woman in Springfield came to Lincoln with a pitiful story. Her son had gone to St. Louis and taken a job on a Mississippi steamboat. When he arrived in New Orleans he was thrown into jail. He had been born free, but he had no papers to prove it. So he was kept in prison until his boat left. Now he was going to be sold as a slave to pay the prison expenses.

Lincoln took the case to the Governor of Illinois. The governor replied that he had no right or power to interfere. In response to a letter, the Governor of Louisiana replied that he couldn't do anything, either. So Lincoln went back to see the Governor of Illinois a second time, urging him to act, but the governor shook his head.

Lincoln rose from his chair, exclaiming with unusual emphasis: “By God, Governor, you may not have the legal power to secure the release of this poor boy, but I intend to make the ground in this country too hot for the foot of a slave-owner.”

The next year Lincoln was forty-six, and he confided to his friend Whitney that he “kinder needed” glasses; so he stopped at a jewelry store and bought his first pair—for thirty-seven and a half cents.

14

We have now come to the summer of 1858, and we are about to watch Abraham Lincoln making the first great fight of his life. We shall see him emerge from his provincial obscurity and engage in one of the most famous political battles in United States history.

He is forty-nine now—and where has he arrived after all his years of struggle?

In business, he has been a failure.

In marriage, he has found stark, bleak unhappiness.

In law, he is fairly successful, with an income of three thousand a year; but in politics and the cherished desires of his heart, he has met with frustration and defeat.

“With me,” he confessed, “the race of ambition has been a failure, a flat failure.”

But from now on events move with a strange and dizzying swiftness. In seven more years he will be dead. But in those seven years he will have achieved a fame and luster that will endure to the remotest generations.

His antagonist in the contest we are to watch is Stephen A. Douglas. Douglas is now a national idol. In fact, he is worldrenowned.

In the four years that had elapsed since the repeal of the Missouri Compromise, Douglas had made one of the most amazing recoveries in history. He had redeemed himself by a dramatic and spectacular political battle. It came about in this way:

Kansas knocked at the door of the Union, asking to be admitted as a slave State. But should she be so admitted? Douglas said “no,” because the legislature that had framed her constitution was not a real legislature. Its members had been elected by chicanery and shot-guns. Half the settlers in Kansas—men who had a right to vote—were never registered, and so couldn't vote. But five thousand pro-slavery Democrats who lived in western Missouri and had not the shadow of a legal right to cast ballots in Kansas went to a United States arsenal, armed themselves, and, on election day, marched over into Kansas with flags flying and bands playing—and voted for slavery. The whole thing was a farce, a travesty on justice.

And what did the free-State men do? They prepared for action. They cleaned up their shot-guns, oiled their rifles, and began banging away at signs on trees and knot-holes in barn doors, to improve their marksmanship. They were soon marching and drilling and drinking. They dug trenches, threw up breastworks, and turned hotels into forts. If they couldn't win justice with ballots, they would win it with bullets!

In almost every town and village throughout the North, professional orators harangued the citizenry, passed hats, and collected money to buy arms for Kansas. Henry Ward Beecher, pounding his pulpit in Brooklyn, cried that guns would do more for the salvation of Kansas than Bibles. From that time on, Sharp's rifles were known as “Beecher's Bibles.” They were shipped from the East in boxes and barrels labeled as “Bibles,” as “Crockery,” as “Revised Statutes.”

After five free-State settlers had been murdered, an old sheepraiser, a religious fanatic who cultivated grapes and made wine on the side, rose up on the plains of Kansas and said: “I have no choice. It has been decreed by Almighty God that I should make an example of these pro-slavery men.”

His name was John Brown, and he lived at Osawatomie.

One night in May he opened the Bible, read the Psalms of David to his family, and they knelt in prayer. Then after the singing of a few hymns, he and his four sons and a son-in-law mounted their horses and rode across the prairie to a pro-slavery man's cabin, dragged the man and his two boys out of bed, chopped off their arms, and split their heads open with an ax. It rained before morning, and the water washed some of the brains out of the dead men's skulls.

From that time on, both sides slew and stabbed and shot. The term “Bleeding Kansas” was written on the pages of history.

Now, Stephen A. Douglas knew that a constitution framed by a bogus legislature in the midst of all that fraud and treachery was not worth the blotting-paper that it took to dry it.

So Douglas demanded that the people of Kansas be permitted to vote at an honest and peaceful election on the question of whether Kansas should be admitted as a slave or a free State.

His demand was altogether right and proper. But the President of the United States, James Buchanan, and the haughty pro-slavery politicians in Washington wouldn't tolerate such an arrangement.

So Buchanan and Douglas quarreled.

The President threatened to send Douglas to the political shambles, and Douglas retaliated: “By God, sir, I made James Buchanan; and by God, sir, I'll unmake him.”

As Douglas said that, he not only made a threat, but he made history. In that instant, slavery had reached the apex of its political power and arrogance. From that moment on, its power declined with a swift and dramatic abruptness.

The battle that followed was the beginning of the end, for in that fight Douglas split his own party wide open and prepared the way for Democratic disaster in 1860, and so made the election of Lincoln not only possible but inevitable.

Douglas had staked his own political future on what he believed, and on what almost every one in the North believed, was an unselfish fight for a magnificent principle. And Illinois loved him for it. He had now come back to his home State, the most admired and idolized man in the nation.

The same Chicago that had hooted and lowered the flags to half-mast and tolled the church bells as he entered the city in 1854—that same Chicago now despatched a special train with brass bands and reception committees to escort him home. As he entered the city, one hundred and fifty cannon in Dearborn Park roared a welcome, hundreds of men fought to shake his hand, and thousands of women tossed flowers at his feet. People named their first-born in his honor; and it is probably no exaggeration to say that some of his frenzied followers would actually have died for him on the scaffold. Forty years after his death men still boasted that they were “Douglas Democrats.”

A few months after Douglas made his triumphal entry into Chicago the people of Illinois were scheduled to elect a United States Senator. Naturally the Democrats nominated Douglas. And whom did the Republicans put up to run against him? An obscure man named Lincoln.

During the campaign that followed, Lincoln and Douglas met in a series of fiery debates, and these debates made Lincoln famous. They fought over a question charged with emotional dynamite, public excitement rose to fever heat. Throngs such as had never been known before in the history of the United States rushed to hear them. No halls were large enough to accommodate them; so the meetings were held in the afternoon in groves or out on the prairies. Reporters followed them, newspapers played up the sensational contests, and the speakers soon had a nation for their audience.

Two years later, Lincoln was in the White House.

These debates had advertised him, they had paved the way.

For months before the contest began Lincoln had been preparing; as thoughts and ideas and phrases formed in his mind, he wrote them down on stray scraps of paper—on the backs of envelopes, on the margins of newspapers, on pieces of paper sacks. These he stored in his tall silk hat and carried about wherever he went. Finally he copied them on sheets of paper, speaking each sentence aloud as he wrote it, constantly revising, recasting, improving.

After completing the final draft of his first speech, he invited a few intimate friends to meet him one night in the library of the State House. There, behind locked doors, he read his speech, pausing at the end of each paragraph, asking for comments, inviting criticisms. This address contained the prophetic words that have since become famous:

“A house divided against itself cannot stand.”

“I believe this government cannot endure permanently half slave and half free.

“I do not expect the Union to be dissolved—I do not expect the house to fall—but I do expect it will cease to be divided.

“It will become all one thing or all the other.”

As he read that, his friends were astonished and alarmed. It was too radical, they said; it was “a damn fool utterance,” it would drive voters away.

Finally Lincoln rose slowly and told the group of the intense thought that he had given the subject, and ended the conference by declaring that the statement “A house divided against itself cannot stand” was the truth of all human experience.

“It has been true,” said Lincoln, “for six thousand years. And I want some universally known figure, expressed in a simple language, that will arouse men to the peril of the times. The time has come when this truth should be uttered, and I am determined neither to change nor modify my assertion. I am willing, if necessary, to perish with it. If it is decreed that I should go down because of this speech, then let me go down linked to the truth. Let me die in the advocacy of what is just and right.”

The first of the great debates was held on the twenty-first day of August in the little farming town of Ottawa, seventy-five miles out of Chicago. Crowds began arriving the night before. Soon the hotels, private houses, and livery-stables were filled to capacity; and for a mile up and down the valley camp-fires blazed on bluffs and bottom-lands as if the town were surrounded by an invading army.

Before daybreak the tide set in again; and the sun rose that morning over the Illinois prairies to look down on country roads filled with buggies and wagons, with pedestrians, and with men and women on horseback. The day was hot, the weather had been dry for weeks. Huge clouds of dust arose and drifted over the corn-fields and meadows.

At noon a special train of seventeen cars arrived from Chicago; seats were packed, aisles jammed, and eager passengers rode on the roofs.

Every town within forty miles had brought its band. Drums rolled, horns tooted, there was the tramp, tramp of parading militia. Quack doctors gave free snake-shows and sold their painkillers. Jugglers and contortionists performed in front of saloons. Beggars and scarlet women plied their trades. Firecrackers exploded, cannon boomed, horses shied and ran away.

In some towns, the renowned Douglas was driven through the streets in a fine carriage drawn by six white horses. A mighty hurrah arose. The cheering was continuous.

Lincoln's supporters, to show their contempt for this display and elegance, drove their candidate through the street on a decrepit old hay-rack drawn by a team of white mules. Behind him came another hay-rack filled with thirty-two girls. Each girl bore the name of a State, and above them rose a huge motto:

Westward the star of empire takes its way.

The girls link on to Lincoln as their mothers linked to Clay.

The speakers, committees, and reporters wedged and squeezed their way through the dense crowd for half an hour before they could reach the platform.

It was protected from the broiling sun by a lumber awning. A score of men climbed on the awning; it gave way under their weight; boards tumbled down on the Douglas committee.

In almost every way the two speakers differed sharply.

Douglas was five feet four. Lincoln was six feet four.

The big man had a thin tenor voice. The little man had a rich baritone.

Douglas was graceful and suave. Lincoln was ungainly and awkward. Douglas had the personal charm of a popular idol. Lincoln's sallow wrinkled face was filled with melancholy, and he was entirely lacking in physical magnetism.

Douglas was dressed like a rich Southern planter, in ruffled shirt, dark-blue coat, white trousers, and a white broad-brimmed hat. Lincoln's appearance was uncouth, grotesque: the sleeves of his rusty black coat were too short, his baggy trousers were too short, his high stovepipe hat was weather-beaten and dingy.

Douglas had no flair for humor whatever, but Lincoln was one of the greatest story-tellers that ever lived.

Douglas repeated himself wherever he went. But Lincoln pondered over his subject ceaselessly, until he said he found it easier to make a new speech each day than to repeat an old one.

Douglas was vain, and craved pomp and fanfare. He traveled on a special train draped in flags. On the rear of the train was a brass cannon mounted on a box-car. As he approached a town, his cannon fired time after time, to proclaim to the natives that a mighty man was at their gates.

But Lincoln, detesting what he called “fizzlegigs and fireworks,” traveled in day-coaches and freight-trains and carried a battered old carpet-bag, and a green cotton umbrella with the handle gone and a string tied around the middle to keep it from flapping open.

Douglas was an opportunist. He had no “fixed political morals,” as Lincoln said. To win—that was his goal. But Lincoln was fighting for a great principle, and it mattered to him very little who won now, if only justice and mercy triumphed in the end.

“Ambition has been ascribed to me,” he said. “God knows how sincerely I prayed from the first that this field of ambition might not be opened. I claim no insensibility to political honors; but to-day, could the Missouri Compromise be restored, and the whole slavery question replaced on the old ground of ‘toleration’ by necessity where it exists, with unyielding hostility to the spread of it, on principle, I would, in consideration, gladly agree that Judge Douglas should never be out, and I never in, an office, so long as we both or either, live.

“It makes little difference, very little difference, whether Judge Douglas or myself is elected to the United States Senate; but the great issue which we have submitted to you to-day is far above and beyond any personal interests or the political fortunes of any man. And that issue will live, and breathe, and burn, when the poor, feeble, stammering tongues of Judge Douglas and myself are silent in the grave.”

During these debates Douglas maintained that any State, anywhere, at any time, had a right to have slavery if the majority of its citizens voted for it. And he didn't care whether they voted it up or down. His celebrated slogan was this: “Let each State mind its own business and let its neighbors alone.”

Lincoln took directly the opposite stand.

“Judge Douglas's thinking slavery is right,” he explained, “and my thinking it wrong, is the precise fact upon which depends the whole controversy.

“He contends that whatever community wants slaves has a right to have them. So they have, if it is not a wrong. But if it is a wrong, he cannot say people have a right to do wrong.

“He cares as little whether a State shall be slave or free as whether his neighbor shall plant his farm with tobacco or stock it with horned cattle. But the great mass of mankind differ with Judge Douglas: they consider slavery a great moral wrong.”

Douglas went up and down the State, crying out time after time that Lincoln favored giving Negroes social equality.

“No,” retorted Lincoln, “all I ask for the Negro is that, if you do not like him, you let him alone. If God gave him but little, let him enjoy that little. He is not my equal in many respects, but in his right to enjoy ‘life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness,’ in his right to put into his mouth the bread that his hands have earned, he is my equal and the equal of Judge Douglas and the equal of every living man.”

In debate after debate Douglas accused Lincoln of wanting the whites to “hug and marry the blacks.”

And time after time, Lincoln was forced to deny it: “I object to the alternative which says that because I do not want a Negro woman for a slave, I must want her for a wife. I have lived until my fiftieth year, and have never had a Negro woman either for a slave or a wife. There are enough white men to marry all the white women; and enough Negro men to marry all the Negro women; and, for God's sake, let them be so married.”

Douglas tried to dodge and befog the issues. His arguments, Lincoln said, had got down to the point where they were as thin as “soup made by boiling the shadow of a pigeon that had starved to death.” He was using “specious and fantastic arrangements of words, by which a man can prove a horse-chestnut to be a chestnut horse.”

“I can't help feeling foolish,” continued Lincoln, “in answering arguments that are no arguments at all.”

Douglas said things that weren't true. He knew that they were falsehoods, and so did Lincoln.

“If a man,” responded Lincoln, “will stand up and assert, and repeat and reassert, that two and two do not make four, I know nothing that will stop him. I cannot work an argument into the consistency of a mental gag and actually close his mouth with it. I don't like to call Judge Douglas a liar, but when I come square up to him, I don't know what else to call him.”

And so the fight raged on, week after week. Day after day Lincoln continued his attacks. Others leaped into the fray. Lyman Trumbull called Douglas a liar, and declared that he had been guilty of “the most damnable effrontery that ever man put on.” Frederick Douglas, the famous Negro orator, came to Illinois and joined in the assault. The Buchanan Democrats waxed vicious and ferocious in their denunciation of Douglas. Carl Schurz, the fiery German-American reformer, indicted him before the foreign voters. The Republican press in screaming head-lines branded him as “a forger.” With his own party divided, and himself hounded and harassed on every side, Douglas was fighting against tremendous odds. In desperation, he wired his friend Usher F. Linder “The hell-hounds are on my track. For God's sake, Linder, come and help me fight them.”

The operator sold a copy of the telegram to the Republicans, and it was head-lined in a score of papers.

Douglas's enemies screamed with delight, and from that day on as long as he lived, the recipient of the telegram was called “For God's Sake Linder.”

On election night, Lincoln remained in the telegraph office, reading the returns. When he saw that he had lost, he started home. It was dark and rainy and gloomy. The path leading to his house had been worn pig-backed and was slippery. Suddenly, one foot shot from under and hit the other. Quickly he recovered his balance. “It's a slip,” he said, “and not a fall.”

Shortly after that he read an editorial about himself in an Illinois paper. It said:

Hon. Abe Lincoln is undoubtedly the most unfortunate politician that has ever attempted to rise in Illinois. In everything he undertakes, politically, he seems doomed to failure. He has been prostrated often enough in his political schemes to have crushed the life out of any ordinary man.

The vast crowds that had rushed to hear him debate with Douglas encouraged Lincoln to believe that he might make a little money now by giving lectures; so he prepared to talk on “Discoveries and Inventions,” rented a hall in Bloomington, stationed a young lady at the door to sell tickets—and not one solitary person came to hear him. Not one!

So once more he returned to his dingy office with the inkstain on the wall and the garden seeds sprouting on top of the bookcase.

It was high time he was getting back, for he had been away from his law practice for six months, earning nothing. Now he was out of funds entirely; he didn't have enough cash on hand even to pay his butcher's and grocer's bills.

So again he hitched up Old Buck to his ramshackle buggy, and again he started driving over the prairie circuit.

It was November, and a cold snap was coming. Across the gray sky above him wild geese flew southward, honking loudly; a rabbit darted across the road; off in the woods somewhere a wolf howled. But the somber man in the buggy neither saw nor heard what was going on about him. Hour after hour, he rode on, his chin on his breast, lost in speculation, submerged in despair.

15

When the newly formed Republican party met in Chicago in the spring of 1860 to nominate a Presidential candidate, few people dreamed that Abraham Lincoln had a chance. A short time before that, he himself had written to a newspaper editor: “I must in all candor say I do not think myself fit for the presidency.”

It was generally accepted in 1860 that the nomination honors were going to the handsome William H. Seward of New York. There could hardly be any question about that, for straw ballots were taken on the trains carrying the delegates to Chicago, and they gave Seward twice as many votes as all the other candidates combined. On many of the trains there was not a single ballot cast for Abraham Lincoln. It is possible that some of the delegates did not even know that such a man existed.

The convention met on Seward's fifty-ninth birthday. How fitting! He was positive that he would receive the nomination as a birthday present. He was so confident of it that he said good-by to his colleagues in the United States Senate and invited his intimate friends to attend a great feast of celebration at his home in Auburn, New York; and a cannon was rented, hauled into his front yard, loaded, and cocked up in the air, ready to boom the joyous news to the town.

If the convention had started balloting on Thursday night, that cannon would have been fired, and the story of a nation would have been changed; but the voting could not begin until the printer delivered the papers necessary for keeping the tally. And the printer, on his way to the convention, probably stopped for a glass of beer. At any rate, he was late, and consequently there was nothing for the convention to do that Thursday evening but sit and wait for him.

Mosquitoes were bad in the hall, the place was hot and stuffy, and the delegates hungry and thirsty; so some one stood up and moved that the convention adjourn until ten o'clock the next morning. A motion to adjourn is always in order; it takes precedence over all other motions and it is nearly always popular. This one carried with a rush of enthusiasm.

Seventeen hours elapsed before the convention assembled again. That is not a long time, but it was long enough for Seward's career to be wrecked, and Lincoln's made.

The person largely responsible for the wrecking was Horace Greeley, a grotesque-looking man with a head as round as a cantaloupe; with thin, silky hair as light as an albino's; and with a string necktie that usually worked itself out of place until the bow was approximately under his left ear.

Greeley was not even advocating the nomination of Lincoln, but he was determined with all the bitterness of his soul to even up an old score with William H. Seward and Seward's manager, Thurlow Weed.

The trouble was this: For fourteen years, Greeley had fought side by side with these men; he had helped make Seward Governor of New York and then United States Senator; and he had aided Weed tremendously in his battle to become and remain political boss of the State.

And what had Greeley gotten out of all this struggle and combat? Very little but neglect. He had wanted to be made State printer, and Weed had taken that place for himself. He had longed to be appointed postmaster of New York City, and Weed did not offer to recommend him. He had aspired to be governor, or even lieutenant-governor, and Weed not only said “no,” but said it in a way that hurt and rankled.

Finally, when he could stand no more, Greeley sat down and wrote a long, stinging letter to Seward. It would fill seven pages of this book, and every paragraph of it was seared with bitterness.

That fiery message had been written on Saturday night, November 11, 1854.... And this was 1860. Greeley had waited six long years for an opportunity to get his revenge, but at last it had arrived, and he made the most of it. He didn't go to bed at all, that fateful Thursday night while the Republican nominating convention was having a recess in Chicago; but from sundown until long after dawn, he hurried from delegation to delegation, reasoning, arguing, pleading. His paper, the “New York Tribune,” was read all over the North; and it influenced public opinion as no other paper had ever done. He was a famous man, voices were hushed whenever he appeared, and the delegates listened to him with respect.

He hurled all kinds of arguments against Seward. He pointed out that Seward had repeatedly denounced the Masonic order; that in 1830 he had been elected to the State Senate on the anti-Mason ticket, and, as a consequence had aroused bitter, widespread, and undying resentment.

Later, when he was Governor of New York, Seward had favored the destruction of the common-school fund and the establishment of separate schools for foreigners and Catholics, and thus had stirred up another hornet's nest of fiery hatred.

Greeley pointed out that the men who had made up the once powerful Know Nothing party were violently opposed to Seward and would vote for a hound dog in preference to him.

And that wasn't all. Greeley pointed out that this “arch agitator” had been too radical, that his “bloody program” and talk of a higher law than the Constitution had frightened the border States, and that they would turn against him.

“I will bring you the men who are candidates for governor in these States,” Greeley promised, “and they will confirm what I say.”

He did, and the excitement was intense.

With clenched fists and blazing eyes, the gubernatorial candidates in Pennsylvania and Indiana declared that Seward's nomination meant inevitable defeat in their States, inevitable disaster.

And the Republicans felt that, to win, they must carry those States.

So, suddenly, the flood-tide that had been running toward Seward began to recede. And Lincoln's friends rushed about from delegation to delegation, trying to persuade those who were opposed to Seward to concentrate on Lincoln. Douglas was sure to be nominated by the Democrats, they said, and no man in the country was better equipped to fight Douglas than Lincoln. To him, it was an old job; he was used to it. Besides, Lincoln was born a Kentuckian, and he could win votes in the doubtful border States. Furthermore, he was the kind of candidate the Northwest wanted—a man who had fought his way up from splitting rails and breaking sod, a man who understood the common people.

When arguments like these didn't succeed, they used others. They won Indiana's delegates by promising Caleb B. Smith a place in the Cabinet, and they won Pennsylvania's fifty-six votes with the assurance that Simeon Cameron would sit at Lincoln's right hand.

On Friday morning the balloting began. Forty thousand people had poured into Chicago, eager for excitement. Ten thousand wedged into the convention hall, and thirty thousand packed the streets outside. The seething mob reached for blocks.

Seward led on the first ballot. On the second, Pennsylvania cast her fifty-two votes for Lincoln, and the break began. On the third, it was all but a stampede.

Inside the hall, ten thousand people, half crazed with excitement, leaped upon the seats, shouting, yelling, smashing their hats on one another's heads. A cannon boomed on the roof—and thirty thousand people in the streets raised a shout.

Men hugged one another and danced about wildly, weeping and laughing and shrieking.

One hundred guns at the Tremont House belched and barked their volleys of fire; a thousand bells joined in the clamor; while whistles on railway engines, on steamboats, on factories, were opened and tied open for the day.

For twenty-four hours the excitement raged.

“No such uproar,” declared the “Chicago Tribune,” “has been heard on earth since the walls of Jericho fell down.” In the midst of all this rejoicing, Horace Greeley saw Thurlow Weed, the erstwhile “maker of Presidents,” shedding bitter tears. At last, Greeley had his sweet revenge.

In the meantime what was happening down in Springfield? Lincoln had gone to his law office as usual that morning and tried to work on a case. Too restless to concentrate, he soon tossed the legal papers aside and went out and pitched ball for a while back of a store, then played a game or two of billiards, and finally went to the “Springfield Journal” to hear the news. The telegraph office occupied the room above. He was sitting in a big arm-chair, discussing the second ballot, when suddenly the operator burst down the stairway, crying: “Mr. Lincoln, you are nominated! You are nominated!”

Lincoln's lower lip trembled slightly, his face flushed. For a few seconds he stopped breathing.

It was the most dramatic moment of his life.

After nineteen years of desolating defeats, he had been suddenly whirled to the dizzy heights of victory.

Men rushed up and down the streets shouting the news. The mayor ordered the firing of a hundred guns.

Scores of old friends flocked about Lincoln, half laughing, half crying, shaking his hands, tossing their hats into the air, yelling in mad excitement.

“Excuse me, boys,” he pleaded; “there is a little woman down on Eighth Street who will want to hear this.”

And away he dashed, his coat-tails sailing behind him.

The streets of Springfield were rosy all that night with the light of bonfires fed by tar-barrels and rail fences, and the saloons never closed their doors.

It wasn't long before half of the nation was singing:

Old Abe Lincoln came out of the wilderness,
Out of the wilderness, out of the wilderness;
Old Abe Lincoln came out of the wilderness,
Down in Illinois.

16

Stephen A. Douglas did more than any one else to elevate Lincoln to the White House, for Douglas split the Democratic party and put three candidates in the field against Lincoln instead of one.

With the opposition hopelessly divided, Lincoln realized, early in the contest, that he would be victorious; but, nevertheless, he feared that he would not be able to carry his own precinct or his home town. A committee made a house-to-house canvass in advance, to find out how the people in Springfield were going to ballot. When Lincoln saw the result of this canvass, he was astonished: all except three of the twenty-three ministers and theological students in town were against him, and so were many of their stanchest followers. Lincoln commented bitterly: “They pretend to believe in the Bible and be God-fearing Christians; yet by their ballots they are demonstrating that they don't care whether slavery is voted up or down. But I know God cares and humanity cares, and if they don't, surely they have not read their Bibles aright.”

It is surprising to discover that all of Lincoln's relatives on his father's side, and all except one on his mother's side, voted against him. Why? Because they were Democrats.

Lincoln was elected by a minority of the votes of the nation. His opponents had approximately three votes to his two. It was a sectional triumph, for of his two million votes only twenty-four thousand came from the South. A change of only one vote in twenty would have given the Northwest to Douglas and thrown the election into the House of Representatives, where the South would have won.

In nine Southern States no one cast a Republican ballot. Think of it. In all Alabama, Arkansas, Florida, Georgia, Louisiana, Mississippi, North Carolina, Tennessee, and Texas not one man voted for Abraham Lincoln. This was ominous.

To appreciate what happened immediately after Lincoln's election, we must review the story of a movement that had raged over the North like a hurricane. For thirty years a fanatical group, obsessed by a holy zeal for the destruction of slavery, had been preparing the country for war. During all that time an unbroken stream of vitriolic pamphlets and bitter books had flowed from their presses; and paid lecturers had visited every city, town, and hamlet in the North, exhibiting the tattered, filthy garments worn by slaves, displaying their chains and manacles, holding up bloodstained whips and spiked collars and other instruments of torture. Escaped slaves themselves were pressed into service and toured the country, giving inflammatory accounts of brutalities they had seen and atrocities they had endured.

In 1839 the American Anti-Slavery Society issued a booklet entitled “American Slavery As It Is—The Testimony of 1,000 Witnesses.” In this pamphlet, eye-witnesses related specific instances of cruelties they had observed: slaves had had their hands plunged into boiling water, they had been branded with red-hot irons, their teeth had been knocked out, they had been stabbed with knives, their flesh had been torn by bloodhounds, they had been whipped until they died, had been burned at the stake. Shrieking mothers had had their children torn from them forever and sold in the slave-pen and on the auction-block. Women were whipped because they did not bear more children, and strong white men with big bones and large muscles were offered twenty-five dollars for cohabiting with black women, since light-colored children sold for more money, especially if they were girls.

The favorite and most flaming indictment of the Abolitionist was miscegenation. Southern men were accused of cherishing negro slavery because of their love of “unbridled licentiousness.”

“The South,” cried Wendell Phillips, “is one great brothel where half a million women are flogged to prostitution.”

Tales of sensuality so revolting that they could not be reprinted now, were broadcast in Abolition pamphlets then. Slaveowners were accused of violating their own mulatto daughters and selling them to be the mistresses of other men.

Stephen S. Foster declared that the Methodist Church in the South had fifty thousand black female members who were forced with whips to lead immoral lives, and he declared that the sole reason why Methodist preachers of that region favored slavery was because they wanted concubines for themselves.

Lincoln himself, during his debates with Douglas, declared that in 1850 there were 405,751 mulattoes in the United States, and that nearly all had sprung from black slaves and white masters.

Because the Constitution protected the rights of slave-owners, the Abolitionists cursed it as “a covenant with death and an agreement with hell.”

As a climax to all Abolition literature, the wife of a povertystricken professor of theology sat down at her dining-room table and wrote a book which she called “Uncle Tom's Cabin.” Sobbing as she wrote, she told her story in a storm of feeling. Finally she said God was writing the story. It dramatized and made real the tragedies of slavery as nothing else had ever done. It stirred the emotions of millions of readers and achieved a greater sale and exerted a more profound influence than any other novel that has ever been written.

When Lincoln was introduced to Harriet Beecher Stowe, the author, he called her the little woman that started the big war.

And what was the result of this well-meant but fanatical campaign of overstatement waged by the Abolitionists of the North? Did it convince the Southerners that they were wrong? Far from it. The effect was such as might have been expected. The hatred stirred up by the Abolitionists did what hatred always does: it bred hatred in return. It made the South wish to part company with its insolent, meddlesome critics. Truth seldom flourishes in an atmosphere of politics or of emotion, and on both sides of the Mason and Dixon's Line tragic error had grown to its bloody blossom time.

When the “black Republicans” elected Lincoln in 1860, the Southerners were firmly convinced that slavery was doomed, and that they had to choose at once between abolition and secession. So why not secede? Didn't they have a right to?

That question had been hotly debated back and forth for half a century, and various States at one time or another had threatened to leave the Union. For example: during the War of 1812 the New England States talked very seriously of forming a separate nation; and the Connecticut Legislature passed a resolution declaring that “the state of Connecticut is a free, sovereign and independent state.”

Even Lincoln himself had once believed in the right of secession. He had said during a speech in Congress: “Any people anywhere, being inclined and having the power, have the right to rise up and shake off the existing government, and form a new one that suits them better. That is a most valuable, a most sacred right—a right which we hope and believe is to liberate the world. Nor is the right confined to cases in which the whole people of an existing government may choose to exercise it. Any portion of such people that can, may revolutionize and make their own of so much of the territory as they inhabit.”

He had said that in 1848. This, however, was 1860, and he no longer believed it. But the South did. Six weeks after Lincoln's election South Carolina passed an Ordinance of Secession. Charleston celebrated the new “Declaration of Independence” with martial music and bonfires and fireworks and dancing in the streets. Six other States followed in rapid succession; and two days before Lincoln left Springfield for Washington, Jefferson Davis was elected President of a new nation, founded upon what was called “the great truth... that slavery is the negro's natural and normal condition.”

The outgoing administration of Buchanan, honeycombed with disloyalty, did nothing whatever to prevent all this; so Lincoln was obliged to sit helplessly in Springfield for three months, and watch the Union dissolving and the republic tottering on the verge of ruin. He saw the Confederacy buying guns and building forts and drilling soldiers; and he realized that he would have to lead a people through a civil war—bitter and bloody.

He was so distressed that he couldn't sleep at night. He lost forty pounds in weight, from worry.

Lincoln, who was superstitious, believed that coming events cast their shadow through dreams and omens. The day after his election in 1860 he went home in the afternoon and threw himself down on a haircloth sofa. Opposite him was a bureau with a swinging mirror; and, as he looked into the mirror, he saw himself reflected with one body but with two faces—one very pale. He was startled, and he got up, but the illusion vanished. He lay down again, and there was the ghost, plainer than before. The thing worried and haunted him; and he told Mrs. Lincoln about it. She was sure it was a sign that he would be elected to a second term of office, but that the death pallor of one face meant he would not live through the second term.

Lincoln himself soon came to believe very strongly that he was going to Washington to die. He received scores of letters with sketches of gibbets and stilettoes; and almost every mail brought him threats of death.

After the election, Lincoln said to a friend:

“I am worrying to know what to do with my house. I don't want to sell myself out of a home, but if I rent it, it will be pretty well used up by the time I get back.”

But finally he found a man who he thought would take care of the place and keep it in repair; so Lincoln rented it to him for ninety dollars a year; and then inserted this notice in the “Springfield Journal:”

The furniture consisting of Parlor and Chamber Sets, Carpets, Sofas, Chairs, Wardrobes, Bureaus, Bedsteads, Stoves, China, Queensware, Glass, etc., at the residence on the corner of Eighth and Jackson Street is offered at private sale without reserve. For particulars apply at the premises at once.

The neighbors came and looked things over. One wanted a few chairs and a cook-stove, another asked the price of a bed.

“Take whatever you want,” Lincoln probably replied, “and pay me what you think it is worth.”

They paid him little enough.

Mr. L. L. Tilton, superintendent of the Great Western Railway, bought most of the furniture; and later took it with him to Chicago, where it was destroyed in the great fire of 1871.

A few pieces remained in Springfield; and years afterward a bookseller purchased as much of it as possible and took it to Washington and installed it in the rooming-house where Lincoln died. That house stands almost directly across the street from Ford's Theater, and is now the property of the United States Government—a national shrine and museum.

The second-hand chairs that Lincoln's neighbors could have bought for a dollar and a half piece, are to-day worth more than their weight in gold and platinum. Everything that Lincoln touched intimately has now taken on value and glory. The black walnut rocking-chair in which he sat when Booth shot him, sold in 1929 for two thousand five hundred dollars. And a letter that he wrote appointing Major-General Hooker Commander-in-Chief of the Army of the Potomac recently sold at public auction for ten thousand dollars, while a collection of four hundred and eighty-five telegrams that he sent during the war, now owned by Brown University, are valued at a quarter of a million dollars. An unsigned manuscript of one of his unimportant talks was recently purchased for eighteen thousand dollars, and a copy of the Gettysburg address in Lincoln's handwriting brought hundreds of thousands.

The people of Springfield in 1861 little realized what caliber of man Lincoln was, and what he was destined to become.

For years the future great President had been walking down their streets almost every morning with a market-basket over his arm, a shawl about his neck, going to the grocery store and butcher's shop and carrying home his provisions. For years he had been going out each evening to a pasture on the edge of town and cutting out his cow from the rest of the herd and driving her home and milking her, grooming his horse, cleaning the stable, and cutting the firewood and carrying it in for the kitchen stove.

Three weeks before he left for Washington, Lincoln began the preparation of his first inaugural address. Wanting solitude and seclusion, he locked himself in an upstairs room over a general store and set to work. He owned very few books himself; but his law partner had something of a library, and Lincoln asked Herndon to bring him a copy of the Constitution, Andrew Jackson's Proclamation against Nullification, Henry Clay's great speech of 1850, and Webster's Reply to Hayne. And so amidst a lot of plunder in dingy, dusty surroundings, Lincoln wrote the famous speech ending with this beautiful plea to the Southern States:

I am loath to close. We are not enemies but friends. We must not be enemies. Though passion may have strained, it must not break our bonds of affection. The mystic chords of memory, stretching from every battlefield and patriot's grave to every living heart and hearthstone all over this broad land, will swell the chorus of the Union when again touched, as surely they will be, by the better angel of our nature.

Before leaving Illinois he traveled seventy miles to Charleston, in that State, to say farewell to his stepmother. He called her “Mamma,” as he had always done; and she clung to him, saying between her sobs: “I didn't want you to run for President, Abe, and I didn't want to see you elected. My heart tells me that something will happen to you, and that I'll never see you again till we meet in heaven.”

During those last days in Springfield, he thought often of the past and New Salem and Ann Rutledge, dreaming once again the dreams that had proved to be far beyond all earthly realities. A few days before he left for Washington he talked at length about Ann, to a New Salem pioneer who had come to Springfield to reminisce and say farewell. “I loved her deeply,” Lincoln confessed, “and I think of her now very, very often.”

The night before he left Springfield forever Lincoln visited his dingy law office for the last time and settled a few business details. Herndon tells us:

After these things were all disposed of, he crossed to the opposite side of the room and threw himself down on the old office sofa, which, after many years of service, had been moved against the wall for support. He lay for some moments, his face toward the ceiling, without either of us speaking. Presendy he inquired, “Billy, how long have we been together?”

“Over sixteen years,” I answered.

“We've never had a cross word during all that time, have we?” to which I returned a vehement, “No, indeed we have not.”

He then recalled some incidents of his early practice and took great pleasure in delineating the ludicrous features of many a lawsuit on the circuit.... He gathered a bundle of books and papers he wished to take with him and started to go; but before leaving he made the strange request that the sign-board which swung on its rusty hinges at the foot of the stairway should remain. “Let it hang there undisturbed,” he said, with a significant lowering of his voice. “Give our clients to understand that the election of a President makes no change in the firm of Lincoln and Herndon. If I live I'm coming back some time, and then we'll go right on practising law as if nothing had ever happened.”

He lingered for a moment as if to take a last look at the old quarters, and then passed through the door into the narrow hallway. I accompanied him downstairs. On the way he spoke of the unpleasant features surrounding the Presidential office. “I am sick of office-holding already,” he complained, “and I shudder when I think of the tasks that are still ahead.”

Lincoln probably was worth about ten thousand dollars at the time; but he was so short of cash then that he had to borrow money from his friends to pay for his trip to Washington.

The Lincolns spent their last week in Springfield at the Chenery House. The night before they left, their trunks and boxes were brought down to the hotel lobby and Lincoln himself roped them. Then he asked the clerk for some of the hotel cards, turned them over, and wrote on the back: “A. Lincoln, Executive Mansion, Washington, D.C.,” and tacked them on his baggage.

The next morning, at half-past seven, the dilapidated old bus backed up to the hotel, and Lincoln and his family got in and jolted away to the Wabash station, where a special train was waiting to take them to Washington.

It was dark and rainy, but the station platform was crowded with a thousand or fifteen hundred of his old neighbors. They formed a line and slowly filed by Lincoln, shaking his great bony hand. Finally the ringing of the engine bell warned him that it was time to go aboard. He entered his private car by the front steps and a minute later appeared on the rear platform.

He had not intended to make a speech. He had told the newspaper reporters that it would not be necessary for them to be at the station, as he would have nothing to say. However, as he looked for the last time into the faces of his old neighbors, he felt he must say something. The words he uttered that morning in the falling rain are not to be compared with those he spoke at Gettysburg, or placed beside the sublime spiritual masterpiece that he pronounced on the occasion of his second inauguration. But this farewell speech is as beautiful as one of the Psalms of David, and it contains perhaps more of personal emotion and pathos than any other of Lincoln's addresses.

There were only two times in his life that Lincoln wept when trying to speak. This morning was one of them:

“My friends: No one, not in my situation, can appreciate my feeling of sadness at this parting. To this place, and the kindness of these people, I owe everything. Here I have lived a quarter of a century, and have passed from a young to an old man. Here my children have been born, and one is buried. I now leave, not knowing when or whether ever I may return, with a task before me greater than that which rested upon Washington. Without the assistance of that Divine Being who ever attended him, I cannot succeed. With that assistance, I cannot fail. Trusting in Him, who can go with me, and remain with you, and be everywhere for good, let us confidently hope that all will yet be well. To His care commending you as I hope in your prayers you will commend me, I bid you an affectionate farewell.”

17

While Lincoln was en route to Washington for his inauguration, both the United States Secret Service and private detectives discovered what they believed was a plot to assassinate him as he passed through Baltimore.

In alarm Lincoln's friends pleaded with him to abandon the schedule that had been announced, and urged him to slip into Washington incognito by night.

That sounded cowardly, and Lincoln knew it would raise a storm of scoffs and sneers. He was decidedly against it. But finally, after hours of pleading, he bowed to the wishes of his trusted advisers, and prepared to make the rest of the trip secretly.

As soon as Mrs. Lincoln heard about the altered arrangements she insisted that she would go with him, and when she was told most emphatically that she must come on a later train she lost her temper and protested so loudly that she all but gave the plan away.

It had been announced that Lincoln would speak in Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, on February 22, spend the night there, and then leave the next morning for Baltimore and Washington.

He made his speech in Harrisburg according to schedule; but, instead of spending the night there, he slipped out of the back door of the hotel that evening at six and, disguised in an old threadbare overcoat and a soft wool hat such as he had never worn before, he was driven to an unlighted railway coach, and a few minutes later an engine was whirling him away to Philadelphia, and the telegraph wires in Harrisburg were cut at once so that the information would not be relayed to the would-be assassins.

At Philadelphia, his party had to wait for an hour to change trains and stations. In order to prevent recognition during that time, Lincoln and Allan Pinkerton, the famous detective, drove about the streets of the city in a darkened cab.

At 10:55, leaning on Pinkerton's arm and stooping so as not to draw attention to his height, Lincoln entered the station by a side door. He carried his head bent forward and had his old traveling shawl drawn close so that it almost covered his face. In that guise, he crossed the waiting-room and made his way to the rear section of the last sleeping-car on the train, which one of Pinkerton's aides, a woman, had had cut off from the rest of the car by a heavy curtain and reserved for her “invalid brother.”

Lincoln had received scores of threatening letters, declaring that he would never live to enter the White House, and General Winfield Scott, Commander-in-Chief of the Army, feared that Lincoln would be shot during the inaugural address—and so did thousands of others.

Many people in Washington were afraid to attend the ceremony.

So old General Scott had sixty soldiers stationed under the platform at the east portico of the Capitol from which Lincoln read his inaugural address; and he had soldiers standing on guard in the Capitol behind the President, and soldiers encircling the audience in front of him. And after the ceremony, the new President stepped into a carriage and rode back through Pennsylvania Avenue under the protection of buildings covered with sharpshooters in green coats, and between rows of infantrymen with bristling bayonets.

When he finally reached the White House without a bullet in his heart, many people were surprised.

Others were disappointed.

For several years prior to 1861 the nation had been struggling under a financial depression. Suffering had been so intense that the Government had been compelled to send troops to New York City to prevent hungry mobs from breaking into the sub-Treasury.

Thousands of gaunt, desperate men were still looking for work when Lincoln was inaugurated; and they knew that the Republicans, coming into power for the first time, would dismiss all Democratic office-holders, even down to the ten-dollar-aweek clerks.

Scores of applicants were scrambling for every job; and Lincoln had not been in the White House two hours when he was overwhelmed by them. They rushed through the halls; jammed the corridors; took entire possession of the East Room; and invaded even the private parlors.

Beggars came, importuning him for the price of a lunch. One man wanted Lincoln to give him an old pair of pants.

A widow came, seeking an appointment for a man who had promised to marry her provided she could get him an office that would support a family.

Hundreds came merely to get his autograph. An Irishwoman who kept a boarding-house rushed to the White House to implore Lincoln to help her collect a board bill from a government clerk.

As soon as an office-holder became seriously ill, dozens of applicants flocked to Lincoln, asking for the appointment “in case he should die.”

Every one was armed with testimonials, but of course Lincoln couldn't read a tenth of them. One day when two applicants for the same post-office thrust huge bundles of letters into his hands he simplified matters by tossing both packages unopened onto the scales, and appointed the man who had the heavier one.

Scores came to see Lincoln again and again, demanding jobs and abusing him savagely because he refused. Many were loafers without a shred of merit. One woman came asking for an appointment for her husband, admitting he was too drunk to come himself.

Their sordid selfishness, their voracious greed, appalled Lincoln. They intercepted him on his way to lunch. They rushed up to his carriage as he drove through the streets, presenting their credentials, begging for jobs. Even after Lincoln had been President for a year and the nation had been at war for ten months, the milling mob still hounded him.

“Will they never cease?” he exclaimed.

The mad onslaught of office-seekers had killed Zachary Taylor before he had been President a year and a half. The worry of it killed “Tippecanoe” Harrison in four weeks. But Lincoln had to endure the office-seekers and run a war at the same time. Finally, however, even his iron constitution all but broke under the strain. Stricken with an attack of smallpox, he said:

“Tell all the office-seekers to come at once, for now I have something I can give to all of them.”

Lincoln hadn't been in the White House twenty-four hours when he was confronted with a grave and momentous problem. The garrison holding Fort Sumter, in the harbor at Charleston, South Carolina, was almost out of food. The President had to decide whether to provision the fort or surrender it to the Confederates.

His army and navy advisers said: “Don't try to send food. If you do, it will mean war.”

Six of the seven members of his Cabinet said the same thing. But Lincoln knew that he couldn't evacuate Sumter without virtually recognizing secession and encouraging it, and dissolving the Union.

In his inaugural address he had declared that he had the most solemn oath “registered in heaven” to “preserve, protect, and defend” the Union. He intended to keep his oath.

So he gave the orders, and away sailed the U.S.S. Powhatan, carrying bacon and beans and bread for Fort Sumter. But no guns, no men, no ammunition.

When Jefferson Davis heard the news he telegraphed General Beauregard to attack Fort Sumter if he thought it necessary.

Major Anderson, in command of the fortress, sent word to General Beauregard that, if he would wait only four days, the garrison would be compelled to evacuate through starvation, for they were already living on nothing but salt pork.

Why didn't Beauregard wait?

Perhaps it was because a few of his advisers felt that “unless blood were sprinkled in the faces of the people,” some of the seceding States might return to the Union.

Shooting a few Yankees would arouse enthusiasm and cement the Confederacy.

So Beauregard issued his tragic orders; and, at half-past four on the morning of April 12, a shell screamed through the air and fell hissing into the sea near the walls of the fort.

For thirty-four hours, the bombardment continued.

The Confederates turned the affair into a social event. Brave young men, gay in their new uniforms, fired their cannon to the applause of fashionable society women promenading the wharves and the Battery.

On Sunday afternoon the Union soldiers surrendered the fort and four barrels of salt pork; and, with the Stars and Stripes flying, and the band playing “Yankee Doodle,” they sailed away, bound for New York.

For a week Charleston abandoned itself to joy. A Te Dewn was sung with great pomp in the cathedral; and crowds paraded the streets, drinking and singing and carousing in tap rooms and taverns.

Judged by the loss of life, the bombardment of Sumter was nothing. Neither side lost a man. But judged by the train of events which it set in motion, few battles have been more momentous. It was the beginning of the bloodiest war the world had ever known up to that time.

PART THREE

18

Lincoln issued a call for seventy-five thousand men, and threw the country into a frenzy of patriotic fervor. Mass-meetings were held in thousands of halls and public squares, bands played, flags waved, orators harangued, fireworks were set off; and men, leaving the plow and the pencil, flocked to the flag.

In ten weeks, a hundred and ninety thousand recruits were drilling and marching and singing:

John Brown's body lies a-mouldering in the grave,
But his soul goes marching on.

But who was to lead these troops to victory? There was one recognized military genius in the army then—and only one. His name was Robert E. Lee. He was a Southerner; but, nevertheless, Lincoln offered him the command of the Union Army. If Lee had accepted, the whole history of the war would have been vastly different. For a time he did think seriously of accepting: thought about it, read his Bible, and got down on his knees and prayed about it, and paced the floor of his bedchamber all night, trying honestly to come to a righteous decision.

He agreed with Lincoln on many things. He hated slavery as Lincoln hated it; Lee had freed his own negroes long ago. He loved the Union almost as Lincoln loved it; he believed that it was “perpetual,” that secession was “revolution,” that “no greater calamity” could befall the nation.

But—and this was the trouble—he was a Virginian, a proud Virginian, a Virginian who put State above Nation. For two hundred years his forebears had been mighty factors in the destiny, first of the Colony, and then of the State. His father, the famous “Light Horse Harry” Lee, had helped Washington chase the redcoats of King George; after that, he had been Governor of Virginia; and he had taught his son, Robert E., to love the State more than the Union.

So when Virginia cast her lot with the South, Lee quietly announced: “I cannot lead a hostile army against my relatives, my children and my home. I go to share the miseries of my people.”

That decision probably lengthened the Civil War by two or three years.

To whom could Lincoln now turn for help and guidance? General Winfield Scott was then in command of the army. Scott was an old man. He had won a notable victory at Lundy's Lane in the War of 1812. And this was 1861. Forty-nine years later. He was weary, now, in body and mind. His youthful initiative and courage had long since perished.

Besides, he was suffering from a spinal affliction. “For more than three years,” he wrote, “I have been unable to mount a horse or walk more than a few paces at a time, and that with much pain.”

In addition, he now had “other and new infirmities—dropsy and vertigo.”

Such was the man to whom Lincoln had to look to lead the nation to victory: a broken old soldier who ought to have been in the hospital, with a nurse and a water mattress.

Lincoln had called in April for seventy-five thousand men to serve for three months. Their enlistments would expire in July; so, in the last part of June, a great hue and cry arose for action! Action! Action!

Day after day Horace Greeley kept “The Nation's War Cry” standing in bold type at the head of the “Tribune's” editorial columns: “Forward to Richmond!”

Business was bad. The banks were afraid to extend credit. Even the Government had to pay twelve per cent for borrowed money. People were disturbed. “Now, look here,” they said, “there is no use fooling any longer. Let's strike one sharp blow, capture Lee's army, and have this nasty mess over and done with once and for all.”

That sounded attractive, and every one agreed.

Every one except the military authorities: they knew the army wasn't ready. But the President, bowing to public clamor, finally ordered an advance.

So, on a hot, brilliant July day, McDowell, with his “Grand Army,” thirty thousand strong, marched away to attack the Confederates at Bull Run, a creek in Virginia. No American general then living had ever before commanded so large a body of men.

What an army it was! Raw. Half trained. Several of the regiments had arrived within the last ten days, and had no idea of discipline.

“With all my personal effort,” said Sherman, who commanded a brigade, “I could not prevent the men from straggling for water, blackberries, and anything on the way that they fancied.”

The Zouaves and Turcos in those days were regarded as mighty warriors; so many soldiers aspired to dress like them and act like them. Consequently, thousands of the troops marched away to Bull Run, that day, with their heads in scarlet turbans, their legs in red baggy breeches. They looked more like a comicopera troupe than men marching to death.

Several silk-hatted Congressmen drove out to watch the battle, taking with them their wives and pet dogs, and baskets of sandwiches and bottles of Bordeaux.

Finally, at ten o'clock on a broiling day in late July, the first real battle of the Civil War began.

What happened?

As soon as some of the inexperienced troops saw cannonballs crashing through the trees, heard men shrieking, and saw them pitching forward on the ground with blood running out of their mouths—as soon as they saw this, the Pennsylvania regiment and the New York Battery happened to recall that their ninety-day term of enlistment had expired; and they insisted on being mustered out of service. Then and there! Quick! And, as McDowell reports, they “moved to the rear to the sound of the enemy's cannon.”

The rest of the troops fought surprisingly well until about half-past four in the afternoon. Then suddenly the Confederates, throwing twenty-three hundred fresh men into the assault, took the field by storm.

From mouth to mouth ran the report, “Johnston's army has come.”

A panic ensued.

Twenty-five thousand soldiers, refusing to obey orders, broke from the field in mad confusion. McDowell and scores of officers made frantic efforts to stem the rout, but it was useless.

Quickly the Confederate artillery shelled the road, already jammed with fleeing soldiers and commissariat wagons and ambulances and the carriages of silk-hatted, sightseeing Congressmen. Women screamed and fainted. Men shouted and cursed and trampled on one another, A wagon was upset on a bridge. The highway was clogged. Plunging and kicking horses were cut from wagons and ambulances and artillery pieces; and frightened men in red turbans and yellow trousers leaped upon them and dashed away, the traces trailing in the dust, the harness dragging at their heels.

They imagined that the Confederate cavalry was in close pursuit. The cry of “the cavalry! the cavalry!” convulsed them with fear.

The grand debacle had now become a terror-stricken mob.

Nothing like it had ever before been witnessed on any American battle-field.

Maddened men threw away their guns, coats, caps, belts, bayonets, and fled as if driven by some unknown fury. Some sank on the road in utter exhaustion and were crushed beneath the oncoming horses and wagons.

The day was Sunday, and the distant roar of the cannon twenty miles away reached Lincoln's ears as he sat in church. At the close of the services, he rushed to the War Department, to read the telegrams that had already begun to pour in from different parts of the field. Fragmentary and incomplete as they were, Lincoln was eager to discuss them with General Scott; so he hurried to the old general's quarters, and found him taking a nap.

General Scott awoke, yawned, rubbed his eyes; but he was so infirm he couldn't get up without help. “He had some sort of harness with a pulley arrangement attached to the ceiling of the room; and, grasping the strap, he pulled his vast bulk into an upright position and swung his feet off the lounge upon the floor.”

“I don't know,” he said, “how many men are in the field, where they are, how they are armed, how they are equipped, or what they are capable of doing. Nobody comes to tell me, and I am in ignorance about it.”

And he was the head of all the Union armies!

The old general looked at a few telegrams that were coming in from the battle-field, told Lincoln there was nothing to worry about, complained of his aching back, and went to sleep again.

At midnight the broken army, in a riot of disorder, began to stagger across the Long Bridge and pour over the Potomac into Washington.

Tables were quickly set up on the sidewalks, wagon-loads of bread suddenly appeared from somewhere, and society women stood over wash-boilers of steaming soup and coffee, dispensing food.

McDowell, utterly exhausted, had fallen asleep under a tree while writing a despatch, his pencil still in his hand, a sentence half finished. His soldiers were too weary now to care for anything, so they threw themselves on the sidewalks and slept, inert as dead men, in the steadily falling rain—some still clutching their muskets as they slept.

Lincoln sat that night until long after dawn, listening to the stories of the newspaper correspondents and silk-hatted civilians who had witnessed the debacle.

Many public men were thrown into a panic. Horace Greeley wanted to end the war at once, on any terms. He was positive the South could never be conquered.

London bankers were so certain that the Union would be destroyed that their agent in Washington rushed to the Treasury Department on Sunday afternoon, demanding that the United States Government give security immediately for forty thousand dollars that was owing them.

He was told to come back on Monday, that the United States Government would probably still be doing business at the old stand then.

Failure and defeat were not new experiences to Lincoln. He had known them all his life; they did not crush him; his faith in the ultimate triumph of his cause remained firm, his confidence unshaken. He went among the disheartened soldiers, shaking hands with them, and saying over and over: “God bless you. God bless you.” He cheered them, sat down and ate beans with them, revived their drooping spirits, and talked of brighter to-morrows.

It was to be a long war. He saw that now. So he asked Congress for a levy of four hundred thousand men. Congress raised him a hundred thousand, and authorized half a million to serve for three years.

But who could lead them? Old Scott, unable to walk, unable to get out of bed without a harness and pulley, and snoring the afternoon away during a battle? Absolutely not. He was slated for the discard.

And there now gallops into the limelight one of the most charming and disappointing generals that ever sat in a saddle.

Lincoln's troubles were not over. They were just beginning.

19

During the first few weeks of the war a handsome young general named McClellan marched into West Virginia with twenty cannon and a portable printing-press, and whipped a few Confederates. His battles didn't amount to much—mere skirmishes. That was all. But they were the first victories of the North, so they seemed important. McClellan saw to that; he dashed off scores of dramatic and bombastic despatches on his portable press, proclaiming his achievements to the nation.

A few years later his absurd antics would have been laughed at; but the war was new then, people were confused and eager for some kind of leader to appear; so they took this boastful young officer at his own valuation. Congress offered him a resolution of thanks, people called him “the Young Napoleon,” and after the defeat at Bull Run Lincoln brought him to Washington and made him commander of the Army of the Potomac.

He was a born leader of men. His troops would burst into applause when they saw him galloping toward them on his white charger. Besides, he was a hard and conscientious worker; he took the army that had been crushed at Bull Run, drilled it, renewed its self-confidence, and built up its morale. No one could excel him at that sort of thing; and by the time October came he had one of the largest and best-trained armies that had ever been seen in the Western world. His troops were not only trained to fight; they were eager for the fray.

Every one was crying for action—every one but McClellan. Lincoln repeatedly urged him to strike a blow. But he wouldn't do it. He held parades and talked a lot about what he was going to do; but that was all it amounted to—talk.

He delayed, he procrastinated, he gave all manner of excuses. But go forward he would not.

Once he said he couldn't advance because the army was resting. Lincoln asked him what it had done to make it tired.

Another time—after the Battle of Antietam—an amazing thing happened. McClellan had far more men than Lee. Lee had been defeated; and had McClellan pursued him, he might have captured his army and ended the war. Lincoln kept urging him for weeks to follow Lee—urging by letter, by telegram, and by special messenger. Finally McClellan said he couldn't move because his horses were fatigued and had sore tongues!

It you ever visit New Salem, you will see a depression about a rod down the hillside from Offut's grocery where Lincoln worked as a clerk. The Clary's Grove Boys used to have their cock-fights there, and Lincoln acted as referee. For weeks Bab McNab had been boasting of a young rooster that could whip anything in Sangamon County. But when this fowl was finally put into the pit, he turned tail and refused to fight. Bab, in disgust, grabbed him and tossed him high into the air. The rooster alighted on a pile of firewood near by, then strutted and ruffled up his feathers and crowed defiantly.

“Yes, damn you!” said McNab. “You're great on dressparade, but you are not worth a cuss in a fight.”

Lincoln said that McClellan reminded him of Bab McNab's rooster.

Once, during the Peninsular Campaign, General Magruder with five thousand men held up McClellan with a hundred thousand. McClellan, afraid to attack, threw up breastworks and kept nagging Lincoln for more men, more men, more men.

“If by magic,” said Lincoln, “I could reinforce McClellan with a hundred thousand men, he would go into ecstasy, thank me, and tell me he would go to Richmond to-morrow; but when to-morrow came, he would telegraph that he had certain information that the enemy had four hundred thousand men and that he could not advance without reinforcements.”

“If McClellan had a million men,” said Stanton, Secretary of War, “he would swear that the enemy had two million, and then sit down in the mud and yell for three million.”

“The Young Napoleon” had bounded into fame with one leap, and it had gone to his head like champagne. His egotism was boundless. He described Lincoln and his Cabinet as “hounds”... “wretches”... “some of the greatest geese I have ever seen.”

He was positively insulting to Lincoln; and when the President came to see him, McClellan kept him waiting for half an hour in the anteroom.

Once the general got home at eleven o'clock at night and his servant informed him that Lincoln had been waiting there for hours to see him. McClellan passed the door of the room where the President sat, ignored him, went on upstairs, and sent down word that he had gone to bed.

The newspapers played up incidents like these, and they became the gossip and scandal of Washington. With tears rolling down her cheeks, Mrs. Lincoln implored the President to remove “that awful wind-bag,” as she called him.

“Mother,” he replied, “I know he doesn't do right, but I mustn't consider my feelings at a time like this. I am willing to hold McClellan's hat, if he will only bring us victories.”

The summer drifted into autumn; autumn passed into winter; spring was almost at hand; and still McClellan did nothing but drill men and have dress-parades, and talk.

The nation was aroused, and Lincoln was being condemned and criticized on all sides for McClellan's inaction.

“Your delay is ruining us,” cried Lincoln, as he issued an official order for an advance.

McClellan had to move now or resign. So he rushed to Harper's Ferry, ordering his troops to follow immediately. He planned to invade Virginia from that point, after bridging the Potomac with boats which were to be brought through the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal. But, at the last moment, the whole project had to be abandoned because the boats were six inches too wide to float through the canal locks.

When McClellan told Lincoln of this fiasco and said that the pontoons were not ready, the patient, long-suffering President lost his temper at last; and, lapsing into the phraseology of the hay-fields of Pigeon Creek Valley, Indiana, he demanded, “Why, in the hell, ain't they ready?”

The nation was asking the same question in about the same tone.

At last, in April, “the Young Napoleon” made a grand speech to his soldiers, as the older Napoleon used to do, and then started off with one hundred and twenty thousand men singing “The Girl I Left Behind Me.”

The war had been going on for a year. McClellan boasted that he was going to clean up the whole thing now, at once, and let the boys get home in time to plant a little late corn and millet.

Incredible as it seems, Lincoln and Stanton were so optimistic that they wired the governors of the various States to accept no more volunteers, to close the recruiting-places, and to sell the public property belonging to these organizations.

One of the military maxims of Frederick the Great was: “Know the man you are fighting.” Lee and Stonewall Jackson appreciated full well the kind of a weak-kneed Napoleon they had to deal with—a timid, cautious, whining Napoleon who was never on the battle-field, because he couldn't endure the sight of blood.

So Lee let him spend three months crawling up to Richmond. McClellan got so close that his men could hear the clocks in the church towers striking the hour.

Then the inspired Lee crashed upon him in a series of terrific onslaughts, and, in seven days, forced him back to the shelter of his gunboats and killed fifteen thousand of his men.

Thus the “en grande affair,” as McClellan called it, ended in one of the bloodiest failures of the war.

But, as usual, McClellan blamed it all on “those traitors in Washington.” The old story: they hadn't sent him enough men. Their “cowardice and folly” made his “blood boil.” He hated Lincoln and the Cabinet, now, more than he despised the Confederates. He denounced their actions as “the most infamous thing history has ever recorded.”

McClellan had more troops than his enemies—usually far more. He was never able to use at one time all that he then possessed. But he kept on demanding more. More. He asked for an additional ten thousand, then for fifty thousand, finally for a hundred thousand. They were not to be had. He knew it, and Lincoln knew that he knew it. Lincoln told him his demands were “simply absurd.”

McClellan's telegrams to Stanton and the President were fiery and insulting. They sounded like the ravings of a madman. They accused Lincoln and Stanton of doing their best to destroy his army. They made charges so grave that the telegraph operator refused to deliver them.

The nation was appalled, Wall Street was seized with panic, the country was submerged in gloom.

Lincoln grew thin and haggard. “I am as nearly inconsolable,” he said, “as one can be and live.”

McClellan's father-in-law and chief of staff, P. B. Marcy, said there was nothing to do now but capitulate.

When Lincoln heard this, he flushed with anger, sent for Marcy, and said:

“General, I understand you have used the word ‘capitulate.’ That is a word not to be used in connection with our army.”

20

Lincoln had learned, back in New Salem, that it was easy to rent a building and stock it with groceries; but to make it pay required qualities which neither he nor his drunken partner possessed.

He was destined to discover, through years of heartbreak and bloodshed, that it was easy to get a half million soldiers who were willing to die, and a hundred million dollars to equip them with rifles and bullets and blankets; but to win victories required a kind of leadership which it was almost impossible to find.

“How much in military matters,” exclaimed Lincoln, “depends on one master mind!”

So, time and again, he went down on his knees, asking the Almighty to send him a Robert E. Lee or a Joseph E. Johnston or a Stonewall Jackson.

“Jackson,” he said, “is a brave, honest, Presbyterian soldier. If we only had such a man to lead the armies of the North, the country would not be appalled with so many disasters.”

But where in all the Union forces was another Stonewall Jackson to be found? Nobody knew. Edmund Clarence Stedman published a famous poem every verse of which ended with the plea, “Abraham Lincoln, give us a Man.”

It was more than the refrain of a poem. It was the cry of a bleeding and distraught nation.

The President wept as he read it.

For two years he tried to find the leader for whom the nation was crying. He would give the army to one general who would lead it to futile slaughter, and set ten or thirty or forty thousand widows and orphans weeping and wailing throughout the land. Then this discredited commander would be relieved; and another, equally inept, would try his hand and get ten thousand more slaughtered; and Lincoln, clad in dressing-gown and carpet-slippers, would pace the floor all night as the reports came in, crying over and over:

“My God! What will the country say? My God! What will the country say?”

Then another general would assume command, and the futile slaughter would go on.

Some military critics now hold that McClellan, with all his astounding faults and amazing incapacity, was probably the best commander the Army of the Potomac ever had. So imagine, if you can, what the others must have been!

After McClellan's failure, Lincoln tried John Pope. Pope had done splendid work out in Missouri, had captured an island in the Mississippi and several thousand men.

He was like McClellan in two ways: he was handsome, and he was boastful. He declared that his headquarters was “in the saddle;” and he issued so many bombastic announcements that he was soon called “Proclamation Pope.”

“I have come to you from the West, where we have always seen the backs of our enemies.” With that blunt, tactless sentence, he opened his first address to the army. He then proceeded to rebuke the troops for their inaction in the East, and insinuated that they were infernal cowards; and ended by boasting of the military miracles he would perform.

This proclamation made the new commander about as popular as a diamond-backed rattlesnake in dog-days: officers and men alike detested him.

McClellan's hatred for him was intense. Pope had come to take his place. Nobody realized that better than did McClellan—he was already writing for a position in New York—and he was consumed with jealousy, was bitter with envy and resentment.

Pope led the army into Virginia; a great battle was imminent; he needed every man he could get; so Lincoln showered McClellan with telegrams, ordering him to rush his men to Pope's aid with all possible celerity.

But did McClellan obey? He did not. He argued, he delayed, he protested, he telegraphed excuses, he recalled corps that he had sent ahead, and he “exhausted all the resources of a diabolical ingenuity in order to keep Pope from receiving reinforcements.” “Let Mr. Pope,” said he, contemptuously, “get out of his own scrape.”

Even after he heard the roar of the Confederate artillery, he still managed to keep thirty thousand of his troops from going to the aid of his obnoxious rival.

So Lee overwhelmed Pope's army on the old battle-field of Bull Run. The slaughter was terrible. The Federal soldiers again fled in a panic.

It was the story of the first Bull Run over again: once more a bloody and beaten mob poured into Washington.

Lee pursued them with his victorious troops. And even Lincoln believed the capital was lost. Gunboats were ordered up the river, and all the clerks in Washington—civilian and government alike—were called to arms to defend the city.

Stanton, Secretary of War, in a wild panic, telegraphed the governors of half a dozen States, imploring them to send all their militia and volunteer forces by special trains.

Saloons were closed, church bells tolled; men fell on their knees, beseeching Almighty God to save the city.

The old people and the women and children fled in terror. The streets resounded with the hoofs of hurrying horses, with the rattle of carriages dashing away to Maryland.

Stanton, preparing to transfer the Government to New York, ordered the arsenal stripped and all its supplies shipped North.

Chase, Secretary of the Treasury, ordered the nation's silver and gold transferred in feverish haste to the sub-Treasury in Wall Street.

Lincoln, weary and discouraged, exclaimed with a mingled groan and sigh:

“What shall I do?... What shall I do?... The bottom is out of the tub, the bottom is out of the tub.”

People believed that McClellan, in order to get revenge, had longed to see “Mr. Pope” defeated and his army crushed.

Even Lincoln had already called him to the White House and told him that people were accusing him of being a traitor, of wanting to see Washington captured and the South triumphant.

Stanton stormed about in a rage, his face fiery with indignation and hatred. Those who saw him said that if McClellan had walked into the war-office then, Stanton would have rushed at him and knocked him down.

Chase was even more bitter. He didn't want to hit McClellan. He said the man ought to be shot.

And the pious Chase wasn't speaking figuratively. Neither was he exaggerating. He literally wanted McClellan blindfolded, backed up against a stone wall, and a dozen bullets sent crashing through his heart.

But Lincoln, with his understanding nature and Christ-like spirit, condemned no one. True, Pope had failed, but hadn't he done his best? Lincoln, himself, had met defeat too often to blame any one else for failure.

So he sent Pope out to the Northwest to subdue an uprising of Sioux Indians, and gave the army back to McClellan. Why? Because, Lincoln said: “There is no man in the army who can lick these troops of ours into shape half as well as he.... If he can't fight, himself, he excels in making others ready to fight.” The President knew that he would be condemned for restoring “little Mac” to command. And he was—bitterly. Even by his Cabinet. Stanton and Chase actually declared that they would rather have Washington captured by Lee than to see the traitorous and contemptible McClellan given command of the army again.

Lincoln was so hurt at their violent opposition that he said he would resign if the Cabinet wished it.

A few months later, after the Battle of Antietam, McClellan absolutely refused to obey Lincoln's orders to follow Lee and attack him, so the army was taken away from him again; and his military career was ended forever.

The Army of the Potomac must have another leader. But who was he? Where was he? No one knew.

In desperation, Lincoln offered the command to Burnside. He wasn't fit for it, and he knew it. He refused it twice; and, when it was forced upon him, he wept. Then he took the army and made a rash attack on Lee's fortifications at Fredericksburg, and lost thirteen thousand men. Men uselessly butchered, for there wasn't the faintest hope of success.

Officers as well as privates began to desert in large numbers.

So Burnside, in turn, was relieved, and the army given to another braggart, “Fighting Joe” Hooker.

“May God have mercy on Lee,” he vaunted, “for I shall not.”

He led what he called “the finest army on the planet” against Lee. He had twice as many men as the Confederates, but Lee hurled him back across the river at Chancellorsville and destroyed seventeen thousand of his troops.

It was one of the most disastrous defeats of the war.

It occurred in May, 1863; and the President's secretary records that he heard the tramp of Lincoln's feet during all the terrible hours of sleepless nights as he paced up and down his room, crying, “Lost! Lost! All is lost!” Finally, however, he went down to Fredericksburg to cheer up “Fighting Joe” and encourage the army.

Lincoln was denounced bitterly for all this futile slaughter; and gloom and discouragement settled over the nation.

And quickly on top of these military sorrows, came a domestic tragedy. Lincoln was inordinately fond of his two little sons, Tad and Willie. He often stole away, on a summer evening, to play “town ball” with them, his coat-tails flying out behind him as he ran from base to base. Sometimes, he would shoot marbles with them all the way from the White House to the war-office. At night he loved to get down on the floor and roll and romp with them. On bright, warm days he would sometimes go out back of the White House and play with the boys and their two goats.

Tad and Willie kept the White House in an uproar, organizing minstrel shows, putting the servants through military drill, running in and out among the office-seekers. If they took a fancy to a certain applicant, they would see that he got in to see “Old Abe” immediately. If they couldn't get him in the front way, they knew of back entrances.

With as little respect for ceremony and precedent as their father had, they dashed in and interrupted a Cabinet meeting once to inform the President that the cat in the basement had just had kittens.

On another occasion the stern Salmon P. Chase was irritated and disgusted because Tad climbed all over his father and finally perched on his shoulder and sat astride of his neck while Chase was discussing the grave financial situation that confronted the country.

Some one gave Willie a pony. He insisted on riding it in all kinds of winter weather; so he got wet and chilled and came down with a severe cold. Soon it had become a serious fever. Night after night Lincoln sat for hours by his bedside; and when the little fellow passed away, his father, choking with sobs, cried:

“My poor boy! My poor boy! He was too good for this earth. God has called him home. It is hard, hard to have him die.”

Mrs. Keckley, who was in the room at the time, says:

He buried his head in his hands, and his tall frame was convulsed with emotion.... The pale face of her dead boy threw Mrs. Lincoln into convulsions. She was so completely overwhelmed with sorrow she did not attend the funeral.

After Willie's death Mrs. Lincoln could not bear to look upon his picture. Mrs. Keckley tells us:

She could not bear the sight of anything he loved, not even a flower. Costly bouquets were presented to her, but she turned from them with a shudder, and either placed them in a room where she could not see them, or threw them out of the window. She gave away all of Willie's toys... and, after his death, she never again crossed the threshold of the Guests' Room in which he died or the Green Room in which he was embalmed.

In a frenzy of grief Mrs. Lincoln called in a so-called spiritualist who masqueraded under the title of “Lord Colchester.” This unmitigated impostor was exposed later and ordered out of town under a threat of imprisonment. But Mrs. Lincoln, in her distress, received “Lord Colchester” in the White House; and there, in a darkened room, she was persuaded that the scratching on the wainscoting, the tapping on the wall, and the rapping of the table, were loving messages from her lost boy.

She wept as she received them.

Lincoln, prostrate with grief, sank into a listless despair. He could hardly discharge his public duties. Letters, telegrams lay on his desk unanswered. His physician feared that he might never rally, that he might succumb entirely to his desolation.

The President would sometimes sit and read aloud for hours, with only his secretary or his aide for an audience. Generally it was Shakspere he read. One day he was reading “King John” to his aide, and when he came to the passage in which Constance bewails her lost boy, Lincoln closed the book, and repeated these words from memory:

And, father cardinal, I have heard you say
That we shall see and know our friends in heaven:
If that be true, I shall see my boy again.

“Colonel, did you ever dream of a lost friend,” the President asked, “and feel that you were holding sweet communion with him, and yet have a sad consciousness that it was not a reality? I often dream of my boy Willie like that.” And dropping his head on the table, Lincoln sobbed aloud.

21

When Lincoln turned to his Cabinet, he found there the same quarrels and jealousy that existed in the army.

Seward, Secretary of State, regarded himself as the “Premier,” snubbed the rest of the Cabinet, meddled in their affairs, and aroused deep resentment.

Chase, Secretary of the Treasury, despised Seward; detested General McClellan; hated Stanton, Secretary of War; and loathed Blair, the Postmaster-General.

Blair, in turn, went around “kicking over beehives,” as Lincoln put it, and boasting that when he “went in for a fight” he “went in for a funeral.” He denounced Seward as “an unprincipled liar,” and refused to have any dealings with him whatever; and as for Stanton and Chase, he wouldn't condescend even to speak to those scoundrels—not even at a Cabinet meeting.

Blair went in for so many fights that finally he went in for his own funeral—as far as politics were concerned. The hatred that he aroused was so fiery and widespread that Lincoln had to ask him to resign.

There was hatred everywhere in the Cabinet.

The Vice-President, Hannibal Hamlin, wouldn't speak to Gideon Welles, Secretary of the Navy; and Welles, topped with an elaborate wig and decorated with a vast growth of white whiskers, kept a diary, and from almost every page of it, he “hurls the shafts of his ridicule and contempt” at well-nigh all his colleagues.

Welles especially detested Grant, Seward, and Stanton.

And as for the violent, insolent Stanton, he was the most prodigious hater of all. He despised Chase, Welles, Blair, Mrs. Lincoln, and apparently almost every one else in creation.

“He cared nothing for the feeling of others,” wrote Grant, “and it gave him more pleasure to refuse a request than to grant it.”

Sherman's hatred for the man was so fierce that he humiliated Stanton on a reviewing-stand before a vast audience, and rejoiced about it ten years later as he wrote his Memoirs.

“As I approached Mr. Stanton,” says Sherman, “he offered me his hand, but I declined it publicly, and the fact was universally noticed.”

Few men who ever lived have been more savagely detested than Stanton.

Almost every man in the Cabinet considered himself superior to Lincoln.

After all, who was this crude, awkward, story-telling Westerner they were supposed to serve under?

A political accident, a “dark horse” that had got in by chance and crowded them out.

Bates, the Attorney-General, had entertained high hopes of being nominated for President, himself, in 1860; and he wrote in his diary that the Republicans made a “fatal blunder” in nominating Lincoln, a man who “lacks will and purpose,” and “has not the power to command.”

Chase, too, had hoped to be nominated instead of Lincoln; and, to the end of his life, he regarded Lincoln with “a sort of benevolent contempt.”

Seward also was bitter and resentful. “Disappointment? You speak to me of disappointment,” he once exclaimed to a friend as he paced the floor, “to me who was justly entitled to the Republican nomination for the Presidency and who had to stand aside and see it given to a little Illinois lawyer!

“You speak to me of disappointment!”

Seward knew that if it hadn't been for Horace Greeley, he himself would have been President. He knew how to run things, he had had twenty years of experience in handling the vast affairs of state.

But what had Lincoln ever run? Nothing except a log-cabin grocery store in New Salem, and he had “run that in the ground.”

Oh, yes, and he had had a post-office once, which he carried around in his hat.

That was the extent of the executive experience of this “prairie politician.”

And now here he sat, blundering and confused, in the White House, letting things drift, doing nothing, while the country was on a greased chute headed straight for disaster.

Seward believed—and thousands of others believed—that he had been made Secretary of State in order to rule the nation, that Lincoln was to be a mere figurehead. People called Seward the Prime Minister. He liked it. He believed that the salvation of the United States rested with him and him alone.

“I will try,” he said when accepting his appointment, “to save freedom and my country.”

Before Lincoln had been in office five weeks Seward sent him a memorandum that was presumptuous. Amazing. It was more than that. It was positively insulting. Never before in the history of the nation had a Cabinet member sent such an impudent, arrogant document to a President.

“We are at the end of a month's administration,” Seward began, “and yet without a policy either domestic or foreign.” Then with a calm assumption of superior wisdom, he proceeded to criticize this ex-grocery, store keeper from New Salem and inform him how the Government ought to be run.

He ended by brazenly suggesting that from now on Lincoln ought to sit in the background where he belonged, and let the suave Seward assume control and prevent the country from going to hell.

One of Seward's suggestions was so wild and erratic as to stun Lincoln. Seward didn't like the way France and Spain had been carrying on lately in Mexico. So he proposed to call them to account. Yes, and Great Britain and Russia, too. And if “satisfactory explanations are not received—” what do you suppose he intended to do?

Declare war. Yes. One war wasn't enough for this statesman. He was going to have a nice little assortment of wars going full blast at the same time.

He did prepare an arrogant note which he proposed sending to England—a note bristling with warnings, threats, and insults. If Lincoln hadn't deleted the worst passages and toned the others down, it might have caused war.

Seward took a pinch of snuff and declared that he would love to see a European power interfere in favor of South Carolina, for then the North would “pitch into that power,” and all the Southern States would help fight the foreign foe.

And it very nearly became necessary to fight England. A Northern gunboat held up a British mail-steamer on the high seas, took off two Confederate commissioners destined for England and France, and lodged them behind prison bars in Boston.

England began preparing for war, shipped thousands of troops across the Atlantic, landed them in Canada, and was ready to attack the North.

Although Lincoln admitted it was “the bitterest pill he had ever swallowed,” nevertheless he had to surrender the Confederate commissioners and apologize.

Lincoln was utterly astounded by some of Seward's wild ideas. From the outset Lincoln had keenly realized that he, himself, was inexperienced in handling the vast and cruel responsibilities that confronted him. He needed help—and wisdom, and guidance. He had appointed Seward hoping to get just that. And see what had happened!

All Washington was talking about Seward's running the administration. It touched Mrs. Lincoln's pride, and aroused her boiling wrath. With fire in her eye, she urged her humble husband to assert himself.

“I may not rule myself,” Lincoln assured her, “but certainly Seward shall not. The only ruler I have is my conscience and my God and these men will have to learn that yet.”

The time came when all of them did.

Salmon P. Chase was the Chesterfield of the Cabinet: strikingly handsome, six feet two inches tall, looking the part of a man born to rule, cultured, a classical scholar, master of three languages, and father of one of the most charming and popular hostesses in Washington society. Frankly, he was shocked to see a man in the White House who didn't know how to order a dinner.

Chase was pious, very pious: he attended church three times on Sunday, quoted the Psalms in his bathtub, and put the motto “In God We Trust” on our national coins. Reading his Bible and a book of sermons every night before retiring, he was utterly unable to comprehend a President who took to bed with him a volume of Artemus Ward or Petroleum Nasby.

Lincoln's flair for humor, at almost all times and under nearly all circumstances, irritated and annoyed Chase.

One day an old crony of Lincoln's from Illinois called at the White House. The doorkeeper, looking him over with a critical eye, announced that the President couldn't be seen, that a Cabinet meeting was in session.

“That don't make no difference,” the caller protested. “You just tell Abe that Orlando Kellogg is here and wants to tell him the story of the stuttering justice. He'll see me.”

Lincoln ordered him shown in at once, and greeted him with a fervent handshake. Turning to the Cabinet, the President said:

“Gentlemen: This is my old friend, Orlando Kellogg, and he wants to tell us the story of the stuttering justice. It is a very good story, so let's lay all business aside now.”

So grave statesmen and the affairs of the nation waited while Orlando told his yarn and Lincoln had his loud guffaw.

Chase was disgusted. He feared for the future of the nation. He complained that Lincoln “was making a joke out of the war,” that he was hurrying the country on to “the abyss of bankruptcy and ruin.”

Chase was as jealous as a member of a high-school sorority. He had expected to be made Secretary of State. Why hadn't he? Why had he been snubbed? Why had the post of honor gone to the haughty Seward? Why had he been made a mere Secretary of the Treasury? He was bitter and resentful.

He had to play third fiddle now. Yes, but he would show them; 1864 was coming. There would be another election then, and he was determined to occupy the White House himself after that. He thought of little else now. He threw his whole heart and soul into what Lincoln called “Chase's mad hunt for the Presidency.”

To Lincoln's face, he pretended to be his friend. But the moment he was out of sight and out of hearing, Chase was the President's ceaseless, bitter, and sneaking foe. Lincoln was frequently compelled to make decisions that offended influential people. When he did, Chase hurried to the disgruntled victim, sympathized with him, assured him that he was right, whipped up his resentment toward Lincoln, and persuaded him that if Salmon P. Chase had been running things he would have been treated fairly.

“Chase is like the blue-bottle fly,” said Lincoln; “he lays his eggs in every rotten place he can find.”

For months Lincoln knew all of this; but with a magnanimous disregard of his own rights, he said:

“Chase is a very able man, but on the subject of the Presidency, I think he is a little insane. He has not behaved very well lately, and people say to me, ‘Now is the time to crush him out.’ Well, I'm not in favor of crushing anybody out. If there is anything that a man can do and do it well, I say, let him do it. So I am determined, so long as he does his duty as head of the Treasury Department, to shut my eyes to his attack of the White House fever.”

But the situation grew steadily worse. When things didn't go Chase's way, he sent in his resignation. He did this five times, and Lincoln went to him and praised him and persuaded him to resume his duties. But finally even the long-suffering Lincoln had enough of it. There had now developed such ill feeling between them that it was unpleasant for them to meet each other. So the next time, the President took Chase at his word and accepted his resignation.

Chase was amazed. His bluff had been called.

The Senate Committee on Finance hurried to the White House in a body. They protested. Chase's going would be a misfortune, a calamity. Lincoln listened, and let them talk themselves out. He then related his painful experiences with Chase; said that Chase always wanted to rule, and resented his (Lincoln's) authority.

“He is either determined to annoy me,” said Lincoln, “or that I shall pat him on the shoulder and coax him to stay. I don't think I ought to do it. I will take him at his word. His usefulness as a Cabinet officer is at an end. I will no longer continue the association. I am willing, if necessary, to resign the office of President. I would rather go back to a farm in Illinois and earn my bread with a plow and an ox than to endure any longer the state I have been in.”

But what was Lincoln's estimate of the man who had humiliated and insulted him? “Of all the great men I have ever known, Chase is equal to about one and a half of the best of them.”

Despite all the ill feeling that had been stirred up, Lincoln then performed one of the most beautiful and magnanimous acts of his career. He conferred upon Chase one of the highest honors a President of the United States can bestow: he made him Chief Justice of the United States Supreme Court.

Chase, however, was a docile kitten in comparison with the stormy Stanton. Short, heavy-set, with the build of a bull, Stanton had something of that animal's fierceness and ferocity.

All his life he had been rash and erratic. His father, a physician, hung a human skeleton in the barn where the boy played, hoping that he too would become a doctor. The young Stanton lectured to his playmates about the skeleton, Moses, hell fire, and the flood; and then went off to Columbus, Ohio, and became a clerk in a book-store. He boarded in a private family, and one morning shortly after he left the house, the daughter of the family fell ill with cholera, and was dead and in her grave when Stanton came home for supper that night.

He refused to believe it.

Fearing that she had been buried alive, he hurried to the cemetery, found a spade, and worked furiously for hours, digging up her body.

Years later, driven to despair by the death of his own daughter, Lucy, he had her body exhumed after she had been buried thirteen months, and kept her corpse in his bedroom for more than a year.

When Mrs. Stanton died, he put her nightcap and nightgown beside him in bed each night and wept over them.

He was a strange man. Some people said that he was half crazy.

Lincoln and Stanton had first met during the trial of a patent case in which they, together with George Harding of Philadelphia, had been retained as counsel for the defendant. Lincoln had studied the case minutely, had prepared with extraordinary care and industry, and wanted to speak. But Stanton and Harding were ashamed of him; they brushed him aside with contempt, humiliated him, and refused to let him say a word at the trial.

Lincoln gave them a copy of his speech, but they were sure it was “trash” and didn't bother to look at it.

They wouldn't walk with Lincoln to and from the courthouse; they wouldn't invite him to their rooms; they wouldn't even sit at a table and eat with him. They treated him as a social outcast.

Stanton said—and Lincoln heard him say it:

“I will not associate with such a damned, gawky, long-armed ape as that. If I can't have a man who is a gentleman in appearance with me in the case, I will abandon it.”

“I have never before been so brutally treated as by that man Stanton,” Lincoln said. He returned home, mortified, sunk once more in terrible melancholy.

When Lincoln became President, Stanton's contempt and disgust for him deepened and increased. He called him “a painful imbecile,” declared that he was utterly incapable of running the Government, and that he ought to be ousted by a military dictator. Stanton repeatedly remarked that Du Chaillu was a fool to run off to Africa, looking for a gorilla, when the original gorilla was, at that moment, sitting in the White House scratching himself.

In his letters to Buchanan, Stanton abused the President in language so violent that it can't be put into print.

After Lincoln had been in office ten months, a national scandal reverberated throughout the land. The Government was being robbed! Millions lost! Profiteers! Dishonest war contracts! And so on.

In addition to that, Lincoln and Simon Cameron, Secretary of War, differed sharply on the question of arming slaves.

Lincoln asked Cameron to resign. He must have a new man to run the War Department. Lincoln knew that the future of the nation might depend upon his choice. He also knew precisely the man he needed. So Lincoln said to a friend:

“I have made up my mind to sit down on all my pride—it may be a portion of my self-respect—and appoint Stanton Secretary of War.”

That proved to be one of the wisest appointments Lincoln ever made.

Stanton stood at his desk in the war-office, a regular tornado in trousers, surrounded by clerks trembling like Eastern slaves before their pasha. Working day and night, refusing to go home, eating and sleeping in the war-office, he was filled with wrath and indignation by the loafing, swaggering, incompetent officers that infested the army.

And he fired them right and left and backward and forward.

Cursing and swearing, he insulted meddlesome Congressmen. He waged a fierce and relentless war on dishonest contractors; ignored and violated the Constitution; arrested even generals, clapped them into prison and kept them there for months without trial. He lectured McClellan as if he were drilling a regiment, declared that he must fight. He swore that “the champagne and oysters on the Potomac must stop;” seized all the railroads; commandeered all the telegraph lines, made Lincoln send and receive his telegrams through the war-office; assumed command of all the armies, and wouldn't let even an order from Grant pass through the adjutant-general's office without his approval.

For years Stanton had been racked with head pains, had suffered from asthma and indigestion.

However, he was driven like a dynamo by one absorbing passion: to hack and stab and shoot until the South came back into the Union.

Lincoln could endure anything to achieve that goal.

One day a Congressman persuaded the President to give him an order transferring certain regiments. Rushing to the waroffice with the order, he put it on Stanton's desk; and Stanton said very sharply that he would do no such thing.

“But,” the politician protested, “you forget I have an order here from the President.”

“If the President gave you such an order,” Stanton retorted, “he is a damned fool.”

The Congressman rushed back to Lincoln, expecting to see him rise up in wrath and dismiss the Secretary of War.

But Lincoln listened to the story, and said with a twinkle in his eye: “If Stanton said I was a damned fool, then I must be, for he is nearly always right. I'll just step over and see him myself.”

He did, and Stanton convinced him that his order was wrong and Lincoln withdrew it.

Realizing that Stanton bitterly resented interference, Lincoln usually let him have his way.

“I cannot add to Mr. Stanton's troubles,” he said. “His position is the most difficult in the world. Thousands in the army blame him because they are not promoted, and other thousands blame him because they are not appointed. The pressure upon him is immeasurable and unending. He is the rock on the beach of our national ocean against which the breakers dash and roar, dash and roar without ceasing. He fights back the angry waters and prevents them from undermining and overwhelming the land. I do not see how he survives, why he is not crushed and torn to pieces. Without him, I should be destroyed.”

Occasionally, however, the President “put his foot down,” as he called it; and then—look out. If “Old Mars” said then that he wouldn't do a thing, Lincoln would reply very quietly: “I reckon, Mr. Secretary, you'll have to do it.”

And done it was.

On one occasion he wrote an order saying: “Without an if or an and or but, let Colonel Elliott W. Rice be made Brigadier-General in the United States army—Abraham Lincoln.”

On another occasion he wrote Stanton to appoint a certain man “regardless of whether he knows the color of Julius Caesar's hair or not.”

In the end Stanton and Seward and most of those who began by reviling and scorning Abraham Lincoln learned to revere him.

When Lincoln lay dying in a rooming-house across the street from Ford's Theater, the iron Stanton, who had once denounced him as “a painful imbecile,” said, “There lies the most perfect ruler of men the world has ever seen.”

John Hay, one of Lincoln's secretaries, has graphically described Lincoln's manner of working in the White House:

He was extremely unmethodical. It was a four years' struggle on Nicolay's part and mine to get him to adopt some systematic rules. He would break through every regulation as fast as it was made. Anything that kept the people themselves away from him, he disapproved, although they nearly annoyed the life out of him by unreasonable complaints and requests.

He wrote very few letters, and did not read one in fifty that he received. At first we tried to bring them to his notice, but at last he gave the whole thing over to me, and signed, without reading them, the letters I wrote in his name.

He wrote perhaps half a dozen a week himself—not more.

When the President had any rather delicate matter to manage at a distance from Washington, he rarely wrote but sent Nicolay or me.

He went to bed ordinarily from ten to eleven o'clock... and rose early. When he lived in the country at the Soldiers' Home, he would be up and dressed, eat his breakfast (which was extremely frugal, an egg, a piece of toast, coffee, etc.) and ride into Washington all before eight o'clock. In the winter, at the White House, he was not quite so early. He did not sleep well, but spent a good while in bed....

At noon he took a biscuit, a glass of milk in winter, some fruit or grapes in summer.... He was abstemious—ate less than any man I know.

He drank nothing but water, not from principle, but because he did not like wine or spirits....

Sometimes he would run away to a lecture or concert or theater for the sake of a little rest....

He read very little. He scarcely ever looked into a newspaper unless I called his attention to an article on some special subject. He frequently said, “I know more about it than any of them.” It is absurd to call him a modest man. No great man was ever modest.

22

Ask the average American citizen to-day why the Civil War was fought; and the chances are that he will reply, “To free the slaves.”

Was it?

Let's see. Here is a sentence taken from Lincoln's first inaugural address: “I have no purpose, directly or indirectly, to interfere with the institution of slavery in the States where it now exists. I believe I have no lawful right to do so, and I have no inclination to do so.”

The fact is that the cannon had been booming and the wounded groaning for almost eighteen months before Lincoln issued the Emancipation Proclamation. During all that time the radicals and the Abolitionists had urged him to act at once, storming at him through the press and denouncing him from the public platform.

Once a delegation of Chicago ministers appeared at the White House with what they declared was a direct command from Almighty God to free the slaves immediately. Lincoln told them that he imagined that if the Almighty had any advice to offer He would come direct to headquarters with it, instead of sending it around via Chicago.

Finally Horace Greeley, irritated by Lincoln's procrastination and inaction, attacked the President in an article entitled, “The Prayer of Twenty Millions.” Two columns bristling with bitter complaints.

Lincoln's answer to Greeley is one of the classics of the war —clear, terse, and vigorous. He closed his reply with these memorable words:

My paramount object in this struggle is to save the Union, and is not either to save or destroy slavery. If I could save the Union without freeing any slave, I would do it; and if I could save it by freeing all the slaves, I would do it; and if I could save it by freeing some and leaving others alone, I would also do that. What I do about slavery and the colored race, I do because I believe it helps to save the Union; and what I forbear, I forbear because I do not believe it would help to save the Union. I shall do less whenever I shall believe what I am doing hurts the cause, and I shall do more whenever I shall believe doing more will help the cause. I shall try to correct errors when shown to be errors, and I shall adopt new views so fast as they shall appear to be true views.

I have here stated my purpose according to my view of official duty; and I intend no modification of my oftexpressed personal wish that all men everywhere could be free.

Lincoln believed that if he saved the Union and kept slavery from spreading, slavery would, in due time, die a natural death. But if the Union were destroyed, it might persist for centuries.

Four slave States had remained with the North, and Lincoln realized that if he issued his Emancipation Proclamation too early in the conflict he would drive them into the Confederacy, strengthen the South, and perhaps destroy the Union forever. There was a saying at the time that “Lincoln would like to have God Almighty on his side; but he must have Kentucky.”

So he bided his time, and moved cautiously.

He himself had married into a slave-owning, border-State family. Part of the money that his wife received upon the settlement of her father's estate had come from the sale of slaves. And the only really intimate friend that he ever had—Joshua Speed—was a member of a slave-owning family. Lincoln sympathized with the Southern point of view. Besides, he had the attorney's traditional respect for the Constitution and for law and property. He wanted to work no hardships on any one.

He believed that the North was as much to blame for the existence of slavery in the United States as was the South; and that in getting rid of it, both sections should bear the burden equally. So he finally worked out a plan that was very near to his heart. According to this, the slave-owners in the loyal border States were to receive four hundred dollars for each of their negroes. The slaves were to be emancipated gradually, very gradually. The process was not to be entirely completed until January 1, 1900. Calling the representatives of the border States to the White House, he pleaded with them to accept his proposal.

“The change it contemplates,” Lincoln argued, “would come gently as the dews of heaven, not rending or wrecking anything. Will you not embrace it? So much good has not been done, by one effort, in all past time, as, in the providence of God, it is now your high privilege to do. May the vast future not have to lament you have neglected it.”

But they did neglect it, and rejected the whole scheme. Lincoln was immeasurably disappointed.

“I must save this Government, if possible,” he said; “and it may as well be understood, once for all, that I shall not surrender this game, leaving any available card unplayed.... I believe that freeing the slaves and arming the blacks has now become an indispensable military necessity. I have been driven to the alternative of either doing that or surrendering the Union.”

He had to act at once, for both France and England were on the verge of recognizing the Confederacy. Why? The reasons were very simple.

Take France's case first. Napoleon III had married Marie Eugénie de Montijo, Comtesse de Teba, reputed to be the most beautiful woman in the world, and he wanted to show off a bit. He longed to cover himself with glory, as his renowned uncle, Napoleon Bonaparte, had done. So when he saw the States slashing and shooting at one another, and knew they were much too occupied to bother about enforcing the Monroe Doctrine, he ordered an army to Mexico, shot a few thousand natives, conquered the country, called Mexico a French empire, and put the Archduke Maximilian on the throne.

Napoleon believed, and not without reason, that if the Confederates won they would favor his new empire; but that if the Federals won, the United States would immediately take steps to put the French out of Mexico. It was Napoleon's wish, therefore, that the South would make good its secession, and he wanted to help it as much as he conveniently could.

At the outset of the war, the Northern navy closed all Southern ports, guarded 189 harbors and patrolled 9,614 miles of coast line, sounds, bayous, and rivers.

It was the most gigantic blockade the world had ever seen.

The Confederates were desperate. They couldn't sell their cotton; neither could they buy guns, ammunition, shoes, medical supplies, or food. They boiled chestnuts and cotton-seed to make a substitute for coffee, and brewed a decoction of blackberry leaves and sassafras root to take the place of tea. Newspapers were printed on wall-paper. The earthen floors of smokehouses, saturated with the drippings of bacon, were dug up and boiled to get salt. Church bells were melted and cast into cannon. Street-car rails in Richmond were torn up to be made into gunboat armor.

The Confederates couldn't repair their railroads or buy new equipment, so transportation was almost at a standstill; corn that could be purchased for two dollars a bushel in Georgia, brought fifteen dollars in Richmond. People in Virginia were going hungry.

Something had to be done at once. So the South offered to give Napoleon III twelve million dollars' worth of cotton if he would recognize the Confederacy and use the French fleet to lift the blockade. Besides, they promised to overwhelm him with orders that would start smoke rolling out of every factory chimney in France night and day.

Napoleon therefore urged Russia and England to join him in recognizing the Confederacy. The aristocracy that ruled England adjusted their monocles, poured a few drinks of Johnny Walker, and listened eagerly to Napoleon's overtures. The United States was getting too rich and powerful to please them. They wanted to see the nation divided, the Union broken. Besides, they needed the South's cotton. Scores of England's factories had closed, and a million people were not only idle but destitute and reduced to actual pauperism. Children were crying for food; hundreds of people were dying of starvation. Public subscriptions to buy food for British workmen were taken up in the remotest corners of the earth: even in far-off India and povertystricken China.

There was one way, and only one way, that England could get cotton, and that was to join Napoleon III in recognizing the Confederacy and lifting the blockade.

If that were done, what would happen in America? The South would get guns, powder, credit, food, railroad equipment, and a tremendous lift in confidence and morale.

And what would the North get? Two new and powerful enemies. The situation, bad enough now, would be hopeless then.

Nobody knew this better than Abraham Lincoln. “We have about played our last card,” he confessed in 1862. “We must either change our tactics now or lose the game.”

As England saw it, all the colonies had originally seceded from her. Now the Southern colonies had, in turn, seceded from the Northern ones; and the North was fighting to coerce and subdue them. What difference did it make to a lord in London or a prince in Paris whether Tennessee and Texas were ruled from Washington or Richmond? None. To them, the fighting was meaningless and fraught with no high purpose.

“No war ever raging in my time,” wrote Carlyle, “was to me more profoundly foolish looking.”

Lincoln saw that Europe's attitude toward the war must be changed, and he knew how to do it. A million people in Europe had read “Uncle Tom's Cabin—” had read it and wept and learned to abhor the heartaches and injustice of slavery. So Abraham Lincoln knew that if he issued his Proclamation of Emancipation, Europeans would see the war in a different light. It would no longer be a bloody quarrel over the preservation of a Union that meant nothing to them. Instead, it would be exalted into a holy crusade to destroy slavery. European governments would then not dare to recognize the South. Public opinion wouldn't tolerate the aiding of a people supposed to be fighting to perpetuate human bondage.

Finally, therefore, in July, 1862, Lincoln determined to issue his proclamation; but McClellan and Pope had recently led the army to humiliating defeats. Seward told the President that the time was not auspicious, that he ought to wait and launch the proclamation on the crest of a wave of victory.

That sounded sensible. So Lincoln waited; and two months later the victory came. Then Lincoln called his Cabinet together to discuss the issuing of the most famous document in American history since the Declaration of Independence.

It was a momentous occasion—and a grave one. But did Lincoln act gravely and solemnly? He did not. Whenever he came across a good story, he liked to share it. He used to take one of Artemus Ward's books to bed with him; and when he read something humorous, he would get up, and, clad in nothing but his night-shirt, he would make his way through the halls of the White House to the office of his secretaries, and read it to them.

The day before the Cabinet meeting which was to discuss the issuing of the Emancipation Proclamation, Lincoln had gotten hold of Ward's latest volume. There was a story in it that he thought very funny. So he read it to the Cabinet now, before they got down to business. It was entitled, “High-handed Outrage in Utiky.”

After Lincoln had had his laugh, he put the book aside and began solemnly: “When the rebel army was at Frederick, I determined, as soon as it should be driven out of Maryland, to issue a proclamation of emancipation. I said nothing to any one, but I made the promise to myself and—to my Maker. The rebel army is now driven out, and I am going to fulfil that promise. I have called you together to hear what I have written down. I do not wish your advice upon the main matter, for that I have determined for myself. What I have written is that which my reflections have determined me to say. But if there is anything in the expressions I use, or in any minor matter, which any of you thinks had best be changed, I shall be glad to receive the suggestions.”

Seward suggested one slight change in wording; then, a few minutes later, he proposed another.

Lincoln asked him why he hadn't made both suggestions at the same time. And then Lincoln interrupted the consideration of the Emancipation Proclamation to tell a story. He said a hired man back in Indiana told the farmer who had employed him that one steer in his best yoke of oxen had died. Having waited a while, the hired man said, “The other ox in that team is dead, too.”

“Then why didn't you tell me at once,” asked the farmer, “that both of them were dead?”

“Well,” answered the hired man, “I didn't want to hurt you by telling you too much at the same time.”

Lincoln presented the proclamation to his Cabinet in September, 1862; but it was not to take effect until the first day of January, 1863. So when Congress met the following December, Lincoln appealed to that body for support. In making his plea he uttered one of the most magnificent sentences he ever penned —a sentence of unconscious poetry.

Speaking of the Union, he said:

“We shall nobly save or meanly lose

The last, best hope of earth.”

On New Year's Day, 1863, Lincoln spent hours shaking hands with the visitors that thronged the White House. In the middle of that afternoon, he retired to his office, dipped his pen in the ink, and prepared to sign his proclamation of freedom. Hesitating, he turned to Seward and said: “If slavery isn't wrong, nothing is wrong, and I have never felt more certain in my life that I was doing right. But I have been receiving calls and shaking hands since nine o'clock this morning, and my arm is stiff and numb. Now this signature is one that will be closely examined, and if they find my hand trembled, they will say, ‘He had some compunctions.’”

He rested his arm a moment, then slowly signed the document, and gave freedom to three and a half million slaves.

The proclamation did not meet with popular approval then. “The only effect of it,” wrote Orville H. Browning, one of Lincoln's closest friends and strongest supporters, “was to unite and exasperate the South and divide and distract us in the North.”

A mutiny broke out in the army. Men who had enlisted to save the Union swore that they wouldn't stand up and be shot down to free niggers and make them their social equals. Thousands of soldiers deserted, and recruiting fell off everywhere.

The plain people upon whom Lincoln had depended for support failed him utterly. The autumn elections went overwhelmingly against him. Even his home state of Illinois repudiated the Republican party.

And quickly, on top of the defeat at the polls, came one of the most disastrous reverses of the war—Burnside's foolhardy attack on Lee at Fredericksburg and the loss of thirteen thousand men. A stupid and futile butchery. This sort of thing had been going on for eighteen months now. Was it never going to stop? The nation was appalled. People were driven to despair. The President was violently denounced everywhere. He had failed. His general had failed. His policies had failed. People wouldn't put up with this any longer. Even the Republican members of the Senate revolted; and, wanting to force Lincoln out of the White House, they called upon him, demanding that he change his policies and dismiss his entire Cabinet.

This was a humiliating blow. Lincoln confessed that it distressed him more than any other one event of his political life.

“They want to get rid of me,” he said, “and I am half disposed to gratify them.”

Horace Greeley now sharply regretted the fact that he had forced the Republicans to nominate Lincoln in 1860.

“It was a mistake,” he confessed, “the biggest mistake of my life.”

Greeley and a number of other prominent Republicans organized a movement having these objects in view: to force Lincoln to resign, to put Hamlin, the Vice-President, in the White House, and then to compel Hamlin to give Rosecrans command of all the Union armies.

“We are now on the brink of destruction,” Lincoln confessed. “It appears to me that even the Almighty is against us. I can see hardly a ray of hope.”

23

In the spring of 1863, Lee, flushed with a phenomenal series of brilliant victories, determined to take the offensive and invade the North. He planned to seize the rich manufacturing centers of Pennsylvania, secure food, medicine, and new clothes for his ragged troops, possibly capture Washington, and compel France and Great Britain to recognize the Confederacy.

A bold, reckless move! True, but the Southern troops were boasting that one Confederate could whip three Yankees, and they believed it; so when their officers told them they could eat beef twice a day when they reached Pennsylvania, they were eager to be off at once.

Before he quit Richmond, Lee received disquieting news from home. A terrible thing had happened! One of his daughters had actually been caught reading a novel. The great general was distressed; so he wrote, pleading with her to devote her leisure to such innocuous classics as Plato and Homer, and Plutarch's Lives. After finishing the letter, Lee read his Bible and knelt in prayer, as was his custom; then he blew out the candle and turned in for the night....

Presently he was off with seventy-five thousand men. His hungry army plunged across the Potomac, throwing the country into a panic. Farmers rushed out of the Cumberland Valley, driving their horses and cattle before them; and negroes, their eyes white with fear, fled in terror, lest they be dragged back to slavery.

Lee's artillery was already thundering before Harrisburg, when he learned that, back in the rear, the Union Army was threatening to break his lines of communication. So he whirled around as an angry ox would to gore a dog snapping at his heels; and, quite by chance, the ox and the dog met at a sleepy little Pennsylvania village with a theological seminary, a place called Gettysburg, and fought there the most famous battle in the history of our country.

During the first two days of the fighting the Union Army lost twenty thousand men; and, on the third day, Lee hoped finally to smash the enemy by a terrific assault of fresh troops under the command of General George Pickett.

These were new tactics for Lee. Up to this time, he had fought with his men behind breastworks or concealed in the woods. Now he planned to make a desperate attack out in the open.

The very contemplation of it staggered Lee's most brilliant assistant, General Longstreet.

“Great God!” Longstreet exclaimed. “Look, General Lee, at the insurmountable difficulties between our line and that of the Yankees—the steep hills, the tiers of artillery, the fences. And then we shall have to fight our infantry against their battery. Look at the ground we shall have to charge over, nearly a mile of it there in the open, under the line of their canister and shrapnel. It is my opinion that no fifteen thousand men ever arrayed for battle could take that position.”

But Lee was adamant. “There were never such men in an army before,” he replied. “They will go anywhere and do anything if properly led.”

So Lee held to his decision, and made the bloodiest blunder of his career.

The Confederates had already massed one hundred and fifty cannon along Seminary Ridge. If you visit Gettysburg, you can see them there to-day, placed precisely as they were on that fateful July afternoon when they laid down a barrage such as, up to that time, had never before been heard on earth.

Longstreet in this instance had keener judgment than Lee. He believed that the charge could result in nothing but pointless butchery; so he bowed his head and wept and declined to issue the order. Consequently, another officer had to give the command for him; and, in obedience to that command, General George Pickett led his Southern troops in the most dramatic and disastrous charge that ever occurred in the Western world.

Strangely enough, this general who led the assault on the Union lines was an old friend of Lincoln's. In fact, Lincoln had made it possible for him to go to West Point. He was a picturesque character, this man Pickett. He wore his hair so long that his auburn locks almost touched his shoulders; and, like Napoleon in his Italian campaigns, he wrote ardent love-letters almost daily on the battle-field. His devoted troops cheered him that afternoon as he rode off jauntily toward the Union lines, with his cap set at a rakish angle over his right ear. They cheered and they followed him, man touching man, rank pressing rank, with banners flying and bayonets gleaming in the sun. It was picturesque. Daring. Magnificent. A murmur of admiration ran through the Union lines as they beheld it.

Pickett's troops swept forward at an easy trot, through an orchard and corn-field, across a meadow, and over a ravine. All the time, the enemy's cannon were tearing ghastly holes in their ranks. But on they pressed, grim, irresistible.

Suddenly the Union infantry rose from behind the stone wall on Cemetery Ridge where they had been hiding, and fired volley after volley into Pickett's defenseless troops. The crest of the hill was a sheet of flame, a slaughter-house, a blazing volcano. In a few minutes, all of Pickett's brigade commanders, except one, were down, and four fifths of his five thousand men had fallen.

A thousand fell where Kemper led;

A thousand died where Garnett bled;

In blinding flame and strangling smoke

The remnant through the batteries broke,

And crossed the fine with Armistead.

Armistead, leading the troops in the final plunge, ran forward, vaulted over the stone wall, and, waving his cap on the top of his sword, shouted:

“Give 'em the steel, boys!”

They did. They leaped over the wall, bayoneted their enemies, smashed skulls with clubbed muskets, and planted the battle-flags of the South on Cemetery Ridge.

The banners waved there, however, only for a moment. But that moment, brief as it was, recorded the high-water mark of the Confederacy.

Pickett's charge—brilliant, heroic—was nevertheless the beginning of the end. Lee had failed. He could not penetrate the North. And he knew it.

The South was doomed.

As the remnant of Pickett's bleeding men struggled back from their fatal charge, Lee, entirely alone, rode out to encourage them, and greeted them with a self-condemnation that was little short of sublime.

“All this has been my fault,” he confessed. “It is I who have lost this fight.”

During the night of July 4 Lee began to retreat. Heavy rains were falling, and by the time he reached the Potomac the water was so high that he couldn't cross.

There Lee was, caught in a trap, an impassable river in front of him, a victorious enemy behind him. Meade, it seemed, had him at his mercy. Lincoln was delighted; he was sure the Federal troops would swoop down upon Lee's flank and rear now, rout and capture his men, and bring the war to an abrupt and triumphant close. And if Grant had been there, that is probably what would have happened.

But the vain and scholarly Meade was not the bulldog Grant. Every day for an entire week Lincoln repeatedly urged and commanded Meade to attack, but he was too cautious, too timid. He did not want to fight; he hesitated, he telegraphed excuses, he called a council of war in direct violation of orders—and did nothing, while the waters receded and Lee escaped.

Lincoln was furious.

“What does this mean?” he cried. “Great God! What does this mean? We had them within our grasp, and had only to stretch forth our hands and they were ours; yet nothing that I could say or do could make the army move. Under the circumstances, almost any general could have defeated Lee. If I had gone up there, I could have whipped him, myself.” In bitter disappointment, Lincoln sat down and wrote Meade a letter, in which he said:

My dear General, I do not believe you appreciate the magnitude of the misfortune involved in Lee's escape. He was within our easy grasp, and to have closed upon him would, in connection with our other late successes, have ended the war. As it is, the war will be prolonged indefinitely. If you could not safely attack Lee last Monday, how can you possibly do so south of the river, when you can take with you very few more than two-thirds of the force you then had in hand? It would be unreasonable to expect and I do not expect that you can now effect much. Your golden opportunity is gone, and I am distressed immeasurably because of it.

Lincoln read this letter, and then stared out the window with unseeing eyes, and did a bit of thinking: “If I had been in Meade's place,” he probably mused to himself, “and had had Meade's temperament and the advice of his timid officers, and if I had been awake as many nights as he had, and had seen as much blood, I might have let Lee escape, too.”

The letter was never sent. Meade never saw it. It was found among Lincoln's papers after his death.

The Battle of Gettysburg was fought during the first week of July; six thousand dead and twenty-seven thousand wounded were left on the field. Churches, schools, and barns were turned into hospitals; groans of the suffering filled the air. Scores were dying every hour, corpses were decaying rapidly in the intense heat. The burial parties had to work fast. There was little time to dig graves; so, in many instances, a little dirt was scooped over a body where it lay. After a week of hard rains, many of the dead were half exposed. The Union soldiers were gathered from their temporary graves, and buried in one place. The following autumn the Cemetery Commission decided to dedicate the ground, and invited Edward Everett, the most famous orator in the United States, to deliver the address.

Formal invitations to attend the exercises were sent to the President, to the Cabinet, to General Meade, to all members of both houses of Congress, to various distinguished citizens, and to the members of the diplomatic corps. Very few of these people accepted; many didn't acknowledge the invitation.

The committee had not the least idea that the President would come. In fact, they had not even troubled to write him a personal invitation. He got merely a printed one. They imagined that his secretaries might drop it in the waste-basket without even showing it to Lincoln.

So when he wrote saying he would be present, the committee was astonished. And a bit embarrassed. What should they do? Ask him to speak? Some argued that he was too busy for that, that he couldn't possibly find time to prepare. Others frankly asked, “Well, even if he had the time, has he the ability?” They doubted it.

Oh, yes, he could make a stump speech in Illinois; but speaking at the dedication of a cemetery? No. That was different. That was not Lincoln's style. However, since he was coming anyway, they had to do something. So they finally wrote him, saying that after Mr. Everett had delivered his oration, they would like to have him make “a few appropriate remarks.” That was the way they phrased it—“a few appropriate remarks.”

The invitation just barely missed being an insult. But the President accepted it. Why? There is an interesting story behind that. The previous autumn Lincoln had visited the battle-field of Antietam; and, one afternoon while he and an old friend from Illinois, Ward Lamon, were out driving, the President turned to Lamon and asked him to sing what Lincoln called his “sad little song.” It was one of Lincoln's favorites.

“Many a time, on the Illinois circuit and often at the White House when Lincoln and I were alone,” says Lamon, “I have seen him in tears while I was rendering that homely melody.”

It went like this:

I've wandered to the village, Tom; I've sat beneath the tree
Upon the schoolhouse play-ground, that sheltered you and me;
But none were left to greet me, Tom, and few were left to know
Who played with us upon the green, some twenty years ago.

Near by the spring, upon the elm you know I cut your name,—
Your sweetheart's just beneath it, Tom; and you did mine the same.
Some heartless wretch has peeled the bark—'twas dying sure but slow,
Just as she died whose name you cut, some twenty years ago.

My lids have long been dry, Tom, but tears came to my eyes;
I thought of her I loved so well, those early broken ties:
I visited the old churchyard, and took some flowers to strow
Upon the graves of those we loved, some twenty years ago.

As Lamon sang it now, probably Lincoln fell to dreaming of the only woman he had ever loved, Ann Rutledge, and he thought of her lying back there in her neglected grave on the Illinois prairie; and the rush of these poignant memories filled his eyes with tears. So Lamon, to break the spell of Lincoln's melancholy, struck up a humorous negro melody.

That was all there was to the incident. It was perfectly harmless, and very pathetic. But Lincoln's political enemies distorted it and lied about it and tried to make it a national disgrace. They made it appear like a gross indecency. The New York “World” repeated some version of the scandal every day for almost three months. Lincoln was accused of cracking jokes and singing funny songs on the battle-field where “heavy details of men were engaged in burying the dead.”

The truth is that he had cracked no jokes at all, that he had sung no songs, that he had been miles away from the battlefield when the incident occurred, that the dead had all been buried before that, and rain had fallen upon their graves. Such were the facts. But his enemies didn't want facts. They were lusting for blood. A bitter cry of savage denunciation swept over the land.

Lincoln was deeply hurt. He was so distressed that he could not bear to read these attacks, yet he didn't feel that he ought to answer them, for that would merely dignify them. So he suffered in silence, and when the invitation came to speak at the dedication of the Gettysburg cemetery, he welcomed it. It was just the opportunity he desired to silence his enemies and pay his humble tribute to the honored dead.

The invitation came late, and he had only a crowded fortnight in which to prepare his speech. He thought it over during his spare moments—while dressing, while being shaved, while eating his lunch, while walking back and forth between Stanton's office and the White House. He mused upon it while stretched out on a leather couch in the war-office, waiting for the late telegraphic reports. He wrote a rough draft of it on a piece of pale-blue foolscap paper, and carried it about in the top of his hat. The Sunday before it was delivered he said: “I have written it over two or three times, but it is not finished. I shall have to give it another lick before I am satisfied.”

He arrived in Gettysburg the night before the dedication. The little town was filled to overflowing. Its usual population of thirteen hundred had been swelled to almost thirty thousand. The weather was fine; the night was clear; a bright full moon rode high through the sky. Only a fraction of the crowd could find beds; thousands paraded up and down the village until dawn. The sidewalks soon became clogged, impassable; so hundreds, locked arm in arm, marched in the middle of the dirt streets, singing, “John Brown's body lies a-mouldering in the grave.”

Lincoln devoted all that evening to giving his speech “another lick.” At eleven o'clock he went to an adjoining house, where Secretary Seward was staying, and read the speech aloud to him, asking for his criticisms. The next morning, after breakfast, Lincoln continued working over it until a rap at the door reminded him that it was time for him to take his place in the procession headed for the cemetery.

As the procession started, he sat erect at first; but presently his body slouched forward in the saddle; his head fell on his chest, and his long arms hung limp at his sides.... He was lost in thought, going over his little speech, giving it “another lick.”

Edward Everett, the selected orator of the occasion, made two mistakes at Gettysburg. Both bad—and both uncalled for. First, he arrived an hour late; and, secondly, he spoke for two hours.

Lincoln had read Everett's oration and when he saw that the speaker was nearing his close, he knew his time was coming, and he honestly felt that he wasn't adequately prepared; so he grew nervous, twisted in his chair, drew his manuscript from the pocket of his Prince Albert coat, put on his old-fashioned glasses, and quickly refreshed his memory.

Presently he stepped forward, manuscript in hand, and delivered his little address in two minutes.

Did his audience realize, that soft November afternoon, that they were listening to the greatest speech that had ever fallen from human lips up to that time? No, most of his hearers were merely curious: they had never seen nor heard a President of the United States, they strained their necks to look at Lincoln, and were surprised to discover that such a tall man had such a high, thin voice, and that he spoke with a Southern accent. They had forgotten that he was born a Kentuckian and that he had retained the intonation of his native State; and about the time they felt he was getting through with his introduction and ready to launch into his speech—he sat down.

What! Had he forgotten? Or was it really all he had to say? People were too surprised and disappointed to applaud.

Many a spring, back in Indiana, Lincoln had tried to break ground with a rusty plow; but the soil had stuck to its moldboard, and made a mess. It wouldn't “scour.” That was the term people used. Throughout his life, when Lincoln wanted to indicate that a thing had failed, he frequently resorted to the phraseology of the corn-field. Turning now to Ward Lamon, Lincoln said:

“That speech is a flat failure, Lamon. It won't scour. The people are disappointed.”

He was right. Every one was disappointed, including Edward Everett and Secretary Seward, who were sitting on the platform with the President. They both believed he had failed woefully; and both felt sorry for him.

Lincoln was so distressed that he worried himself into a severe headache; and on the way back to Washington, he had to lie down in the drawing-room of the train and have his head bathed with cold water.

Lincoln went to his grave believing that he had failed utterly at Gettysburg. And he had, as far as the immediate effect of his speech was concerned.

With characteristic modesty, he sincerely felt that the world would “little note nor long remember” what he said there, but that it would never forget what the brave men who died had done there. How surprised he would be if he should come back to life now and realize that the speech of his that most people remember is the one that didn't “scour” at Gettysburg! How amazed he would be to discover that the ten immortal sentences he spoke there will probably be cherished as one of the literary glories and treasures of earth centuries hence, long after the Civil War is all but forgotten.

Lincoln's Gettysburg address is more than a speech. It is the divine expression of a rare soul exalted and made great by suffering. It is an unconscious prose poem, and has all the majestic beauty and profound roll of epic lines:

Four score and seven years ago
Our fathers brought forth upon this continent,
A new nation, conceived in Liberty,
And dedicated to the proposition
That all men are created equal.

Now we are engaged in a great civil war,
Testing whether that nation, or any nation
So conceived and so dedicated,
Can long endure. We are met
On a great battle-field of that war.
We have come to dedicate a portion of
That field as a final resting-place
For those who here gave their lives
That that nation might live.
It is altogether fitting and proper
That we should do this.

But, in a larger sense,
We can not dedicate—we can not consecrate
We can not hallow this ground. The brave men,
Living and dead, who struggled here
Have consecrated it far above our poor power
To add or detract. The world will little note,
Nor long remember what we say here,
But it can never forget what they did here.
It is for us the living, rather, to be dedicated here
To the unfinished work which they who fought here
Have thus far so nobly advanced.
It is rather for us to be here dedicated
To the great task remaining before us—
That from these honored dead we take
Increased devotion to that cause for which
They gave the last full measure of devotion—
That we here highly resolve that these dead
Shall not have died in vain—that this nation,
Under God, shall have a new birth of freedom—
And that government of the people,
By the people, for the people,
Shall not perish from the earth.

24

When the war began, in 1861, a shabby and disappointed man was sitting on a packing-case in a leather store in Galena, Illinois, smoking a clay pipe. His job, so far as he had one, was that of bookkeeper and buyer of hogs and hides from farmers.

His two younger brothers who owned the store didn't want him around at any price, but for months he had tramped the streets of St. Louis, looking in vain for some kind of position, until his wife and four children were destitute. Finally, in despair, he had borrowed a few dollars for a railway ticket and gone to see his father in Kentucky, begging for assistance. The old man had considerable cash, but, being loath to part with any of it, he sat down and wrote his two younger sons in Galena, instructing them to give their elder brother a job.

So they put him on the pay-roll at once, more as a matter of family politics and family charity than anything else.

Two dollars a day—that was his wage—and it was probably more than he was worth, for he had no more business ability than a jack-rabbit; he was lazy and slovenly, he loved cornwhisky, and he was eternally in debt. He was always borrowing small sums of money; so when his friends saw him coming, they used to look the other way and cross the street to avoid meeting him.

Everything he had undertaken in life, so far, had ended in failure and frustration.

So far.

But no more.

For good news and astounding good fortune were just around the corner.

In a little while he was to go flaring and flaming like a shooting star across the firmament of fame.

He couldn't command the respect of his home town now; but in three years he would command the most formidable army the world had ever seen.

In four years he would conquer Lee, end the war, and write his name in blazing letters of fire on the pages of history.

In eight years he would be in the White House.

After that he would make a triumphal tour of the world, with the high and mighty of all lands heaping honors, medals, flowers, and after-dinner oratory upon him—whom people back in Galena had crossed the street to avoid.

It is an astonishing tale.

Everything about it is strange. Even the attitude of his mother was abnormal. She never seemed to care much for him. She refused to visit him when he was President, and she didn't trouble even to name him when he was born. Her relatives attended to that, in a sort of lottery. When he was six weeks old, they wrote their favorite names on strips torn from a paper sack, mixed them in a hat, and drew one out. His grandmother Simpson had been reading Homer, and she wrote on her slip: “Hiram Ulysses.” It was drawn, and so, by chance, that was the name he bore at home for seventeen years.

But he was bashful and slow-witted, so the village wits called him “Useless” Grant.

At West Point he had still another name. The politician who made out the papers giving him an appointment to the Military Academy imagined that his middle name must be Simpson, his mother's maiden name, so he went as “U. S. Grant.” When the cadets learned this, they laughed and tossed their hats in the air, and shouted, “Boys, we've got Uncle Sam with us!” To the end of his life those who had been his classmates there called him Sam Grant.

He didn't mind. He made few friends, and he didn't care what people called him, and he didn't care how he looked. He wouldn't keep his coat buttoned or his gun clean or his shoes shined, and he was often late for roll-call. And, instead of mastering the military principles used by Napoleon and Frederick the Great, he spent much of his time at West Point poring over novels such as “Ivanhoe” and “The Last of the Mohicans.”

The incredible fact is that he never read a book on military strategy in his life.

After he had won the war the people of Boston raised money to buy him a library, appointing a committee to find out what books he already possessed. To its amazement, the committee learned that Grant didn't own a single military treatise of any description.

He disliked West Point and the army and everything connected with it; and, after he had become world-famous, he said to Bismarck while reviewing Germany's troops:

“I haven't much interest in military affairs. The truth is, I am more of a farmer than a soldier. Although I have been in two wars, I never entered the army without regret, and never left it without pleasure.”

Grant admitted that his besetting sin was laziness, and that he never liked to study. Even after he graduated from West Point he spelled knocked without the initial k and safety without an e; yet he was fairly good at figures, and hoped to be a professor of mathematics. But no position was available, so he spent eleven years with the regular army. He had to have something to eat, and that seemed the easiest way to get it.

In 1853 he was stationed at Fort Humboldt in California. In a near-by village there was a curious character named Ryan. Ryan ran a store, operated a sawmill, and did surveying during the week. On Sunday he preached. Whisky was cheap in those days, and Pastor Ryan kept an open barrel of it in the back of his store. A tin cup was hanging on the barrel, so you could go and help yourself whenever you had the urge. Grant had it often. He was lonely and wanted to forget the army life that he despised; as a result he got drunk so many times that he had virtually to be dismissed from the army.

He didn't have a dollar, and he didn't have a job; so he drifted back east to Missouri and spent the next four years plowing corn and slopping hogs on an eighty-acre farm belonging to his father-in-law. In the wintertime he cut cord-wood, hauled it to St. Louis, and sold it to the city people. But every year he got farther and farther behind, had to borrow more and more.

Finally he quit the farm, moved to St. Louis, and sought employment there. He tried to sell real estate, was a total failure at that, and then drifted about the town for weeks, looking for a job—any kind of job. At last he was in such desperate circumstances that he tried to hire out his wife's negroes, in order to get money to pay the grocer's bill.

Here is one of the most surprising facts about the Civil War: Lee believed that slavery was wrong, and had freed his own negroes long before the conflict came; but Grant's wife owned slaves at the very time that her husband was leading the armies of the North to destroy slavery.

When the war began, Grant was sick of his work in the Galena leather store and wanted to get back into the army.

That ought to have been easy for a West Point graduate, when the army had hundreds of thousands of raw recruits to whip into shape. But it wasn't. Galena raised a company of volunteers, and Grant drilled them because he was the only man in town who knew anything at all about drilling, but when they marched away to war with bouquets in their gun-barrels Grant stood on the sidewalk watching them. They had chosen another man as captain.

Then Grant wrote to the War Department, telling of his experience and asking to be appointed colonel of a regiment. His letter was never answered. It was found in the files of the War Department while he was President.

Finally he got a position in the adjutant's office in Springfield, doing clerical work that a fifteen-year-old girl could have done. He worked all day with his hat on, smoking constantly and copying orders on an old broken-down table with three legs, which had been shoved into a corner for support.

Then a wholly unexpected thing happened, an event that set his feet on the road to fame. The 21st Regiment of Illinois Volunteers had degenerated into an armed mob. They ignored orders, cursed their officers, and chased old Colonel Goode out of camp, vowing that if he showed up again they would nail his hide on a sour-apple tree.

Governor Yates was worried.

He didn't think much of Grant, but after all the man had been graduated from West Point, so the governor took a chance. And on a sunny June day in 1861 Grant walked out to the Springfield fair-grounds to take over the command of a regiment that no one else could rule.

A stick that he carried, and a red bandana tied around his waist—these were his only visible signs of authority.

He didn't have a horse or a uniform, or the money to buy either. There were holes in the top of his sweat-stained hat, and his elbows stuck out of his old coat.

His men began making fun of him at once. One chap started sparring at him behind his back, and another fellow rushed up behind the pugilist and shoved him so hard that he stumbled forward and hit Grant between the shoulders.

Grant stopped all their foolishness immediately. If a man disobeyed orders he was tied to a post and left there all day. If he cursed a gag was put into his mouth. If the regiment was late at roll-call—as they all were on one occasion—they got nothing to eat for twenty-four hours. The ex-hide-buyer from Galena tamed their tempestuous spirits and led them away to do battle down in Missouri.

Shortly after that another piece of amazing good fortune came his way. In those days the War Department was making brigadier-generals by the dozens. Northwestern Illinois had sent Elihu B. Washburne to Congress. Washburne, fired with political ambitions, was desperately eager to show the folks back home that he was on the job, so he went to the War Department and demanded that one brigadier-general come from his district. All right. But who? That was easy: there was only one West Point graduate among Washburne's constituents.

So a few days later Grant picked up a St. Louis newspaper, and read the surprising news that he was a brigadier-general.

He was assigned headquarters at Cairo, Illinois, and immediately began to do things. He loaded his soldiers on boats, steamed up the Ohio, occupied Paducah, a strategic point in Kentucky, and proposed marching down into Tennessee to attack Fort Donelson, which commanded the Cumberland River. Military experts like Halleck said: “Nonsense! You are talking foolishly, Grant. It can't be done. It would be suicide to attempt it.”

Grant went ahead and tried it, and captured the fort and fifteen thousand prisoners in one afternoon.

While Grant was attacking, the Confederate general sent him a note, begging for a truce, to arrange terms of capitulation, but Grant replied rather tartly:

“My only terms are unconditional and immediate surrender. I propose to move immediately upon your works.”

Simon Buckner, the Confederate general to whom this curt message was addressed, had known Sam Grant at West Point and had lent him money to pay his board bill when he was fired from the army. In view of that loan, Buckner felt that Grant ought to have been a trifle more gracious in his phraseology. But Buckner forgave him and surrendered and spent the afternoon smoking and reminiscing with Grant about old times.

The fall of Fort Donelson had far-reaching consequences: it saved Kentucky for the North, enabled the Union troops to advance two hundred miles without opposition, drove the Confederates out of a large part of Tennessee, cut off their supplies, caused the fall of Nashville and of Fort Columbus, the Gibraltar of the Mississippi, spread profound depression throughout the South, and set church bells ringing and bonfires blazing from Maine to the Mississippi.

It was a stupendous victory, and created a tremendous impression even in Europe. It was really one of the turning-points of the war.

From that time on, U. S. Grant was known as “Unconditional Surrender” Grant, and “I propose to move on your works immediately” became the battle-cry of the North.

Here, at last, was the great leader for which the country had been waiting. Congress made him a major-general; he was appointed commander of the Military Department of Western Tennessee, and quickly became the idol of the nation. One newspaper mentioned that he liked to smoke during a battle, and, presto! over ten thousand boxes of cigars were showered upon him.

But in less than three weeks after all this Grant was actually in tears of rage and mortification because of unfair treatment by a jealous superior officer.

His immediate superior in the West was Halleck, a colossal and unmitigated ass. Admiral Foote called Halleck “a military imbecile,” and Gideon Welles, Lincoln's Secretary of the Navy, who knew Halleck intimately, sums him up thus:

“Halleck originates nothing, anticipates nothing, suggests nothing, plans nothing, decides nothing, is good for nothing and does nothing except scold, smoke and scratch his elbows.”

But Halleck thought very well of himself. He had been an assistant professor at West Point, had written books on military strategy, international law, and mining, had been director of a silver-mine, president of a railway, a successful attorney, had mastered French and translated a tome on Napoleon. In his own opinion, he was the distinguished scholar, Henry Wager Halleck.

And who was Grant? A nobody, a drunken and discredited army captain. When Grant came to see him, before attacking Fort Donelson, Halleck was rude, and dismissed his military suggestions with irritation and contempt. Now Grant had won a great victory and had the nation at his feet, while Halleck was still scratching his elbows in St. Louis, unnoticed and ignored. And it galled Halleck.

To make matters worse, he felt that this erstwhile hide-buyer was insulting him. He telegraphed Grant day after day, and Grant brazenly ignored his orders. At least, so Halleck imagined. But he was wrong. Grant had sent report upon report; but, after the fall of Donelson, a break in telegraphic communications had made it impossible for his telegrams to get through. However, Halleck didn't know this, and he was indignant. Victory and public adulation had gone to Grant's head, had they? Well, he would teach this young upstart a lesson. So he wired McClellan repeatedly, denouncing Grant. Grant was this, Grant was that—insolent, drunk, idle, ignoring orders, incompetent. “I'm tired and worn out with this neglect and inefficiency.”

McClellan, too, was envious of Grant's popularity; so he sent Halleck what, in the light of history, is the most amazing telegram of the Civil War: “Do not hesitate to arrest him [Grant] at once if the good of the service requires it, and place C. F. Smith in command.”

Halleck immediately took Grant's army away from him, virtually placed him under arrest, and then leaned back in his chair and scratched his elbows with savage satisfaction.

The war was almost a year old now, and the only general who had won a considerable victory for the North stood stripped of all power and in public disgrace.

Later Grant was restored to command. Then he blundered woefully at the Battle of Shiloh; if Johnston, the Confederate general, had not bled to death during the fighting, Grant's entire army might have been surrounded and captured. Shiloh was, at that time, the greatest battle that had ever been fought on this continent, and Grant's losses were staggering—thirteen thousand men. He had acted stupidly; he had been taken by surprise. He deserved criticism, and it came roaring down upon him. He was falsely accused of being intoxicated at Shiloh, and millions believed it. A tidal wave of popular indignation swept over the country, and the public clamored for his removal. But Lincoln said:

“I can't spare this man. He fights.”

When people told him Grant drank too much whisky, he inquired: “What brand? I want to send a few barrels to some of my other generals.”

The following January Grant assumed command of the expedition against Vicksburg. The campaign against this natural fortress, perched on a high bluff two hundred feet above the Mississippi, was long and heartbreaking. The place was heavily fortified, and the gunboats on the river couldn't elevate their cannon high enough to touch it. Grant's problem was to get his army close enough to attack it.

He went back to the heart of Mississippi and tried to march on it from the east. That failed.

Then he cut away the levees of the river, put his army on boats, and tried to float through the swamps and get at the place from the north. That failed.

Then he dug a canal and tried to change the course of the Mississippi. That failed.

It was a trying winter. Rain fell almost continuously, the river flooded the whole valley, and Grant's troops floundered through miles of swamps, ooze, bayous, tangled forests, and trailing vines. Men stood up to their waists in mud, they ate in the mud, they slept in the mud. Malarial fever broke out, and measles and smallpox. Sanitation was well-nigh impossible, and the death-rate was appalling.

The Vicksburg campaign was a failure—that was the cry that went up everywhere. A stupid failure, a tragic failure, a criminal failure.

Grant's own generals—Sherman, McPherson, Logan, Wilson —regarded his plans as absurd, and believed they would end in black ruin. The press throughout the country was vitriolic, and the nation was demanding Grant's removal.

“He has hardly a friend left except myself,” Lincoln said.

Despite all opposition, Lincoln clung to Grant; and he had his faith richly rewarded, for, on July 4, the same day that the timid Meade let Lee escape at Gettysburg, Grant rode into Vicksburg on a horse taken from the plantation of Jefferson Davis, and won a greater victory than any American general had achieved since the days of Washington.

After eight months of desolating failure, Grant had captured forty thousand prisoners at Vicksburg, placed the entire Mississippi River in the hands of the North, and split the Confederacy.

The news set the nation aflame with enthusiasm.

Congress passed a special act in order that Grant could be made lieutenant-general—an honor that no man had worn since the death of Washington—and Lincoln, calling him to the White House, made a short address appointing him commander of all the armies of the Union.

Forewarned that he would have to reply with a speech of acceptance, Grant drew out of his pocket a little wrinkled piece of paper containing only three sentences. As he began to read, the paper shook, his face flushed, his knees trembled, and his voice failed. Breaking down completely, he clutched the shaking paper with both hands, shifted his position, took a deep breath, and began all over again.

The hog-and-hide buyer from Galena found it easier to face bullets than to deliver a speech of eighty-four words before an audience of eleven men.

Mrs. Lincoln, eager to make a social event out of Grant's presence in Washington, had already arranged a dinner and a party in the general's honor. But Grant begged to be excused, saying he must hasten back to the front.

“But we can't excuse you,” the President insisted. “Mrs. Lincoln's dinner without you would be ‘Hamlet’ without Hamlet.”

“A dinner to me,” replied Grant, “means a million dollars a day loss to the country. Besides, I've had about enough of this show business, anyway.”

Lincoln loved a man who would talk like that—one who, like himself, despised “fizzlegigs and fireworks,” and one who would “take responsibility and act.”

Lincoln's hopes rose and towered now. He was sure that, with Grant in command, all would soon be well.

But he was wrong. Within four months the country was plunged into blacker gloom and deeper despair than ever, and once more Lincoln was pacing the floor throughout the night, haggard and worn and desperate.

25

In May 1864, the triumphant Grant plunged across the Rapidan River with 122,000 men. He was going to destroy's Lee's army forthwith and end the war at once.

Lee met him in the “wilderness” of North Virginia. The place was well named. It was a jungle of rolling hills and swampy swales smothered with a dense second growth of pine and oaks and matted with underbrush so thick that a cottontail could hardly crawl through it. And in those gloomy and tangled woods, Grant fought a grim and bloody campaign. The slaughter was appalling. The jungle itself caught on fire and hundreds of the wounded were consumed by the flames.

At the end of the second day even the stolid Grant was so shaken that he retired to his tent and wept.

But after every battle, no matter what the results, he gave the same order: “Advance! Advance!”

At the end of the sixth bloody day he sent the famous telegram: “I propose to fight it out on this line if it takes all summer.”

Well, it did take all summer. Moreover, it took all autumn, and all winter, and a part of the next spring.

Grant had twice as many men in the field now as the enemy had, and back of him, in the North, lay a vast reservoir of manpower upon which he could draw, while the South had almost exhausted its recruits and supplies.

“The rebels,” said Grant, “have already robbed the cradle and the grave.”

Grant held that the quick way and the only way to end the war was to keep on killing Lee's men until Lee surrendered.

What if two Northern soldiers were shot for every one the South lost? Grant could make up the wastage, but Lee couldn't. So Grant kept on blasting and snooting and slaying.

In six weeks he lost 54,926 men—as many as Lee had in his entire army.

In one hour at Cold Harbor he lost seven thousand—a thousand more than had been killed on both sides in three days during the Battle of Gettysburg.

And what advantage was achieved by this ghastly loss?

We shall let Grant himself answer the question: “None whatever.” That was his estimate.

The attack at Cold Harbor was the most tragic blunder of his career.

Such slaughter was more than human nerves and human bodies could endure. It broke the morale of the troops; the rank and file of the army were on the verge of mutiny, and the officers themselves were ready to rebel.

“For thirty-six days now,” said one of Grant's corps commanders, “there has been one unbroken funeral procession past me.”

Lincoln, broken-hearted though he was, realized that there was nothing to do but keep on. He telegraphed Grant to “hold on with a bull dog grip and chew and choke.” Then he issued a call for half a million more men, to serve from one to three years.

The call staggered the country. The nation was plunged into an abyss of despair.

“Everything now is darkness and doubt and discouragement,” one of Lincoln's secretaries recorded in his diary.

On July 2 Congress adopted a resolution that sounded like the lamentations of one of the Hebrew prophets of the Old Testament. It requested the citizens to “confess and repent of their manifold sins, implore the compassion and forgiveness of the Almighty, and beseech him as the Supreme Ruler of the world not to destroy us as a people.”

Lincoln was being cursed now almost as violently in the North as in the South. He was denounced as a usurper, a traitor, a tyrant, a fiend, a monster, “a bloody butcher shouting war to the knife and knife to the hilt, and crying for more victims for his slaughter pens.”

Some of his most bitter enemies declared that he ought to be killed. And one evening as he was riding out to his summer headquarters at the Soldiers' Home, a would-be assassin fired at him and put a bullet through his tall silk hat.

A few weeks later the proprietor of a hotel in Meadville, Pennsylvania, found this inscription scratched on a windowpane: “Abe Lincoln Departed this Life August 13, 1864, by the effect of poison.” The room had been occupied the night before by a popular actor named Booth—John Wilkes Booth.

The preceding June the Republicans had nominated Lincoln for a second term. But they felt now that they had made a mistake, a woeful mistake. Some of the most prominent men in the party urged Lincoln to withdraw. Others demanded it. They wanted to call another convention, admit that Lincoln was a failure, cancel his nomination, and place another candidate at the head of the ticket.

Even Lincoln's close friend Orville Browning recorded in his diary in July, 1864, that the “nation's great need is a competent leader at the head of affairs.”

Lincoln himself now believed that his case was hopeless. He abandoned all thought of being elected for a second term. He had failed. His generals had failed. His war policy had failed. The people had lost faith in his leadership, and he feared that the Union itself would be destroyed.

“Even the heavens,” he exclaimed, “are hung in black.”

Finally a large group of radicals, disgusted with Lincoln, called another convention, nominated the picturesque General John C. Fremont as their candidate, and split the Republican party.

The situation was grave; and there is hardly a doubt that if Frémont hadn't withdrawn from the race later, General McClellan, the Democratic candidate, would have triumphed over his divided opponents and the history of the nation would have been changed.

Even with Fremont out of the race, Lincoln received only 200,000 more votes than McClellan.

Notwithstanding the vitriolic condemnation poured upon him, Lincoln went calmly on, doing his best and answering no one.

“I desire,” he said, “to so conduct the affairs of this administration that if, at the end, when I come to lay down the reins of power, I have lost every other friend on earth, I shall at least have one friend left, and that friend shall be deep down inside of me.... I am not bound to win, but I am bound to be true. I am not bound to succeed, but I am bound to live up to the light I have.”

Weary and despondent, he often stretched himself out on a sofa, picked up a small Bible, and turned to Job for comfort: “Gird up now thy loins like a man; for I will demand of thee, and answer thou me.”

In the summer of 1864, Lincoln was a changed man, changed in mind and body from the physical giant who had come off the prairies of Illinois three years before. Year by year his laughter had grown less frequent; the furrows in his face had deepened; his shoulders had stooped; his cheeks were sunken; he suffered from chronic indigestion; his legs were always cold; he could hardly sleep; he wore habitually an expression of anguish. He said to a friend: “I feel as though I shall never be glad again.”

When Augustus Saint-Gaudens saw a life-mask of Lincoln that had been made in the spring of 1865, the famous sculptor thought that it was a death-mask, insisted that it must be, for already the marks of death were upon his face.

Carpenter, the artist who lived at the White House for months while he was painting the scene of the Emancipation Proclamation, wrote:

During the first week of the battle of the Wilderness, the President scarcely slept at all. Passing through the main hall of the domestic apartment on one of those days, I met him, clad in a long morning wrapper, pacing back and forth, his hands behind him, great black rings under his eyes, his head bent forward upon his breast—the picture of sorrow and care and anxiety.... There were whole days when I could scarcely look into his furrowed face without weeping.

Callers found him collapsed in his chair, so exhausted that he did not look up or speak when they first addressed him.

“I sometimes fancy,” he declared, “that every one of the throng that comes to see me daily darts at me with thumb and finger and picks out his piece of my vitality and carries it away.”

He told Mrs. Stowe, the author of “Uncle Tom's Cabin,” that he would never live to see peace.

“This war is killing me,” he said.

His friends, alarmed at the change in his appearance, urged him to take a vacation.

“Two or three weeks would do me no good,” he replied. “I cannot fly from my thoughts. I hardly know how to rest. What is tired lies within me and can't be got at.”

“The cry of the widow and the orphan,” said his secretary, “was always in Lincoln's ear.”

Mothers and sweethearts and wives, weeping and pleading, rushed to him daily to obtain pardons for men who had been condemned to be shot. No matter how worn he was, how exhausted, Lincoln always heard their stories, and generally granted their requests, for he never could bear to see a woman cry, especially if she had a baby in her arms.

“When I am gone,” he moaned, “I hope it can be said of me that I plucked a thistle and planted a flower wherever I thought a flower would grow.”

The generals scolded and Stanton stormed: Lincoln's leniency was destroying the discipline of the army, he must keep his hands off. But the truth is he hated the brutal methods of brigadier-generals, and the despotism of the regular army. On the other hand, he loved the volunteers on whom he had to depend for winning the war—men who, like himself, had come from the forest and farm.

Was one of them condemned to be shot for cowardice? Lincoln would pardon him, saying, “I have never been sure but what I might drop my gun and run, myself, if I were in battle.”

Had a volunteer become homesick and run away? “Well, I don't see that shooting will do him any good.”

Had a tired and exhausted Vermont farm boy been sentenced to death for falling asleep on sentinel duty? “I might have done the same thing, myself,” Lincoln would say.

A mere list of his pardons would fill many pages.

He once wired to General Meade, “I am unwilling for any boy under eighteen to be shot.” And there were more than a million boys under that age in the Union armies. In fact, there were a fifth of a million under sixteen, and a hundred thousand under fifteen.

Sometimes the President worked a bit of humor into his most serious messages; as, for example, when he wired Colonel Mulligan, “If you haven't shot Barney D. yet, don't.”

The anguish of bereaved mothers touched Lincoln very deeply. On November 21, 1864, he wrote the most beautiful and famous letter of his life. Oxford University has a copy of this letter hanging on its wall, “as a model of pure and exquisite diction which has never been excelled.”

Although written as prose, it is really unconscious and resonant poetry:

Executive Mansion,

Washington, Nov. 21, 1864.

To Mrs. Bixby, Boston, Mass.

Dear Madame,

I have been shown in the files of the War Department

A statement of the Adjutant General of Massachusetts

That you are the mother of five sons

Who have died gloriously on the field of battle. I feel

How weak and fruitless must be any words of mine

Which would attempt to beguile you from the grief

Of a loss so overwhelming. But I cannot refrain

From tendering to you the consolation that may be found

In the thanks of the Republic they died to save.

I pray that our Heavenly Father may assuage

The anguish of your bereavement, and leave you only

The cherished memory of the loved and lost,

And the solemn pride that must be yours to have laid

So costly a sacrifice upon the altar of freedom.

Yours very sincerely and respectfully,

A. Lincoln.

One day Noah Brooks gave Lincoln a volume of Oliver Wendell Holmes's verses. Opening the book, Lincoln began reading the poem “Lexington” aloud, but when he came to the stanza beginning:

Green be the grass where her martyrs are lying!
Shroudless and tombless they sunk to their rest,

his voice quavered, he choked, and handing the volume back to Brooks, he whispered: “You read it. I can't.”

Months afterward he recited the entire poem to friends in the White House, without missing a word.

On April 5, 1864, Lincoln received a letter from a brokenhearted girl in Washington County, Pennsylvania.

“After long hesitation through dread and fear,” she began, “I have at last concluded to inform you of my troubles.” The man to whom she had been engaged for some years had joined the army, had later been permitted to go home to vote, and they had, as she put it, “very foolishly indulged too freely in matrimonial affairs.” And now “the results of our indulgences are going to bring upon us both an unlawful family providing you do not take mercy upon us and grant him a leave of absence in order to ratify past events.... I hope and pray to God that you will not cast me aside in scorn and dismay.”

Reading the letter, Lincoln was deeply touched. He stared out the window with unseeing eyes in which there were doubtlessly tears....

Picking up his pen, Lincoln wrote the following words to Stanton across the bottom of the girl's letter: “Send him to her by all means.”

The terrible summer of 1864 dragged to an end, and the autumn brought good news: Sherman had taken Atlanta and was marching through Georgia. Admiral Farragut, after a dramatic naval battle, had captured Mobile Bay and tightened the blockade in the Gulf of Mexico. Sheridan had won brilliant and spectacular victories in the Shenandoah Valley. And Lee was now afraid to come out in the open; so Grant was laying siege to Petersburg and Richmond....

The Confederacy had almost reached the end.

Lincoln's generals were winning now, his policy had been vindicated, and the spirits of the North rose as on wings; so, in November, he was elected for a second term. But instead of taking it as a personal triumph, he remarked laconically that evidently the people had not thought it wise “to swap horses while crossing a stream.”

After four years of fighting, there was no hatred in Lincoln's heart for the people of the South. Time and again he said: “‘Judge not that ye be not judged.’ They are just what we would be in their position.”

So in February, 1865, while the Confederacy was already crumbling to dust, and Lee's surrender was only two months away, Lincoln proposed that the Federal Government pay the Southern States four hundred million dollars for their slaves; but every member of his Cabinet was unfriendly to the idea and he dropped it.

The following month, on the occasion of his second inauguration, Lincoln delivered a speech that the late Earl Curzon, Chancellor of Oxford University, declared to be “the purest gold of human eloquence, nay of eloquence almost divine.”

Stepping forward and kissing a Bible open at the fifth chapter of Isaiah, he began an address that sounded like the speech of some great character in drama.

“It was like a sacred poem,” wrote Carl Schurz. “No ruler had ever spoken words like these to his people. America had never before had a president who had found such words in the depths of his heart.”

The closing words of this speech are, in the estimation of the writer, the most noble and beautiful utterances ever delivered by the lips of mortal man. He never reads them without thinking somehow of an organ playing in the subdued light of a great cathedral.

Fondly do we hope—fervently do we pray—that this mighty scourge of war may speedily pass away. Yet, if God wills that it continue until all the wealth piled by the bondman's two hundred and fifty years of unrequited toil shall be sunk, and until every drop of blood drawn with the lash shall be paid by another drawn with the sword, as was said three thousand years ago, so still it must be said, “The judgments of the Lord are true and righteous altogether.”

With malice toward none; with charity for all; with firmness in the right, as God gives us to see the right, let us strive on to finish the work we are in; to bind up the nation's wounds; to care for him who shall have borne the battle, and for his widow, and his orphan—to do all which may achieve and cherish a just and lasting peace among ourselves, and with all nations.

Two months later, to a day, this speech was read at Lincoln's funeral services in Springfield.

26

In the latter part of March, 1865, something very significant happened in Richmond, Virginia. Mrs. Jefferson Davis, wife of the President of the Confederacy, disposed of her carriage horses, placed her personal effects on sale at a dry-goods store, packed up the remainder of her belongings, and headed farther south.... Something was about to happen.

Grant had been besieging the Confederate capital now for nine months. Lee's troops were ragged and hungry. Money was scarce, and they were rarely paid; and when they were, it was with the paper script of the Confederacy, which was almost worthless now. It took three dollars of it to buy a cup of coffee, five dollars to buy a stick of firewood, and a thousand dollars was demanded for a barrel of flour.

Secession was a lost cause. And so was slavery. Lee knew it. And his men knew it. A hundred thousand of them had already deserted. Whole regiments were packing up now and walking out together. Those that remained were turning to religion for solace and hope. Prayer-meetings were being held in almost every tent; men were shouting and weeping and seeing visions, and entire regiments were kneeling before going into battle.

But notwithstanding all this piety, Richmond was tottering to its fall.

On Sunday, April 2, Lee's army set fire to the cotton and tobacco warehouses in the town, burned the arsenal, destroyed the half-finished ships at the wharves, and fled from the city at night while towering flames were roaring up into the darkness.

They were no sooner out of town than Grant was in hot pursuit with seventy-two thousand men, banging away at the Confederates from both sides and the rear, while Sheridan's cavalry was heading them off in front, tearing up railway lines, and capturing supply-trains.

Sheridan telegraphed to headquarters, “I think if this thing is pushed, Lee will surrender.”

Lincoln wired back, “Let the thing be pushed.”

It was; and, after a running fight of eighty miles, Grant finally hemmed the Southern troops in on all sides. They were trapped, and Lee realized that further bloodshed would be futile.

In the meantime Grant, half blind with a violent sick headache, had fallen behind his army and halted at a farmhouse on Saturday evening.

“I spent the night,” he records in his Memoirs, “in bathing my feet in hot water and mustard, and putting mustard plasters on my wrists and the back part of my neck, hoping to be cured by morning.”

The next morning, he was cured instantaneously. And the thing that did it was not a mustard plaster, but a horseman galloping down the road with a letter from Lee, saying he wanted to surrender.

“When the officer [bearing the message] reached me,” Grant wrote, “I was still suffering with the sick-headache, but the instant I saw the contents of the note, I was cured.”

The two generals met that afternoon in a small bare parlor of a brick dwelling to arrange terms. Grant as usual was slouchily dressed: his shoes were grimy, he had no sword, and he wore the same uniform that every private in the army wore—except that his had three silver stars on the shoulder to show who he was.

What a contrast he made to the aristocratic Lee, wearing beaded gauntlets and a sword studded with jewels! Lee looked like some royal conqueror who had just stepped out of a steel engraving, while Grant looked more like a Missouri farmer who had come to town to sell a load of hogs and a few hides. For once Grant felt ashamed of his frowzy appearance, and he apologized to Lee for not being better dressed for the occasion.

Twenty years before, Grant and Lee had both been officers in the regular army while the United States was waging a war against Mexico. So they fell to reminiscing now about the days of long ago, about the winter the “regulars” spent on the border of Mexico, about the poker games that used to last all night, about their amateur production of “Othello” when Grant played the sweetly feminine role of Desdemona.

“Our conversation grew so pleasant,” Grant records, “that I almost forgot the object of our meeting.”

Finally, Lee brought the conversation around to the terms of surrender; but Grant replied to that very briefly, and then his mind went rambling on again, back across two decades, to Corpus Christi and the winter in 1845 when the wolves howled on the prairies... and the sunlight danced on the waves... and wild horses could be bought for three dollars apiece.

Grant might have gone on like that all afternoon if Lee had not interrupted and reminded him, for the second time, that he had come there to surrender his army.

So Grant asked for pen and ink, and scrawled out the terms. There were to be no humiliating ceremonies of capitulation such as Washington had exacted from the British at Yorktown in 1781, with the helpless enemy parading without guns, between long lines of their exultant conquerors. And there was to be no vengeance. For four bloody years the radicals of the North had been demanding that Lee and the other West Point officers who had turned traitor to their flag be hanged for treason. But the terms that Grant wrote out had no sting. Lee's officers were permitted to keep their arms, and his men were to be paroled and sent home; and every soldier who claimed a horse or a mule could crawl on it and ride it back to his farm or cotton-patch and start tilling the soil once more.

Why were the terms of surrender so generous and gentle? Because Abraham Lincoln himself had dictated the terms.

And so the war that had killed half a million men came to a close in a tiny Virginia village called Appomattox Court House. The surrender took place on a peaceful spring afternoon when the scent of lilacs filled the air. It was Palm Sunday.

On that very afternoon Lincoln was sailing back to Washington on the good ship River Queen. He spent several hours reading Shakspere aloud to his friends. Presently he came to this passage in “Macbeth:”

Duncan is in his grave;
After life's fitful fever he sleeps well;
Treason has done his worst: nor steel, nor poison,
Malice domestic, foreign levy, nothing,
Can touch him further.

These lines made a profound impression on Lincoln. He read them once, then paused, gazing with unseeing eyes through the port-hole of the ship.

Presently he read them aloud again.

Five days later Lincoln himself was dead.

27

We must retrace our steps now, for I want to tell you of an amazing thing that happened shortly before the fall of Richmond—an incident that gives one a vivid picture of the domestic miseries that Lincoln endured in silence for almost a quarter of a century.

It happened near Grant's headquarters. The general had invited Mr. and Mrs. Lincoln to spend a week with him near the front.

They were glad to come, for the President was almost exhausted. He hadn't had a vacation since he entered the White House, and he was eager to get away from the throng of office-seekers who were harassing him once more at the opening of his second term.

So he and Mrs. Lincoln boarded the River Queen and sailed away down the Potomac, through the lower reaches of Chesapeake Bay, past old Point Comfort, and up the James River to City Point. There, high on a bluff, two hundred feet above the water, sat the ex-hide-buyer from Galena, smoking and whittling.

A few days later the President's party was joined by a distinguished group of people from Washington, including M. Geoffroi, the French minister. Naturally the visitors were eager to see the battle lines of the Army of the Potomac, twelve miles away; so the next day they set out upon the excursion—the men on horseback, Mrs. Lincoln and Mrs. Grant following in a half-open carriage.

General Adam Badeau, Grant's military secretary and aidede-camp and one of the closest friends General Grant ever had, was detailed to escort the ladies that day. He sat on the front seat of the carriage, facing them and with his back to the horses. He was an eye-witness to all that occurred, and I am quoting now from pages 356—362 of his book entitled “Grant in Peace:”

In the course of conversation, I chanced to mention that all the wives of officers at the army front had been ordered to the rear—a sure sign that active operations were in contemplation. I said not a lady had been allowed to remain, except Mrs. Griffin, the wife of General Charles Griffin, who had obtained a special permit from the President.

At this Mrs. Lincoln was up in arms. “What do you mean by that, sir?” she exclaimed. “Do you mean to say that she saw the President alone? Do you know that I never allow the President to see any woman alone?”

She was absolutely jealous of poor, ugly Abraham Lincoln.

I tried to pacify her and to palliate my remark, but she was fairly boiling over with rage. “That's a very equivocal smile, sir,” she exclaimed: “Let me out of this carriage at once. I will ask the President if he saw that woman alone.”

Mrs. Griffin, afterward the Countess Esterhazy, was one of the best known and most elegant women in Washington, a Carroll, and a personal acquaintance of Mrs. Grant, who strove to mollify the excited spouse, but all in vain. Mrs. Lincoln again bade me stop the driver, and when I hesitated to obey, she thrust her arms past me to the front of the carriage and held the driver fast. But Mrs. Grant finally prevailed upon her to wait till the whole party alighted....

At night, when we were back in camp, Mrs. Grant talked over the matter with me, and said the whole affair was so distressing and mortifying that neither of us must ever mention it; at least, I was to be absolutely silent, and she would disclose it only to the General. But the next day I was released from my pledge, for “worse remained behind.”

The same party went in the morning to visit the Army of the James on the north side of the river, commanded by General Ord. The arrangements were somewhat similar to those of the day before. We went up the river in a steamer, and then the men again took horses and Mrs. Lincoln and Mrs. Grant proceeded in an ambulance. I was detailed as before to act as escort, but I asked for a companion in the duty; for after my experience, I did not wish to be the only officer in the carriage. So Colonel Horace Porter was ordered to join the party. Mrs. Ord accompanied her husband; as she was the wife of the commander of an army she was not subject to the order for return; though before that day was over she wished herself in Washington or anywhere else away from the army, I am sure. She was mounted, and as the ambulance was full, she remained on her horse and rode for a while by the side of the President, and thus preceded Mrs. Lincoln.

As soon as Mrs. Lincoln discovered this her rage was beyond all bounds. “What does the woman mean,” she exclaimed, “by riding by the side of the President? and ahead of me? Does she suppose that he wants her by the side of him?”

She was in a frenzy of excitement, and language and action both became more extravagant every moment.

Mrs. Grant again endeavored to pacify her, but then Mrs. Lincoln got angry with Mrs. Grant; and all that Porter and I could do was to see that nothing worse than words occurred. We feared she might jump out of the vehicle and shout to the cavalcade.

Once she said to Mrs. Grant in her transports: “I suppose you think you'll get to the White House yourself, don't you?” Mrs. Grant was very calm and dignified, and merely replied that she was quite satisfied with her present position; it was far greater than she had ever expected to attain. But Mrs. Lincoln exclaimed; “Oh! you had better take it if you can get it. Tis very nice.” Then she reverted to Mrs. Ord, while Mrs. Grant defended her friend at the risk of arousing greater vehemence.

When there was a halt, Major Seward, a nephew of the Secretary of State, and an officer of General Ord's staff, rode up, and tried to say something jocular. “The President's horse is very gallant, Mrs. Lincoln,” he remarked; “he insists on riding by the side of Mrs. Ord.”

This of course added fuel to the flame.

“What do you mean by that, sir?” she cried.

Seward discovered that he had made a huge mistake, and his horse at once developed a peculiarity that compelled him to ride behind, to get out of the way of the storm.

Finally the party arrived at its destination and Mrs. Ord came up to the ambulance. Then Mrs. Lincoln positively insulted her, called her vile names in the presence of a crowd of officers, and asked what she meant by following up the President. The poor woman burst into tears and inquired what she had done, but Mrs. Lincoln refused to be appeased, and stormed till she was tired. Mrs. Grant still tried to stand by her friend, and everybody was shocked and horrified. But all things come to an end, and after a while we returned to City Point.

That night the President and Mrs. Lincoln entertained General and Mrs. Grant and the General's staff at dinner on the steamer, and before us all Mrs. Lincoln berated General Ord to the President, and urged that he should be removed. He was unfit for his place, she said, to say nothing of his wife. General Grant sat next and defended his officer bravely. Of course General Ord was not removed.

During all this visit similar scenes were occurring. Mrs. Lincoln repeatedly attacked her husband in the presence of officers because of Mrs. Griffin and Mrs. Ord, and I never suffered greater humiliation and pain on account of one not a near personal friend than when I saw the Head of the State, the man who carried all the cares of the nation at such a crisis—subjected to this inexpressible public mortification. He bore it as Christ might have done; with an expression of pain and sadness that cut one to the heart, but with supreme calmness and dignity. He called her “mother,” with his old-time plainness; he pleaded with eyes and tones, and endeavored to explain or palliate the offenses of others, till she turned on him like a tigress; and then he walked away, hiding that noble, ugly face that we might not catch the full expression of its misery.

General Sherman was a witness of some of these episodes and mentioned them in his memoirs many years ago.

Captain Barnes, of the navy, was a witness and a sufferer too. Barnes had accompanied Mrs. Ord on her unfortunate ride and refused afterward to say that the lady was to blame. Mrs. Lincoln never forgave him. A day or two afterward he went to speak to the President on some official matter when Mrs. Lincoln and several others were present. The President's wife said something to him unusually offensive that all the company could hear. Lincoln was silent, but after a moment he went up to the young officer, and taking him by the arm led him into his own cabin, to show him a map or a paper, he said. He made no remark, Barnes told me, upon what had occurred. He could not rebuke his wife; but he showed his regret, and his regard for the officer, with a touch of what seemed to me the most exquisite breeding imaginable.

Shortly before these occurrences Mrs. Stanton had visited City Point, and I chanced to ask her some question about the President's wife.

“I do not visit Mrs. Lincoln,” was the reply.

But I thought I must have been mistaken; the wife of the Secretary of War must visit the wife of the President; and I renewed my inquiry.

“Understand me, sir?” she repeated; “I do not go to the White House; I do not visit Mrs. Lincoln.” I was not at all intimate with Mrs. Stanton and this remark was so extraordinary that I never forgot it; but I understood it afterward.

Mrs. Lincoln continued her conduct toward Mrs. Grant, who strove to placate her and then Mrs. Lincoln became more outrageous still. She once rebuked Mrs. Grant for sitting in her presence. “How dare you be seated,” she said, “until I invite you?”

Elizabeth Keckley, who accompanied Mrs. Lincoln on this trip to Grant's headquarters, tells of a dinner party that “Mrs. President” gave aboard the River Queen.

One of the guests was a young officer attached to the Sanitary Commission. He was seated near Mrs. Lincoln, and, by way of pleasantry, remarked: “Mrs. Lincoln, you should have seen the President the other day, on his triumphal entry into Richmond. He was the cynosure of all eyes. The ladies kissed their hands to him, and greeted him with the waving of handkerchiefs. He is quite a hero when surrounded by pretty young ladies.”

The young officer suddenly paused with a look of embarrass-ment.

Mrs. Lincoln turned to him with flashing eyes, with the remark that his familiarity was offensive to her.

Quite a scene followed, and I do not think that the Captain who incurred Mrs. Lincoln's displeasure will ever forget that memorable evening.

“I never in my life saw a more peculiarly constituted woman,” says Mrs. Keckley. “Search the world over and you will not find her counterpart.”

“Ask the first American you meet, ‘What kind of a woman was Lincoln's wife?’” says Honoré Willsie Morrow in her book “Mary Todd Lincoln,” “and the chances are ninety nine to one hundred that he'll reply that she was a shrew, a curse to her husband, a vulgar fool, insane.”

The great tragedy of Lincoln's life was not his assassination, but his marriage.

When Booth fired, Lincoln did not know what had hit him, but for twenty-three years he had reaped almost daily what Herndon described as “the bitter harvest of conjugal infelicity.”

“Amid storms of party hate and rebellious strife,” says General Badeau, “amid agonies... like those of the Cross... the hyssop of domestic misery was pressed to Lincoln's lips, and he too said: ‘Father, forgive: they know not what they do.’”

One of Lincoln's warmest friends during his life as President was Orville H. Browning, Senator from Illinois. These two men had known each other for a quarter of a century, and Browning was frequently a dinner guest in the White House and sometimes spent the night there. He kept a detailed diary, but one can only wonder what he recorded in it about Mrs. Lincoln, for authors have not been permitted to read the manuscript without pledging their honor not to divulge anything derogatory to her character. This manuscript was recently sold for publication with the provision that all shocking statements regarding Mrs. Lincoln should be deleted before it was put into print.

At public receptions in the White House it had always been customary for the President to choose some lady other than his wife to lead the promenade with him.

But custom or no custom, tradition or no tradition, Mrs. Lincoln wouldn't tolerate it. What? Another woman ahead of her? And on the President's arm? Never!

So she had her way, and Washington society hooted.

She not only refused to let the President walk with another woman, but she eyed him jealously and criticized him severely for even talking to one.

Before going to a public reception Lincoln would come to his jealous wife, asking whom he might talk to. She would mention woman after woman, saying she detested this one and hated that one.

“But Mother,” he would remonstrate, “I must talk with somebody. I can't stand around like a simpleton and say nothing. If you will not tell me who I may talk with, please tell me who I may not talk with.”

She determined to have her own way, cost what it might, and, on one occasion, she threatened to throw herself down in the mud in front of every one unless Lincoln promoted a certain officer.

At another time she dashed into his office during an important interview, pouring out a torrent of words. Without replying to her, Lincoln calmly arose, picked her up, carried her out of the room, set her down, returned, locked the door, and went on with his business as if he had never been interrupted.

She consulted a spiritualist, who told her that all of Lincoln's Cabinet were his enemies.

That didn't surprise her. She had no love for any of them.

She despised Seward, calling him “a hypocrite,” “an abolition sneak,” saying that he couldn't be trusted, and warning Lincoln to have nothing to do with him.

“Her hostility to Chase,” says Mrs. Keckley, “was bitter.”

And one of the reasons was this: Chase had a daughter, Kate, who was married to a wealthy man and was one of the most beautiful and charming women in Washington society. Kate would attend the White House receptions; and, to Mrs. Lincoln's immense disgust, she would draw all the men about her and run away with the show.

Mrs. Keckley says that “Mrs. Lincoln, who was jealous of the popularity of others, had no desire to build up the social position of Chase's daughter through political favor to her father.”

With heat and temper, she repeatedly urged Lincoln to dismiss Chase from the Cabinet.

She loathed Stanton, and when he criticized her, she “would return the compliment by sending him books and clippings describing him as an irascible and disagreeable personality.”

To all these bitter condemnations, Lincoln would say:

“Mother, you are mistaken; your prejudices are so violent you do not stop to reason. If I listened to you, I should soon be without a cabinet.”

She disliked Andrew Johnson intensely; she hated McClellan; she despised Grant, calling him “an obstinate fool and a butcher,” declaring that she could handle an army better than he could, and frequently vowing that if he were ever made President, she would leave the country and never come back to it as long as he was in the White House.

“Well, Mother,” Lincoln would say, “supposing that we give you command of the army. No doubt you would do much better than any general that has been tried.”

After Lee surrendered, Mr. and Mrs. Grant came to Washington. The town was a blaze of light: crowds were making merry with songs and bonfires and revelry; so Mrs. Lincoln wrote the general, inviting him to drive about the streets with her and the President “to see the illumination.”

But she did not invite Mrs. Grant.

A few nights later, however, she arranged a theater party and invited Mr. and Mrs. Grant and Mr. and Mrs. Stanton to sit in the President's box.

As soon as Mrs. Stanton received the invitation, she hurried over to Mrs. Grant, to inquire if she were going.

“Unless you accept the invitation,” said Mrs. Stanton, “I shall refuse. I will not sit in the box with Mrs. Lincoln unless you are there too.”

Mrs. Grant was afraid to accept.

She knew that if the general entered the box, the audience would be sure to greet the “hero of Appomattox” with a salvo of applause.

And then what would Mrs. Lincoln do? There was no telling. She might create another disgraceful and mortifying scene.

Mrs. Grant refused the invitation, and so did Mrs. Stanton; and by refusing, they may have saved the lives of their husbands, for that night Booth crept into the President's box and shot Lincoln; and if Stanton and Grant had been there, he might have tried to kill them also.

28

In 1863 a group of Virginia slave barons formed and financed a secret society the object of which was the assassination of Abraham Lincoln; and in December, 1864, an advertisement appeared in a newspaper published in Selma, Alabama, begging for public subscriptions for a fund to be used for the same purpose, while other Southern journals offered cash rewards for his death.

But the man who finally shot Lincoln was actuated neither by patriotic desires nor commercial motives. John Wilkes Booth did it to win fame.

What manner of man was Booth? He was an actor, and nature had endowed him with an extraordinary amount of charm and personal magnetism. Lincoln's own secretaries described him as “handsome as Endymion on Latmos, the pet of his little world.” Francis Wilson, in his biography of Booth, declares that “he was one of the world's successful lovers.... Women halted in the streets and instinctively turned to admire him as he passed.”

By the time he was twenty-three, Booth had achieved the status of a matinee idol; and, naturally, his most famous role was Romeo. Wherever he played, amorous maidens deluged him with saccharine notes. While he was playing in Boston huge crowds of women thronged the streets in front of the Tremont House, eager to catch but one glimpse of their hero as he passed. One night a jealous actress, Henrietta Irving, knifed him in a hotel room, and then tried to commit suicide; and the morning after Booth shot Lincoln, another of his sweethearts, Ella Turner, an inmate of a Washington “parlor house,” was so distressed to learn that her lover had turned murderer and fled the city, that she clasped his picture to her heart, took chloroform, and lay down to die.

But did this flood of female adulation bring happiness to Booth? Very little, for his triumphs were confined almost wholly to the less discriminating audiences of the hinterland, while there was gnawing at his heart a passionate ambition to win the plaudits of the metropolitan centers.

But New York critics thought poorly of him, and in Philadelphia he was hooted off the stage.

This was galling, for other members of the Booth family were famous on the stage. For well-nigh a third of a century, his father, Junius Brutus Booth, had been a theatrical star of the first magnitude. His Shakesperian interpretations were the talk of the nation. No one else in the history of the American stage had ever won such extraordinary popularity. And the old man Booth had reared his favorite son, John Wilkes, to believe that he was to be the greatest of the Booths.

But the truth is that John Wilkes Booth possessed very little talent, and he didn't make the most of the trifling amount he did have. He was good-looking and spoiled and lazy, and he refused to bore himself with study. Instead, he spent his youthful days on horseback, dashing through the woods of the Maryland farm, spouting heroic speeches to the trees and squirrels, and jabbing the air with an old army lance that had been used in the Mexican War.

Old Junius Brutus Booth never permitted meat to be served at the family table, and he taught his sons that it was wrong to kill any living thing—even a rattlesnake. But John Wilkes evidently was not seriously restrained by his father's philosophy. He liked to shoot and destroy. Sometimes he banged away with his gun at the cats and hound dogs belonging to the slaves, and once he killed a sow owned by a neighbor.

Later he became an oyster pirate in Chesapeake Bay, then an actor. Now, at twenty-six, he was a favorite of gushing highschool girls, but, in his own eyes, he was a failure. And besides, he was bitterly jealous, for he saw his elder brother, Edwin, achieving the very renown that he himself so passionately desired.

He brooded over this a long time, and finally decided to make himself forever famous in one night.

This was his first plan: He would follow Lincoln to the theater some night; and, while one of his confederates turned off the gas-lights, Booth would dash into the President's box, rope and tie him, toss him onto the stage below, hustle him through a back exit, pitch him into a carriage, and scurry away like mad in the darkness.

By hard driving, he could reach the sleepy old town of Port Tobacco before dawn. Then he would row across the broad Potomac, and gallop on south through Virginia until he had lodged the Commander-in-Chief of the Union Army safely behind the Confederate bayonets in Richmond.

And then what?

Well, then the South could dictate terms and bring the war to an end at once.

And the credit for this brilliant achievement would go to whom? To the dazzling genius John Wilkes Booth. He would become twice as famous, a hundred times as famous as his brother Edwin. He would be crowned in history with the aura of a William Tell. Such were his dreams.

He was making twenty thousand dollars a year then in the theater, but he gave it all up. Money meant little to him now, for he was playing for something far more important than material possessions. So he used his savings to finance a band of Confederates that he fished out of the backwash of Southern sympathizers floating around Baltimore and Washington. Booth promised each one of them that he should be rich and famous.

And what a motley crew they were! There was Spangler, a drunken stage-hand and crab-fisherman; Atzerodt, an ignorant house-painter and blockade-runner with stringy hair and whiskers, a rough, fierce fellow; Arnold, a lazy farm-hand and a deserter from the Confederate Army; O'Laughlin, a livery-stable worker, smelling of horses and whisky; Surratt, a swaggering nincompoop of a clerk; Powell, a gigantic penniless brute, the wild-eyed, half-mad son of a Baptist preacher; Herold, a silly, giggling loafer, lounging about stables, talking horses and women, and living on the dimes and quarters given him by his widowed mother and his seven sisters.

With this supporting cast of tenth-raters, Booth was preparing to play the great role of his career. He spared neither time nor money in planning the minutest details. He purchased a pair of handcuffs, arranged for relays of fast horses at the proper places, bought three boats, and had them waiting in Port Tobacco Creek, equipped with oars and rowers ready to man them at a moment's notice.

Finally, in January, 1865, he believed that the great moment had come. Lincoln was to attend Ford's Theater on the eighteenth of that month, to see Edwin Forrest play “Jack Cade.” So the rumor ran about town. And Booth heard it. So he was on hand that night with his ropes and hopes—and what happened? Nothing. Lincoln didn't appear.

Two months later it was reported that Lincoln was going to drive out of the city on a certain afternoon to attend a theatrical performance in a near-by soldiers' encampment. So Booth and his accomplices, mounted on horses and armed with bowieknives and revolvers, hid in a stretch of woods that the President would have to pass. But when the White House carriage rolled by, Lincoln was not in it.

Thwarted again, Booth stormed about, cursing, pulling at his raven-black mustache, and striking his boots with his ridingwhip. He had had enough of this. He was not going to be frustrated any longer. If he couldn't capture Lincoln, by God, he could kill him.

A few weeks later Lee surrendered and ended the war, and Booth saw then that there was no longer any point in kidnapping the President; so he determined to shoot Lincoln at once.

Booth did not have to wait long. The following Friday he had a hair-cut, and then went to Ford's Theater to get his mail. There he learned that a box had been reserved for the President for that night's performance.

“What!” Booth exclaimed. “Is that old scoundrel going to be here to-night?”

Stage-hands were already making ready for a gala performance, draping the left-hand box with flags against a background of lace, decorating it with a picture of Washington, removing the partition, doubling the space, lining it with crimson paper and putting in an unusually large walnut rocking-chair to accommodate the President's long legs.

Booth bribed a stage-hand to place the chair in the precise position that he desired; he wanted it in the angle of the box nearest the audience, so that no one would see him enter. Through the inner door, immediately behind the rocker, he bored a small peep-hole; then dug a notch in the plastering behind the door leading from the dress-circle to the boxes, so that he could bar that entrance with a wooden plank. After that Booth went to his hotel and wrote a long letter to the editor of the “National Intelligencer,” justifying the plotted assassination in the name of patriotism, and declaring that posterity would honor him. He signed it and gave it to an actor, instructing him to have it published the next day.

Then he went to a livery-stable, hired a small bay mare that he boasted could run “like a cat,” and rounded up his assistants and put them on horses; gave Atzerodt a gun, and told him to shoot the Vice-President; and handed a pistol and knife to Powell, ordering him to murder Seward.

It was Good Friday, ordinarily one of the worst nights of the year for the theater, but the town was thronged with officers and enlisted men eager to see the Commander-in-Chief of the Army, and the city was still jubilant, celebrating the end of the war. Triumphal arches still spanned Pennsylvania Avenue, and the streets were gay with dancing torch-light processions, shouting with high elation to the President as he drove by that night to the theater. When he arrived at Ford's the house was packed to capacity and hundreds were being turned away.

The President's party entered during the middle of the first act, at precisely twenty minutes to nine. The players paused and bowed. The brilliantly attired audience roared its welcome. The orchestra crashed into “Hail to the Chief.” Lincoln bowed his acknowledgment, parted his coat-tails, and sat down in a walnut rocking-chair upholstered in red.

On Mrs. Lincoln's right sat her guests: Major Rathbone of the Provost-Marshal General's office and his fiancee, Miss Clara H. Harris, the daughter of Senator Ira Harris of New York, blue-bloods high enough in Washington society to meet the fastidious requirements of their Kentucky hostess.

Laura Keene was giving her final performance of the celebrated comedy “Our American Cousin.” It was a gay and joyous occasion; and sparkling laughter rippled back and forth across the audience.

Lincoln had taken a long drive in the afternoon, with his wife; she remarked afterward that he had been happier that day than she had seen him in years. Why shouldn't he be? Peace. Victory. Union. Freedom. He had talked to Mary that afternoon about what they would do when they left the White House at the close of his second term. First, they would take a long rest in either Europe or California; and when they returned, he might open a law office in Chicago, or drift back to Springfield and spend his remaining years riding over the prairie circuit that he loved so well. Some old friends that he had known in Illinois had called at the White House, that same afternoon, and he had been so elated telling jokes that Mrs. Lincoln could hardly get him to dinner.

The night before, he had had a strange dream. He had told the members of his Cabinet about it that morning: “I seemed to be in a singular and indescribable vessel,” he said, “that was moving with great rapidity toward a dark and indefinite shore. I have had this extraordinary dream before great events, before victories. I had it preceding Antietam, Stone River, Gettysburg, Vicksburg.”

He believed that this dream was a good omen, that it foretold good news, that something beautiful was going to happen.

At ten minutes past ten Booth, inflamed with whisky, and dressed in dark riding-breeches, boots, and spurs, entered the theater for the last time in his life—and noted the position of the President. With a black slouch hat in his hand, he mounted the stairs leading to the dress-circle, and edged his way down an aisle choked with chairs, until he came to the corridor leading to the boxes.

Halted by one of the President's guards, Booth handed him his personal card with confidence and bravado, saying that the President wished to see him; and, without waiting for permission, pushed in and closed the corridor door behind him, wedging it shut with a wooden upright from a music-stand.

Peeping through the gimlet-hole that he had bored in the door behind the President, he gaged the distance, and quietly swung the door open. Shoving the muzzle of his high-calibered derringer close to his victim's head, he pulled the trigger and quickly leaped to the stage below.

Lincoln's head fell forward and then sidewise as he slumped in his chair.

He uttered no sound whatever.

For an instant the audience thought that the pistol-shot and the leap to the stage were a part of the play. No one, not even the actors themselves, suspected that the President had been harmed.

Then a woman's shriek pierced the theater and all eyes turned to the draped box. Major Rathbone, blood gushing from one arm, shouted: “Stop that man! Stop him! He has killed the President!”

A moment of silence. A wisp of smoke floating out of the Presidential box. Then the suspense broke. Terror and mad excitement seized the audience. They burst through the seats, wrenching the chairs from the floor, broke over railings, and, trying to clamber upon the stage, tore one another down and trampled upon the old and feeble. Bones were broken in the crush, women screamed and fainted, and shrieks of agony mingled with fierce yells of “Hang him!”... “Shoot him!”... “Burn the theater!”

Some one shouted that the playhouse itself was to be bombed. The fury of the panic doubled and trebled. A company of frantic soldiers dashed into the theater at double-quick, and charged the audience with muskets and fixed bayonets, shouting: “Get out of here! Damn you, get out!”

Physicians from the audience examined the President's wound; and, knowing it to be fatal, refused to have the dying man jolted over the cobblestones back to the White House. So four soldiers lifted him up—two at his shoulders and two at his feet—and carried his long, sagging body out of the theater and into the street, where blood dripping from his wound reddened the pavement. Men knelt to stain their handkerchiefs with it—handkerchiefs which they would treasure a lifetime, and, dying, bequeath as priceless legacies to their children.

With flashing sabers and rearing horses, the cavalry cleared a space; and loving hands bore the stricken President across the street to a cheap lodging-house owned by a tailor, stretched his long frame diagonally across a sagging bed far too short for him, and pulled the bed over to a dismal gas-jet that flickered yellow light.

It was a hall room nine by seventeen feet in size, with a cheap reproduction of Rosa Bonheur's painting of “The Horse Fair” hanging above the bed.

The news of the tragedy swept over Washington like a tornado; and, racing in its wake, came the impact of another disaster: at the same hour of the attack on Lincoln, Secretary Seward had been stabbed in bed and was not expected to live. Out of these black facts, fearsome rumors shot through the night like chain-lightning: Vice-President Johnson had been slain. Stanton had been assassinated. Grant shot. So ran the wild tales.

People were sure now that Lee's surrender had been a ruse, that the Confederates had treacherously crept into Washington and were trying to wipe out the Government with one blow, that the Southern legions had sprung to arms again, that the war, bloodier than ever, was starting once more.

Mysterious messengers dashed through the residence districts, striking the pavement two short staccato raps, thrice repeated—the danger-call of a secret society, the Union League. Awakened by the summons, members grasped their rifles and rushed wildly into the street.

Mobs with torches and ropes boiled through the town, howling: “Burn the theater!”... “Hang the traitor!”... “Kill the rebels!”

It was one of the maddest nights this nation has ever known!

The telegraph flashed the news, setting the nation on fire. Southern sympathizers and copperheads were ridden on rails and tarred and feathered; the skulls of some were crushed with paving-stones. Photograph galleries in Baltimore were stormed and wrecked because they were believed to contain pictures of Booth; and a Maryland editor was shot because he had published some scurrilous abuse of Lincoln.

With the President dying; with Johnson, the Vice-President, sprawled on his bed stone-drunk and his hair matted with mud; with Seward, Secretary of State, stabbed to the verge of death, the reins of power were grasped immediately by Edward M. Stanton, the gruff, erratic, and tempestuous Secretary of War.

Believing that all high officers of the Government were marked for slaughter, Stanton, in wild excitement, dashed off order after order, writing them on the top of his silk hat as he sat by the bedside of his dying chief. He commanded guards to protect his house and the residences of his colleagues; he confiscated Ford's Theater and arrested every one connected with it; he declared Washington to be in a state of siege; he called out the entire military and police force of the District of Columbia, all the soldiers in the surrounding camps, barracks, and fortifications, the Secret Service men of the United States, the spies attached to the Bureau of Military Justice; he threw pickets around the entire city, fifty feet apart; he set a watch at every ferry, and ordered tugs, steamers, and gunboats to patrol the Potomac.

Stanton wired the chief of police in New York to rush him his best detectives, telegraphed orders to watch the Canadian border, and commanded the President of the Baltimore and Ohio Railway to intercept General Grant in Philadelphia and bring him back to Washington at once, running a pilot locomotive ahead of his train.

He poured a brigade of infantry into lower Maryland, and sent a thousand cavalrymen galloping after the assassin, saying over and over: “He will try to get South. Guard the Potomac from the city down.”

The bullet that Booth fired pierced Lincoln's head below the left ear, plowed diagonally through the brain, and lodged within half an inch of the right eye. A man of lesser vitality would have been cut down instantly; but for nine hours Lincoln lived, groaning heavily.

Mrs. Lincoln was kept in an adjoining room; but every hour she would insist on being brought to his bedside, weeping and shrieking, “O my God, have I given my husband to die?”

Once as she was caressing his face and pressing her wet cheek against his, he suddenly began groaning and breathing louder than ever. Screaming, the distraught wife sprang back and fell to the floor in a faint.

Stanton, hearing the commotion, rushed into the room, shouting, “Take that woman away, and don't let her in here again.”

Shortly after seven o'clock the groaning ceased and Lincoln's breathing became quiet. “A look of unspeakable peace,” wrote one of his secretaries who was there, “came over his worn features.”

Sometimes recognition and understanding flash back into the secret chambers of consciousness immediately before dissolution.

In those last peaceful moments broken fragments of happy memories may have floated brightly through the deep hidden caverns of his mind—vanished visions of the long ago: a log fire blazing at night in front of the open shed in the Buckhorn Valley of Indiana; the roar of the Sangamon plunging over the mill-dam at New Salem; Ann Rutledge singing at the spinning-wheel; Old Buck nickering for his corn; Orlando Kellogg telling the story of the stuttering justice; and the law office at Springfield with the ink-stain on the wall and garden seeds sprouting on top of the bookcase....

Throughout the long hours of the death-struggle Dr. Leale, an army surgeon, sat by the President's bedside holding his hand. At twenty-two minutes past seven the doctor folded Lincoln's pulseless arms, put half-dollars on his eyelids to hold them shut, and tied up his jaw with a pocket handkerchief. A clergyman offered a prayer. Cold rain pattered down on the roof. General Barnes drew a sheet over the face of the dead President; and Stanton, weeping and pulling down the windowshades to shut out the light of the dawn, uttered the only memorable sentence of that night: “Now he belongs to the ages.”

The next day little Tad asked a caller at the White House if his father was in heaven.

“I have no doubt of it,” came the reply.

“Then I am glad he has gone,” said Tad, “for he was never happy after he came here. This was not a good place for him.”

PART FOUR

29

The funeral train bearing Lincoln's body back to Illinois crawled through vast crowds of mourning people. The train itself was smothered in crepe; and the engine, like a hearse-horse, was covered with a huge black blanket trimmed with silver stars.

As it steamed northward faces began to appear beside the track—faces that rapidly multiplied in numbers and increased in sadness.

For miles before the train reached the Philadelphia station it ran between solid walls of humanity, and when it rolled into the city thousands of people were milling and jamming through the streets. Mourners stood in lines three miles long, stretching away from Independence Hall. They edged forward, inch by inch, for ten hours in order to look down at last upon Lincoln's face for but one second. On Saturday at midnight the doors were closed, but the mourners, refusing to be dispersed, kept their places all night long and by three o'clock Sunday morning the crowds were greater than ever and boys were selling their places in line for ten dollars.

Soldiers and mounted police fought to keep traffic lanes open, while hundreds of women fainted, and veterans who had fought at Gettysburg collapsed as they struggled to keep order.

For twenty-four hours before the funeral services were scheduled to take place in New York excursion trains running day and night poured into that city the greatest crowds it had ever known—crowds that filled the hotels and overflowed into private homes and backwashed across the parks and onto steamboat piers.

The next day sixteen white horses, ridden by Negroes, pulled the hearse up Broadway, while women, frantic with grief, tossed flowers in its path. Behind came the tramp, tramp, tramp of marching feet—a hundred and sixty thousand mourners with swaying banners bearing quotations like these: “Ah, the pity of it, Iago—the pity of it!”... “Be still, and know that I am God.”

Half a million spectators fought and trampled upon one another in an effort to view the long procession. Second-story windows facing Broadway were rented for forty dollars each, and window-panes were removed in order that the openings might accommodate as many heads as possible.

Choirs robed in white sang hymns on street corners, marching bands wailed their dirges, and at intervals of sixty seconds the roar of a hundred cannon reverberated over the town.

As the crowds sobbed by the bier in City Hall, New York, many spoke to the dead man, some tried to touch his face; and, while the guard was not looking, one woman bent over and kissed the corpse.

When the casket was closed in New York, at noon on Tuesday, thousands who had been unable to view the remains hurried to the trains and sped westward to other points where the funeral car was scheduled to stop. From now on until it reached Springfield the funeral train was seldom out of the sound of tolling bells and booming guns. By day it ran under arches of evergreens and flowers and past hillsides covered with children waving flags; by night its passing was illumined by countless torches and flaming bonfires stretching half-way across the continent.

The country was in a frenzy of excitement. No such funeral had ever before been witnessed, in all history. Weak minds here and there snapped under the strain. A young man in New York slashed his throat with a razor, crying, “I am going to join Abraham Lincoln.”

Forty-eight hours after the assassination a committee from Springfield had hurried to Washington, pleading with Mrs. Lincoln to have her husband buried in his home town. At first, she was sharply opposed to the suggestion. She had hardly a friend left in Springfield, and she knew it. True, she had three sisters living there, but she thoroughly disliked two of them and despised the third one, and she felt nothing but contempt for the rest of the gossiping little village.

“My God, Elizabeth!” she said to her colored dressmaker, “I can never go back to Springfield.”

So she planned to have Lincoln interred in Chicago or placed under the dome of the National Capitol, in the tomb originally constructed for George Washington.

However, after seven days of pleading, she consented to have the body taken back to Springfield. The town raised a public fund, bought a beautiful tract of land consisting of four city blocks—now occupied by the State Capitol—and set men digging day and night.

Finally, on the morning of May 4, the funeral train was in town, the tomb was ready, and thousands of Lincoln's old friends had forgathered for the services, when Mrs. Lincoln, in a sudden rage of erratic temper, countermanded all plans and haughtily decreed that the body must be interred, not where the tomb had been built, but in the Oak Ridge Cemetery, two miles out in the woods.

There were to be no ifs or ands or buts about it. If she did not have her way, she threatened to use “violent” means to carry the remains back to Washington. Why? For a very unlovely reason: the tomb that had been erected in the middle of Springfield stood on what was known as the “Mather block,” and Mrs. Lincoln despised the Mather family. Years before, one of the Mathers had, in some way, aroused her fiery wrath; and now, even in the hushed presence of death, she still cherished her bitter resentment, and would not consent to let Lincoln's body lie for one single night on ground that had been contaminated by the Mathers.

For a quarter of a century this woman had lived under the same roof with a husband who had had “malice toward none,” and “charity for all.” But like the Bourbon kings of France, she had learned nothing, she had forgotten nothing.

Springfield had to bow to the widow's mandate; and so at eleven o'clock the remains were taken out to a public vault in Oak Ridge Cemetery. Fighting Joe Hooker rode ahead of the hearse; and behind it was led Old Buck, covered with a red, white, and blue blanket on which were embroidered the words, “Old Abe's Horse.”

By the time Old Buck got back to his stable, there was not a shred of the blanket left; souvenir-hunters had stripped him bare. And, like buzzards, they swooped down upon the empty hearse, snatching at the draperies and fighting over it until soldiers charged them with bayonets.

For five weeks after the assassination Mrs. Lincoln lay weeping in the White House, refusing to leave her chamber night or day.

Elizabeth Keckley, who was at her bedside during all this time, wrote:

I shall never forget the scene. The wails of a broken heart, the unearthly shrieks, the terrible convulsions, the wild, tempestuous outbursts of grief from the soul. I bathed Mrs. Lincoln's head with cold water, and soothed the terrible tornado as best I could.

Tad's grief at his father's death was as great as the grief of his mother, but her terrible outbursts awed the boy into silence....

Often at night, when Tad would hear her sobbing, he would get up, and come to her bed in his white sleeping-clothes: “Don't cry, Mamma; I can't sleep if you cry! Papa was good, and he has gone to Heaven. He is happy there. He is with God and brother Willie. Don't cry, Mamma, or I will cry too.”

30

The instant that Booth fired at Lincoln, Major Rathbone, who was sitting in the box with the President, leaped up and grabbed the assassin. But he couldn't hold him, for Booth slashed at him desperately with a bowie-knife, cutting deep gashes in the major's arm. Tearing himself from Major Rathbone's grasp, Booth sprang over the railing of the box and leaped to the stage floor, twelve feet below. But, as he jumped, he caught his spur in the folds of the flag that draped the President's box, fell awkwardly, and broke the small bone in his left leg.

A spasm of pain shot through him. He did not wince or hesitate. He was acting now the supreme role of his career: this was the scene that was to make his name immortal.

Quickly recovering himself, he brandished his dagger, shouted the motto of Virginia, Sic semper tyrannis—“Thus ever to tyrants”—plunged across the stage, knifed a musician who accidentally got in his way, floored an actress, darted out at the back door, jumped upon his waiting horse, raised the butt of his revolver and knocked down the boy, “Peanut John,” who was holding the animal, and spurred madly down the street, the steel shoes from his little horse striking fire from the cobblestones in the night.

For two miles he raced on through the city, passing the Capitol grounds. As the moon rose above the tree-tops he galloped on to the Anacostia bridge. There Sergeant Cobb, the Union sentry, dashed out with rifle and bayonet, demanding:

“Who are you? And why are you out so late? Don't you know it is against the rules to let any one pass after nine o'clock?”

Booth, strange to relate, confessed his real name, saying that he lived in Charles County, and, being in town on business, he had waited for the moon to come up and light him home.

That sounded plausible enough; and, anyway, the war was over, so why make a fuss? Sergeant Cobb lowered his rifle and let the rider pass.

A few minutes later Davy Herold, one of Booth's confederates, hurried across the Anacostia bridge with a similar explanation, joined Booth at their rendezvous, and the two of them raced on through the shadows of lower Maryland, dreaming of the wild acclaim that was sure to be theirs in Dixie.

At midnight they halted in front of a friendly tavern in Surrattville; watered their panting horses; called for the field-glasses, guns, and ammunition that had been left there that afternoon by Mrs. Surratt; drank a dollar's worth of whisky; then, boasting that they had shot Lincoln, spurred on into the darkness.

Originally they had planned to ride from here straight for the Potomac, expecting to reach the river early the next morning and row across at once to Virginia. That sounded easy, and they might have done it and never have been captured at all, except for one thing. They could not foresee Booth's broken leg.

But, despite the pain, Booth galloped on that night with Spartan fortitude—galloped on, although the broken, jagged bone was, as he recorded in his diary, “tearing the flesh at every jump” of his horse. Finally when he could endure the punishment no longer, he and Herold swung their horses off to the left, and shortly before daybreak on Saturday morning reined up in front of the house of a country physician named Mudd—Dr. Samuel A. Mudd—who lived twenty miles southeast of Washington.

Booth was so weak and he was suffering so intensely that he couldn't dismount alone. He had to be lifted out of his saddle and carried groaning to an unstairs bedroom. There were no telegraph lines or railways in this isolated region; so none of the natives had yet learned of the assassination. Hence, the doctor suspected nothing. How had Booth come to break his leg? That was simple as Booth explained it—his horse had fallen on him. Dr. Mudd did for Booth what he would have done for any other suffering man; he cut away the boot from the left leg, set the fractured bone, tied it up with pasteboard splints made from a hat-box, fashioned a rude crutch for the cripple, and gave him a shoe to travel with.

Booth slept all that day at Dr. Mudd's house, but as twilight drew on he edged out of the bed painfully. Refusing to eat anything, he shaved off his handsome mustache, threw a long gray shawl around his shoulders so that the end of it would cover the telltale initials tattooed upon his right hand, disguised himself with a set of false whiskers, and paid the doctor twenty-five dollars in greenbacks. Then once more he and Herold mounted their horses and headed for the river of their hopes.

But directly across their path lay the great Zekiah Swamp, a huge bog matted with brush and dogwood, oozy with mud and slimy with stagnant pools—the home of lizards and snakes. In the darkness the two riders missed their way and for hours wandered about, lost.

Late in the night they were rescued by a negro, Oswald Swann. The pain in Booth's leg was so excruciating now that he couldn't sit astride his horse; so he gave Swarm seven dollars to haul him the rest of the night in his wagon, and as dawn was breaking on Easter Sunday the driver halted his white mules before “Rich Hill,” the home of a wealthy, well-known Confederate, Captain Cox.

Thus ended the first lap of Booth's futile race for life.

Booth told Captain Cox who he was and what he had done; and, to prove his identity, he showed his initials tattooed in India ink on his hand.

He implored Captain Cox, in the name of his mother, not to betray him, pleading that he was sick and crippled and suffering, and declaring that he had done what he thought was best for the South.

Booth was in such a condition now that he couldn't travel any farther, either on horseback or by wagon; so Captain Cox hid the two fugitives in a thicket of pines near his house. The place was more than a thicket, it was a veritable jungle densely undergrown with laurel and holly; and there, for the next six days and five nights, the fugitives waited for Booth's wounded leg to improve enough to permit them to continue their flight.

Captain Cox had a foster-brother, Thomas A. Jones. Jones was a slave-owner, and for years he had been an active agent of the Confederate Government, ferrying fugitives and contraband mail across the Potomac. Captain Cox urged Jones to look after Herold and Booth; so every morning he brought them food in a basket. Knowing that each wood-path was being searched and that spies were everywhere, he called his hogs as he carried the basket and pretended to be feeding his live stock.

Booth, hungry as he was for food, was hungrier still for information. He kept begging Jones to tell him the news, to let him know how the nation was applauding his act.

Jones brought him newspapers, and Booth devoured them eagerly, searching in vain, however, for the burst of acclaim he had coveted so passionately. He found in them only disillusion and heartbreak.

For more than thirty hours he had been racing toward Virginia, braving the tortures of the flesh. But, violent as they had been, they were easy to endure compared with the mental anguish that he suffered now. The fury of the North—that was nothing, he had expected that. But when the Virginia papers showed that the South — his South—had turned upon him, condemning and disowning him, he was frantic with disappointment and despair. He, who had dreamed of being honored as a second Brutus and glorified as a modern William Tell, now found himself denounced as a coward, a fool, a hireling, a cutthroat.

These attacks stung him like the sting of an adder. They were bitter as death.

But did he blame himself? No. Far from it. He blamed everybody else—everybody except himself and God. He had been merely an instrument in the hands of the Almighty. That was his defense. He had been divinely appointed to shoot Abraham Lincoln, and his only mistake had been in serving a people “too degenerate” to appreciate him. That was the phrase he set down in his diary—“too degenerate.”

“If the world knew my heart,” he wrote, “that one blow would have made me great, though I did not desire greatness.... I have too great a soul to die like a criminal.”

Lying there, shivering under a horse-blanket, on the damp ground near Zekiah Swamp, he poured out his aching heart in tragic bombast:

Wet, cold and starving, with every man's hand against me, I am here in despair, and why? For doing what Brutus was honored for—for what made Tell a hero. I have stricken down a greater tyrant than they ever knew, and I am looked upon as a common cut-throat; yet my action was purer than either of theirs.... I hoped for no gain.... I think I have done well, I do not repent the blow I struck.

As Booth lay there writing, three thousand detectives and ten thousand cavalrymen were scouring every nook and corner of southern Maryland, searching houses, exploring caves, ransacking buildings, and fine-tooth-combing even the slimy bogs of Zekiah Swamp, determined to hunt Booth down and bring him in, dead or alive, and claim the various rewards—approximating a hundred thousand dollars, offered for his capture. Sometimes he could hear the cavalry who were hunting him, galloping by on a public road only two hundred yards away.

At times he could hear their horses neighing and whinnying and calling to one another. Suppose his and Herold's horses should answer them. That would probably mean capture. So that night Herold led their horses down into Zekiah Swamp and shot them.

Two days later buzzards appeared! Specks in the sky at first, they winged closer and closer, finally wheeling and soaring and soaring and wheeling directly above the dead animals. Booth was frightened. The buzzards might attract the attention of the pursuers, who would almost certainly recognize the body of his bay mare.

Besides, he had decided that he must somehow get to another doctor.

So the next night, Friday, April 21—one week after the assassination—he was lifted from the ground and put astride a horse belonging to Thomas A. Jones, and once more he and Herold set out for the Potomac.

The night was ideal for their purposes: dense with a misty fog, and so dark that the men literally had to feel for one another in the inky blackness.

Jones, faithful dog that he was, piloted them from their hiding-place to the river, stealing through open fields, over a public highway, and across a farm. Realizing that soldiers and Secret Service men were swarming everywhere, Jones would steal ahead fifty yards at a time, stop, listen, and give a low whistle. Then Booth and Herold would advance to him.

In that way, slowly, startled by the slightest noise, they traveled for hours, reaching at last the steep and crooked path that led from the bluff down to the river. A stiff wind had been blowing that day; and, through the darkness, they could hear the mournful sound of the water pounding on the sand below.

For almost a week the Union soldiers had been riding up and down the Potomac, destroying every boat on the Maryland shore. But Jones had outwitted them: he had had his colored man, Henry Rowland, using the boat to fish for shad every day, and had had it hidden in Dent's meadow every night.

So when the fugitives reached the water's edge this evening everything was in readiness. Booth whispered his thanks to Jones, paid him seventeen dollars for his boat and a bottle of whisky, climbed in, and headed for a spot on the Virginia shore five miles away.

All through the foggy, ink-black night Herold pulled at the oars while Booth sat in the stern, trying to navigate with compass and candle.

But they hadn't gone far when they struck a flood-tide which is very strong at this point, owing to the narrowness of the channel. It swept them up the river for miles, and they lost their bearings in the fog. After dodging the Federal gunboats that were patrolling the Potomac, they found themselves, at dawn, ten miles up the river, but not one foot nearer to the Virginia shore than they had been the night before.

So they hid all that day in the swamps of Nanjemoy Cove; and the next night, wet and hungry, they pulled across the river; and Booth exclaimed: “I am safe at last, thank God, in glorious old Virginia.”

Hurrying to the home of Dr. Richard Stewart, who was an agent for the Confederate Government and the richest man in King George County, Virginia, Booth expected to be welcomed as the saviour of the South. But the doctor had already been arrested several times for aiding the Confederacy, and, now that the war was over, he wasn't going to risk his neck by helping the man who had killed Lincoln. He was too shrewd for that. So he wouldn't let Booth even enter his house. He did give the fugitives a little food, grudgingly, but he made them eat it in the barn, and then sent them to sleep that night with a family of negroes.

And even the negroes didn't want Booth. He had to frighten them into letting him stay with them.

And this in Virginia!

In Virginia, mind you, where he had confidently expected the very hills to reverberate with the lusty cheers that would greet the mere mention of his name.

The end was drawing near now. It came three days later. Booth had not gotten far. He had ferried across the Rappahannock at Port Royal, in the company of three Confederate cavalrymen returning from the war, had ridden one of their horses three miles farther South, and, with their help, had then palmed himseif off on a farmer, saying that his name was Boyd and that he had been wounded in Lee's army near Richmond.

And so for the next two days, Booth stayed at the Garrett farm-house, sunning himself on the lawn, suffering from his wound, consulting an old map, studying a route to the Rio Grande, and making notes of the road to Mexico.

The first evening he was there, while he sat at the supper table, Garrett's young daughter began babbling about the news of the assassination, which she had just heard through a neighbor. She talked on and on, wondering who had done it and how much the assassin had been paid for it.

“In my opinion,” Booth suddenly remarked, “he wasn't paid a cent, but did it for the sake of notoriety.”

The next afternoon, April 25, Booth and Herold were stretched out under the locust trees in the Garrett yard, when suddenly Major Ruggles, one of the Confederate cavalrymen who had helped them across the Rappahannock, dashed up and shouted: “The Yanks are crossing the river. Take care of yourself.”

They scurried away to the woods, but when darkness fell they stole back to the house.

To Garrett, that looked suspicious. He wanted to get rid of his mysterious “guests” at once. Was it because he suspected that they might have shot Lincoln? No, he never even thought of that. He imagined they were horse-thieves. When they said at the supper table that they wanted to buy two horses, his suspicions grew, and when bedtime came, and the fugitives, thinking of their safety, refused to go upstairs and insisted on sleeping under the porch or in the barn—then all doubt was removed.

Garrett was positive now that they were horse-thieves. So he put them in an old tobacco warehouse that was being used then for storing hay and furniture—put them in and locked them in with a padlock. And finally, as a double precaution, the old farmer sent his two sons, William and Henry, tiptoeing out in the darkness with blankets, to spend the night in an adjoining corn-crib, where they could watch and see that no horses were whisked away during the night.

The Garrett family went to bed, that memorable evening, half expecting a little excitement.

And they got it before morning.

For two days and nights, a troop of Union soldiers had been hot on the trail of Booth and Herold, picking up clue after clue, talking to an old negro who had seen them crossing the Potomac, and finding Rollins, the colored ferryman who had poled them across the Rappahannock in a scow. This ferryman told them that the Confederate soldier who had given Booth a lift on his horse as they rode away from the river was Captain Willie Jett, and that the captain had a sweetheart who lived in Bowling Green, twelve miles away. Perhaps he had gone there.

That sounded likely enough, so the troopers climbed quickly into their saddles and spurred on in the moonlight toward Bowling Green. Arriving there at midnight, they thundered into the house, found Captain Jett, jerked him out of his bed, thrust a revolver against his ribs, and demanded:

“Where is Booth? Damn your soul, where did you hide him? Tell us or we'll blow your heart out.”

Jett saddled his pony, and led the Northern men back to the Garrett farm.

The night was black, the moon having gone down, and there were no stars. For nine miles the dust rose in choking clouds under the galloping feet of the horses. Soldiers rode one on each side of Jett, with the reins of his horse tied to their saddles, so that he couldn't escape in the dark.

At half-past three in the morning the troopers arrived in front of the worn old whitewashed Garrett house.

Quickly, quietly, they surrounded the house and trained their guns on every door and window. Their leader banged on the porch with his pistol butt, demanding admittance.

Presently Richard Garrett, candle in hand, unbolted the door, while the dogs barked furiously, and the wind whipped the tail of his night-shirt against his trembling legs.

Quickly Lieutenant Baker grabbed him by the throat, thrusting a pistol to his head and demanding that he hand over Booth.

The old man, tongue-tied with terror, swore that the strangers were not in the house, that they had gone to the woods.

That was a lie, and it sounded like it; so the troopers jerked him out of the doorway, dangled a rope in his face, and threatened to string him up at once to a locust tree in the yard.

At that instant one of the Garrett boys who had been sleeping in the corn-crib ran up to the house and told the truth. With a rush the troopers encircled the tobacco barn.

There was a lot of talk before the shooting started. For fifteen or twenty minutes the Northern officers argued with Booth, urging him to surrender. He shouted back that he was a cripple, and asked them to “give a lame man a show,” offering to come out and fight the entire squad one by one, if they would withdraw a hundred yards.

Herold lost his courage and wanted to surrender. Booth was disgusted.

“You damned coward,” he shouted, “get out of here. I don't want you to stay.”

And out Herold went, his arms in front of him, ready to be handcuffed, while he pleaded for mercy, declaring from time to time that he liked Mr. Lincoln's jokes, and swearing that he had had no part in the asassination.

Colonel Conger tied him to a tree and threatened to gag him unless he ceased his silly whimpering.

But Booth would not surrender. He felt that he was acting for posterity. He shouted to his pursuers that the word “surrender” was not in his vocabulary, and he warned them to prepare a stretcher for him as they put “one more stain on the glorious old banner.”

Colonel Conger resolved to smoke him out, and ordered one of the Garrett boys to pile dry brush against the barn. Booth saw the boy doing it, and cursed him and threatened to put a bullet through him if he didn't stop. He did stop, but Colonel Conger slipped around to a corner of the barn in the rear, pulled a wisp of hay through a crack, and lighted it with a match.

The barn had originally been built for tobacco, with spacings four inches wide left to let in the air. Through these spacings the troopers saw Booth pick up a table to fight the mounting fire—an actor in the limelight for the last time, a tragedian playing the closing scene of his farewell performance.

Strict orders had been given to take Booth alive. The Government didn't want him shot. It wanted to have a big trial and then hang him.

And possibly he might have been taken alive had it not been for a half-cracked sergeant—“Boston” Corbett, a religious fanatic.

Every one had been warned repeatedly not to shoot without orders. Corbett afterward declared that he had had orders —orders direct from God Almighty.

Through the wide cracks of the burning barn, “Boston” saw Booth throw away his crutch, drop his carbine, raise his revolver, and spring for the door.

“Boston” was positive that he would shoot his way out and make a last, desperate dash for liberty, firing as he ran.

So, to prevent any futile bloodshed, Corbett stepped forward, rested his pistol across his arm, took aim through a crack, prayed for Booth's soul, and pulled the trigger.

At the crack of the pistol Booth shouted, leaped a foot in the air, plunged forward, and fell face down on the hay, mortally wounded.

The roaring flames were moving rapidly now across the dry hay. Lieutenant Baker, eager to get the dying wretch out of the place before he was roasted, rushed into the flaming building and leaped upon him, wrenching his revolver from his clenched fist and pinioning his arms to his side for fear that he might merely be feigning death.

Quickly Booth was carried to the porch of the farmhouse, and a soldier mounted a horse and spurred down the dusty road three miles to Port Royal for a physician.

Mrs. Garrett had a sister, Miss Halloway, who was boarding with her and teaching school. When Miss Halloway realized that the dying man there under the honeysuckle vine on the porch was the romantic actor and great lover, John Wilkes Booth, she said he must be cared for tenderly, and she had a mattress hauled out for him to lie upon; and then she brought out her own pillow, put it under his head, and, taking his head upon her lap, offered him wine. But his throat seemed paralyzed, and he couldn't swallow. Then she dipped her handkerchief in water and moistened his lips and tongue time after time, and massaged his temples and forehead.

The dying man struggled on for two and a half hours, suffering intensely; begging to be turned on his face, his side, his back; coughing and urging Colonel Conger to press his hands down hard upon his throat; and crying out in his agony: “Kill me! Kill me!”

Pleading to have a last message sent to his mother, he whispered haltingly:

“Tell her... I did... what I thought... was best... and that I died... for my country.”

As the end drew near, he asked to have his hands raised so he could look at them; but they were totally paralyzed, and he muttered:

“Useless! Useless!”

They were his last words.

He died just as the sun was rising above the tops of the venerable locust trees in the Garrett yard. His “jaw drew spasmodically and obliquely downward, his eyeballs rolled toward his feet and began to swell... and with a sort of gurgle, and sudden check, he stretched his feet and threw back his head.” It was the end.

It was seven o'clock. He had died within twenty-two minutes of the time of day Lincoln had died; and “Boston” Corbett's bullet had struck Booth in the back of the head, about an inch below the spot where he himself had wounded Lincoln.

The doctor cut off a curl of Booth's hair, and gave it to Miss Halloway. She kept the lock of hair and the bloody pillowslip on which his head had lain—kept them and cherished them until, finally, in later years, poverty overtook her and she was obliged to trade half of the stained pillow-slip for a barrel of flour.

31

Booth had hardly ceased breathing before the detectives were kneeling to search him. They found a pipe, a bowie-knife, two revolvers, a diary, a compass greasy with candle drippings, a draft on a Canadian bank for about three hundred dollars, a diamond pin, a nail file, and the photographs of five beautiful women who had adored him. Four were actresses: Effie Germon, Alice Grey, Helen Western, and “Pretty Fay Brown.” The fifth was a Washington society woman, whose name has been withheld out of respect for her descendants.

Then Colonel Doherty jerked a saddle-blanket off a horse, borrowed a needle from Mrs. Garrett, sewed the corpse up in the blanket, and gave an old Negro, Ned Freeman, two dollars to haul the body to the Potomac, where a ship was waiting.

On page 505 of his book entitled the “History of the United States Secret Service” Lieutenant La Fayette C. Baker tells the story of that trip to the river:

When the wagon started, Booth's wound, now scarcely dribbling, began to run anew. Blood fell through the crack of the wagon, and fell dripping upon the axle, and spotting the road with terrible wafers. It stained the planks and soaked the blankets... and all the way blood dribbled from the corpse in a slow, incessant, sanguine exudation.

In the midst of all this an unexpected thing happened. Ned Freeman's old wagon, according to Baker, was “a very shaky and absurd” contraption “which rattled like approaching dissolution.” It not only “rattled like approaching dissolution,” but under the strain and speed of the trip, the rickety old wagon actually began to dissolve there on the roadway. A king-bolt snapped, the wagon pulled apart, the front wheels tore away from the hind ones, the front end of the box fell to the ground with a thud, and Booth's body lurched “forward as if in a last effort to escape.”

Lieutenant Baker abandoned the rickety old death-car, commandeered another wagon from a neighboring farmer, pitched Booth's body into that, hurried on to the river, and stowed the corpse aboard a government tug, the John S. Ide, which chugged away with it to Washington.

At dawn the next morning the news spread through the city: Booth had been shot. His body was lying that very minute on the gunboat Montauk, riding at anchor in the Potomac.

The capital was thrilled, and thousands hurried down to the river, staring in grim fascination at the death-ship.

In the middle of the afternoon Colonel Baker, chief of the Secret Service, rushed to Stanton with the news that he had caught a group of civilians on board the Montauk, in direct violation of orders, and that one of them, a woman, had cut off a lock of Booth's hair.

Stanton was alarmed. “Every one of Booth's hairs,” he cried, “will be cherished as a relic by the rebels.”

He feared that they might become far more than mere relics. Stanton firmly believed that the assassination of Lincoln was part of a sinister plot conceived and directed by Jefferson Davis and the leaders of the Confederacy. And he feared that they might capture Booth's body and use it in a crusade to fire the Southern slaveholders to spring to their rifles once more and begin the war all over again.

He decreed that Booth must be buried with all possible haste, and buried secretly; he must be hidden away and blotted out of existence, with no trinket, no shred of his garments, no lock of his hair, nothing left for the Confederates to use in a crusade.

Stanton issued his orders; and that evening, as the sun sank behind a fiery bank of clouds, two men—Colonel Baker and his cousin, Lieutenant Baker—stepped into a skiff, pulled over to the Montauk, boarded her, and did three things in plain sight of the gaping throng on the shore:

First, they lowered Booth's body, now incased in a pine gun-box, over the side of the ship and down into the skiff; next, they lowered a huge ball and heavy chain; then they climbed in themselves, shoved off, and drifted downstream.

The curious crowd on the shore did precisely what the detectives had expected them to do: they raced along the bank, shoving, splashing, talking excitedly, determined to watch the funeral ship and see where the body was sunk.

For two miles they kept even with the drifting detectives. Then darkness crept up the river, clouds blotted out the moon and the stars, and even the sharpest eyes could no longer make out the tiny skiff in midstream.

By the time the detectives reached Geeseborough Point, one of the loneliest spots on the Potomac, Colonel Baker was sure that they were completely hidden from view; so he headed the skiff into the great swamp that begins there—a malodorous spot, rank with rushes and slough weeds, a burial-ground where the army cast its condemned horses and dead mules.

Here, in this eerie morass, the two detectives waited for hours, listening to find out if they had been followed; but the only sounds they could hear were the cry of bullfrogs and the ripple of the water among the sedges.

Midnight came; and, with breathless quiet and the utmost caution, the two men rowed stealthily back up-stream, fearing to whisper, and dreading even the lisping of the oars and the lapping of the water at the gunwales.

They finally reached the walls of the old penitentiary, rowed to a spot where a hole had been chopped in the solid masonry near the water's edge to let them in. Giving the countersign to the officer who challenged them, they handed over a white pine casket with the name “John Wilkes Booth” printed on the lid; and, half an hour later, it was buried in a shallow hole in the southwest corner of a large room in the government arsenal where ammunition was stored. The top of the grave was carefully smoothed over, so that it looked like the rest of the dirt floor.

By sunrise the next morning excited men with grapplinghooks were dragging the Potomac, and raking and prodding among the carcasses of dead mules in the great swamp behind Geeseborough Point.

All over the nation millions were asking what had been done with Booth's body. Only eight men knew the answer—eight loyal men who were sworn never to disclose the secret.

In the midst of all this mystery, wild rumors sprang into existence and newspapers broadcast them over the land. Booth's head and heart had been deposited in the Army Medical Museum at Washington—so said the “Boston Advertiser.” Other papers stated that the corpse had been buried at sea. Still others declared it had been burned; and a weekly magazine published an “eye-witness” sketch, showing it being sunk in the Potomac at midnight.

Out of the welter of contradiction and confusion another rumor arose: the soldiers had shot the wrong man, and Booth had escaped.

Probably this rumor arose because Booth dead looked so different from Booth alive. One of the men Stanton ordered to go aboard the gunboat Montauk on April 27, 1865, and identify the body, was Dr. John Frederick May, an eminent physician of Washington. Dr. May said that when the tarpaulin that covered the remains was removed—

to my great astonishment, there was revealed a body in whose lineaments there was to me no resemblance to the man I had known in life. My surprise was so great that I at once said to General Barnes: “There is no resemblance in that corpse to Booth, nor can I believe it to be that of him.”... It being afterwards, by my request, placed in a sitting position, standing and looking down upon it, I was finally enabled to imperfectly recognize the features of Booth. But never in a human being had a greater change taken place, from the man whom I had seen in the vigor of life and health, than in that of the haggard corpse which was before me, with its yellow and discolored skin, its unkempt and matted hair, and its whole facial expression sunken and sharpened by the exposure and starvation it had undergone.

Other men who saw the corpse did not recognize Booth even “imperfectly,” and they told their doubts about the city. And the rumor traveled fast.

Matters were not helped by the secrecy with which the Government guarded the body, the speed and mystery of its burial, and Stanton's refusal to give out any information or to deny ugly tales.

The “Constitutional Union,” a paper published in the capital, said the entire performance was a hoax. Other papers joined in the cry. “We know Booth escaped,” echoed the “Richmond Examiner.” The “Louisville Journal” openly contended that there had been something rotten in the whole show, and that “Baker and his associates had wilfully conspired to swindle the United States Treasury.”

The battle raged bitterly; and, as usual in such cases, witnesses sprang up by the hundreds, declaring that they had met Booth and talked to him long after the shooting affray at the Garrett barn. He had been seen here, there, and everywhere: fleeing to Canada, dashing into Mexico, traveling on ships bound for South America, hurrying to Europe, preaching in Virginia, hiding on an island in the Orient.

And so was born the most popular and persistent and mysterious myth in American history. It has lived and thrived for almost three quarters of a century; and, to this day, thousands of people believe it—many of them people of unusual intelligence.

There are even some learned men of the colleges who profess to believe the myth. One of the most prominent churchmen in this country has gone up and down the land, declaring in his lectures to hundreds of audiences that Booth escaped. The author, while writing this chapter, was solemnly informed by a scientifically trained man that Booth had gone free.

Of course, Booth was killed. There can be no doubt of it. The man who was shot in Garrett's tobacco barn used every argument he could think of to save his life; and he had a splendid imagination; but, in his most desperate moments, it never occurred to him to deny that he was John Wilkes Booth. That was too absurd, too fantastic, to try even in the face of death.

And to make doubly sure that it was Booth who had been killed, Stanton sent ten men to identify the corpse after it reached Washington. One, as we have already recorded, was Dr. May. He had cut “a large fibroid tumor” from Booth's neck, and the wound in healing had left “a large and ugly scar.” Dr. May, who identified him by that scar says:

From the body which was produced by the captors, nearly every vestige of resemblance of the living man had disappeared. But the mark made by the scalpel during life remained indelible in death, and settled beyond all question at the time, and all cavil in the future, the identity of the man who had assassinated the President.

Dr. Merrill, a dentist, identified the body by a filling he had recently put into one of Booth's teeth.

Charles Dawson, a clerk in the National Hotel, where Booth had stopped, identified the dead man by the initials “J. W. B.” tattooed on Booth's right hand.

Gardner, the well-known Washington photographer, identified him; and so did Henry Clay Ford, one of Booth's most intimate friends.

When Booth's body was dug up by order of President Andrew Johnson, on February 15, 1869, it was identified again by Booth's close friends.

Then it was taken to Baltimore to be reburied in the Booth family plot in Greenmount Cemetery; but before it was reburied, it was identified again by Booth's brother and mother, and friends who had known him all his life.

It is doubtful whether any other man who ever lived has been as carefully identified in death as Booth was.

And yet the false legend lives on. During the eighties, many people believed that the Rev. J. G. Armstrong of Richmond, Virginia, was Booth in disguise, for Armstrong had coal-black eyes, a lame leg, dramatic ways, and wore his raven hair long to hide a scar on the back of his neck—so people said.

And other “Booths” arose, no less than twenty of them.

In 1872 a “John Wilkes Booth” gave dramatic readings and sleight-of-hand performances before the students of the University of Tennessee; married a widow; tired of her; whispered that he was the real assassin; and, stating that he was going to New Orleans to get a fortune that awaited him, he disappeared, and “Mrs. Booth” never heard of him again.

In the late seventies a drunken saloon-keeper with the asthma, at Granbury, Texas, confessed to a young lawyer named Bates that he was Booth, showed an ugly scar on the back of his neck, and related in detail how Vice-President Johnson had persuaded him to kill Lincoln and promised him a pardon if he should ever be caught.

A quarter of a century passed; and, on January 13, 1903, a drunken house-painter and dope-fiend, David E. George, killed himself with strychnine in the Grand Avenue Hotel in Enid, Oklahoma. But before he destroyed himself, he “confessed” that he was John Wilkes Booth. He declared that after he shot Lincoln, his friends had hidden him in a trunk and got him aboard a ship bound for Europe, where he lived for ten years.

Bates, the lawyer, read about this in the papers, rushed to Oklahoma, looked at the body, and declared that David E. George was none other than the asthmatic saloon-keeper of Granbury, Texas, who had confessed to him twenty-five years before.

Bates had the undertaker comb the corpse's hair just as Booth had worn his; wept over the remains; had the body embalmed; took it back to his home in Memphis, Tennessee, and kept it in his stable for twenty years, while trying to palm it off on the Government and claim the huge reward that had been offered—and paid—for the capture of Booth.

In 1908 Bates wrote a preposterous book entitled: “The Escape and Suicide of John Wilkes Booth, or the First True Account of Lincoln's Assassination, Containing a Complete Confession by Booth, Many Years after His Crime.” He sold seventy thousand copies of his sensational paper-back volume; created a considerable stir; offered his mummified “Booth” to Henry Ford for one thousand dollars; and finally began exhibiting it in side-shows throughout the South, at ten cents a look.

Five different skulls are now being exhibited in carnivals and tents as the skull of Booth.

32

After she left the White House Mrs. Lincoln got into serious difficulties, and made an exhibition of herself that became national gossip.

In matters of household expense she was excessively penurious. It had long been customary for the Presidents to give a number of state dinners each season. But Mrs. Lincoln argued her husband into breaking the tradition, saying that these dinners were “very costly;” that these were war-times and public receptions would be more “economical.”

Lincoln had to remind her once that “we must think of something besides economy.”

When it came, however, to buying things that appealed to her vanity—such as dresses and jewelry—she not only forgot economy, but seemed bereft of all reason and indulged in a fantastic orgy of spending.

In 1861 she had come off the prairie, confidently expecting that as “Mrs. President” she would be the center of the glittering constellation of Washington society. But to her amazement and humiliation she found herself snubbed and ostracized by the haughty aristocrats of that Southern city. In their eyes, she, a Kentuckian, had been untrue to the South: she had married a crude, awkward “nigger-lover” who was making war upon them.

Besides, she had almost no likable personal qualities. She was, it must be admitted, a mean, common, envious, affected, mannerless virago.

Unable to attain social popularity herself, she was bitterly jealous of those who had achieved it. The then reigning queen of Washington society was the renowned beauty Adele Cutts Douglas, the woman who had married Mrs. Lincoln's former sweetheart, Stephen A. Douglas. The glamorous popularity of Mrs. Douglas and Salmon P. Chase's daughter, inflamed Mrs. Lincoln with envy, and she resolved to win social victories with money—money spent on clothes and jewelry for herself.

“To keep up appearances,” she told Elizabeth Keckley, “I must have money, more money than Mr. Lincoln can spare me. He is too honest to make a penny outside of his salary; consequently, I had, and still have, no alternative but to run in debt.”

In debt she plunged, to the extent of seventy thousand dollars! A staggering sum when we remember that Lincoln's salary as President was only twenty-five thousand, and that it would have taken every penny of his income for over two years and nine months to pay for her finery alone.

I have quoted several times from Elizabeth Keckley. She was an unusually intelligent negro woman who had bought her freedom and come to Washington to set up a dress-making shop. Within a short time she had the patronage of some of the capital's leading social figures.

From 1861 to 1865 she was with Mrs. Lincoln almost daily in the White House, making dresses and serving her as a personal maid. She finally became not only Mrs. Lincoln's confidante and adviser, but her most intimate friend. The night that Lincoln lay dying, the only person Mrs. Lincoln kept calling for was Elizabeth Keckley.

Fortunately for history, Mrs. Keckley wrote a book about her experiences. It has been out of print for half a century, but dilapidated copies can be purchased now and then from rare-book dealers for ten or twenty dollars. The title is rather long: “Behind the Scenes, by Elizabeth Keckley, Formerly a Slave, but More Recently Modiste and Friend to Mrs. Abraham Lincoln: Or Thirty Years a Slave and Four Years in the White House.”

Elizabeth Keckley records that in the summer of 1864, when Lincoln was running for a second term, “Mrs. Lincoln was almost crazy with fear and anxiety.”

Why? One of her New York creditors had threatened to sue her; and the possibility that Lincoln's political enemies might get wind of her debts and use them as political thunder in the bitter campaign, drove her almost to distraction.

“If he is reelected, I can keep him in ignorance of my affairs; but if he is defeated, then the bills will be sent in, and he will know all,” she sobbed hysterically.

“I could go down on my knees,” she cried to Lincoln “and plead for votes for you.”

“Mary,” he remonstrated, “I am afraid you will be punished for this overwhelming anxiety. If I am to be elected, it will be all right; if not, you must bear the disappointment.”

“And does Mr. Lincoln suspect how much you owe?” inquired Mrs. Keckley.

And here was Mrs. Lincoln's answer, as reported on page 150 of “Behind the Scenes:”

“God, no!—this was a favorite expression of hers [Mrs. Lincoln's]— and I would not have him suspect. If he knew that his wife was involved to the extent that she is, the knowledge would drive him mad.”

“The only happy feature of Lincoln's assassination,” says Mrs. Keckley, “was that he died in ignorance of these debts.”

He hadn't been in his grave a week before Mrs. Lincoln was trying to sell his shirts with his initials marked on them, offering them at a shop on Pennsylvania Avenue.

Seward, hearing about it, went, with a heavy heart, and bought up the lot himself.

When Mrs. Lincoln left the White House, she took with her a score of trunks and half a hundred packing-boxes.

That created a good deal of nasty talk.

She had already been repeatedly and publicly accused of swindling the United States Treasury by falsifying an expenseaccount for the entertainment of Prince Napoleon, and her enemies pointed out that though she had come to the Executive Mansion with only a few trunks, she was now leaving it with a whole car-load of stuff.... Why?... Was she looting the place? Had she stripped it bare of everything she could?

Even as late as October 6, 1867—almost two and a half years after she left Washington—the “Cleveland Herald,” speaking of Mrs. Lincoln, said:

“Let the country know that it required one hundred thousand dollars to make good the spoliation at the White House, and let it be proved who had the benefit of such plundering.”

True, a great many things were stolen from the White House during the reign of the “rosy empress,” but the fault was hardly hers. She made mistakes, of course: one of the first things she did was to discharge the steward and a number of the other employees, saying she was going to superintend the place herself, and put it on an economical basis.

She tried it, and the servants purloined almost everything except the door-knobs and the kitchen stove. The “Washington Star” for March 9, 1861, records that many of the guests who attended the first White House reception lost their overcoats and evening wraps. It wasn't long before even the White House furnishings were being carted away.

Fifty packing-boxes and a score of trunks! What was in them? Trash, for the most part: useless gifts, statuary, worthless pictures and books, wax wreaths, deer-heads, and a lot of old clothes and hats hopelessly outmoded—things she had worn back in Springfield years before.

“She had a passion,” says Mrs. Keckley, “for hoarding old things.”

While she was packing, her son Robert, recently graduated from Harvard, advised her to put a match to the old trumpery. When she scorned the idea, he said:

“I hope to heaven that the car that carries these boxes to Chicago catches fire and burns up all your old plunder.”

The morning Mrs. Lincoln drove away from the White House, “there was scarcely a friend to tell her good-by,” records Mrs. Keckley. “The silence was almost painful.”

Even Andrew Johnson, the new President, failed to bid her farewell. In fact, he never even wrote her a line of sympathy after the assassination. He knew that she despised him, and he reciprocated her feelings.

Absurd as it seems now in the light of history, Mrs. Lincoln firmly believed then that Andrew Johnson had been back of the plot to assassinate Lincoln.

With her two sons, Tad and Robert, Lincoln's widow traveled to Chicago, stopped for a week at the Tremont House, found it too expensive, and moved to some “small, plainly-furnished” rooms at a summer resort called Hyde Park.

Sobbing because she couldn't afford better living quarters, she refused to see or even correspond with any of her former friends or relatives, and settled down to teaching Tad to spell.

Tad had been his father's favorite. His real name was Thomas, but Lincoln had nicknamed him “Tad” or “Tadpole” because as a baby he had had an abnormally large head.

Tad usually slept with his father. The child would he around the office in the White House until he fell asleep, and then the President would shoulder him and carry him off to bed. Tad had always suffered from a slight impediment in his speech, and his father humored him; and, so with the ingenuity of a bright boy, he used his handicap as a foil to ward off attempts to educate him. He was now twelve years old, but he could neither read nor write.

Mrs. Keckley records that during his first spelling lesson, Tad spent ten minutes arguing that “a-p-e” spelled monkey. The word was illustrated with a small woodcut of what he believed to be a monkey, and it required the combined efforts of three people to convince him that he was wrong.

Mrs. Lincoln used every means in her power to persuade Congress to give her the hundred thousand dollars that Lincoln would have been paid had he lived out his second term. When Congress refused she was vitriolic in her denunciation of the “fiends” who had blocked her plans with “their infamous and villainous falsehoods.”

“The father of wickedness and lies,” she said, “will get these hoary-headed sinners when they pass away.”

Congress did finally give her twenty-two thousand—approximately the amount that would have been due Lincoln had he served the rest of that year. With this she bought and furnished a marble-front house in Chicago.

Two years elapsed, however, before Lincoln's estate was settled; and, during that time, her expenses mounted and her creditors howled. Presently she had to take in roomers; then boarders; and at last she was obliged to give up her home and move into a boarding-house, herself.

Her exchequer became more and more depleted, until, in September, 1867, she was, as she phrased it, “pressed in a most startling manner for means of subsistence.”

So she packed up a lot of her old clothes and laces and jewelry, and, with her face hidden under a heavy crepe veil, she rushed to New York incognita, registered as a “Mrs. Clark,” met Mrs. Keckley there, gathered up an armful of worn dresses, got into a carriage, drove over to the second-hand clothing dealers on Seventh Avenue, and tried to sell her wardrobe. But the prices offered were disappointingly low.

She next tried the firm of Brady & Keyes, diamond brokers, at 609 Broadway. Listening with amazement to her story, they said:

“Now listen, put your affairs in our hands, and we will raise a hundred thousand dollars for you in a few weeks.”

That sounded rosy; so she wrote, at their request, two or three letters, telling of her dire poverty.

Keyes flaunted these letters in the face of the Republican leaders, threatening to publish them unless he got cash.

But the only thing he got from these men was their opinion of Mrs. Lincoln.

Then she urged Brady & Keyes to mail a hundred and fifty thousand circulars, appealing to the generosity of people everywhere for aid; but it was well-nigh impossible to get prominent men to sign the letter.

Boiling now with wrath at the Republicans, she turned for help to Lincoln's enemies. The New York “World” was a Democratic paper that had once been suspended by government order, and its editor arrested because of its violent attacks on Lincoln. Through its columns Mrs. Lincoln pleaded poverty, admitting that she was trying to sell not only her old clothes, but even such trifles as “a parasol cover” and “two dress patterns.”

It was just before a state election; so the Democratic “World” printed a letter from her, fiercely denouncing such Republicans as Thurlow Weed, William H. Seward, and Henry J. Raymond of the “New York Times.”

With its tongue in its cheek, “The World” solemnly invited its Democratic readers to send in cash contributions to care for the abandoned and suffering widow of the first Republican President. There were few contributions.

Next she tried to get the colored people to raise money for her, urging Mrs. Keckley to throw her heart and soul into the undertaking, and promising that if the Negroes raised twenty-five thousand dollars Mrs. Keckley would get a “cut” of three hundred dollars a year during Mrs. Lincoln's life, and all of the twenty-five thousand dollars at Mrs. Lincoln's death.

Then Brady & Keyes advertised a sale of her clothes and jewelry. Crowds thronged to their store, handling the dresses, criticizing them, declaring that they were out of style, that they were absurdly high-priced, that they were “worn” and “jagged under the arms and at the bottom of the skirts,” and had “stains on the lining.”

Brady & Keyes also opened a subscription-book at their store, hoping that if the sightseers would not buy they might donate money for Mrs. Lincoln.

Finally in despair, the merchants took her clothes and jewels to Providence, Rhode Island, intending to set up an exhibition and charge twenty-five cents admission. The city authorities wouldn't hear of it.

Brady & Keyes did finally sell eight hundred and twenty-four dollars' worth of her effects, but they charged eight hundred and twenty dollars for their services and expenses.

Mrs. Lincoln's campaign to raise money for herself not only failed, it also brought upon her a storm of public condemnation. Throughout the campaign she made a disgraceful exhibition of herself—and so did the public.

She “has dishonored herself, her country and the memory of her late lamented husband,” cried the Albany “Journal.”

She was a liar and a thief—such was the accusation brought against her by Thurlow Weed in a letter to the “Commercial Advertiser.”

For years, back in Illinois, she had been “a terror to the village of Springfield,” her “eccentricities were common talk,” and “the patient Mr. Lincoln was a second Socrates within his own dwelling—” so thundered the “Hartford Evening Press.” But the “Journal” of Springfield stated editorially that for years it had been known that she was deranged, and that she should be pitied for all her strange acts.

“That dreadful woman, Mrs. Lincoln,” complained the Springfield, Massachusetts, “Republican,” “insists on thrusting her repugnant personality before the world to the great mortification of the nation.”

Mortified by these attacks, Mrs. Lincoln poured out her broken heart in a letter to Mrs. Keckley:

Robert came up last evening like a maniac and almost threatening his life, looking like death because the letters of “The World” were published in yesterday's paper.... I weep whilst I am writing. I pray for death this morning. Only my darling Taddie prevents my taking my life.

Estranged now from her sisters and kindred, she finally broke even with Robert, defying and maligning him so bitterly that certain passages of her letters had to be deleted before publication.

When Mrs. Lincoln was forty-nine years old, she wrote the Negro dressmaker: “I feel as if I had not a friend in the world save yourself.”

No other man in United States history has been so respected and loved as Abraham Lincoln; and possibly no other woman in United States history has been so fiercely denounced as his wife.

Less than a month after Mrs. Lincoln had tried to sell her old clothes, Lincoln's estate was settled. It amounted to $110,295, and was divided equally among Mrs. Lincoln and her two sons, each receiving $36,765.

Mrs. Lincoln now took Tad abroad and lived in solitude, reading French novels and avoiding all Americans.

Soon she was pleading poverty again. She petitioned the United States Senate to grant her a yearly pension of five thousand dollars. The bill was greeted in the Senate with hisses from the gallery and words of abuse from the floor.

“It is a sneaking fraud!” cried Senator Howell of Iowa.

“Mrs. Lincoln was not true to her husband!” shouted Senator Yates of Illinois. “She sympathized with the rebellion. She is not worthy of our charity.”

After months of delay and torrents of condemnation she was finally given three thousand a year.

In the summer of 1871 Tad died of typhoid fever, passing away in violent agony. Robert, her only remaining son, was married.

Alone, friendless, and in despair, Mary Lincoln became the prey of obsessions. One day in Jacksonville, Florida, she bought a cup of coffee and then refused to drink it, swearing it was poisoned.

Boarding a train for Chicago, she wired the family physician, imploring him to save Robert's life. But Robert was not ill. He met her at the station and spent a week with her at the Grand Pacific Hotel, hoping to quiet her.

Often in the middle of the night she would rush to his room, declaring that fiends were attempting to murder her, that Indians “were pulling wires out of her brain,” that “doctors were taking steel springs out of her head.”

In the daytime she visited the stores, making absurd purchases, paying, for example, three hundred dollars for lace curtains when she had no home in which to hang them.

With a heavy heart Robert Lincoln applied to the County Court of Chicago, for a trial of his mother's sanity. A jury of twelve men decided that she was insane, and she was confined in a private asylum at Batavia, Illinois.

At the end of thirteen months she was, unfortunately, released— released, but not cured. Then the poor, ailing woman went abroad to live among strangers, refusing to write Robert or let him know her address.

One day while living alone in Pau, France, she mounted a step-ladder to hang a picture above the fireplace; the ladder broke, and she fell, injuring her spinal cord. For a long time, she was unable even to walk.

Returning to her native land to die, she spent her last days at the home of her sister Mrs. Edwards, in Springfield, saying over and over: “You ought to pray now that I be taken to my husband and children.”

Although she then had six thousand dollars in cash and seventy-five thousand in government bonds, nevertheless her mind was constantly racked by absurd fears of poverty, and she was haunted by the fear that Robert, then Secretary of War, would be assassinated like his father.

Longing to escape from the harsh realities that pressed upon her, she shunned every one, closed her doors and windows, pulled down the shades, darkened her room, and lighted a candle even when the sun was shining bright.

“No urging,” says her physician, “would induce her to go out into the fresh air.”

And there, amidst the solitude and soft quiet of the candlelight, her memory doubtless winged its way back across the cruel years, and, dwelling at last among the cherished thoughts of her young womanhood, she imagined herself waltzing once more with Stephen A. Douglas, charmed by his gracious manner and listening to the rich music of his melodious vowels and clear-cut consonants.

At times she imagined that her other sweetheart, a young man named Lincoln—Abraham Lincoln—was coming to court her that night. True, he was only a poor, homely, struggling lawyer who slept in an attic above Speed's store, but she believed he might be President if she could stimulate him to try hard, and, eager to win his love, she longed to make herself beautiful for him. Although she had worn nothing but the deepest black for fifteen years, she would, at such times, slip down to the stores in Springfield; and, according to her physician, she purchased and piled up “large quantities of silks and dress goods in trunks and by the cart load, which she never used and which accumulated until it was really feared that the floor of the store room would give way.”

In 1882, on a peaceful summer evening, the poor, tired, tempestuous soul was given the release for which she had so often prayed. Following a paralytic stroke, she passed quietly away in her sister's house where, forty years before, Abraham Lincoln had put on her finger a ring bearing the words: “Love is eternal.”

33

In 1876, a gang of counterfeiters tried to steal Lincoln's body. It is an astonishing story, which few books on Lincoln say anything about.

“Big Jim” Kinealy's gang, one of the cleverest counterfeiting crews that ever vexed and perplexed the United States Secret Service, had its headquarters, during the seventies, in the guileless corn-and-hog town of Lincoln, Illinois.

For years Big Jim's suave and mild-mannered “shovers,” as they were called, had been sneaking out across the country and shoving bogus five-dollar bills across the counters of credulous merchants. The profits had been fantastic. But by the spring of 1876, a deadly paralysis was creeping over the gang, for their supply of counterfeit currency was almost exhausted, and Ben Boyd, the master engraver who made their bogus greenbacks, was in prison.

For months Big Jim sniffed vainly about St. Louis and Chicago, trying to get another engraver to make counterfeit bills. Finally he resolved that somehow the invaluable Ben Boyd must be set free.

Big Jim conceived the unholy idea of stealing the body of Abraham Lincoln, and hiding it away. Then, while the whole North was in an uproar, Big Jim would calmly drive a hard and fabulous bargain: he would agree to return the sacred corpse in exchange for Ben Boyd's pardon and a huge pile of gold.

Dangerous? Not at all. For Illinois had upon her statute-book no law against the purloining of bodies.

So in June, 1876, Big Jim set about clearing the decks for action. He despatched five of his conspirators to Springfield, where they opened a saloon and dance-hall, masquerading as bartenders while making their preparations.

Unfortunately for him, one of his “bartenders” drank too much whisky one Saturday night in June, drifted into a redlight house in Springfield, and talked too much. He boasted that he was soon going to have a barrelful of gold.

He whispered the details: on the eve of the next fourth of July, while Springfield was shooting off rockets, he would be out in the Oak Ridge Cemetery, “stealing old Lincoln's bones,” as he put it; and late that night he would bury them in a sandbar under a bridge spanning the Sangamon.

An hour later the parlor-house madam was hurrying to the police, to tell her thrilling news. By morning she had blabbed it to a dozen other men. Soon the whole town had the story, and the masquerading bartenders dropped their towels and fled the city.

But Big Jim was not defeated. He was only delayed. He shifted his headquarters from Springfield to 294 West Madison Street, Chicago. He owned a saloon there. In the front room his man, Terrence Mullen, dispensed liquor to working-men; and in the back he had a sort of club-room, a secret rendezvous for counterfeiters. A bust of Abraham Lincoln stood over the bar.

For months a thief named Lewis G. Swegles had been patronizing this saloon and working himself into the good graces of Big Jim's gang. He admitted that he had served two terms in the penitentiary for stealing horses, and boasted that he was now “the boss body-snatcher of Chicago.” He declared he supplied the medical schools of the town with most of their cadavers. That sounded plausible enough then, for grave-robbing was a national horror; medical colleges, in order to obtain bodies for dissection in their class rooms, were forced to buy them from ghouls who sneaked up to the rear door at two o'clock in the morning, with caps pulled low over their eyes and bulging sacks slung across their backs.

Swegles and Kinealy's gang perfected the details of their plan for rifling Lincoln's tomb. They would stuff the body into a long sack, pitch it into the bottom of a spring-wagon, and, with relays of fresh horses, would drive with all possible speed to northern Indiana; and there with only the water-fowl to see them, they would hide the body among the lonely dunes, where the wind from over the lake would soon wipe out all telltale tracks in the shifting sands.

Before leaving Chicago, Swegles bought a London newspaper; and, tearing out a piece, he stuffed the rest inside the bust of Lincoln that stood over the bar at 294 West Madison Street. That night, November 6, he and two of Big Jim's gang climbed aboard a Chicago & Alton train headed for Springfield, taking with them the fragment of torn newspaper, which they proposed to leave beside the empty sarcophagus as they dashed off with the body. The detectives finding the paper would naturally keep it as a clue. Then while the nation was rocking with excitement, one of the gang would approach the governor of the State and offer to return Lincoln's body for two hundred thousand dollars in gold and the freedom of Ben Boyd.

And how would the governor know that the self-styled spokesman was not an impostor? The gangster would carry with him the London newspaper; the detectives, fitting their fragment into the torn page, would accept him as the bona-fide representative of the ghouls.

The gang arrived in Springfield, according to schedule. They had chosen what Swegles called “a damned elegant time” for their adventure. November 7 was election day; for months the Democrats had been denouncing the Republicans for the graft and corruption that had besmirched Grant's second administration, while the Republicans had waved the “bloody shirt” of the Civil War in the face of the Democrats. It was one of the most bitter elections in United States history. That night, while excited crowds were milling about the newspaper offices and jamming the saloons, Big Jim's men hurried out to Oak Ridge Cemetery—dark now, and deserted—sawed the padlock off the iron door of Lincoln's tomb, stepped inside, pried the marble lid off the sarcophagus, and lifted the wooden casket half out.

One of the gang ordered Swegles to bring up the horses and spring-wagon which he had been delegated to have ready and waiting in a ravine two hundred yards northeast of the monument. Swegles hurried down the steep bluff until he was lost in the darkness.

Swegles was not a grave-robber. He was a reformed criminal now employed as a stool-pigeon by the Secret Service. He had no team and wagon waiting in the ravine; but he did have eight detectives waiting for him in the memorial room of the tomb. So he raced around there and gave them the signal they had all agreed upon: he struck a match, lighted a cigar, and whispered the password “Wash.”

The eight Secret Service men, in their stocking-feet, rushed out of their hiding-place, every man with a cocked revolver in each hand. They dashed around the monument with Swegles, stepped into the dark tomb, and ordered the ghouls to surrender.

There was no answer. Tyrrell, the district chief of the Secret Service, lighted a match. There lay the coffin, half out of the sarcophagus. But where were the thieves? The detectives searched the cemetery in all directions. The moon was coming up over the tree-tops. As Tyrrell rushed up onto the terrace of the monument, he could make out the forms of two men, staring at him from behind a group of statuary. In the excitement and confusion, he began firing at them with both pistols, and in an instant they were firing back. But they weren't the thieves. He was shooting at his own men.

In the meantime, the thieves, who had been waiting a hundred feet away in the darkness, for Swegles to return with the horses, dashed off through the woods.

Ten days later they were caught in Chicago, brought to Springfield, thrown into a jail, and surrounded by heavy guards day and night. For a time there was intense public excitement and indignation. Lincoln's son Robert, who had married into the wealthy Pullman family, employed the best lawyers in Chicago to prosecute the gang. They did what they could, but they had a hard time. There was no law in Illinois, then, against stealing a body. If the thieves had actually stolen the coffin, they might have been prosecuted for that, but they hadn't stolen it; they had not taken it out of the tomb. So the best the highpriced attorneys from Chicago could do was to prosecute the ghouls for having conspired to steal a coffin worth seventy-five dollars, the maximum penalty for which offense was five years. But the case did not come to trial for eight months; public indignation had died down by that time, and politics were at work; and, on the first ballot, four jurors actually voted for acquittal. After a few more ballots the twelve men compromised and sent the ghouls to the Joliet prison fox one year.

Since Lincoln's friends were afraid that other thieves might steal the body, the Lincoln Monument Association hid it away for two years in an iron coffin under a heap of loose boards lying in a damp, dark passageway behind the catacombs—a sort of cellar. During that time thousands of pilgrims paid their respects to an empty sarcophagus.

For various reasons Lincoln's remains have been moved seventeen times. But they will be moved no more. The coffin is now imbedded in a great ball of steel and solid concrete, six feet beneath the floor of the tomb. It was placed there on September 26, 1901.

On that day the casket was opened, and human eyes gazed down for the last time upon his face. Those who saw him then remarked how natural he appeared. He had been dead thirty-six years; but the embalmers had done their work well, and he still looked very much as he had looked in life. His face was a trifle darker, and there was a touch of mold on one wing of his black tie.

译序并毛姆小传

一八七四年，威廉·萨默塞特·毛姆出生于巴黎，父亲是英国驻法国使馆的律师，母亲是巴黎社交界的名人，据说是个美女，也写作，因此家里爱举办文学沙龙。小说家莫泊桑和版画家、插画家古斯塔夫·多雷都曾是他家的座上客。毛姆八岁时，母亲死于肺结核，从此毛姆终生都把母亲的照片放在床头以表怀念。肺结核是十九世纪的不治之症，二十世纪上半叶也还有无数人死于此病，如著名作家凯瑟琳·曼斯菲尔德和劳伦斯。毛姆也得过肺结核，因此“一战”期间到苏格兰疗养了两年，但他自言“非常享受他的疾病”，因为他爱那病中的孤寂和他病房大窗外的璀璨的星空。

一八八四年，毛姆的父亲死于癌症，十岁的毛姆成了孤儿，生活仅依赖一百五十镑的年金，因此只好回英国和没有孩子的叔叔婶婶同住。他叔叔是个教区牧师，在肯特郡海边怀特斯德布地区的万圣教堂任职，为人冷淡，被他抚养的日子并不好过。进坎特伯雷国王学校后，毛姆的日子仍不好过，在学校里颇受欺负，部分原因是那时他只会说法语。紧张和难过造成毛姆终生口吃，同时也使他养成了一个习惯：对那些惹他不高兴的人，他很会说伤害他们的话。十六岁时他终于拒绝再上国王学校，转而跑去德国的海德堡大学学了一年文学、哲学和德语。

他家是律师世家。毛姆祖父是英格兰与威尔士律师协会的创建人之一，父亲是律师，三个哥哥也都是著名律师，大哥后来更是做了英国上议院的大法官。可是毛姆不想当律师，他也不想当牧师，口吃本也无法布道。他还不想当公务员，当时他叔叔认为公务员已经不再是个绅士职业，于是他学了医。他进了伦敦南部贫民窟兰贝斯的圣托马斯医院的医学院，学了五年，这所学校如今成了伦敦国王学院的一部分。毛姆当住院医生时接生过六十三个孩子，但是拿到医生资格后却从未行过医，因为当时（一八九七年）他的处女作《兰贝斯的丽莎》出版了。小说基于他在贫民窟和医院的行医见闻，描写了工人阶级的痛苦、疾病，以及他们对爱情的绝望追求。《兰贝斯的丽莎》和左拉的《娜娜》、斯蒂芬·克莱恩的《街头女郎玛吉》以及乔治·吉辛的《新寒士街》一样用自然主义手法写成。书在几周内售罄，证明颇为成功，于是毛姆彻底放弃行医，全职写作。他自言“我写作如鸭入水”。有人说这段学医的经历于他的写作事业无益，毛姆却说：“我见过人如何死亡，如何忍受疼痛，我见过希望什么样，恐惧和放松又是什么样。”

接下来的十年间，毛姆游历了伦敦、巴黎、西班牙的塞维利亚和意大利南部的卡普里岛，旅行和写作成了他终生的模式。但他这一阶段的作品不再有《兰贝斯的丽莎》的成功，直到一九〇七年他的戏剧《弗里德里克夫人》上演。次年，毛姆更是有四部戏同时上演，以至于《笨拙》杂志都刊登了一幅漫画，画中莎士比亚一边咬指甲一边紧张地看着有毛姆戏剧的布告牌。今人只以为毛姆是名小说家，其实他的戏剧一样成功。

“一战”爆发时毛姆已是著名作家，早过了征兵年龄，因此他加入了红十字会“文学救护车司机队”，去法国服务。这支队伍由二十四位著名作家组成，包括美国作家多斯·帕索斯、海明威和诗人E．E．卡明斯。毛姆在敦刻尔克附近开救护车的间隙里校对了《人生的枷锁》的出版校样。此书被公认为毛姆的代表作，起初名叫“斯蒂芬·凯利的艺术气质”，也想过叫“灰烬中的美”，具自传色彩，主人公菲利普·凯利是个孤儿，一个足部畸形的医学生，由他虔诚的叔叔抚养长大。之所以写《人生的枷锁》，毛姆自言是因为从前那些记忆让他不安，记忆变成了折磨。为了祛魅，为了从那些令他难以忍受的执念中解脱出来，他写了两年，还不介意书越写越长。写完后他认为那些鬼魂都被他打倒了，那些人和事将不会再出现。没想到三十年后当他为一家唱片公司朗读此书将之录音时，却又一次忍不住崩溃痛哭起来，导致音也没录成。

一九一五年《人生的枷锁》出版，起初英美批评界都不看好，《纽约世界》说凯利的浪漫执着是“一个可怜傻瓜的感伤奴性”。美国作家、《嘉莉妹妹》的作者德莱塞挽救了它，说此书是天才之作，将它与贝多芬的交响乐作比，从此这书才长销不衰起来，并且再未断卖。《人生的枷锁》书名源于斯宾诺莎《伦理学》第四部分“关于人生的枷锁，或情感的力量”的小标题，对此斯宾诺莎有如此题解：“我管人类没有能力控制或约束情感叫作枷锁，受情感控制的人不是自己的主人。”

作家身份据说是情报工作的最好掩护，加之情报工作具有吸引毛姆的“浪漫感和滑稽感”，因此“一战”时毛姆被英国情报部门录用，一九一五年去了瑞士开展工作，旨在对抗德国。一九一七年六月，他又被军情六处派去俄国执行秘密任务，目的是想维持临时政府的统治。但是仅仅两个半月后，布尔什维克就掌了权。毛姆说他如果能早到六个月，他就很有可能成功。真如此，则十月革命不会有，世界上第一个社会主义国家不会有。一个小说家的话真实性有多大，姑妄听之。不过毛姆为人安静，敏于观察，有一种冷静判断的天赋，还有一种不被表象欺骗的能力（他认为这点继承自他的律师父亲），使他觉得自己适合做情报工作。这段经历后来被他写进了短篇小说集《英国间谍阿兴登》（一九二八年），文学史上因此第一次有了一个老练、淡漠的绅士型间谍。这个人物的刻画据说后来影响了伊安·弗莱明的零零七，弗莱明更是明言《量子危机》就是为了向毛姆的文风致敬。《英国间谍阿兴登》是个反浪漫的间谍故事，类似约翰·勒卡雷的《柏林谍影》，而非约翰·巴肯的《三十九级台阶》。

毛姆是个世界旅行者。一九一六年他去南太平洋的塔希提岛为小说《月亮与六便士》（一九一九年）搜集素材，写一个股票经纪人如何放弃欧洲、放弃家庭，追寻自然与艺术的事，事迹影射法国画家高更。一九二二年出版的《在中国屏风上》是一部短篇随笔集，写的是毛姆在中国的旅行见闻。《面纱》（一九二五年）描述了一个女人在爱情与婚姻中的自我成长，因书中写到在香港的英国人这一群体，毛姆至少改了两次，删去了一些人物，以免被当时仍住在香港的一些人误会写的是自己。《客厅里的绅士》（一九三〇年）写的是毛姆在缅甸、暹罗（泰国）、柬埔寨和越南的游历。以一个中国仆人命名的《阿金》（一九三三年）也是一本以毛姆二十世纪二十年代游历东南亚的见闻为素材写的短篇小说集。这些书中描写了殖民主义在印度、中国、东南亚和太平洋的最后时光。终于，倦游了的毛姆在一九二六年买下了位于法属里维埃拉的费拉角的摩尔别墅，这里成了他的家。除了“二战”那些年的漂泊，他在这里一直住到死。他广邀朋友来此，摩尔别墅因此成了二十世纪二三十年代欧美最大的文学沙龙之一。一九四〇年法国战败后毛姆离开里维埃拉，在美国度过了“二战”的大部分时间。他开始在好莱坞编剧本，他是最早从电影改编中挣了大钱的作家之一，仅短篇小说《雨》就拍了三次。

感情方面，毛姆应该是个双性恋者，因为他曾结婚生女，但又有两个长期的同性伴侣。第一个延续了三十年，直至对方去世；第二个维系了二十年，直至毛姆去世。毛姆在印度、中国、东南亚、太平洋的游历全都有第一位的陪伴，那人在伴侣之外，还是个能干的秘书。不过毛姆自觉爱情生活从来不顺，他承认：“我爱的人一般都不爱我，有人爱我时，我又觉得尴尬……为了不伤害这些人的感情，我经常表演我根本没有的激情。”

毛姆在世时，同性恋被广泛认为是道德缺陷和非法行为，加之一八九五年对王尔德的审判及其入狱造成的震动太大，毛姆终生未公开自己的性向。有评论家认为同性情结在毛姆身上产生了一种矛盾效果。一方面，不知是他的性向令自己难堪，还是他故意遮掩，总之他对同性恋艺术家从无好评。他说：“不可否认，同性恋的世界观较常人狭隘。人类在某些方面的自然反应他没有。至少人类的某些普通、典型的情感他永远无法体验。不管他如何微妙地看待生活，他都无法完整地看待生活……如今我禁不住要问我自己，我在格列柯的画作中看到的那种受折磨的幻想和邪恶的怪异感是否就是这样的性变态所致。”格列柯指的是十六世纪的那位西班牙画家。另一方面，毛姆常常赋予他的女性人物时代少见的性欲，《兰贝斯的丽莎》、《寻欢作乐》、《面纱》和《刀锋》里都有一个不计后果、决心要满足自己性欲的女主人公。

冷淡疏远大概是毛姆性格的最大特色，家人看不透他，五十年的友谊也不能使朋友明白他。有评论者认为这种冷淡疏远是毛姆精心营造的一个恶作剧，一重假面具，一层保护色。道德家和感伤者说他的作品中有太多不必要的残酷、暴力和复仇，说他对恶太宽容，太不加批判。毛姆自己也说，的确，别人的罪恶很少影响到他，除非妨碍到了他个人。曾为他作传的一个侄子说毛姆家族有种英国中上阶层的尊严感。终其一生，毛姆都不觉得作家是个体面职业，再加上他同性恋的隐秘身份，他跟侄子说他觉得自己“四分之三不正常，只有四分之一正常”。这种气质一定影响到了他作品的精神气质：在表面的见多识广和精于世故之下总是涌动着一股紧张和焦虑的暗流。

毛姆极其多产。他著有长篇小说二十部，短篇小说约一百篇，剧本约三十个，此外尚有多种游记、回忆录和文艺评论。他的书几乎全都大卖，《人生的枷锁》和《刀锋》被公认为他的代表作，生前就卖了四千万册。他的戏剧上演后也很成功，还有一长串的电影改编，再加上精明的股票投资，他无疑是作家中的富豪，二十世纪三十年代收入最高的英国作家，光是短篇小说《雨》就让他赚了百万美元。但在写作质量上，他却从未能从批评家和同代人那里赢得最高级别的尊重。毛姆认为这是因为自己“没有抒情素质，词汇量小，我想扩大我的词汇量，可是试过什么办法都没用。我没有暗喻的天赋，也很难弄出新颖的、令人震惊的明喻”。如此自知，作家中不多见。福克纳、托马斯·曼、乔伊斯和伍尔夫走红时，毛姆也曾一度尝试现代主义的写作手法，但他平淡朴实的文风却招致“连篇累牍的陈词滥调，最后不禁令人感叹作者说废话的能力和不会表达个性的无能”的批评。能这么勇于革新又敢于这么现眼，也是种可爱。

在文学价值上，《人生的枷锁》被认为无法和同时期乔伊斯的《一个青年艺术家的肖像》或劳伦斯的《儿子与情人》相比。毛姆自嘲他是那种“一招鲜，吃遍天”的人，晚年还说自己也就能“在二流作家里坐到最前排”。曾有批评家将他与萨克雷、纪德、哈代、康拉德、阿诺德·班尼特和高尔斯华绥并列，这实在不妥。又有人认为毛姆应该和班尼特、奥尔德斯·赫胥黎、格雷厄姆·格林并列，但这似乎也还是不妥。总之，无论怎样给作家排序都很难合了每个人的意。

美国作家、批评家埃德蒙·威尔逊说毛姆是个“半垃圾的小说家，写得很差，但是受到不怎么严肃的、基本不在乎写作的读者的追捧”。这话非常狠，也不公平，因为后世有很多很在乎写作的作家都给了毛姆很高的评价。张爱玲曾多次谈到她嗜读毛姆，对之念念不忘。公认非常严肃、非常有内涵的乔治·奥威尔说毛姆是对他影响最大的现代作家，他最欣赏毛姆直截了当、毫不做作的讲故事的能力。美国畅销书作家斯蒂芬·金也称赞毛姆讲故事的能力。英国作家安东尼·伯吉斯的小说《尘世权力》（一九八〇年）的主人公更是以毛姆作为原型。

不管同行和批评家的意见是褒是贬，毛姆在普通读者那里一直都很受欢迎。他不是个复杂难读的作家，行文没有冗长的感伤，用词简约，文风生动，充满讽刺。换句话说，他的作品可读性强，读者只要拿起他的作品就会放不下。即使读者觉得写得最不好的作品，比如《卡特琳娜》，也还是有人认为自有其趣。毛姆还有一个优点是，虽然他的不少小说故事都发生在外国，但他对异国情调把握得很好，并不显摆外国名字，也不像有些作家那样对异国风俗表现出一种炫耀式的熟悉。

现在该谈谈毛姆的文学评论了。西方学界普遍认为毛姆的文学批评不够好，太过“常识”，讲作家生平多于分析作品，好读但易忘。说的都对，可是生逢一个后理论时代，读多了那些披着理论外衣、充满难词术语的学院派著作，读者会禁不住怀疑这些评论其实根本就不关乎文学，也偏离了文学批评的初衷。在这种情况下再读写于二十世纪三十到五十年代的毛姆的文学批评，会发现他的坦荡率真，毫无包袱。毛姆最大的优点有两个，一是从“人”的角度体贴作者和人物，知道他们并非完人，只是会犯错的人类，于是不故意美化菲尔丁为不酗酒胡闹、不背叛妻子的道德先生，还能依据社会史还原奥斯汀的“不文雅”，指出她重道德完善和良好教养的个人原因，这是对目前早被庞大的文化工业“神化”了的奥斯汀的“祛魅”，于读者而言是个有益的提醒。他还反对传记作者和评论家对勃朗特家悲惨生活的一贯渲染，认为约克郡的气候和风景自有可爱之处，牧师的收入也没有少到不能维持体面生活的地步。二是毛姆能从作家的角度看作家，不强为作家圆谎，比如他不附和萨克雷认为菲尔丁在写作《汤姆·琼斯》之前就已经有了全局规划的观点，反而指出菲尔丁每章前的引言纯属蛇足，书中的几处情节也很多余。至于他对艾米莉·勃朗特是同性恋因而导致《呼啸山庄》独特构思的阐发，结合他自己隐秘的同性恋历史，大概很难定论其背后的真实态度。读者不妨姑妄读之听之。

毛姆的文学评论之所以好读，除他自身原因外，还因为最初发表时，这些评论都刊载在报刊之上，面向“普通读者”，没有高深的必要。《总结》（一九三八年）可算是毛姆的文学自传，写的是他从一八九〇年到一九三八年的生活，包括童年、初登剧坛时的成功，以及如何从写戏剧转向写小说。这是本充满隽语的小书。小薄书《书与你》（一九四〇年）是毛姆为《星期六晚邮报》所作的三篇文章的合集。《作家笔记》（一九四九年）记录了毛姆五十年间的观察与思考，展示了毛姆很多作品发生发展的过程。《随性而至》（一九五三年）是六篇文章的合集，其中既有对康德的探讨，也有对侦探小说的评论。《十本小说及其作者》（一九五四年）是毛姆为《红皮书》杂志所作文章的合集，是他对他心目中最伟大的十本小说及其作者的评论。此处不妨全体列举出来，以示毛姆在文学上的品位与判断：菲尔丁的《汤姆·琼斯》，奥斯汀的《傲慢与偏见》，司汤达的《红与黑》，巴尔扎克的《高老头》，狄更斯的《大卫·科波菲尔》，福楼拜的《包法利夫人》，麦尔维尔的《白鲸》，艾米莉·勃朗特的《呼啸山庄》，陀思妥耶夫斯基的《卡拉马佐夫兄弟》，以及托尔斯泰的《战争与和平》。（《十本小说及其作者》一书在美国有个版本叫《小说的艺术》，中译名多作《巨匠与杰作》。）《观点：五篇文章》（一九五九年），内容同毛姆之前的批评合集一样多样。

以上几乎涵盖了毛姆的所有文学批评。这些书全有中译本，有的还不止一个版本，不过各版本内容不尽相同，有时文字出入还很大。有的因译者有意节选，有的则因译文所本的原文本就不同。这也说明毛姆的文字虽然看似平实流畅，好像随笔写来，但其实大约每次出版前都会再增删修改一番。既然珠玉在前，本译本不再针对某本书进行翻译。又因为迄今为止还未有一部译著将毛姆谈英国文学的文字系统整理成书，因此本书从英国文学的角度选取篇目，不再关注美国文学和欧陆文学。虽然旨在补缺，但为完整计，本书有一编选原则，即片段不选，如讲散文的部分（散见于毛姆写十七世纪末坎特伯雷大主教蒂洛森的文章）不选；只讲作家不讲作品，或主讲作家少讲作品的也不选，如写阿诺德·班尼特、H．G．威尔斯和凯瑟琳·曼斯菲尔德的文章不选。

因此本书包括常见的《书与你》的第一篇，作为毛姆对英国文学的概论，也包括《十本小说及其作者》中的《汤姆·琼斯》、《傲慢与偏见》、《大卫·科波菲尔》和《呼啸山庄》四篇，还包括一篇国内迄今未有翻译但其实非常重要的“吉卜林与其短篇小说”，以及两篇迄今也未有翻译但也同样重要的毛姆为个人两卷本短篇小说全集所作的序。毛姆在这两篇序言中不仅谈了他的短篇小说创作，也谈了莫泊桑和契诃夫对他的影响。就这两大短篇小说流派在英语文学中的发展而言，一般认为凯瑟琳·曼斯菲尔德代表契诃夫一派，毛姆则代表莫泊桑一派。

关于后三篇，即谈吉卜林的一篇和两篇短篇小说的自序，均收录于一九六三年美国阿诺出版社出版的一个名为《毛姆序言与导言选集》的合集中。顾名思义，此书所选都是毛姆为自己文集或别人文集所作的序，其中颇有一些中国学界以前没太注意的毛姆的散佚文字。其中由毛姆自序的短篇小说全集是他众多短篇小说选集中的标定本，意义自不必说。吉卜林一篇是毛姆为《吉卜林散文选》（一九五二年）所作的序。所谓“散文”，在英文中的概念是指非“韵文”，即非诗歌的文体，并非中文理解的“散文”，在《吉卜林散文选》中实则指短篇小说。毛姆为此书编选了若干他认为重要的吉卜林短篇小说，在序中说明了编选原则，并对吉卜林的小说成就做出了评价。

在编排顺序上，《书与你》是对英国文学的概述，理当位列第一，五篇谈作家（菲尔丁、奥斯汀、狄更斯、艾米莉·勃朗特和吉卜林）作品的文章则按所涉作家的生年排列，最后两篇自序写于毛姆人生末年，语气也有盖棺论定之意，因此位列最后。

本书书名《聪明的消遣》来自毛姆自语，是他对小说功用的总结。通读此书的读者还会发现毛姆其他一些被不断提及的想法：人生在世，不如读书；不爱读文学无可指摘，谁也没有义务必须读文学，读文学也没有一定之法，但是要读就读那些“有益有趣”的作品。“益”“趣”并重的提法似乎有些矛盾，因为在“益”“趣”二者间，毛姆更倾向于“趣”。他直言作家不是教师，不是牧师，而是艺术家。可他所读之人和所介绍之书又都无出西方正典之外的，说明他的品位其实还是最正统、最正确的。如果说作为译者的我对毛姆的文学批评有任何失望之处，那就是除了希望他的批评能多些洞察外，还能多表露一些他真实的个人癖好和当代趣味。

李博婷

《书与你》第一篇

一个人说话时，经常不注意。我在一本名为《总结》的书里说，年轻人经常问我应该读什么书好。我当时没有考虑说这话的后果，可是此后我就收到了各色人等的大量来信，问我给了什么建议。虽然我对来信尽量作答，但这事无法在私信中说清，再加上似乎有很多人希望得到指导，那么我想我不如从自身经历出发，简要陈述一下我的建议，让读者能够读一些既有趣又有益的书。

我想强调的第一件事是，读书应是令人享受的。当然有很多书是我们不得不读的，或为通过考试，或为获取信息，但是读那类书无法获得快乐。读它们是为了获取知识，我们至多能期待的就是坚持把书读完，且不觉得厌倦，谁让我们有需求呢。在读那些书时，我们是抱着不得不读，而不是喜欢去读的心态，但这不是我想谈的那种读书。以下我将提到的书既无法帮你获得学位、赚钱谋生，也不能教你驾驶船只，或使熄火的马达重新转动起来，但它们能使你活得更充实。不过，如果你不喜欢读那些书，它们也无法使你充实。

我这里说的“你”是指成年人，是那些工作之余有一定闲暇并想读读书的人，而且，他想读的书是那类如果不读会让他觉得很可惜的书。我说的“你”不是“书虫”，“书虫”自可在书山中找到自己的一条路，他的好奇心会引他走上很多乏人问津的幽僻蹊径，自会在寻得几乎被人遗忘了的好书时收获乐趣。我想谈论的仅是那些“杰作”，那些长久以来被人们一致认为至高无上的作品。那些杰出的作品我们本应都读过，但可惜，其实只有少数人读过。有些杰作得到过最好的评论家们的一致认可，文学史家也曾花过相当篇幅对之进行讨论，但如今普通人已经无法读之乐之了。这类作品对研究者而言很重要，但是时代在变化，人们的品味在变化，书中滋味早已被剥夺殆尽，如今再读它们不靠意志力则难以卒读了。且让我略举一例。我曾读过乔治·艾略特的《亚当·比德》，但我无法以手扪心，说我读时愉快。我本就出于责任感而读，读完时我长出了一口气，庆幸自己终于读完了。

对于这类书，我不想置词。每个人都是最好的评论家。不管学者们如何评价一本书，哪怕他们对它一致称颂，但只要你对这本书不感兴趣，那它也与你无关。不要忘了批评家们也经常犯错，评论史也充满了最知名的评论家们所犯的错，读书的你才是你所读之书价值的最终评判者。这一点自然也适用于我将要给你推荐的书。我们人人不同，只是大略相像，因此不必假设对我有意义的书对你也会如此。不过，我读完这些书后感到充实，假如我没读过它们，我就不会是现在的我了。如果你们中有人因为听了我的话，而去读我推荐的书，却又无法卒读，那么我恳请你们，就放下它吧。一本书，你要是不喜欢读，就不会对你有任何用处。没有人有义务去读诗、读小说，或读我们归类为“美文”(1)（我希望我知道这个词的英文，但我不认为有这么一个英文词）的那类作品。人只需为了乐趣读书。谁能肯定地说，能给一个人带来乐趣的，也必能让另一个人觉得有趣？

但是切勿以为享受乐趣是不道德的。乐趣本是一大善，所有乐趣都如此，只是它会造成不同的后果，理智者会刻意避开某些乐事。乐趣也无须粗俗或肉欲。那些懂得“智识之乐”最令人满足和最长久之人是一代人中的智者。人生在世，不如养成读书的习惯，那会让你受益匪浅。盛年之后，只有不多的几项消遣能令你满意。游戏中只有单人纸牌、解象棋残局和填字游戏是你无须对手就可以独自玩耍的。读书却无此不便，它是唯一一桩可以随时拿起，想做多久就做多久，有其他事来时又可以随时放下的事情。除此之外，大概只有针黹之事有同样功效，不过做针线会使焦躁不安的情绪越发焦躁。在如今有了公共图书馆和廉价版图书的幸福日子里，没有其他娱乐能像读书这样可以如此低价地获得。养成读书习惯等于给自己构筑了一个避难所，可以让你逃离人世间几乎所有的苦难。我说“几乎所有”，是因为我不假装读书能缓解饥饿的折磨，或减轻单相思的痛苦。但是，几本令人入迷的侦探小说和一个热水瓶足可以使任何人忽略最严重的伤风。相反，如果一个人被迫去读那些令他厌烦的书，他还怎么能养成为阅读而阅读的习惯呢？

为方便起见，以下我将按时间顺序谈一下我要谈的书，可是如果你决定要读这些书的话，我却觉得你没有必要按此顺序去读。更好的建议是你爱怎么读就怎么读，我甚至觉得你没必要一本接一本地读。就我个人而言，同时读四五本书才更惬意。毕竟，你每天心境不同，即使是一天内，你也不是总抱着一样的急切感去读一本书。在这些事上随意即可，我当然选择最适合我的方案。于是上午开始工作前，我会先读一会儿科学或哲学书，因为读此类书要求头脑清醒、注意力集中。这样开始有助于我一天的工作。接下来工作做完，我感觉放松，却又不想做劳心费力之事时，我会读点历史、散文、评论或自传，晚上则读小说。除此之外，我手边还总有一卷诗，以便有心情之时展卷。我的床头也总放着一本那种难得一遇的书，哦，就是那种可以随意翻开一处，任意读上一段又可以平静放下的书。

言归正传。我书单上的第一本书是笛福的《摩尔·弗兰德斯》。迄今为止，还没有一个英国作家比笛福写得更逼真。当你读他这本书的时候，你很难想起来自己是在读小说，你更像是在读一份写得精湛至极的报告。你确信他书中人物说的话是他们本来就会说的话，他们做的事也合情合理，你毫不怀疑他们在那种情况下一定会如此表现。《摩尔·弗兰德斯》不是一本符合道德准则的书。其内容驳杂、粗俗、野蛮，但我认为它有一种英国人性格里固有的活力。笛福几乎没有想象力，也不够幽默，但他有着宽广丰富的生活经历。他还是个优秀的记者，他对稀奇事和生动的细节有着敏锐的观察力。笛福没有高潮观念，也不试图构建什么模式，因此读者不会被自己不想抵抗的力量裹挟席卷，他会随波逐流一直向前走，可能当他来到一条小巷时，他就会溜进去走掉了。说得更清楚一点就是，写得一样的东西读完两三百页后，读者会厌倦。这其实没什么不好。就我个人而言，我倒是很愿意陪着作者一路前行，直到他最后给他那下流粗鄙的女主人公找到一个体面的、悔悟后的避难所。

之后，我希望诸君读读斯威夫特的《格列佛游记》。我待会儿再讲约翰逊博士，但此处不妨先引用他对此书的评价：“你只要能想得出大人国和小人国来，其他就都好办了。”约翰逊博士是个极好的批评家，极富智慧，但他这话却是胡说。《格列佛游记》里有机智和反讽，独特的构思，出色的幽默，以及辛辣的讽刺和活力。它的风格很妙。没人能比斯威夫特更会紧凑、清晰、自然地驾驭我们国家的这门笨拙的语言了。我希望约翰逊博士评价斯威夫特能像他评价另一个人一样：“不管是谁，只要想获得一种亲切但不粗俗、文雅但不炫耀的英文写作风格，须得日夜研读艾迪生(2)的作品。”他还可以再加上一组形容词：刚健但不自负。

接下来是两本小说。菲尔丁的《汤姆·琼斯》，这本小说大概是英国文学里最健康的一本小说了。此书豪爽、勇敢、欢快，当然也很直率。英俊、活泼、人很友好的汤姆·琼斯是我们大家都想结识的人，但他做的某些事却遭到了卫道士的谴责。但是我们在乎吗？当然不！除非我们是一本正经的道学家。因为我们只知道汤姆·琼斯公正无私，他的心是金子做的。菲尔丁和笛福不同，他是个自觉的艺术家。他对小说的规划让他可以描述很多事，创造很多人物。这些人和事在一个因现实的喧哗与骚动而辛辣尖锐的世界里显得那么壮观和真实。菲尔丁很拿自己当回事——当然每个作家都理应如此——在很多重要问题上他都禁不住要发表看法。《汤姆·琼斯》的每部分开头处他都要写个小评论文，讨论点这事那事。这些评论文有其幽默真诚的一面，但我个人认为跳过不读也不会造成损失。我有个想法，觉得没有人读《汤姆·琼斯》会不感到愉悦，因为它充满男子气概，它阳光健康，毫无虚伪矫饰，能温暖你的心灵。

斯特恩的《项狄传》性质则完全不同。约翰逊博士对《查尔斯·格兰迪森爵士》(3)的看法可以照搬给它：“如果你读它是为了故事情节，那还不如上吊。”读这本书要看你的性情，它可以非常通俗易懂，也可以非常无聊和做作。它不统一，不连贯，不断跑题，但它新颖、有趣、哀婉。它会增加你的精神财富，因为书中有五六个人物极有个性，非常可爱；你一旦认识了他们，就会觉得要是不认识他们，损失将会不可弥补。我也不希望你错过斯特恩的《多情之旅》，除了迷人之外我对它没有别的评价。

现在让我们暂别小说，说说别的。我猜世人公认鲍斯威尔的《塞缪尔·约翰逊传》是英语写成的最伟大的传记。你在任何年纪读此书都会觉得既有益又有趣。任何时候你拿起此书，随意翻到哪一页读起，都能得到娱乐。不过时至今日还要夸赞这样一本已经很著名的书不免可笑，因为实在没有必要。不如让我加上一本不太著名的书，我认为此书不为人所知是不公平的。这就是鲍斯威尔的《赫布里底群岛(4)纪行》。我猜大家都知道，鲍斯威尔的手稿本来是马隆编辑的，而马隆为了迎合时代拘谨的文雅品味，删去了很多令此书有趣的东西。而伊沙姆上校在购买了鲍斯威尔的手稿后，出了一个未删节的新版本，这一版本会让你对约翰逊和鲍斯威尔的了解更加深入。如果说《赫布里底群岛纪行》增添了你对那个刚毅的老博士的爱和崇拜，它也一样会增添你对他那个曾受到大肆谩骂攻击的可怜传记作者的尊敬。可是这样一个作者岂容蔑视？他能敏锐地发现有趣的事物，他能欣赏生动的词句，他还有种罕见的天赋：能重现一个场景的气氛，还原一段生动的对话。

约翰逊博士是影响了十八世纪整个英国的人物。他被认为最能代表英国的国民性，既具有那些纯粹的优点，也具有那些不讨喜的缺点。如果说我们都读过鲍斯威尔为他作的传，可能对他的了解会比对很多与我们共度一生的人了解都多，却很少有人读过约翰逊博士自己写的文章。还好，至少他写过一本令人得到至高享受的作品。在我看来，再没有一本书比约翰逊的《诗人传》更适合带去旅行或放在床头了。此书写得流畅、辛辣、幽默，充满常识。虽说有时他的一些看法会令我们吃惊，比如他认为格雷(5)沉闷，对弥尔顿的《利西达斯》也没有好话说，但你仍会乐见其说，因为这些观点是他个性的表达。他对他笔下的诗人和诗作同样感兴趣。那些诗哪怕你一个字都没读过，你一样会被他对诗人敏锐、生动、宽容的描述所娱乐。

接下来的这本书令我有些犹豫。因为我必须提醒读者，我原计划要谈的都是我认为不读会令人遗憾的书。而吉本的这本《自传》我虽喜欢，却不太肯定不读它会对我造成多大影响。如果我没读过这本书一定会失去一份强烈的乐趣，但是如果我在这里提它，我觉得我也必须提别的好多书——那些如果按照另一个标准来衡量，也非常值得一读但算不上经典的书，这些书将需要单独的一章来介绍。无论如何，吉本的《自传》可读性强，篇幅短，既庄重又幽默，行文有一种他所擅长的特殊优雅。我禁不住要举一例说明他的幽默。吉本在洛桑时恋爱了，但他父亲威胁要剥夺他的继承权，他只得谨慎地放弃了娶意中人为妻的想法。他对此事的吟诵是这样结束的：“作为恋人，我叹息；作为儿子，我服从；我的创伤，被时间、分离以及一套新的生活习惯无情地愈合了。”此书哪怕没有别的内容，仅凭这句妙语也值得一读了。

现在我想放弃迄今为止都在大致遵循的时间顺序，谈谈两本伟大的小说：《大卫·科波菲尔》和巴特勒的《众生之道》。我这么做，不仅因为它们在英国长篇小说的伟大传统中占有重要的地位，同时也因为它们具备了英国文学的典型特征，我在上文简要提到的那些作品也都有这些特征。可能除《项狄传》外，所有这些书都有共同之处，如旺盛的活力、坦率、幽默和健康，而我愿意认为这些特征代表了我们的民族性。这些书并无特别微妙之处，也都少了点精致，但这是属于行动者而非思考者的文学，其中有很多常识、一些感伤，以及大量的人性。关于《大卫·科波菲尔》，除了说这是狄更斯最好的小说，还能说什么呢？狄更斯的缺点在这本书里最不明显，优点却最明显。《众生之道》后，又有很多长篇小说问世，我却认为《众生之道》是最后一部用伟大的方式写出的英国小说，是最后一部不受法、俄伟大小说家们影响的重要小说。它是《汤姆·琼斯》的正统继承者，它的作者有一种那个老字典编纂人(6)的气质，而后者，被公认是个典型的英国人。

那么，让我再回过头来谈谈简·奥斯汀。我不会说她是英国最伟大的小说家，狄更斯才是，尽管狄更斯有无数毛病，比如喜欢夸张、粗俗、啰唆，还善感。但他是个有惊人天赋的小说家，他用不同的视角描述我们所知的世界；他创造了一个世界。他把悬念、戏剧性和幽默感运用到他的作品中，如此才让人感受到生活中的百态与忙乱喧闹。据我所知，另外只有一位小说家也做到了这点，那就是托尔斯泰。狄更斯以他无穷的活力塑造出了一系列的人物，他们各式各样，各具个性，每一个都随着生活而颤抖——不，“颤抖”这个词不对，是“动荡”。狄更斯以一种惊人的技巧掌控着他那些复杂的、经常还很不靠谱的故事情节，他竟然还处理得很好；或许只有身为小说家才能彻底理解他的技巧是多么高超。但是奥斯汀代表完美。她的写作范围确实狭小，因为她接触到的是一个由乡绅、牧师和中产阶级构成的小世界。但是，在对人物的洞察上，谁能与她匹敌？在对人物内心的精准与合理的探索上，谁又能超越她？她不需要我的赞美。我唯一想提醒你注意的是她的一个特点，一个她非常自然地在文中运用，以至于你都已经不以为奇的特点。那就是：整体而言，她的小说里一般不发生什么特别重大的社会事件，她也基本避免戏剧性事件的出现，但你仍然会被引诱着读了一页又一页，迫切想知道下边发生了什么（我真不知道她是怎么做到的）。这正是一个小说家最核心的才能。没这个本事，小说家就完了。我想不出还有谁比奥斯汀在这种才能上更圆满。现在，我唯一的难题是要决定在她不多的几本小说里到底推荐哪一本。就我个人而言，我最喜欢《曼斯菲尔德庄园》。我承认它的女主人公是个小假正经，男主人公又是个浮夸的笨蛋，但是我不在乎。因为《曼斯菲尔德庄园》写得机智、诙谐、感人，是一部集反讽的幽默与微妙的观察于一身的杰作。

行文至此，我想请大家注意一下黑兹利特。他的名气被查尔斯·兰姆掩盖了，但在我心目中他才是更好的散文家。兰姆迷人、温柔、机智，认识他就会爱上他，他也一直都能获得读者的欢心。黑兹利特不行，他为人粗鲁笨拙，好嫉妒，好争吵。说实话，他的性格不讨人喜欢。但是不幸的是，能写出最好的书的人并不总是最好的人，关键还是要看艺术家的性格。就我个人而言，我发现使我更感兴趣的是黑兹利特那痛苦、反叛而尖刻的灵魂，而不是兰姆隐忍却易感伤的和善。作为作家，黑兹利特有力、大胆、健康，他想说的话都说得很坚决。他的文章都是“肉”，读完一篇你会觉得像是吃了充实的一餐，满足了胃口。而读兰姆，你只会觉得这顿饭味道不错，做得讲究。黑兹利特最好的作品大都收录在《席间闲谈》中，他的散文也曾几次结集出版，每本选集无一例外都会包括《我与诗人的初相识》。在我看来，此文不仅是他写过的最令人激动的文章，也是英语散文中最好的一篇。

现在要再介绍两本小说：萨克雷的《名利场》和艾米莉·勃朗特的《呼啸山庄》。篇幅不够，我不能说太多了。如今的批评家很爱挑剔萨克雷。他可能是那个时代的不幸者，他应该活在我们这个时代，写在我们这个时代，这样他就可以不受传统的制约，正是那种制约使得维多利亚时代的小说家不敢说出真相，不管这真相在他看来是多么苦涩。萨克雷的视角是现代的，他对人类的平庸深有觉悟，他对人性中的矛盾感兴趣。不管你如何不喜欢他的感伤和说教，如何遗憾他一味向公众的要求妥协时的软弱，有一个事实是无法改变的，那就是他创造的贝姬·夏普是英国小说里最真实、生动、有力的人物之一。

《呼啸山庄》非常独特。这本小说读起来别扭，有时太过出格离奇，会把你完全搞蒙。但它又无比热情激昂，非常动人，具有如同伟大诗篇一般的深度和力度。读《呼啸山庄》不像是在读小说，因为当你读小说时，哪怕再投入，必要时也总能提醒自己这只不过是个编出来的故事；而当你读《呼啸山庄》时，你却好似亲身经历了一场在你的生命中足以摧毁一切的不幸。

篇幅所限，我只能再提三本不读会遗憾的小说。它们是乔治·艾略特的《米德尔马契》、特罗洛普的《尤斯蒂斯钻石》和梅瑞狄斯的《利己主义者》。

读者可能已经惊讶地注意到了，迄今为止我没谈及诗歌。我不认为我们民族产生过能够媲美其他国家的画家、雕塑家和作曲家。虽然我们的绘画、雕塑和作曲的成就不错，却并没到杰出的程度。但是我会说我国的诗人是最优秀的，而且我不认为这是出于民族或国家的偏见。诗歌是文学之花、之冠，诗歌不能平庸。我记得埃德蒙·戈斯(7)跟我说过，他宁可读一卷并不出彩的诗集，也不愿读一本平庸的小说，因为读诗花的时间少，还不费脑子。然而只是押韵的东西却于我无用，不管格律多么无可挑剔。对我而言，诗歌必须伟大，否则就什么都不是，还不如读报纸。我无法随时随地地读诗，我希望处于特定情绪和称心的环境中才去读诗。我喜欢夏日将尽时在花园里读，也喜欢坐在一片能看到海的悬崖上，或是躺在树林里长满青苔的河岸上，然后再把口袋里的诗卷拿出来品读。可是哪怕最伟大的诗人也写过很多冗长乏味的诗，还有很多写诗者虽然创作出卷帙无数，最后能拿得出手的诗作却只有两三篇。虽然我认为这两三首已经足够证明诗人存在的合理性了，但我不想收获这么少而读那么多。我喜欢诗选。我知道评论家们对诗选嗤之以鼻，他们说想要了解一个作者必须读他的全集。但我不是一个评论家，而是一个普通人，我读诗只是因为需要慰藉、恢复活力和获得平静。我感谢那些感觉敏锐的学者，正是他们不避烦劳，从体量庞大的英国诗歌中去粗取精，才选出了适合我需要的读物。我读过的三本最好的诗选是帕尔格雷夫主编的《英诗金库》、牛津出版社的《牛津英诗选》，以及杰拉尔德·布利特选编的《英国短诗荟萃》。不过，我们既然生活在当今世界中，就不该忽视当代诗人的诗选，他们也是有可能给我们提供重要作品的。不幸的是，我知道的唯一一本当代诗选，作品选得非常不好，我甚至不愿提它的名字。

当然，每个人都应该读读莎士比亚的悲剧。他不仅是有史以来最伟大的诗人，还是我们民族的光荣。我本人虽然对莎士比亚的戏剧很熟，还是希望能有一位有品味、知识和判断力的人出来编一本莎士比亚的戏剧和诗歌精选集，不仅要包括我们人所共知的那些著名选段，也要包括一些极好的片段，甚至单独的诗行，如此好使我永远能于一册之中，便尽得莎翁所有诗歌的精华。（自从我写过这话以后，现已有乔治·瑞兰德编选的一个集子问世，名为《人生阶段》(8)。此书几乎达成了我的心愿，任何人对此类选集的期待不过如此了。对一个动荡不安的世界而言，此书不啻为一份受欢迎的礼物。）

(1) “美文”原文belles-lettres为法文。

(2) 约瑟夫·艾迪生（1672—1719），英国散文家、剧作家、诗人，与理查德·斯蒂尔（1672—1729）合办过《闲话报》（1710）和《旁观者》（1711）等刊物。

(3) 本书的全名为《查尔斯·格兰迪森爵士的历史》，是英国作家塞缪尔·理查逊（1689—1761）的一部书信体小说，出版于1753年。

(4) 赫布里底群岛位于苏格兰西部。

(5) 指英国诗人格雷（1716—1771），他最著名的诗作为《乡村墓地挽歌》。

(6) 指约翰逊博士，因为约翰逊编过英语字典，在1928年《牛津英语大字典》诞生前的一百五十年间，约翰逊字典是最受欢迎的英语字典，为后世的英语字典编纂奠定了基础，提供了范式。

(7) 埃德蒙·戈斯（1849—1928），英国作家、诗人、评论家。

(8) 《人生阶段》出版于1939年，正是“二战”开始之时，毛姆因此有“动荡不安的世界”之语。

亨利·菲尔丁与《汤姆·琼斯》

1

写亨利·菲尔丁的难处在于世人对他所知甚少。一七六二年，菲尔丁去世八年后，阿瑟·墨非为他作了篇小传，作为对他一版著作的介绍。但是墨非其实并不了解菲尔丁，要说了解，似乎也仅限于菲尔丁的晚年。因此他几无可写，又要写满八十页，只好东拉西扯些冗长无趣的旁枝末节。他所述事实不仅极少，还经常被后来的研究证明是不准确的。最近一位详写菲尔丁的人是牛津大学彭布罗克学院的院长霍姆斯·达顿博士，他那两大卷《菲尔丁研究》是他辛劳的记录。达顿生动地描写了菲尔丁生时的政治环境，以及一七四五年小王位觊觎者(1)的那场失败的冒险，他的研究给菲尔丁一生波折的事业添加了色彩、深度和实质。有关菲尔丁，我不认为还有什么是这位杰出的作者未写到的了。

菲尔丁出生于绅士家庭。他父亲是索尔兹伯里的牧师约翰·菲尔丁的第三子，约翰·菲尔丁又是一位德斯蒙德伯爵的第五子。德斯蒙德家是登比家的支系，登比家则认为自己是哈布斯堡家族(2)的后裔。吉本，写《罗马帝国衰亡史》的吉本，在其自传中写道：“查理五世(3)的后继者们可能不认其英国兄弟，但是叫作《汤姆·琼斯》的这部传奇，这幅人情世态的美妙画卷，却将超越埃斯科里亚尔的宫殿(4)和奥地利皇室的鹰徽长存于世。”吉本的措辞读来铿锵，但遗憾的是，那些高贵的爵爷对其家系渊源的声称其实并无根据。他们的姓氏拼写是Feilding （而不是“菲尔丁”现在的拼写Fielding）。还有一个著名的故事。据说，某次，当时的德斯蒙德伯爵问菲尔丁这是怎么回事，菲尔丁回答说：“我只能猜这是因为我们这一支在阁下您那支之前学会了拼写。”

菲尔丁的父亲参过军，在马尔巴罗公爵(5)手下打过仗，据说“表现勇敢，名声不错”。他娶了王座法院法官亨利·古尔德爵士的女儿萨拉为妻。一七〇七年，在他的乡村邸宅——位于格拉斯顿伯里附近的夏朴罕庄园，我们的作家亨利·菲尔丁出生了。两三年后菲尔丁夫妇又添了两个女儿，全家搬到了多塞特郡的东斯陶尔，这是法官留给女儿的产业，次年亨利·菲尔丁上了伊顿公学。他在那里结交了一些珍贵的朋友。即便他离开伊顿的时候不是像墨非说的那样“对希腊作者有着非同寻常的熟悉，又在很小的时候就已把拉丁经典烂熟于胸”，他也肯定培养出了对古典学问的真爱。人生末年贫病交加时，他会读西塞罗的《论自我安慰》寻求慰藉。死前坐船去里斯本时，他也会随身携带一卷柏拉图的作品。

离开伊顿后，菲尔丁没上大学，而是去索尔兹伯里和他外祖母古尔德夫人住了一阵子，那时古尔德法官已经去世了。按达顿博士的说法，菲尔丁在外祖母家读了一点法律书籍，还读了大量各种题材的文学书籍。他那时是个英俊的青年，身高超过六英尺，强壮有力，活泼好动，眼睛深邃，罗马式的鼻子，上唇短而带一个嘲讽的弯儿，下巴向前突出，显示出倔强的性格。头发褐色带卷，牙齿洁白整齐。十八岁时他就显现出了将来会有的样子。有段时间他和一个忠仆住在莱姆里吉斯，这人肯为他“打人、杀人、致人残废”。菲尔丁在此爱上了一位名叫萨拉·安德鲁的小姐。这位小姐本就生得美，再加上相当有钱，更添了魅力。菲尔丁于是制订出了一个计划，想和她私奔，如有必要，还想用强力迫使她私奔，然后和她结婚。可惜事情败露，这个年轻女子被连忙转移走，和更合适的人安全结了婚。之后两三年，菲尔丁在伦敦用着外祖母给的零花钱，趁着自己还英俊潇洒，尽情干着他这样一个出身高贵的年轻人所能干的那些吃喝玩乐的美事。一七二八年，受亲戚玛丽·沃特利—蒙太古夫人的影响，再加上得到了迷人却并不特别贞洁的女演员安妮·奥德菲尔德的帮助，他的一部戏剧在剧院云集的朱瑞巷上演了，制作人是柯莱·西柏。这部剧叫《歌舞会中的恋爱》，演了四场。之后不久，他去了荷兰的莱顿大学，他父亲答应每年给他两百镑。但他父亲不久再婚了，不能或不愿继续负担先前许诺的生活费，于是大约一年后菲尔丁不得不回到了英国。他当时经济状况非常窘迫，正如他自己曾诙谐地说过的那样，他别无选择，要么当个出租马车车夫，要么替人捉刀(6)。

曾在《英国文人系列》中为菲尔丁作传的奥斯汀·道伯森说：“菲尔丁的秉性和机遇将他引向舞台。”菲尔丁有当剧作家所需的那种兴致与幽默，也有对当时社会的敏锐观察力。除此，他还有一定程度的独创性和一种结构感。道伯森所谓的“秉性”很可能是指，首先，菲尔丁有种表现欲，这是身为剧作家必不可少的；其次，菲尔丁把写剧看成赚快钱的轻松手段。所谓“机遇”，大概是委婉地说菲尔丁是个俊男，精力旺盛，合了一个著名女演员的意。取悦女主角从来都是年轻剧作家最能确保上戏的手段。在一七二九年到一七三七年间，菲尔丁创作并改编了二十六部剧，其中至少有三部大获成功。这三部里边又有一部把斯威夫特都逗笑了，而在这位教长(7)的记忆中，有生以来他总共只笑过两次。菲尔丁的纯喜剧写得不是很成功。据我所知，他最成功之处似乎是他自己发明了一种体裁。这种体裁载歌载舞，有简短的主题说明，有戏仿，有对名人的影射。实际上，就和我们现在流行的、讽刺时事的滑稽剧差不多。按照墨非的说法，菲尔丁的闹剧“通常都是两三个上午的急就章，他写东西太容易了”。达顿博士认为这是夸大其词。我认为不是。这些剧有的很短。我自己就听说过一个周末就写出一部轻喜剧的例子，而且写得还不差。菲尔丁的最后两部剧抨击了当时的政治腐败，因为抨击得太有力，内阁出台了《戏剧审查法案》，要求剧院经理在上戏前务必先从宫务大臣处获得许可。这个法直到现在还在折磨着英国作家。从此菲尔丁基本不再写戏剧，如果写，就只有一个理由：太缺钱。

我不假装通读过他的戏剧，我只是翻过，并时不时地读一场，我发现他戏剧中的对话很是自然活泼。我读过最有趣的一段是他在《伟大的大拇指汤姆》的演员表里以当时流行的口吻对一个人物的描述：“一个绝无过失的女人，只除了有点太爱喝酒。”菲尔丁的戏剧常被认为无甚出奇。无疑，他如果不是《汤姆·琼斯》的作者，那么他的戏剧连想都不会有人想起。它们缺少两百年后坐在书斋里读他戏剧的那些批评家所期待的文学性，而康格里夫(8)的戏剧就有这种文学性。但是戏剧是拿来演的，而不是读的。有文学性当然好，可是使一出戏剧成为好剧的并非文学性，反而这种性质还可能（也经常）使戏剧演不好。菲尔丁的戏剧现在已经没了当初的优点，因为戏剧靠的是现实，因此戏剧是昙花一现的，几乎就像报纸的昙花一现一样短暂。菲尔丁的戏剧，我已经说过，能成功靠的是时事。不过哪怕他的戏分量再轻，也一定有其长处。只是因为一个年轻人有写戏的愿望，还有一个受欢迎的女演员的推动，都不至于使剧院经理一个接一个地上他的戏，除非他的戏打动了观众。观众才是此事的最终的评判者。如果剧院经理连观众的口味都摸不准的话，那他准保要破产了。菲尔丁的戏至少有观众喜欢的长处。《伟大的大拇指汤姆》演了“超过四十晚”，《帕斯昆》演了六十晚，而约翰·盖伊的《乞丐的歌剧》也无非就演了这么久。

菲尔丁对他的戏剧的价值不抱幻想，自言他本该在开始写舞台剧的时候就放弃。他写戏只是为了钱，并且不觉得观众有什么理解力。墨非说：“他现在还健在的很多朋友都知道，当他签了合同答应写个戏剧或写个闹剧的时候，他会很晚才从酒馆回家。第二天上午他就能给演员们拿出一场戏来，而那是写在他包烟草的纸上的，他很喜欢这么做。”排练那部名为《婚礼那天》的喜剧时，参演的盖里克(9)不看好其中一场戏，要求菲尔丁砍掉。“不，该死！”菲尔丁说，“这场戏要是不好，也得让观众发现不好。”戏剧开演了，观众闹嚷着表示不悦。盖里克回到休息室，发现那位剧作者“正在那儿陶醉于自己的天才，用一瓶香槟安慰自己。他已经喝了不少了，此时斜眼看着盖里克，烟草和着口水顺嘴角往下滴着。‘出什么事了，盖里克？’他说，‘他们在嘘什么？’

“‘我早跟你说过让你砍掉那场戏，我就知道不行。他们把我吓坏了，我一整晚都镇定不下来了。’

“‘哦，该死！’菲尔丁回答，‘他们发现了吗？’”

这个故事是墨非讲的，我必须说我怀疑它的真实性。我认识剧院经理，和他们打过交道，他们就是盖里克那样。在我看来，如果盖里克认为某场戏会毁了整出剧，他是不可能答应出演的。但是如果这事不是真的，又怎么会被人编出来。这至少表明了菲尔丁的朋友和伙伴对他的看法。

如果关于菲尔丁的戏剧我说了不少，而戏剧又只不过是他文学生涯的一个插曲，那是因为我认为戏剧对他作为小说家的发展起到了重要作用。很多杰出的小说家都尝试过写戏剧，但我想不起谁是真正成功了的。原因是写小说和写戏剧所需的技巧大不相同，知道如何写小说对写戏剧毫无帮助。小说家为了展开主题，想要花多少时间就花多少时间；他想要多细致地描写人物就可以有多细致；他还可以通过叙述人物的动机，向读者解释人物的行为。如果他有技巧，他能让不可能的事变得逼真可能。如果他有叙述的天赋，他还能逐渐构筑起高潮，而漫长的准备会让这个高潮无比惊人，最极致的一例就是克拉丽莎宣布她被诱奸的那封信(10)。小说家不必表现动作，他只需告诉读者有这么一个动作。他可以让人物用对话解释自己，想写多少页就写多少页。但是戏剧靠的是动作，我说的动作当然不是落下悬崖或被公共汽车碾压这样的剧烈动作，类似递给一个人一杯水这样的动作就可以具备最高的戏剧张力。观众的注意力是非常有限的，需要不断有事发生才能吸引他们的注意。必须一直有新鲜东西。主题必须马上言明，其发展必须遵循一条明确的路线，不能偏移到不相干的小路上去。对话必须干脆切题，必须使观众听到后，不用停下来思考就能明白意思。人物必须有整体性，不能超出观众的理解力，必须一眼就能看明白。人物可以复杂，但是必须复杂得合理。戏剧不能有没系上的线头，或者未了之事。一出戏不管多么微不足道，基础必须稳固，结构也必须紧凑。

如果一个剧作家掌握了我刚才说的这些戏剧的核心品质，可以让观众愿意坐在那里愉快地看完一出戏，那他写小说的时候就有优势了。他学会了简洁，学会了让事件快速发生的重要性，学会了不在半路游移，而是紧扣主题，不断推进他的故事。他还学会了不靠描述，而是让人物通过言行来表现自己。这样一来，当他在小说所许可的更广阔的画布上施展时，他就不仅可以从小说这一形式的特殊优势中获益，他作为剧作家的训练也会使他的小说生动活泼、进展迅速、富有戏剧性。这些都是很好的品质，是某些很好的小说家也不具备的品质，哪怕他们在别的方面富有优点。我不认为菲尔丁写戏剧的那些年是浪费了。相反，我认为他当时获得的经验对他写小说极具价值。

一七三四年，菲尔丁和夏洛特·克莱德克结了婚。她是索尔兹伯里一个寡妇的女儿，这个寡妇只有两个女儿。除了美丽迷人外，我们对她一无所知。克莱德克夫人是个很世俗、很有主意的女人，她明显不赞成菲尔丁对她女儿的追求。这无可厚非，因为菲尔丁的生计实在不稳，而他和戏剧界的联系也很难让一个谨慎的母亲鼓起信心来。不管怎么样，两个相爱的人私奔了。克莱德克夫人追过，但还是“没来得及阻止他们结婚”。菲尔丁把夏洛特写成《汤姆·琼斯》中的索菲亚，以及《艾米莉亚》中的艾米莉亚，读者由此可以知道她在她的爱人，也就是她的丈夫眼中的确切模样了。克莱德克夫人一年后死了，留给夏洛特一千五百镑。钱来得正是时候，因为那年年初上演的一出菲尔丁的戏惨遭失败，他正缺钱。他当时习惯时不时地去他母亲的小产业上住上一阵，现在他和他年轻的妻子同去了。接下来的九个月里他大宴宾客，尽情享受着乡村所能带来的种种乐趣。等他拿着夏洛特剩下的钱回到伦敦时，他找到了干草街的“小剧场”，很快就在那上演了据说是他最好的，也是最成功的一出戏——《帕斯昆：一出时代的讽刺剧》。

当《戏剧审查法案》变成法律，菲尔丁的戏剧事业因此结束之时，他已经有了一妻二子，还有了一点很珍贵的、不够养活妻儿的钱，他不得不找条活路。他三十一岁了。他进了中殿律师学院。虽然按照墨非的说法，“他早年寻欢作乐的恶习还会时不时地萌发，加之他充沛的精力，使他沉迷于伦敦的疯狂享乐中”，但他努力学习，最终成了律师。他准备好好干番事业，但他业务不多，可能是因为律师们都对他这个仅靠写轻喜剧和政治讽刺剧出名的人有所怀疑。何况当律师三年后，他开始经常痛风，使他无法定期出庭。为了挣钱他不得不向报纸卖文，并同时挤时间写了他的第一部小说《约瑟夫·安德鲁》。两年后他的妻子死了。她的死使他痛苦得发疯。路易莎·斯图尔特夫人说：“他热烈地爱着她，她也如此回报他的爱。但他们过得并不幸福，因为他们总是很穷，很少感到平静和安全。全世界都知道他的轻率所在：他只要有钱就会乱花，根本不会为明天着想。有时候他们有体面的住处，日子过得还算舒适。可有时候他们住在糟糕的阁楼上，连生活必需品都没有，更别说他还时常被人从负债人拘留所和别的藏身之处找出来。他靠着能屈能伸的高兴劲儿扛了过去，可忧愁和焦虑却折磨着她娇弱的心灵，毁坏了她的身体。她逐渐憔悴了，最后发了烧，在他的怀里死去了。”这段话很真实，部分在《艾米莉亚》中得到了确认。我们知道小说家习惯把他们自身经历过的任何小事都用于创作，因此当菲尔丁创作比利·布斯这个人物的时候，他就是以自己为原型进行刻画的，还以妻子为原型塑造了艾米莉亚这个人物，还用上了他们婚姻生活中发生过的各种事。妻子去世四年后，他娶了妻子的女仆玛丽·丹尼尔，她那时已有了三个月的身孕。这桩婚事使他的朋友倍感震惊，他妹妹本来从夏洛特死后就与他同住的，后来也离开了他的家。他的亲戚玛丽·沃特利—蒙太古夫人对此非常轻蔑不屑，嫌他居然可以“销魂于给他煮饭的女佣”。玛丽·丹尼尔确实没什么个人魅力，但她是个好人，菲尔丁提到她时，从来都是怀着爱意与尊敬。她是个正派女人，把他照顾得很好，是个贤妻良母，给他生了两儿一女。

当菲尔丁还是个拼命奋斗的剧作家时，他曾向权倾一时的罗伯特·沃波尔爵士献过殷勤。他把名为《现代丈夫》的戏剧热情洋溢地敬献给沃波尔，但这位不知感恩的首相却不愿为他做任何事。于是菲尔丁决定投靠沃波尔的反对者，还立刻就向反对党领袖之一的切斯特菲尔德爵爷示好。正如达顿博士所说的那样，菲尔丁“明确表示愿意把他的机智和幽默为反对党所用，只要他们愿意用”。他们终于表示愿意，菲尔丁于是被任命为一份名为《斗士》的报纸的主编，这份报纸的创立就是为了攻击和嘲笑沃波尔及其内阁。一七四二年沃波尔倒台了，很快由亨利·佩勒姆接替。现在菲尔丁为之服务的党派掌权了。多年来他为支持政府以及为政府辩护的报纸做编辑和写稿工作，现在他自然期待他的服务能得到奖赏。他在伊顿公学结交的、至今还在维系着的一个朋友名叫乔治·利特尔顿，此人出身于显赫的政治家庭（至今仍很显赫），还是个慷慨的文学赞助人。利特尔顿当时被任命为佩勒姆政府的财政大臣，于是在利特尔顿的影响下，菲尔丁在一七八四年被任命为威斯敏斯特的治安官。很快，为了使他可以更为有效地行使职权，他的管辖范围扩大到了米德尔塞克斯，他也和家人搬到了伦敦警察法庭所在的博街的官方住所。他的律师训练，他对生活的了解，以及他天生的才能，使他非常适合这个职位。菲尔丁说在他任职前，这个职位一年可以赚五百镑脏钱，但他任职后，这个职位一年顶多只能挣三百镑干净钱了。通过贝德福德公爵的关系，菲尔丁还从公众服务资金中领到了一笔养老金，每年大概有一两百镑。一七四九年他出版了《汤姆·琼斯》，此书一定是他还在为政府编报纸期间就在写的。他因此书一共挣了七百镑。那时的钱至少值现在的五六倍，因此这笔钱大约等于现在的四千镑。今天一部小说能挣这么多也很好了。

此时菲尔丁的健康已经很糟糕了。痛风经常发作，他经常需要去巴斯，或是去他在伦敦附近的一间农舍疗养，但他没有停止写作。他写与工作有关的政论文，其中一篇文章名为《近来抢劫案多发之威胁的成因探讨》，据说引起了《杜松子法案》(11)的通过。他还写了《艾米莉亚》。他的勤奋令人感叹。一七五一年《艾米莉亚》出版时，他又着手编《考文特花园日报》。他的健康愈发差了，明显不能在博街继续行使职能了。一七五四年，在打掉了一个令伦敦人谈之色变的“恶棍和割喉者团伙”后，他辞了职，让位于他的同父异母弟弟约翰·菲尔丁。现在看来，他唯一的生机就是找一个气候比英国和暖的地方，于是同年六月，他离开故国，乘理查德·维尔船长的“葡萄牙王后号”去了里斯本。他于八月到达，两个月后就死了，时年仅四十七岁。

2

以上我依据不完整的材料简略介绍了菲尔丁的生平。当我思考菲尔丁的人生时，我心头涌起了一种独特的情感。他是个男人。很少有小说家在书中比他投入的自我更多，因此当你读他的小说时，你会感受到一种感情，就像你对相熟多年的某个人所感受到的那种感情一样。他身上有一种他那个时代的时代感，有种英国人的特质，直到最近这种人还很普遍。你会在伦敦遇见他，在赛马中心纽马克特遇见他，在莱斯特郡的打猎季节遇见他，八月在疗养地考兹遇见他，仲冬时节在戛纳和蒙特卡洛遇见他。他是个绅士，他有教养，长得好，性情好，对人和善，容易相处。他并不特别文雅，但他能宽容那些文雅之士。他喜欢姑娘，却经常发现自己被列为离婚诉讼中涉嫌通奸的共同被告。他不是这个世界上最勤劳的那种人，但他也看不出他为什么要成为这样的人。他虽然不做事，但也绝不懒散。他有一份适当的收入，花得也大方。如果战争爆发，他会参军，他的勇敢将有目共睹。他绝对无害，人人都喜欢他。然而时光荏苒，年华不再，他不再有钱，生活也不再似往昔容易。他只得放弃打猎，但他还是打得一手好高尔夫，你也会永远高兴地看见他出现在俱乐部的棋牌室里。他会娶个老情人，一个有钱的寡妇，于是在中年的时候安定下来，做她的好丈夫。可是今天的世界容不下他了，不消几年他这类人就要绝种了。这样一个人，我觉得就是菲尔丁。但他恰巧有一份伟大的天赋使他成了作家。当他想努力工作时，他就能努力工作。他也喜欢醇酒和女人。人们一讨论道德，脑子里主要想的就是贞洁，但贞洁只是道德中很小的一部分，还可能不是最主要的部分。菲尔丁欲望强烈，并且毫不犹豫地屈从于此，可他也能爱得温柔。注意，是性爱，不是爱情。性爱和爱情不同，性爱是植根于性的，但是没有爱也可以有性。拒绝承认这点只能说明虚伪或无知。性欲是一种动物本能，不比饥和渴更丢人，也不比饥和渴更有理由不应得到满足。如果菲尔丁享受了性之乐趣，哪怕有些滥交，他也没比大多数男人坏到哪去。他就像我们中的大多数人那样后悔“犯罪”（如果能说这是罪的话），但是机会来临的时候还会再犯。他急躁易怒，但是心地善良且慷慨大方，是个腐败时代里的实诚人。他是个深情的丈夫，慈爱的父亲。他勇敢真诚，对朋友好，朋友们也对他至死不渝。他虽然宽容别人的缺点，但痛恨野蛮和欺诈。他不因成功膨胀，有两只松鸡和一瓶葡萄酒就可以坚强地对抗逆境。他对生活来者不拒，兴致勃勃，愉快接受，并且尽情享受。事实上，他非常像他的汤姆·琼斯，与他的比利·布斯也并无不同。他是个真正的男人。

但是，我应该告诉读者，我所描述的菲尔丁和我上文经常提到的牛津大学彭布罗克学院的院长（霍姆斯·达顿博士）在他的巨著中所描述的菲尔丁并不吻合，虽然我从那部著作中获得了很多有用信息。“直到最近，”达顿博士写道，“一般人心目中的菲尔丁是个天才，‘心眼儿好’，有很多亲切的品质，但是放浪不羁，不负责任，犯过令人遗憾的错误，甚至更严重的过错也不是没有犯过。”他想尽力说服读者，让他们相信菲尔丁过去是被严重中伤了。

但是达顿博士极力否认的这个形象其实就是菲尔丁生前最常见的样子，熟悉他的人就是这样看他的。他生前确实遭到过政敌和文敌的痛击，他们也确有可能夸大了对他的指责。但是如果指责能伤人，那指责就必须合理。例如，已经作古的斯塔福德·克里普斯爵士有很多死敌，他们恨不得往他身上扔泥巴，说他是个两面派，背叛了他所在的阶级，但他们绝不会说他是个色鬼或酒鬼，因为众所周知，斯塔福德爵士为人品德高尚，极有节制。他们如果说他是酒鬼、色鬼，只能让他们自己显得荒谬。同样，围绕一个名人的诸多传奇固然未必全真，但是假如传奇只是似是而非，一样也不会让人相信。墨非讲过一个故事，说某次菲尔丁需要交税，让出版商预付给他一笔款子，可是当他拿钱回家时遇见了一个境遇更差的朋友，菲尔丁就把钱给了这人。收税官来了，菲尔丁带信给他说：“友谊已经召唤走了金钱，请阁下下次再来吧。”达顿博士认为此逸闻不真。可这事如果是编的，那也是因为它是可信的。菲尔丁被指责挥霍无度，他可能确实如此。但这是因为他总是开朗豪爽，对人友好，喜好宴饮交际，并且对金钱满不在乎。他经常欠债，可能有时还被“讨债者和法警”纠缠。他缺钱到无法可想的地步时，无疑会找朋友帮忙，他们也会借钱给他。思想高尚如埃德蒙·伯克(12)也是如此。作为剧作家，菲尔丁在戏剧圈厮混了多年。不管是过去还是现在，没有一个国家的戏剧圈会被认为是一个能教会年轻人禁欲的好地方。帮菲尔丁上演他第一部戏剧的安妮·奥德菲尔德死后葬在威斯敏斯特教堂，但是因为她曾被两位绅士包养，育有两名私生子，因此为她立碑纪念的请求被拒绝了。当年她要是没向年轻英俊的菲尔丁施爱就怪了。而如果她曾用恩客的钱资助过当时一文不名的菲尔丁，那也没什么好奇怪的。屈服的可能只是他的贫穷而不是他的意愿。如果他年轻时经常在女人堆里厮混，那只能说明他和他那个时代（还有我们这个时代）那些有机会、有优势的年轻人无甚不同。他无疑“曾在很多个夜晚在酒馆里喝得酩酊大醉”。但是不管哲学家们怎么坚称，常识都一致认为年轻人的道德和老年人的道德不同，道德准则也因人的身份不同而不同。神学博士滥交应受谴责，年轻人滥交却合乎常情。一个大学里的院长喝醉了不可原谅，虽然偶尔喝醉也在意料之中，但是一个本科生喝醉则无甚关碍。

菲尔丁的敌人攻击他在政治上有奶就是娘，他确实如此。他很乐意用他的伟大才干为沃波尔效劳，但当他发现人家根本不需要时，他也同样乐意投靠沃波尔的反对者。这并不要求牺牲什么原则，因为当时的执政党和反对党唯一真正的区别就在于执政党掌握着官职任命、有薪水，而反对党则没有。腐败无处不在。只要有好处，居高位者一样乐意换边站，就像菲尔丁为了糊口可以变脸一样。但是菲尔丁有一件事值得称赞，那就是当沃波尔发现他很危险，向他提出只要他离开反对党就答应他的条件时，菲尔丁却拒绝了。菲尔丁这样做也很聪明，因为不久沃波尔就倒台了。菲尔丁在上层社会有朋友，在文艺界有朋友，但从他的作品中看，似乎可以肯定他很享受和底层人以及声名狼藉者交往。为此他曾遭到严厉指责。但是在我看来，他如果没有体验过并很享受底层生活的话，他是不可能如此生动美妙地写出那些所谓的底层生活场景的。菲尔丁活着时，别人普遍把他看成一个放荡挥霍之徒。这方面的证据太强大，无法忽视。可是，如果他真是彭布罗克院长希望我们相信的那么体面、正派、节制的话，他就不可能写出《汤姆·琼斯》这种书了。达顿博士非要洗白菲尔丁可能自有其用，但我想有一点误导了博士，即他没想到矛盾的甚至相互排斥的品质是可以同时并存于一个人身上的，而且不知怎的还会造成一种相当合理的和谐。对一个一直过着安逸的学院生活的人而言，被如此误导是很自然的。在院长看来，因为菲尔丁慷慨善良、正直温和、亲切诚实，他就不可能同时还是个败家子，会从阔朋友那儿乞食要钱；就不可能出入酒馆，痛饮到毁了自己的健康的地步；就不可能一有机会就狂嫖滥交。院长宣称，菲尔丁在第一任妻子活着期间都绝对忠实于她。他怎么知道？菲尔丁当然爱他妻子，爱得热烈，但他绝不是第一个只要机会合适，就会暗地里冒一把险的丈夫，尽管他钟爱妻子。他极有可能像他笔下的布斯上尉一样，虽然犯错后无比悔恨，但仍然控制不了下次一有机会还会再犯。

玛丽·沃特利—蒙太古夫人曾在一封信里说：“我对亨利·菲尔丁的死感到难过，不仅是因为我将再也读不到他的作品了，还因为我相信他的损失比别人都大，因为没有人比他更享受生活，虽然很多人比他更有理由享受生活。他最高级的爱好无非是在最低级的堕落和苦恼中放荡。我认为当个夜间婚礼的主持人(13)都比他这份营生更高尚，更不那么令人恶心。当他面对一份鹿肉馅饼或一瓶香槟时，他欢乐的天性会使他忘了一切，虽然他后来把这份天性毁掉了大半。我相信他比这世界上的任何一个王孙公子享受过的欢乐时光都更多。”

3

有人读不了《汤姆·琼斯》。我不是说那些除了报纸和有插图的周刊以外什么都不读的人，或那些除了侦探小说以外什么都不读的人。我是说那些不反对你把他们划为知识分子的人，那些读过一遍以后还会愉快地重读《傲慢与偏见》，满足地重读《米德尔马契》，心怀敬意地重读《金碗》(14)的人。他们可能从未想过要读《汤姆·琼斯》，即使有时尝试过，也没能读得下去。这书让他们觉得无聊。说他们应该喜欢这书是没用的，读书本就没有什么应该不应该。读小说是为了娱乐。我再说一遍，如果一本小说给不了你这个，那就什么都给不了你。如果你觉得一本小说没意思，没人能指责你，就像没人有权因为你不喜欢牡蛎而指责你。但是我禁不住问自己，到底是什么使读者放下了这本书？吉本说它是人情世态的一幅美妙画卷，司各特赞扬它是真理和人性本身，狄更斯欣赏它并从中受益。萨克雷说：“《汤姆·琼斯》这部小说真叫美妙，其结构算得上是个奇迹。那些智慧的穿插情节，那样强大的观察力，那些层次众多、巧妙恰当的措辞和思想，那种堪称伟大的喜剧史诗般的人物多样性，都永远使读者处于钦佩和好奇中。”是因为读者无法对两百年前人们的生活方式、风俗习惯感兴趣？还是因为风格的问题？但是《汤姆·琼斯》的风格很是轻松自然。我忘了是谁说过，可能是菲尔丁的朋友切斯特菲尔德爵爷，他说好的风格让人感觉是一个有文化的人在说话。菲尔丁的风格正是如此。他与读者对话，告诉他们汤姆·琼斯的故事，就像他在晚餐桌上就着一瓶酒对三五知己说话一样。他绝不咬文嚼字。美丽贞洁的索菲亚明显是听惯了“妓女”“杂种”“荡妇”这些词。说到这个，真猜不出为什么菲尔丁写“婊子”（bitch）的时候要省掉两个字母（“b．．．ch”）。事实上，有时候索菲亚的爸爸，乡绅魏斯顿，就是这么随便地用这些词称呼她的。

用谈话风格写小说有其弊端，因为作者会对你推心置腹，会告诉你他对笔下人物的感想，以及他对人物所处环境的看法。作者总在你的近旁，妨碍了你与故事中的人直接交流。他的道德说教有时会惹恼你，一旦他开始离题闲扯，就又会变得乏味无聊。你不想听他对某些道德问题和社会问题发表看法，你只希望他继续讲故事。菲尔丁的漫谈几乎总是明智或有趣，通常也还简短，并有为之道歉的风度，他的温厚也闪耀其中。而当萨克雷不明智地模仿菲尔丁时，他就显得假正经、假虔诚了，你还会不由自主地怀疑他也并不真诚。

菲尔丁在《汤姆·琼斯》的每卷前都置一序言。有些批评家对这些序言很激赏，认为它们起到了锦上添花的作用。我只能说这是因为他们对小说本身不感兴趣。散文家会愿意挑个题目进行讨论。如果题目新，他会告诉你一些你不知道的东西。但是新题目不好找，因此散文家通常期待用自己的态度和看问题的独特方式来使你感兴趣。也就是说，他希望他本人让你感兴趣。但是读小说的时候你不会想要这么做。你不关心作者，他的作用只是讲故事和介绍你认识一堆人物。小说读者想知道的是作者使他感兴趣的人物后来怎么样了，如果他连这个都不想知道，他就没理由读小说了。因为读小说——这话我说多少遍都不会厌烦——不是为了启迪和教导，而是为了一种聪明的消遣。菲尔丁似乎是在写完小说后才添加了那些评论。它们和所介绍的章节几乎没有关联，而且他承认这些评论文字给他找了很多麻烦，于是我们纳闷他为什么要写这些评论。他不可能不知道很多读者认为他的小说低俗，不太道德，甚至淫秽，他可能是想用那些序给他的小说以某种道德的提升。这些序写得很明智，有时还相当精明。如果你熟读了小说，再读这些序时也会相当愉快。但是如果你是第一次读小说，那就不如跳过这些序。《汤姆·琼斯》的情节很好。我从达顿博士的书里得知柯勒律治曾感叹道：“菲尔丁真是个写作大师！”司各特和萨克雷也同样热情。达顿博士引用萨克雷的话说：“不管道德不道德，让任何人都先把这个浪漫故事看成艺术作品，之后他就会觉得它是人类才智最令人震惊的产物。在这部小说中，一件事哪怕再小都是由前事演化而来，都推动了故事的发展，都和整个故事紧密相关。如此一部神助之作（如果我们可以如此措辞的话），在其他小说那里前所未见。你可以砍掉半部《堂吉诃德》，或者添加、调换、改写司各特的任何浪漫传奇故事，两者都不会有任何损失。罗德里克·兰登(15)以及类似主人公不管经历了怎样的冒险奇遇，最后，还可以提琴拿来，婚礼开始。但是《汤姆·琼斯》的故事情节自第一页至最后一页始终环环相扣，衔接紧密。作者一定是在落笔前就在脑子里搭好、撑起了整个结构。他是如何做到这一点的，想想都令人称奇。”

这话有些夸张。《汤姆·琼斯》是按西班牙流浪汉小说和《吉尔·布拉斯》(16)的模式写的，其结构的简单取决于这一文体的本质：主人公因某种原因离开了家，一路上经历各种冒险，遇到各式人等，命运起起落落，最后发了财，娶了个迷人的妻子。菲尔丁一边套用这个模式，一边用无关的故事打断叙述。这真是个不怎么令人愉快的写作手法，而作家之所以采用，我想原因不光是我之前说的：他们总得给书商写点什么东西交稿，一两个故事总能充数；还因为他们担心一长串冒险会很无聊，觉得时不时讲个故事或许能给读者增添点刺激。再有就是如果他们想写短篇小说，除此之外他们没有别的办法能让公众看到。批评家们会斥责这种做法，但它就是不消亡。众所周知，狄更斯在《匹克威克外传》中就用了这种手法，《汤姆·琼斯》的读者也可以毫无损失地跳过“山中人”的故事和菲兹赫伯特太太的叙述。至于萨克雷评价菲尔丁书中的每一件事都其来有自，都推动了故事的发展，其实并不准确。汤姆·琼斯和吉卜赛人的相遇就没有导致任何事的发生，引入亨特夫人以及她向汤姆的求婚也很没必要。那一百镑账单的情节不仅毫无用处，还绝无可能，令人难以置信。至于萨克雷赞叹菲尔丁在动笔前就在脑子里构建了小说的整体结构，在我看来菲尔丁并没有这么做过，就像萨克雷在写《名利场》之前也不可能这么做一样。我觉得更有可能的是，一开始菲尔丁只是在脑子里有了故事主线，后来才边写边把那些具体情节编出来。他的大多数情节都写得不错。像他之前的那些流浪汉小说家一样，他并不在乎可能性。因为在他的书里最不可能的事都发生了，最离谱的巧合也都把人物聚合到了一起。但是他是如此活力十足地督促你一路前行，以至于你几乎没有时间，也不想要抗议这种不可能。他的人物都以原色描绘，粗率中带着豪放。如果他的人物缺少微妙之处，也因活力得到了弥补。这些人物极富个性，如果有所夸张，那也是时代使然，而且夸张的程度可能并未超越喜剧所能容许的范畴。我担心甄可敬先生(17)有点太好了，不像真人。但是菲尔丁在此处的失败也无非是像他之后的每个小说家那样，是因为太想要刻画一个道德完人，而经验告诉我们似乎没法不使甄可敬这样的人物显得有点蠢。读者对这么一个人是会有点不耐烦的，他太好了，于是被各式各样的人欺骗和利用。据说甄可敬原型是普里亚庄园的拉尔夫·艾伦。如果这是真的，菲尔丁对人物的描述也是真的，那只能说明直接源于生活的人物在小说里永远没法太令人信服。

另一方面，布利非也被认为坏得不像真人。菲尔丁痛恨欺骗和伪善，他对布利非的厌恶如此之深，以至于他把描绘这个人物的色彩涂抹得太重了。但是小气、鬼祟、自私、冷血的布利非并非是不常见的一类人，害怕露馅是唯一没有使他变成彻底的恶棍的原因。但是我觉得布利非如果不是坏得这么明显的话，这个人物刻画得倒是更能令人信服。他是讨厌，但是不鲜活，不像尤赖·希普(18)那样真实。我曾经自问，菲尔丁是否出于这样一种直觉有意把这个人物写少了：如果把他写得更活跃、更突出，那会使他过分强大和邪恶，从而掩盖了主角的光辉。

《汤姆·琼斯》一经问世就在公众那里大获成功，批评家们对此却基本都持严厉态度。有些反对令人颇感荒谬。比如，拉克斯伯罗夫人抱怨说书中人物太像“社会上遇见的那些人”。但是这本小说之所以广受谴责，主要还是因为不道德。汉娜·摩尔(19)在回忆录中说她从没见过约翰逊博士对她生气，只除了一次，那是当她提及《汤姆·琼斯》中的一些妙语的时候。“听到你从这么一本道德败坏的书中引文摘句，我真是吃惊，”约翰逊说，“我很遗憾听说你已经读了这本书，一个正派淑女是不该坦白这种事的。我几乎不知道还有什么作品比这本书更堕落。”可是现在，我要说，一个正派淑女最好在结婚前读读这本书。它会告诉她有关人生她所需知道的一切事实，以及很多有关男人的事实，在她进入婚姻这个艰难阶段之前，知道这些对她不会没用。人人都知道约翰逊博士是带有偏见的，他不承认菲尔丁在文学上的造诣，有一次还说菲尔丁是个木头脑袋。当鲍斯威尔提出异议的时候，约翰逊博士说：“说他是个木头脑袋，我的意思是说他是个毫无思想的流氓。”鲍斯威尔则回答：“先生，难道你不认为他非常自然地描绘了人生吗？”对此，约翰逊说：“可是，先生，那是非常卑贱的人生。理查逊过去经常说他如果不知道菲尔丁是谁，他会以为他是个马夫。”我们现在已经习惯了小说里的低贱生活，《汤姆·琼斯》里再也没有什么是我们时代的小说家不曾让我们熟知的了。约翰逊博士可能记得，菲尔丁把索菲亚刻画成了一个温柔迷人、令小说读者感到愉悦的人物。她单纯但不傻，贞洁但不假正经，她有性格、决心和勇气。她有爱心，长得还美。玛丽·沃特利—蒙太古夫人认为《汤姆·琼斯》是菲尔丁的代表作，这一点她判断得很正确。但她遗憾菲尔丁没有发现他已经把男主人公写成了一个浑蛋。我想她指的是那件被认为是汤姆·琼斯先生职业生涯中最应受到谴责的事：贝拉斯顿夫人迷上了他，并且发现他也早准备好了要满足她的欲望，因为他认为女人既然都已表达了那个愿望，男人就该向她“殷勤”行事，这是男人良好教养的一部分。汤姆分文皆无，甚至连一个先令都没有，没法雇车把自己送到贝拉斯顿夫人的住所，可是这位夫人如此富有。女人通常花别人的钱大方，花自己的钱小气，可是这位夫人却有一种罕见的慷慨，她大方地救了汤姆的急。男人从女人那里拿钱总归不好，也不合算，因为有钱女人在这种情况下想要的可比她们花出去的多得多。但在道德上，这并不比女人从男人那里拿钱更值得大惊小怪。如果普遍看法都认为男人用女人的钱更糟糕的话，那只能说普遍看法很愚蠢。我们的时代已经认为有必要发明一个词“小白脸”来指这种把个人魅力变成赚钱手段的男性，因此汤姆的粗俗，哪怕再应受人谴责，也不能算是什么新鲜事了。我毫不怀疑乔治二世(20)统治下小白脸的盛行就像如今乔治五世统治下一样势头强劲。好在就在贝拉斯顿夫人因为陪睡而给了汤姆五十镑的那天，汤姆被房东给他讲的一个她的什么亲戚的倒霉故事感动了，他于是把钱包给了她，让她随便拿吧，去解决那人的困难吧。这也正是汤姆品格的典型体现。他虽然真诚地深爱着美丽的索菲亚，可是同时，他和任何迷人的、容易得手的女人放纵肉欲，也并不觉得有什么良心不安。他还并不因为这些插曲而少爱了索菲亚一点。菲尔丁太聪明，才没有把他的男主人公写得比一般男人更自制。他知道如果我们晚上也能像白天一样谨慎，那我们就会更道德。而当索菲亚听说汤姆这些艳遇时，她也没有不依不饶地过分生气。她在这事上有着她这个性别少见的常识，这肯定是她最迷人的性格之一了。对此，奥斯汀·道布森有一句话说得很好，虽然说得不那么文雅。他说菲尔丁“并不假装要塑造完美的典范，他只想写出普通的人性，他的笔调宁要粗糙不要文雅，宁要自然不要造作，他的愿望是要绝对真实地做到这一切，而不是掩盖缺点短处，或为之寻找借口”。这是现实主义者努力在做的事，但是有史以来，现实主义者一直都在或多或少地因此受到猛烈的抨击。据我所知主要原因有两条。一是有很多人，尤其是年长者、有钱人和有权人，都采取这种态度，即：“我们当然知道世上有很多犯罪和不道德，但我们不想读到这些事。我们为什么要让自己不舒服呢？我们反正也无能为力。这世界毕竟总是有穷有富”。另一种人有别的理由批评现实主义者，他们承认世界上有犯罪和邪恶，残酷和压迫，但是他们问：“这是适合写小说的材料吗？年轻人读长辈们知道但是惋惜、反对的东西好吗？假如年轻人读的小说哪怕不算淫秽可是已经算得上很具挑逗性了，这难道不会腐蚀他们吗？那些表现世界上有很多美、善、自我牺牲、慷慨和英雄主义的小说难道不是更好吗？”现实主义者的回答是：“对于他所接触到的世界，他只想实事求是地说真话。他不相信人能毫不掺杂地行善，他认为人是善与恶的混合体，他容忍传统道德所不容忍的人性的怪癖，他认为这些怪癖是人性的、自然的，因此也就是可以为之辩解的。他希望他对人性善的描写就像他对人性恶的描写一样诚实，如果读者更感兴趣的是恶不是善，那不是他的错。他不能为人类这种动物身上的这个奇怪的特点负责。但是如果他对自己诚实，他会承认恶是可以用闪闪发光的色彩描摹的，善却似乎总带着一抹暗色。如果你问他如何为腐蚀年轻人这个控诉辩解，他会说年轻人最好知道他们将要与之打交道的世界是个什么样。如果他们期待太高，结果很可能是灾难一场。如果一个现实主义者能教会年轻人不要从别人那里期待太高，让他们一开始就知道每个人最关心的都只是他自己；如果不管以何种方式他还能教会他们：一、他们必须为他们得到的一切付出代价，无论地位、财富、荣誉、爱情还是名誉；二、所谓智慧，很大程度在于不要为了得到某样东西付出超值的代价，那他就能比所有的老师和牧师加起来都更能教会年轻人如何过好这艰难的生活。但是，他还会再加一句，说他既不是老师，也不是牧师，他希望他是艺术家。”

(1) 指查尔斯·爱德华·斯图尔特（1720—1788），斯图尔特王朝的王子，人称“小王位觊觎者”。1745年，他趁大部分英国军队都在欧洲大陆参加奥地利王位继承战之机，在苏格兰登陆，纠集人马向南进发，企图夺回英国王位，结果战败逃亡法国。

(2) 哈布斯堡家族，也称奥地利家族，其纹章的主体图案是双头鹰。哈布斯堡家族是欧洲最有影响力的皇室家族，产生过多位神圣罗马帝国皇帝，以及波希米亚、德国、英国、法国、匈牙利、克罗地亚、爱尔兰、西班牙、葡萄牙等国国王。

(3) 查理五世（1500—1558），西班牙国王并神圣罗马帝国皇帝，他继承了西欧、南欧和中欧，以及美洲和亚洲的大片土地，建立了第一个“日不落帝国”。在他之后，哈布斯堡王朝分裂为西班牙和奥地利两个支系，下文“埃斯科里亚尔的宫殿和奥地利皇室的鹰徽”就是指这两个支系。

(4) 指西班牙首都马德里附近规模宏大的埃斯科里亚尔建筑群，包括西班牙国王的陵墓、宫殿、教堂、修道院等，建于1562到1584年间。

(5) 丘吉尔的祖先；十八世纪初，他作为总司令带领英军战胜了西班牙和法国军队。

(6) 此处语带双关，出租马车车夫和替人捉刀，英文都是hackney。

(7) 乔纳森·斯威夫特（1667—1745），爱尔兰作家，代表作为《格列佛游记》和《一只桶的故事》。斯威夫特曾任爱尔兰都柏林圣帕特里克大教堂的教长。

(8) 威廉·康格里夫（1670—1729），英国剧作家，善写风俗喜剧，以对话机智讽刺著称，代表作有《以爱还爱》《如此世道》。

(9) 大卫·盖里克（1717—1779），十八世纪英国著名的演员、剧作家、剧院经理和制作人。

(10) 指十八世纪英国作家理查逊以书信体写作的小说《克拉丽莎》，号称有史以来最长的英语小说。

(11) 十八世纪上半期英国人盛行饮杜松子酒，并因此引发无数社会问题，政府于是在1729、1736、1743、1747和1751年五次出台《杜松子法案》，希望限制杜松子酒的消费，本文所指应是最后一个法案。菲尔丁主张禁绝杜松子酒，认为它滋生犯罪，损害儿童健康。

(12) 埃德蒙·伯克（1729—1797），爱尔兰著名哲学家、政论家，反对英王乔治三世和英国政府，支持北美殖民地以及后来的美国革命，对法国大革命持批判态度。

(13) 由教会牧师主持的合法婚礼在白天举行，晚上结婚的大约是私奔者或身份更加不见容于世的男女。

(14) 《金碗》是美国作家亨利·詹姆斯（1843—1916）1904年写的一本小说，写婚姻、家庭、父女关系的复杂纠缠，被认为是詹姆斯的代表作之一。

(15) 指苏格兰作家托比亚斯·斯摩莱特（1721—1771）所著的流浪汉小说《罗德里克·兰登的冒险》，出版于1748年。

(16) 《吉尔·布拉斯》，勒萨日（1668—1747）的代表作，十八世纪法国著名的流浪汉小说，写一个底层出身的小人物在社会中的沉浮。

(17) Mr．Allworthy，译名从潘家洵先生译本。

(18) 尤赖·希普是狄更斯小说《大卫·科波菲尔》中的一个负面人物，他为人不真诚，谄媚奉承，过分谦卑，他的名字在英文中已经成了“马屁精”的代名词。

(19) 汉娜·摩尔（1745—1833），约翰逊的文学圈中人，英国宗教作家及慈善家，也写诗和戏剧，还反对奴隶贸易。

(20) 乔治二世，1727到1760年间在位，正是《汤姆·琼斯》故事发生的年代，这位国王以情妇、暴脾气，以及粗鲁著称。

简·奥斯汀与《傲慢与偏见》

1

简·奥斯汀的生平事迹可以几句话说完。她家是个古老家族，像英国很多最显赫的家族一样，是靠羊毛贸易发迹的，羊毛贸易一度是这个国家的支柱性产业。发财后，她家也像比她们更厉害的那些家族一样，买了地，逐渐加入了有地士绅的行列。但是奥斯汀所属的这个支系和其他支系相比，似乎只继承了巨大财富中的很少一点，他们落魄了。奥斯汀的父亲叫乔治·奥斯汀，祖父叫威廉·奥斯汀，祖父是汤布里奇那里的外科医生，这个职业在十八世纪初时被认为比律师这一职业高级不了多少。而我们从《劝导》中得知，即使到了奥斯汀生活的时期，律师也还无甚社会地位。《劝导》中有这样一段描写，“只不过是个爵士遗孀”的罗素夫人吃惊地发现从男爵的女儿艾略特小姐居然和律师的女儿克雷太太(1)有交往，而后者“对艾小姐而言，本该啥也不是，本该只是艾小姐敬而远之的对象”。外科医生威廉·奥斯汀去世得早，于是他的哥哥弗朗西斯·奥斯汀把孤儿乔治送进了汤布里奇学校，后来又送去了牛津的圣约翰学院。这些事实是我从查普曼博士的克拉克讲义中获知的，这些讲义现已出书，名为《简·奥斯汀：事实与问题》。我以下所写均受惠于这本好书。

乔治·奥斯汀先是成了圣约翰学院的研究员，领圣职后，在哥德莫山姆的一个名为托马斯·奈特的亲戚的帮助下，获得了汉普郡史蒂文顿地方的牧师职位。两年后，伯父又给他买下了附近一个名叫迪恩的地方的圣职。我们对这位慷慨的亲戚一无所知，但可以猜想他就像《傲慢与偏见》里的加德纳先生一样，是个商人。

乔治·奥斯汀牧师娶了托马斯·雷的女儿卡桑德拉·雷。托马斯·雷是牛津万灵学院的研究员，他还领着亨利镇附近哈珀斯顿的一份圣俸。我年轻时看卡桑德拉·雷这样的人，会认为她出身不俗，也就是说，像赫斯特蒙索的赫尔家一样，她是有地士绅和贵族的远亲。对外科医生的儿子来说，这门亲事让他上了一个台阶。他们生了两女六男共八个孩子，其中两个女儿是卡桑德拉和简。为了增加收入，史蒂文顿的这位牧师还开馆收徒，六个儿子就是在家受教的。其中两个后来上了牛津的圣约翰学院，因为从他们母亲一方的家谱看来，他们算是学院创建者的亲戚。还有一个儿子叫乔治，我们对他一无所知，查普曼认为他又聋又哑。另有两个儿子加入了海军，都取得了辉煌的成就。最幸运的是爱德华，他被托马斯·奈特收养，继承了后者在肯特郡和汉普郡的产业。

简·奥斯汀是小女儿，生于一七七五年。她二十六岁时，父亲辞了职，把职位让给了已领圣职的大儿子，自己搬到了巴斯。乔治·奥斯汀死于一八〇五年，几个月后，他的寡妻和两个女儿搬去了南安普敦。就是在这里，简给姐姐卡桑德拉写信，讲述她和母亲的一次拜访：“我们发现只有蓝丝太太一人在家。不论她如何夸耀子孙，除了一架大钢琴外，什么子孙也没出现……他们很有钱，过得很气派，她也似乎很喜欢有钱。我们向她暗示我们远非如此，很快她就会觉得我们不值得她结交了。”奥斯汀先生死时确实没给奥斯汀太太留下什么钱，但是儿子们添了些，足够她过得还算舒适。被领养的爱德华在欧洲大陆的游学之旅(2)结束后，娶了古德尼斯通从男爵布鲁克·布里奇的女儿伊丽莎白。其领养者托马斯·奈特死于一七九四年，三年后他的遗孀把哥德莫山姆和查顿的产业交给爱德华，自己拿了一份年金去了坎特伯雷生活。多年后，爱德华让他母亲在这两份产业中任选一处居住，她选了查顿。于是简·奥斯汀一直住在那里，除了中间偶尔访亲问友以外，有时拜访会持续好几个星期之久。最后因为生病，她不得不去了温彻斯特，因为那里的医生比农村的好。一八一七年她死于温彻斯特，安葬在温彻斯特大教堂。

2

据说简·奥斯汀长相动人，“她的身材颀长苗条，步履轻盈坚定，整个人显得健康、有活力。她的肤色是健康的浅黑色。她的脸蛋圆鼓鼓的，鼻子嘴巴小巧标致，眼睛是明亮的浅褐色，头发是褐色的，自然拳曲，垂在脸颊两侧。”但我看到过的唯一一张简·奥斯汀的肖像，却展示出一个五官毫无特色、眼睛又大又圆、胸部高耸的胖脸年轻女子。当然也可能是画家没画好。

简和她姐姐感情很深。从女孩到女人，她们俩总在一起。直到简去世，她们俩都睡同一个卧室。卡桑德拉被送去上学的时候，简也跟着一起去了。哪怕她年纪还太小，还无法从女校教育中受益，但她还是跟着去了，因为离开姐姐她会非常难过。她们的妈妈说：“如果卡桑德拉要被砍头，简也会坚持和她有难同当。”“卡桑德拉比简漂亮，性情更冷淡沉静，不爱公开表露感情，不如简开朗，但她的优点是总能控制住自己的脾气。不过简天生脾气好，她的脾气永远不需要控制。”现存大多数简的信，都是简在两姐妹分离时写给卡桑德拉的。很多简·奥斯汀最热情的崇拜者认为这些信价值不高，认为它们表明简·奥斯汀是个冷淡、没感情的人，认为她的兴趣平凡琐碎。我对此感到吃惊，我认为这些信非常自然。简·奥斯汀绝不会想到除了卡桑德拉以外，还会有其他人读到这些信，因此她告诉姐姐的是她认为姐姐会感兴趣的事。比如人们的衣着如何，自己买的那块印花的平纹细布多少钱，自己新认识了什么人，遇到了哪些老友，以及听到了什么闲话。

近年来出版了一些名作家的书信集。我展卷拜读时，时不时会产生一种怀疑：在这些作家的脑海中是不是想过将来有一天自己的通信会被出版。当我知道他们还留有信的副本时，我的怀疑就变成了确信。安德烈·纪德想出版他和克洛岱尔(3)的通信，克洛岱尔可能不想出，就说他手里纪德的信都毁了，纪德却说没关系，他还有副本。纪德还告诉我们，当他发现妻子把他写给她的情书都烧了时，他哭了一星期，因为他认为这些情书是他文学成就的巅峰之作，是他能否吸引后世注意的主要凭证。狄更斯更是每遇外出旅行，就会给朋友写长信，洋洋洒洒地描写他所见到的风景。正如他的第一个传记作者约翰·福斯特所说的那样，这些信一字不改就可直接出版。那时的人似乎更有耐心。可是，如果你收到朋友来信，信里诗情画意地给你描写山川峰峦和纪念碑，可你更想知道的却是他是否遇到了什么有趣的人，是否参加了什么聚会，是否给你买了你希望他捎回来的书、领带或手绢，那么收到这样信的你只会失望。

在写给卡桑德拉的一封信中，简说：“我现在已经掌握了真正的书信艺术。我们总是被告知，书信艺术就是用笔把你想当面说的话写下来。我在这封信里已经尽我所能地和你用最快的速度说话了。”她当然是对的，这就是写信的艺术。她轻松完美地掌握了这门艺术。既然她说她谈话就如她写信一般，而她的信中又充满了机智幽默、辛辣讽刺、诙谐刻薄的妙语，那么我们就可以肯定她的谈话也是令人愉快的。她的每一封信都有引人发笑的趣语。以下我将举例说明她的风格，以博诸君一笑：

贫穷是单身女子容易有的一种可怕倾向，可这也正是她需要结婚的强大理由。

想想吧，赫德太太死了！可怜的女人，她做了这世界上唯一一件她能做而不让人骂的事。

谢尔本镇的黑尔太太昨晚因惊吓产下了一名死婴，生产时间比预产期早了数周。我猜这是因为她一不留神看了她丈夫一眼。

我们目睹了W．K．太太的死。我不知道有谁喜欢她，因此对她的“未亡人”也不抱同情，但是现在，我正为她丈夫的缘故感伤，觉得他还不如娶夏普小姐。

我钦佩张伯伦太太头发做得好，但是比这更亲切的情感，我就感受不到了。朗利小姐就好像所有宽鼻大嘴、衣着时髦、袒胸露乳的矮个女孩一样。斯坦赫普上将颇具绅士风度，只不过他的腿太短，尾巴(4)又太长。

伊莱莎(5)在巴顿见到了克雷文爵爷，这会儿可能又在坎特伯雷见了他一次，因为据说本周某天他们约好了他会去那里。她觉得他的风度非常怡人，唯一不怡人的一点似乎是他现今有个情人和他同住在艾什顿庄园。

W．先生大约二十五六岁年纪，长得不难看，但也不讨人喜欢。当然他也没有头衔。他有种冷静的绅士做派，可是非常沉默。他们说他叫亨利，这说明命运的赐予是多么不公。我见过很多约翰和托马斯，都比他讨人喜欢。

理查德·哈维太太要结婚了，这可是个大秘密，只有一半街坊知道，你千万别说。

黑尔医生的哀悼如此深切，一定是他母亲、他妻子或他本人死了。

简·奥斯汀喜欢跳舞，以下是她向卡桑德拉描述的她去过的一些舞会：

只有十二支舞，我跳了九支，只因为缺少舞伴才没跳剩下那三支。

有一位绅士，是个柴郡的军官，人年轻，长得还帅。有人跟我说，他很想让人介绍跟我认识。但是因为他的愿望还没有强烈到不怕麻烦去采取行动的地步，因此我们最终也没能认识。

美人不多，有也不美。艾尔蒙格(6)小姐看起来气色不佳，布兰特(7)太太是唯一比较受人欣赏的。她还和九月的时候一样，还是大脸、肥颈、钻石束发带、白鞋，有个皮色粉红的丈夫。

查尔斯·波莱特周四开了个舞会，让他所有的邻居都大感不安。你知道他们当然都对他的经济状况无比感兴趣，都巴不得他赶紧破产。他妻子正如所有人希望的那样：愚蠢、易怒、放肆。

一次，简的一个亲戚让人传了闲话。事情牵扯到一位芒特博士，因为他的所作所为，他妻子回了娘家。奥斯汀对此写道：“但是因为芒特博士是个牧师，因此他俩的感情哪怕再不道德，也有一种端庄的姿态。”

奥斯汀牙尖嘴利，幽默感惊人。她喜欢笑，也喜欢惹人发笑。一个幽默家想到一件趣事憋着不说是不可能的。而且，老天知道，想要幽默而有时又没点恶毒也是不行的。人类的恻隐之心很难让人感到兴奋。简对他人的荒唐、自负、做作和虚伪有一种敏锐的感知力，他们使她感到好笑而不是恼怒，这是她令人称道之处。她太善良，不会当面对人说一些使人痛苦的话，但她当然也觉得拿他们开开玩笑，让自己和卡桑德拉乐一乐也没什么不好。我即使在她最刻薄的话里也没听出居心不良，她的幽默是建立在观察和天赋的基础上的，幽默本该如此。可是如有需要，她也可以严肃。她哥哥爱德华·奥斯汀虽然从托马斯·奈特那里继承了肯特郡和汉普郡的产业，但大多数时候都住在坎特伯雷附近的哥德莫山姆庄园，简和卡桑德拉经常来此轮流小住，有时一住就是三个月。爱德华的长女范妮是简最喜欢的侄女，她后来嫁给了爱德华·纳奇布尔爵士，生的儿子受封为贵族，成了布雷伯恩爵爷，就是他第一个出版了奥斯汀的通信集。集子里有两封信是简写给范妮的，范妮那时还年轻，正在考虑如何应对一个想求娶她的年轻人。这两封信写得很好，既有冷静的理智也有温柔的情感。

几年前，彼得·昆纳在《康希尔杂志》发表了一封那时已是纳奇布尔夫人的范妮很多年后写给她妹妹莱斯太太的信，信中提到她们著名的姑妈，这封信着实令奥斯汀的很多崇拜者吃了一惊。它既令人吃惊，又极具那个时代的特色，因此在获得了已故布雷伯恩爵爷的许可后，我把信附在了此处。信中的画线处(8)是原作者所为。因为爱德华·奥斯汀一八一二年改姓了奈特，因此此处须指出，纳奇布尔夫人信中所指的奈特太太是托马斯·奈特的遗孀。从这封信的开头可以判断，关于她们的姑姑是否“文雅”，莱斯太太听到了一些议论，她感到不安，于是写信向姐姐询问传言是否为实。纳奇布尔夫人如此回复：

是的，我的爱，简姑姑因为诸多条件所限，没能达到她的才能所应达到的文雅。假如她能多活五十年，她将在很多方面更加符合我们更为文雅的品味。她们没有钱，身边与之交往的人也绝不高贵，或者简言之，只是些平庸之辈。她们自己虽然智力和学识超群，但在文雅方面，却和这些平庸之辈处于同一水平。不过我认为，她们后来与奈特太太的交往提升了她们的素质，奈特太太很喜欢她们，对她们很友善。简姑姑那么聪明，不会不知道要撇开自身所有那些可能让人觉得“平庸”（如果可以用这个词的话）的迹象，教会自己至少在与人交往时要更文雅些。两位姑姑（卡桑德拉和简）都是在对上流社会及其方式（我指时尚等）毫不知情的情况下被抚养长大的。如果不是因为爸爸的婚姻把她们带到了肯特，给她们带来了奈特太太的善良——奈特太太是会经常轮流请她们做客的——她们将会远远低于上流社会的标准，哪怕她们本人仍然聪明亲切。如果你讨厌这一切，我请你原谅，但我感到这一切涌到我的笔端，似乎自动前来，告知真相。现在差不多是更衣时间了……

我是你永远亲爱的、最友爱的

姐姐F．C．K．

这封信激起了奥斯汀信徒的义愤，他们宣称纳奇布尔夫人写信时已经老迈昏庸了。但是这封信里丝毫没有老迈昏庸的迹象。何况莱斯太太如果觉得她姐姐身体状况无法回答提问，自然也不会写信向她询问。在奥斯汀的信徒看来，范妮简直忘恩负义，简那样宠她，她却这么说简。孩子看父母和长辈，不像父母和长辈看孩子一样怀有同等程度的爱，这很遗憾，但这是事实。父母和长辈如果对此怀有期待的话，那也很不明智。我们都知道简终生未婚，她给范妮的是她如果结婚会给自己孩子的母爱。她很爱孩子，孩子们也最喜欢她。他们喜欢她活泼好玩，喜欢她讲的那些长长的细节详尽的故事。她和范妮成了挚友，范妮可以跟她说可能无法跟父母说的话，因为她父亲已经变成了一名乡绅，整天忙于那些属于乡绅的事，而她母亲则在不断怀孕生产。可是孩子们的眼睛是敏锐的，很容易做出残酷的判断。爱德华·奥斯汀继承了哥德莫山姆和查顿，他就飞黄腾达了，他的婚姻也使他和郡里那些最好的家族建立起了联系。我们不知道简和卡桑德拉如何看待嫂子。查普曼博士还宽容地暗示，妻子的死使爱德华感到“他应该为母亲和妹妹多做点什么，这促使他向她们奉献自己产业上的一幢村舍供她们居住”。而事实上，他很早就拥有了这些产业，有十二年之久了。在我看来，更有可能的情况是，他妻子认为只要他们时不时地请婆家人来住一住，就已经为婆家人做得足够多了，因此并不欢迎她们永久定居在自己家门口。是她的死给了他自由，让他能按自己的意志处理自己的财产。如果情况果真如此，那就逃不过简锐利的眼睛，就有可能启发了简，写下了《理智与情感》中那些描述约翰·达什伍德如何对待继母及继妹的段落。简和卡桑德拉是穷亲戚，如果她们受邀去和有钱的哥嫂常住，去坎特伯雷陪奈特太太常住，去古德尼斯通陪布里奇夫人——她们嫂子的妈妈——常住，那么她们的东道主就不可能对这种善意无知无觉。我们很少有人能在为别人做好事的同时自己却毫无所获。每次简去陪伴奈特老太太，后者总会在陪伴结束时给她点“小费”，而简也总是乐意接受。在一封给卡桑德拉的信中，简说爱德华哥哥给了她和范妮一人五镑。五镑给一个还没长大的女儿是个可爱的小礼物，给家庭女教师是仁慈，给妹妹就是居高临下了。

我很肯定奈特太太、布里奇夫人、爱德华和他妻子都对简很好，都喜欢她，他们怎么可能不呢，但他们仍有可能觉得这两个妹妹是达不到上流社会的标准的，如此假设并非不合理。姐妹俩都很土气。十八世纪时，那些从没离开过乡村和那些每年至少在伦敦住些时日的人之间仍有很大差距，这个差距给喜剧作家们提供了最丰富的创作素材。《傲慢与偏见》中，宾利姐妹鄙视班尼特姐妹的不时髦；可另一方面，伊丽莎白·班尼特也觉得她们做作，对此很不耐烦。实际上班尼特姐妹比奥斯汀姐妹的社会地位还高一个等级，因为班尼特先生虽不富裕，却拥有土地，而尊敬的乔治·奥斯汀却只是个贫穷的乡村牧师。

如果说这样的家教，造成简在肯特郡的贵族淑女们眼中稍微缺了点文雅，那也不算什么稀奇。如果简确实如此，而这又逃过了范妮敏锐的眼睛，我们可以肯定范妮的妈妈也会予以指出。简为人坦率直言，我敢说她经常放纵她率直的幽默感，令那些毫无幽默感的女士无法欣赏。如果她告诉她们她在信里写给卡桑德拉的那些话，说她对谁是通奸女有很强的鉴别能力，那我们大可想象这些女士的尴尬。简生于一七七五年，离《汤姆·琼斯》的出版只不过过去了二十五年，没理由假设在这期间农村的风气就大变了。简的行为举止很可能就像纳奇布尔夫人五十年后说的那样，“远不及上流社会的标准”。从纳奇布尔夫人所说的话进行判断，简去坎特伯雷和奈特太太做伴时，老太太可能暗示过她怎样的行为举止才能让她显得更“文雅”些。很可能正因如此，她才在小说里如此重视良好的教养。今天，像她一样写同一阶层的小说家们可能早就把这点看成理所当然了。就我个人而言，我看不出纳奇布尔夫人的信有何不妥。她的话自笔端“自动前来，告知真相”。这又怎么了？如果有人猜测简说话带有汉普郡口音，举止缺乏某种文雅，穿着家里做的衣服，品味很差，我也丝毫不觉得被冒犯。我们确实从卡罗琳·奥斯汀(9)的《回忆录》中得知，她家人都认为，姐妹俩虽然对穿着很感兴趣，穿得却并不好，但是没说到底是土气还是不合适。写过回忆简·奥斯汀文章的家里人也都小心翼翼地对此赋予比事实更多的社会意义，但这是不必要的。简·奥斯汀一家是值得尊敬的、诚实的好人，属于中上阶层的边缘。如果她家的地位能更稳固些，他们说不定就不那么在意自己的阶层了。正如纳奇布尔夫人所说，奥斯汀姐妹和她们身边最常交往的那些人在一起时很轻松，而那些人在纳奇布尔夫人看来是绝对不属于上层社会的。当姐妹俩面对出身更高的人，比如宾利姐妹这样的时髦女人时，出于自我保护的原因，她们会采取一种批判的态度。我们对乔治·奥斯汀牧师一无所知。他妻子似乎是个好女人，但是有点蠢，还老受疾病困扰，女儿们对她的病看起来既善加照顾，又不乏嘲讽。她活到了差不多九十岁的年纪。儿子们在步入社会前大概沉浸于乡村所能提供的那些享乐之中，如果能借到马，他们会去骑马纵狗打猎。

奥斯汀—雷(10)是第一个替简·奥斯汀作传的人。他书里有一段话，再加点想象，我们可以从中得知简在汉普郡度过的漫长安静的岁月是一种什么样的生活。他说：“可以说，当时有一个普遍的情况是，留给仆人去处理和执行的事比现在少，男女主人亲自去做和监督的事比现在多。关于女主人，我相信普遍认为……她们会亲自参与高级些的烹饪，参与家酿葡萄酒，以及蒸馏药草以制作家用药物的活计……女士们不会轻视纺线的营生，因为家用的亚麻布就是这么织出来的。早餐和茶点后，有些女士喜欢亲自动手洗濯她们的高级瓷器。”从书信中也可得知，奥斯汀家有时连一个仆人都没有，有时只能勉强用一个什么都不懂的小丫头。卡桑德拉做饭，不是因为女士们“留给仆人处理和执行的事少”，而是因为根本就没有仆人做饭。奥斯汀家既不穷也不富。奥斯汀太太和女儿们穿的大部分衣服都是自己做的，女儿们还给哥哥做衬衫。她们自己在家做蜂蜜酒，火腿也是奥斯汀太太熏的。快乐很简单，最兴奋的事就是那些有钱的邻居开舞会。在英国，在那遥远的过去，数百个家庭就过着这样安详、单调和朴实的生活，而其中的一个家庭居然就莫名其妙地诞生了一个天赋异禀的小说家，这难道不是奇事一桩吗？

3

简为人真实。她年轻时爱跳舞、调情和演戏。她喜欢相貌英俊的年轻男子。她对衣服、帽子和围巾有着强烈的兴趣。她善针线，“一般活计和绣花”都行，这一定让她受益匪浅，因为她改过旧长袍，也曾用半条不要的裙子做过帽子。她哥哥亨利在《回忆录》中说：“但凡用手指做的事，简·奥斯汀都能做得很成功。玩挑棒游戏时，我们谁都没法像她似的能把棒撒得那么圆，或者像她似的手那么稳地把棒抽出来。她的杯球(11)表演也堪称神奇。我们在查顿玩的是那种简单的杯球，我们知道她有一回玩的时候曾经连续接球一百次，直到手都酸了。她有时眼睛疲劳，没法长时间读书写作时，会从这个简单的游戏中寻找消遣。”

真是一幅迷人的画面。

没人会把简·奥斯汀说成是个女学究，她对这种类型的女人没什么好感，但是她也明显不是那种没文化的妇女。事实上，她受到的教育就是她那个时代、她那种社会地位的女性都会受到的教育。研究她小说的权威学者查普曼博士根据已知她读过的书列过一个书单，结果很惊人。她当然是读小说的，比如范妮·伯尼、埃奇沃思小姐和拉德克利夫夫人的小说，包括《奥多芙的秘密》。她还读从法语和德语翻译过来的小说，比如歌德的《少年维特之烦恼》。除此之外，只要是能从巴斯和南安普敦的租书铺租到的小说，都在她的书单上。但是她不只对小说感兴趣，她还熟知莎士比亚的作品。当代作家中，她读司各特和拜伦的作品，但她最喜欢的诗人似乎是考珀。这很自然，考珀的诗冷静、优雅、明智，是会吸引到她的。她还读约翰逊和鲍斯威尔的作品，读很多历史书籍，还有各种类型的文学作品。她喜欢朗读，她的声音据说很悦耳。

她还读布道词，尤其喜欢十七世纪一位名叫舍洛克的牧师写的布道词。这事初听似乎令人惊讶，但其实也没什么大不了的。我幼时曾在乡间的一处牧师居所生活过，那里的书房架子上就塞满了装帧精良的布道集。如果布道词能出版，说明它们卖得掉，既然卖得掉，就说明有人读。简·奥斯汀信神而不虔信。当然，她周日去教堂，领圣餐。而且毫无疑问，不管是在史蒂文顿，还是在哥德莫山姆，每日晨昏，奥斯汀一家一定都会共诵祈祷词。但是，正如查普曼博士所说：“这已然不是一个宗教狂热的时代。”正如我们今天每天洗澡，早晚刷牙，不如此就觉得难受一样。我想，对简·奥斯汀和与她同时代的大多数人而言，既然已经用恰当的热情履行了宗教职责，那就可以把与宗教有关的问题放到一边了。就像我们会把一件暂时无用的衣服放到一边一样，把宗教放到一边可以让她在一天和一周剩下的时间里，全心全意、问心无愧地照顾俗事。“福音教派还未形成。”绅士之家早为小儿子安排好了生计，办法就是让他领圣职，给他一份薪俸。他内心是否受到神的召唤是不重要的，但他住的房子应该宽敞方便，他的收入应该恰如其分，这才是最重要的。一个人既领了圣职，就该履行职责。简·奥斯汀当然相信牧师“应该住在他的教民中间，通过对教民的持续关注，证明自己是他们的祝福者和好朋友”。因为她哥哥亨利就是这样做的。亨利机智活泼，是她众多兄弟中最聪明的一个。他曾经经商，有些年还发了大财，但是最后破了产，领了圣职，成了一名模范的教区牧师。

简·奥斯汀对事物的看法与当时的主流观点无异，从其小说和书信中可以得知，她对社会现状是满意的。她毫不怀疑社会应该分阶级，觉得人分穷富是自然的事情。年轻人靠有权势的朋友在为国王服务的事业中得到提升也是正确而合理的。女人的职责就是结婚，当然结婚是为了爱，可是其他条件也得令人满意。这是天下事的正常秩序，没有迹象表明简·奥斯汀认为这其中有任何值得反对的东西。她在给卡桑德拉的一封信中说：“卡洛和他妻子在朴次茅斯过着那里所能想象到的最隐秘的生活，他们连一个仆人都没有。那个女人得多有道德才能答应结这种婚啊！”范妮·普莱斯(12)家之所以生活在粗俗肮脏的环境里，皆因她母亲不谨慎的婚姻导致，这个直观的教训说明一个年轻女子在婚姻之事上应该多多慎重才对。

4

奥斯汀的小说纯属娱乐性小说。如果你碰巧相信娱乐应该是小说家的主要任务，那你必须把她放到一个单独的类别。比她的小说伟大的作品也有，比如《战争与和平》和《卡拉马佐夫兄弟》，但你读这些作品时必须头脑清楚警醒才能获益。可是哪怕你再疲乏沮丧，读简·奥斯汀的小说都可以让你入迷。

她写作的时代认为女人写作不像话。芒克·刘易斯说：“我对所有女性涂鸦者都有一种讨厌、怜悯和鄙视。她们应该拿的工具不是笔，而是针。针才是她们唯一能熟练操作的工具。”小说这种文学形式并不被尊重，令简·奥斯汀相当震惊的是，诗人司各特爵士竟然也写小说。她“小心地不让她做的事被仆人、客人或除家人以外的任何人怀疑到。她在很小的纸上写，为的是小纸容易收走，或容易用吸墨纸盖上。她家前门和书房之间有扇推拉门，开门时会发出吱嘎声，但她不让人修理这点小毛病，为的就是如果有人来了，这声音会提示她赶快把东西收起来”。她大哥詹姆斯甚至从来都没有告诉他当时还在学校读书的儿子，他读得津津有味的那些书是简姑姑写的。她另外一个哥哥亨利也在《回忆录》中说：“假如她还活着，任何名望的累加都不会诱使她把名字附加到出自她笔下的任何一部作品上。”因此她出版的第一本小说《理智与情感》的扉页上仅仅注明作者是“一位女士”。

《理智与情感》并非简·奥斯汀的处女作，她的处女作叫《第一印象》。她父亲曾写信给一个出版商，问能否出版“一部手稿，是本小说，分三卷，长度类似伯尼小姐的《埃弗莱娜》”，还说出版费用作者可以自付，或采用其他形式。但回信拒绝了这一提议。《第一印象》的写作开始于一七九六年冬，完成于一七九七年八月。一般认为，这本书基本上就是十六年后出版的《傲慢与偏见》。之后，简·奥斯汀又很快连续写了《理智与情感》和《诺桑觉寺》，但运气不好，直到五年后一个名叫理查德·克罗斯比的人才花十镑买了当时叫《苏珊》的《诺桑觉寺》。书他一直未出版，最后又用原价卖给了奥斯汀家。因为简·奥斯汀的小说都是匿名出版，因此他不知道他为了这么一点钱就卖掉的那本书的作者其实和《傲慢与偏见》的作者是同一个人，是那位极受大众欢迎的成功作家。从一七九八年写完《诺桑觉寺》到一八〇九年，简·奥斯汀似乎写得很少，只写了一个名叫《沃森家》的片段。对一个如此富有创造力的作家来说，这段沉默实在太久，原因据说是有一桩恋情占据了她的注意力，使她无暇他顾。据说，当时她和母亲、姐姐在德文郡的一个海边度假地休养，“她认识了一名绅士，那人的相貌、头脑和教养都很出众，卡桑德拉觉得他配得上她妹妹，也有可能赢得她妹妹的爱。他们告别时，他表达了希望能很快再见的愿望，卡桑德拉觉得他的动机很明显，但他们再也没能相见。很快，她们就听说他突然死了。”这段相识时间很短，《回忆录》的作者说他无法判断“她的感情是否已经达到了某种程度，以致影响到了她的幸福”。我并不认为有影响。我也不认为奥斯汀能很深地爱上谁。如果她能，她就会给她的女主人公们以更温暖的情感，但事实并非如此。她们的爱里没有激情，她们的意愿都被谨慎调和，被常识控制，而真爱是与这些可估量的品质无关的。以《劝导》为例，简·奥斯汀说安妮·艾略特和温特沃思二人彼此深爱，可我却觉得她骗了自己，也骗了读者。对温特沃思而言，那无疑是司汤达所说的“激情之爱”，但在安妮这一方，却是司汤达说的“得体之爱”。他们先是订婚，然后安妮允许自己听信那个爱管闲事的势利眼罗素夫人的劝告，认为嫁给一个穷人，一个有可能死于战争的海军军官，是不谨慎的。假如她是真的深爱温特沃思，她当然就会愿意去冒险。而且这也不是多大的险，因为她一结婚就会获得她母亲留给她的那份遗产，足足有三千多镑，等于今天的一万两千多镑。所以无论如何她都不会不名一文。她还可以像本威克上校和哈格雷夫斯小姐那对儿一样，先跟温特沃思订婚，等他有了指挥权能娶她的时候再结婚。可安妮却解除了婚约，因为她听了罗素夫人的劝，认为如果再等等的话，她还能找到更合适的人。直到没有一个追求者是她想嫁的人时，她才发现自己原来深爱着温特沃思。我们可以相当肯定，简·奥斯汀认为安妮的行为是自然而合理的。

关于简·奥斯汀长时间的沉默，最合理的解释是她找不着出版商，因此感到受挫。家人听她朗读自己的作品，都认为她的小说很好，但她这个人非常谦虚，而且很明智，她很可能认为他们之所以喜欢她的作品，只是因为他们喜欢她这个人，他们还很可能精明地知道她人物的原型是谁。《回忆录》的作者坚决否认她的人物有原型，查普曼博士似乎赞成这种看法。老实说，他们在为简·奥斯汀争取一种令人难以置信的创造力。所有的伟大作家——司汤达和巴尔扎克，托尔斯泰和屠格涅夫，狄更斯和萨克雷——都有人物所本的原型。简·奥斯汀确实说过：“我太骄傲于我的绅士们，我不愿承认他们只不过是A先生和B上校。”这里的关键词是“只不过”。和所有小说家一样，尽管某个真人给了她创作人物的灵感，但只要她的想象力已经在这个人物身上发挥了作用，那他就无论如何都成了她的创造，但这不等于说这个人物不是从A先生或B上校那里进化来的。

不管怎样，一八〇九年简·奥斯汀同母亲和姐姐定居于安静的查顿，开始着手修改旧手稿，一八一一年《理智与情感》终于出版了。此时女人写作已经不再是件见不得人的事。司布真教授在皇家文学院所做的关于简·奥斯汀的讲座中，引用了伊莱莎·菲所作的《印度来信》的序言。这位女士一七八二年曾被督促出版这部通信集，但因舆论反感“女性写作”，她只得拒绝。但在一八一六年她写道：“从那以后，公众的情绪及其发展已经逐渐起了相当大的变化，现在我们不仅像以前一样有不少为巾帼增光的女性文学人物，我们也有了一些毫不做作的女性。她们勇敢驾驶小船，到那浩瀚大海上扬帆远航去了，不惧那曾经伴随远航而来的批评的风浪，娱乐或教诲就是在这样的航行中被传达给了阅读公众。”

《傲慢与偏见》出版于一八一三年，简·奥斯汀把这本书的版权卖了一百一十镑。

除了上文提到的三部小说，简·奥斯汀还写了另外三部小说：《曼斯菲尔德庄园》、《爱玛》和《劝导》。她的文名虽然建立在这仅有的几本书上，但坚实稳固。她虽然等了很久小说才得以出版，但一经出版，她迷人的才华就立刻得到了认可，之后连最显赫的人物也都开始一致赞美她。我只引用沃尔特·司各特爵士的话，他的慷慨措辞很具代表性：“那位年轻女士在描绘日常生活中的纠葛、感情和人物方面，极具才能，是我所遇到的人中最突出的。粗糙的模仿我也会，谁都会，但是那种因为描写和情感的真实，使得寻常人、事都变得有趣的精妙笔法，却是我做不到的。”

奇怪的是，这位年轻女士最宝贵的一项才能司各特爵士却没说。她的观察确实透彻，她的情感也非常丰沛，但是让她的观察显得中肯，给了她的情感以活力的，是她的幽默。她的作品题材狭窄，所有作品写的其实都是同一类型的故事。她作品中的人物类型也不算丰富，基本都大同小异，只是变换了观察角度而已。她极有自知之明，没有人比她更清楚自己的局限所在。她的生活经历仅限于乡村社会的一个小圈子，她很满足于处理这样的题材，她只写她熟悉的东西。正如查普曼博士最初指出的那样，她从不曾试图再现男人们单独相处时的对话，因为就事实而言，她是不可能听到这些对话的。

有一点已经被大家注意到，就是她虽然经历了世界历史上最激动人心的一些大事，如法国革命、恐怖统治、拿破仑的崛起与败落，她在小说中却对此只字不提。为此她受到指责，说她过分冷漠。但是应该记住，在她那个时代，女人过分关注政治是没教养的表现，政治是男人该管的事，女人甚至都很少读报。不过我们没理由假设：因为她不写这些事，她就不受政治的影响。她很爱她的家人。她有一兄一弟都在海军，经常身处危险之中，她的信件表明她很关心他们。她不写这些事难道不正说明她明智吗？她很谦虚，不觉得她死后还会有人读她的小说。假如这真是她的目的，那她不写这些事就太明智了，因为从文学的角度看，这些事的吸引力不会持久。早几年写“二战”的那些小说现在不是早就过时了吗？这些小说就像日复一日告诉我们当天发生了什么事的报纸一样昙花一现。

大多数小说家写东西都是有好有坏。简·奥斯汀是我知道的唯一例外，她证明了一个道理，即只有平庸之辈才始终维持在同一水准——平庸的水准，而她却从来都不会太偏离自己的最高水准。即使《理智与情感》与《诺桑觉寺》中有许多可指摘之处，但还是让人喜欢的地方多。简·奥斯汀其他的小说也都有热烈的甚至狂热的崇拜者。麦考利(13)认为《曼斯菲尔德庄园》是简·奥斯汀最好的作品；另一些同样著名的读者喜欢《爱玛》；狄士累利(14)读过十七遍《傲慢与偏见》；今天则有人认为《劝导》是简·奥斯汀最精妙的小说。我想绝大多数读者会认为《傲慢与偏见》是她最杰出的作品，在这种情况下，我认为不如接受他们的判断。一本书是否能成为经典，不在于评论家的赞美、教授的解读和学校的研究，而是一代接一代、数量众多的读者能否从中获得乐趣和精神的益处。

我个人认为《傲慢与偏见》是简·奥斯汀所有小说里最令人满意的一本。开篇的第一句话就让人感到痛快：“有一个真理举世皆知，那就是一个有钱的单身汉一定缺个太太。”这话为全书定了调，它所引起的好心情会一直陪伴你读到最后一页，然后你会遗憾这本书居然就这么完了。《爱玛》是简·奥斯汀的小说里唯一让我觉得太过冗长的一部。我对弗兰克·丘吉尔和简·费尔法克斯的恋爱实在不感兴趣。贝茨小姐是好玩，可也未免写得太多了。女主人公是个势利眼，她对那些她认为社会地位低于她的人的那种居高临下的态度真令人作呕。但是我们千万不能指责简·奥斯汀，我们必须记住我们今天读的和她当日的读者读的不是同一本书。风俗和教养的改变使得我们的世界观发生了巨大转变。在某些事上我们比祖先更狭隘，在某些事上更自由。一百年前还很普遍的一种态度，今天却会让我们感到不安。我们通过先入之见和我们自己的行为标准来判断我们所读的书，这不公平，却也不可避免。《曼斯菲尔德庄园》的男女主人公，埃德蒙和范妮，都是令人难以忍受的道学先生，我全部的同情心反而都给了寡廉鲜耻、活泼迷人的亨利和玛丽·克劳福德。我不明白为什么托马斯·伯特伦爵士从海外归来看见家人排戏自娱会勃然大怒。因为奥斯汀本人是非常喜欢家庭演剧的，因此我们不明白她为什么会觉得伯特伦的愤怒是合理的。《劝导》有种罕见的魅力，虽然我们可能希望安妮能少讲求点实际，多点无私，多点冲动，也就是能不那么像老处女似的古板拘谨。要不是因为莱姆里吉斯港口科布码头上的那档子事，我简直都要认为《劝导》是简·奥斯汀六本书中最完美的一本了。简·奥斯汀本就不善于虚构特殊事件，因此这事在我看是个异常笨拙的设计。路易莎·马斯格罗夫跑上几级很陡的台阶，想要跳下来给她的爱慕者温特沃思上校接住。他没接住，她撞到头，昏了过去。我们被告知他是习惯这样接她的，而假如他真要伸手接她，那么即使那时的码头比现在高一倍，也顶多是离地六英尺，她既然是跳下去的，就不可能磕到头。无论如何，她只会跳到这个魁梧的海军军官身上，虽然有可能震一下，吓一跳，但是不可能受伤。可是，她竟然昏迷了，而接下来的慌乱更令人难以置信。打过仗、因赏金发了财的温特沃思上校居然吓瘫了，所有相关人等的反应也都如此白痴，我简直难以相信一向以冷静和坚强对待亲朋好友的疾病与死亡的简·奥斯汀，居然不觉得这个场面极其不合理。

博学机智的评论家加罗德教授说简·奥斯汀不会写故事，“故事”的意思是说一系列发生的事，或者浪漫，或者不寻常。但这不是简·奥斯汀的才能所在，也不是她想做的事。她太理智，她的幽默太活泼，以至于她无法浪漫。而且她感兴趣的不是“不寻常”，而是“寻常”，只不过她用她敏锐的观察、嘲讽和活泼的机智使得寻常也不寻常起来。说到故事，我们大多数人的意思都是指一个前后连贯、首尾相接的叙述，有开头、中间和结尾。《傲慢与偏见》的头开得恰到好处：两个年轻人上场了，他们对伊丽莎白·班尼特和她姐姐简的爱给小说提供了情节，结尾也结得恰到好处：他们结婚了。这是传统的大团圆结局。这种结尾常常受到那些久经世故的人嘲弄。的确，很多婚姻，也许是大多数婚姻，并不幸福。结婚并不能成为任何事的结局，它只不过开启了另一种经验。于是很多作家写小说都从结婚写起，写婚姻的结果，这是他们的权利。但是简单的人把婚姻看成小说的一种满意的结局也还是有其原因的，因为他们有种直觉，认为男女通过婚配满足了生物功能。他们自然会对达到这一圆满的中间过程感兴趣，比如最初如何爱上，后来如何出现障碍、误解，再后来如何山盟海誓。圆满之后，大家的兴趣又转向结果，即男女结合的产物，也就是即将接续他们的后代。对自然而言，每对夫妇都只是这链条上的一环，他们唯一的重要性就在于可以给这链条再添一环。小说家写大团圆结局的理由就在于此。在《傲慢与偏见》里，读者如果知道新郎收入丰厚，将要带领新娘入住豪宅，而豪宅周围有庄园围绕，内部则到处摆满昂贵优雅的家具，那么读者的满意度会有相当程度的提升。

《傲慢与偏见》是一本情节结构精良的书。事情一件接一件地自然发生，无一处让人觉得不合理。不过有一点令人感到奇怪，即伊丽莎白和简的教养、举止良好，可她们的妈妈和三个妹妹却如纳奇布尔夫人说的那样，“远远低于上流社会及其方式的标准”。但是事情必须这样安排，这对故事至关重要。我允许自己好奇：为什么简·奥斯汀不避开这块绊脚石，把伊丽莎白和简写成是班尼特先生第一次婚姻所生，把现在的班尼特太太和三个小女儿写成是二婚的妻女？简·奥斯汀在她所有的女主角里最喜欢伊丽莎白。她说：“我必须承认，我认为，有史以来所有出版的书里的人物有多么令人愉快，伊丽莎白就有多么令人愉快。”假如像某些人以为的那样，她自己就是伊丽莎白的原型，那她就把自己的快活、神采、勇气、机智、敏捷、良好的判断力以及正确的情感都给了伊丽莎白，同时也就不难判断那个安静、和善、美丽的简就是她姐姐卡桑德拉了。达西通常被看作一个可怕的下流坯，他的第一宗罪是他和一群人一起去了一个公共舞会，他却不愿和他不认识也不想认识的人跳舞。这倒也不是多大的罪。伊丽莎白不幸听到了他对宾利说的贬低她的话，但是达西不知道伊丽莎白在听，他可以为自己脱罪，谁让他的朋友非让他做他不想做的事呢。他向伊丽莎白求婚时的确带有一种不可原谅的傲慢，但他这人的性格主要就是骄傲，对自身出身和地位的骄傲，没有了这点，故事也就无从谈起了。而且，他的求婚态度也给了简·奥斯汀机会，展现了全书最充满戏剧性的一幕。可以想象，若是有了后来积累的写作经验，简·奥斯汀将会更恰当地描写达西的态度——非常自然、容易理解的态度，既能引起伊丽莎白的反感，又不用让达西说出那么无礼的话而招致读者的震惊。对凯瑟琳夫人和柯林斯先生的描写可能有些夸张，但在我看来也没有超出喜剧的范围。喜剧看到的生活比日常生活更闪亮，也更冷淡。带点夸张的笔触，也就是闹剧的笔触，通常也不是什么坏事。小心地混杂点闹剧，正如在草莓上撒点糖一样，说不定可以使喜剧性更加“浓郁”。至于凯瑟琳夫人，我们不妨记住，在简·奥斯汀的时代，贵族头衔使其拥有者在面对社会地位低下之人时心生一种极大的优越感。他们不光期待后者对他们抱以最大的尊敬，而且他们也的确得到了后者这样的尊敬。我年轻时认识的某些贵妇，她们那种自以为是的劲儿虽然不至于像凯瑟琳夫人一样露骨，却也相差不远。至于柯林斯，哪怕是今天，谁还不认识几个这样既谄媚逢迎又自高自大的人呢？他们现在学会了装出一副亲切的面孔掩饰这一点，这只能令其更加可憎。

简·奥斯汀不是个伟大的文体学家，但她写得平实不做作，我想约翰逊博士对她的影响可以在她的句子结构中体现出来。她喜欢用拉丁词，不喜欢用平凡的英语词汇。这让她的措辞稍稍带上了一点正式感，但这绝不会令人不愉快，因为它经常会给一句诙谐的话语增添了深意，或给一句恶毒的话语增添了庄重的味道。她笔下的对话可能就像那个时代真正的对话那样自然，虽然在我们看来，可能会觉得这种对话未免僵硬。简·班尼特在说到她恋人的姐妹时，这样说：“她们当然并不支持我与他结交，对此我并不吃惊，因为他本可以在很多方面做出更为有利的选择。”这当然有可能就是她实际会说的话，但我还是觉得那样说话太难以想像了。很明显，现代小说家不会再如此遣词造句了。一字不差地把真实对话笔录下来是很沉闷的，做点改编反而是合理的。相比而言，只是在近些年，小说家们为了追求效果逼真，才开始努力把对话写得尽量口语化。我怀疑让受过教育的人说话时运用排比和对称，语法还要准确，这只是过去的做法，实际上这些人不可能掌握得了这些技巧，我猜读者们已经把这个当成自然而然的事了。

如此一来，虽然简·奥斯汀小说中的对话总有点像书面语，我们必须承认她总是能令她书中的人物说出与本人个性相符的话来。我只记得她出过一次错：“安妮微笑了一下，说：‘我心目中的好伙伴，艾略特先生，是那些聪明多知、谈话丰富之人，我管这样的人叫好伙伴。’‘你错了，’他温和地说，‘这不是好伙伴，这是最好的伙伴。’”

艾略特先生的性格是有缺陷的。但他能如此绝妙地回答安妮，他就一定有一些奥斯汀认为不适合让读者知道的品质。就我个人而言，我非常为这一回答所喜，我宁愿让安妮嫁给他，也不愿让她嫁给那位沉闷无趣的温特沃思。艾略特确实曾为钱跟一个“身份卑微”的女人结了婚，婚后又怠慢了她，他对史密斯太太的态度也很不厚道，但我们毕竟只有女方的一面之词，我们如果有机会知道他的解释，说不定会觉得他的行为是可以原谅的。

简·奥斯汀有一个优点，我几乎都忘了提，那就是她非常好读，比某些更伟大、更有名的小说家都好读。正如司各特所说，她写的是寻常事，是“日常生活中的纠葛、感情和人物”；因此她的书里几乎无事发生，但是当你读完一页的时候，你会急着翻到下一页，想知道下边发生了什么，还是没发生什么，你还是会急切地翻到下一页。能做到这一点的小说家已经具备了小说家所能拥有的最宝贵的天赋了。

(1) “克雷”的英文原文是Clay，意思是泥土，似乎暗示律师身份的卑微。

(2) 这是旧时英国贵族和乡绅阶层的教子习惯，年轻人到了二十一岁的法定成年年纪后，会到欧陆各地游学一番，算是一场教育上的成人礼。

(3) 纪德（1869—1951），法国作家，代表作有《窄门》《人间食粮》《背德者》。克洛岱尔（1868—1955），法国诗人、剧作家、外交家，曾因外交工作清末时在上海和福州逗留过十四年。

(4) 指燕尾服的尾巴。

(5) 伊莱莎（1761—1813），奥斯汀的姑表姐，生于印度，人生经历丰富。第一次结婚嫁给了一名法国军官，成了伯爵夫人。法国大革命期间，其夫命丧断头台。第二次结婚，伊莱莎嫁给了小她十岁的表弟，即奥斯汀的哥哥亨利。伊莱莎和奥斯汀关系亲密，启发了奥斯汀以她为原型创作了很多人物形象。

(6) “艾尔蒙格”英文原文是Iremonger，ire是“怒火”之意，monger意思是“制造者、贩卖者、兜售者”。

(7) “布兰特”英文原文是Blunt，意思是“迟钝、呆笨、生硬、直率”。这两个人的名字出现在“美人”这句的上下文里越显讽刺。

(8) 原文是“斜体”，因斜体在中文行文中看不清楚，因此此处改为画线。

(9) 奥斯汀的侄女。

(10) 奥斯汀的侄子。

(11) 一种小孩游戏，在西班牙语国家最为盛行，十九世纪早期也一度在英国流行。游戏用具是木柄上有一到两个杯子，木柄上连线，线上系一个球。玩游戏时参与者需手握木柄，用臂力奋力把球抛起，再立刻用杯去接球。文中所谓简单的杯球，应该是指木柄只带一个杯子与球。

(12) 简·奥斯汀小说《曼斯菲尔德庄园》的女主人公。

(13) 麦考利（1800—1859），英国历史学家。

(14) 狄士累利（1804—1881），犹太后裔，曾两度出任英国首相，是维多利亚时期最重要的政治家之一，还是名相当多产的小说家。

查尔斯·狄更斯与《大卫·科波菲尔》

1

查尔斯·狄更斯虽然身量不高，但却仪态大方，相貌讨人喜欢。他二十七岁时由麦克利斯画的那张肖像现藏于英国国家肖像美术馆。画中的他坐在写字台前的一把漂亮椅子里，一只优雅的小手轻放在一部手稿的上面。他穿得隆重，系了个极宽大的绸缎颈巾，褐色的头发自然拳曲，垂在脸颊两侧，刚好盖住耳朵。他的眼睛长得很好，眼里那种深思的表情正是崇拜他的公众所期待的，一个成功的年轻作家应有的样子。画作没表现出的是那些与他有接触的人在他脸上看到的那种活力、炯炯的眼神，以及他心灵和头脑的活动。他一直都有点花花公子的派头，年轻时喜欢穿天鹅绒的外衣和华丽的马甲，系彩色的颈巾，戴白色的帽子，可他从来都没能达到他想达到的那种效果。人们惊讶甚至震惊于他的穿着，认为那既草率又俗丽。

狄更斯的祖父威廉·狄更斯开始是个仆人，娶了个女仆，最后成了克鲁堂的管家，克鲁堂是切斯特城议员约翰·克鲁的家宅。威廉·狄更斯有两个儿子：威廉和约翰，与我们有关的是约翰，首先因为他是英国最伟大的小说家的父亲。其次，因为他是他儿子创造出的最伟大的人物麦考伯的原型。威廉·狄更斯死后，他的遗孀继续在克鲁堂当管家，终于在三十五年的服务后拿着一笔退休金退休了。可能是想离两个儿子近点，她住到了伦敦。克鲁家供她两个丧父的儿子受教育，并给他们提供了生计。他们给约翰在海军出纳室找了个职位，他和那里同为文员的一个同事结交起来，并且很快娶了那人的妹妹伊丽莎白·巴罗。从结婚开始，他似乎就有财务上的麻烦，总是找人借钱，任何人只要蠢到肯借给他，他都借。但是他心地善良，使钱慷慨，他不傻，工作也勤奋，虽然他的勤奋只是一阵阵的。他还极嗜好酒，因为他第二次被捕就是由于欠债被一个葡萄酒商控告了。晚年的他被描述为一个讲究穿戴的老花花公子，永远都在抚摸他怀表上系着的那一大串印章。

查尔斯·狄更斯是约翰和伊丽莎白的第一个儿子，但是是他们的第二个孩子，他一八一二年出生于波特西。两年后他父亲被调到伦敦，三年后又调动到查塔姆。小查尔斯就在查塔姆入学读书。他父亲有几本藏书：《汤姆·琼斯》《威克菲尔德牧师》《吉尔·布拉斯》《堂吉诃德》《蓝登传》《佩雷格林·皮克尔传》，查尔斯·狄更斯把它们读了又读。他自己的小说显示出那些小说对他的影响是多么巨大、持久。

一八二二年，已经有了五个孩子的约翰·狄更斯把家搬回了伦敦。查尔斯被留在了查塔姆，为的是继续上学，几个月后他才和家人团聚。团聚时他发现他们住在伦敦城郊的卡姆登镇，那个房子后来被他当成麦考伯的家写进了小说。约翰·狄更斯此时虽然一年能挣三百多镑，价值相当于今天的四倍之多，但他明显处于比以往更加绝望的窘迫之中，似乎没钱送小查尔斯回学校继续读书了。更令小查尔斯憎恶的是，他被要求看孩子、擦鞋、刷衣服，帮狄更斯太太从查塔姆带来的女仆干家务。得闲的时候他在“被田野和水渠围绕的荒凉之地”卡姆登镇晃荡，也在附近的萨默斯镇和肯特镇闲逛，有时跑得更远，甚至发现了苏活和莱姆豪斯(1)。

家里的情形愈发坏了，于是狄更斯太太决定开设一间学校，招收父母住在印度的孩子。可能是从婆婆那里借了钱，她印了准备分发的传单，派孩子们塞到邻居的信箱里。结果当然没有一个学生上门，同时债务问题变得越来越紧迫。查尔斯被派去典当家里一切还能换钱的物件。那些书，那些对他来说意义深远、无比宝贵的书都被卖掉了。然后詹姆斯·拉默特，狄更斯太太的一个远房姻亲，给查尔斯找了一份工作，让他在自己有一半产权的鞋油厂里打工，每周可以挣六先令。狄更斯的父母千恩万谢地接受了这个安排，却把少年狄更斯伤到了痛处，因为他发现父母居然可以如此如释重负地将他脱手。他那时十二岁。此后不久，约翰·狄更斯因欠债被关进了马夏尔西监狱，他妻子则典当了最后一点能典当的东西，带着孩子们去监狱和他会合了。当时的监狱肮脏拥挤，卫生条件极差，因为坐监的不光有犯人，还有他们的家属。如果愿意，犯人们是可以带家属一起蹲监狱的，但我不知道他们被允许这样做是为了缓解监狱生活的困苦，还是因为那些可怜的家属反正也无处可去。如果欠债者有钱，他所需忍受的最大的不便就是失去自由，在某些情况下，就连这个损失也可以得到缓解。某些特殊的犯人如能遵守某些规定，还大可不住在监狱里。以前，监狱长经常勒索犯人，还野蛮残酷地对待犯人。但是到约翰·狄更斯入狱的时候，那些最恶劣的勒索、虐待犯人的刑法已经被废除了，他能使自己过得足够舒服。他家那个忠诚的小女仆住在监狱外，每天进监狱来给他做饭带孩子。他仍然每周挣六镑，但他根本不想还钱。可以推测，他满足于住在债主够不着的地方，并不特别想被释放。在狱中，他很快就恢复了过来。其他欠债人“推举他做掌管狱内经济的委员会的主席”，很快，从看守到最令人讨厌的犯人，他和每个人都搞好了关系。后来的传记作者们迷惑于一件事，即约翰·狄更斯居然能在蹲监狱的同时继续领薪水。唯一的解释就是政府职员是靠关系任命的，像欠债入狱这种事还没有严重到要部里采取激烈的举措停发他薪水的地步。

父亲入狱之初，查尔斯·狄更斯住在卡姆登镇，但是因为卡姆登镇离位于查令十字街附近的亨格福德码头的鞋油厂太远，于是约翰·狄更斯为他在马夏尔西监狱附近的南华克区的兰特街找了个住处，这样他就能和家人一起吃早晚饭了。他被分配干的活并不苦，只是洗瓶子、给瓶子贴标签、把瓶子系起来。一八二四年四月，威廉·狄更斯的太太、克鲁堂的老管家死了，把积蓄留给了两个儿子。约翰·狄更斯的债（被他哥哥）还清了，他重获了自由。他再一次和家人住到了卡姆登镇，也再一次回到了海军出纳室工作。查尔斯继续在工厂洗了一阵子瓶子，但是约翰·狄更斯和詹姆斯·拉默特吵了一架。“是在信上吵的，”查尔斯后来写道，“因为是我把我父亲的那封信带给他，造成了那场争吵的爆发。”詹姆斯·拉默特告诉查尔斯他父亲侮辱了自己，因此他必须得走。“怀着一种奇怪的、好似压抑的轻松，我回了家。”他妈妈试图让事情缓和下来，好使查尔斯能够保住这份工作和周薪，因为此时薪水已经涨到了七先令，而她非常需要这笔钱。查尔斯却因此永远都不原谅她。“我后来从来没有忘记，也不会和不能忘记，我母亲是如此想让我回去。”他说。但是约翰·狄更斯不同意，他把儿子送进了汉姆斯特德街的一所学校，这所学校有个堂皇的名字，叫“威灵顿堂学院”。查尔斯在那上了两年半学。

很难知道查尔斯·狄更斯到底在鞋油厂干了多久。他二月初到的那儿，六月又和家人回来了。表面看来，他在那待了不过四个月。但是鞋油厂给他留下了深刻的印象，他后来把这段经历看成奇耻大辱，以至于不忍提及。当他的好友和第一位传记作者约翰·福斯特偶然提及了一星半点时，狄更斯告诉他，他触碰到了一件令人非常痛苦的事，“即使是现在，”——二十五年后，“只要他还有记忆，他就无法忘怀。”

我们已经听惯了显赫的政治家和工业巨头们夸耀年轻时如何洗盘子、卖报纸，因此很难理解为什么查尔斯·狄更斯会把父母送他进鞋油厂看成他们给他造成的巨大伤害，看成一个需要他隐藏的耻辱的秘密。狄更斯是个快乐、淘气和机灵的孩子，对生活的阴暗一面已经有了很多了解，很小就目睹他父亲的得过且过把全家人害成了什么样。他们是穷人，过得也像穷人。在卡姆登镇时他被要求打扫擦洗，为了能吃上晚饭，他被派去典当衣服或饰品。他一定曾像所有孩子一样和别的孩子们在街上玩耍过，也曾像当时他那个阶层的所有男孩一样，到了一定年龄就去做工，工资还很不错。他一周挣六先令，很快涨到七先令，这至少等于今天的二十五到三十先令。在一段不太长的时间里他必须靠这笔钱养活自己，但是后来搬到马夏尔西监狱附近可以和家人一起吃早晚饭后，他就只需要自己负担午饭了。和他一起干活的男孩们都很友好，因此很难理解他为什么会觉得和他们交往是件丢人的事。他时不时被带到牛津街去见他祖母，不可能不知道她这辈子是个仆人。也可能约翰·狄更斯是个势利眼，毫无根据地夸过口，但是一个十二岁的男孩不太可能对社会阶层有太多认识。而且我们必须假设，如果狄更斯足够成熟，认为自己比其他的工厂小孩都高一个等级，那他也一定足够聪明，明白他的工资对家里来说是多么必要。我们还以为能挣工资会成为他一个骄傲的资本呢。

因此，我们可以假设，因为福斯特的发现，狄更斯写了这一段生活的自传，并给了福斯特，使我们得知了他生活中这段经历的细节。我怀疑当他的想象作用于他的回忆时，他就充满了对曾经的那个小男孩的同情，他就把痛苦、厌恶和屈辱都给了那个男孩，因为这是如今名利双收、受人爱戴的他认为如果他身处那个小男孩的位置将会感受到的东西。而当他运笔写下那个可怜男孩的孤独，写下他被他信任的人背叛时，一切都历历在目，他仁慈的心流血了，泪水打湿了他的双眼。我不认为他是在有意夸大，他是情不自禁地夸大。他的才华，或者说天才，就在于夸大。正是通过讲述和强调麦考伯性格中的喜剧因素，他才令读者发笑。也正是通过强化小耐尔缓慢衰弱过程中的悲怆，他才能令读者哭。他要是不能把他在鞋油厂度过的四个月写得如此令人感动，那他就不是他——一位那么了不起的小说家了。大家都知道，他在《大卫·科波菲尔》里把这段经历再次写了一遍，再次取得了令人撕心裂肺的效果。就我而言，我认为这段经历并不像多年后他既出名又体面，既是个社交人物又是个公众人物时，劝说自己相信的那样给他带来了那么多的痛苦。我更不信这事对他的工作和生活起到了决定性的影响，虽然很多传记家和评论家是这样认为的。

还在马夏尔西监狱的时候，约翰·狄更斯担心他作为债务未清者会失去他在海军出纳室的工作，于是他恳求他部门的头头，让他以健康不佳为由领取退休金。考虑到他工作了二十年和他的六个孩子，他最后被“同情地”准许每年领一百四十镑的退休金。这对像约翰·狄更斯这样的人来说远不够养家，他还得寻找其他方法增加收入。他会点速记，于是在和报社有点关系的内兄的帮助下，他找了份议会记者的工作。查尔斯·狄更斯则留在学校继续读书，直到他十五岁时去给一家律师事务所跑腿。这次查尔斯似乎不觉得有辱身份，他进入了我们现在叫作白领的阶层。几星期后，他父亲给他另找了一个活，让他在另一个律师事务所当文员，一周能挣十先令，后来涨到了十五先令。他觉得这种生活很沉闷，想要提升自己，就学了速记，一年半后就能胜任民事律师公会的主教法庭的速记员的工作。二十岁时，他已经获得了议会记录员的资格，并且很快赢得了“旁听席上最快、最准确之人”的名声。

与此同时，他爱上了一个银行职员的漂亮女儿玛丽亚·比德内尔。他们初见时查尔斯十七岁。玛丽亚是个轻浮、爱调情的年轻女子，她似乎给了他很多挑逗性的鼓励。他们之间甚至可能有过秘密婚约。她对自己有了个爱人的事觉得既好玩又高兴，但是查尔斯身无分文，她是绝不可能想要嫁给他的。两年后他们情断，二人以真正浪漫的方式归还了彼此的礼物和信件，查尔斯觉得自己的心都碎了。多年后他们再见时，玛丽亚·比德内尔已经结婚多年，她肥胖、平庸、愚蠢。她和著名的狄更斯先生和太太吃饭，于是她成了《小杜丽》中弗罗拉·芬奇的原型，早前她就当过《大卫·科波菲尔》中朵拉的原型。

为了离自己效力的报纸近点，查尔斯·狄更斯在河岸街旁那些肮脏的小巷子里找了个住处，但因为对住处不满，他很快又在弗尼沃旅社找了个没配置家具的房间。可他还没来得及采买家具，他父亲就又一次因欠债被捕了，查尔斯不得不出钱让他待在债务人拘留所(2)。“因为约翰·狄更斯将在一段时间内无法与家人团聚”，查尔斯只得又给家人租了个便宜的住处，自己则带着弟弟弗里德里克勉强住进了弗尼沃旅社那间“四楼后”的房间。“正因为他心胸宽广，使钱大方，似乎很会处理类似的困难，”后来为他作传的乌娜·蒲柏—亨尼斯在她写的那本很可读的传记里说，“他家，后来还有他太太家，那群没骨气的亲戚都指望着他给他们找钱找工作，正如每一个养家糊口的人要负担的那样。”

2

在下议院的旁听席上干了大约一年后，狄更斯开始写一系列伦敦生活的随笔。这些随笔的最初篇目发表在《月刊》上，后来的篇目发表在《晨报纪事》上。他写这些东西时没有报酬，但却引起了一个名叫马克隆的出版商的注意。于是在狄更斯二十四岁生日的时候，这些文字分两卷出版成书了，名叫“博兹札记”，并由克里克山克绘制插图。第一版问世时，马克隆付给了狄更斯一百五十镑。这本书反响很好，很快就给他带来了再写的邀请。当时有种风潮，就是把幽默的逸事型小说配上滑稽插图，分期连载在月刊上，每期卖一先令。它们是我们现在滑稽连环漫画的远祖，也和我们的连环漫画一样非常受欢迎。有一天，查普曼出版社的一个合伙人登门拜访，邀请狄更斯写一个业余运动员俱乐部的故事，并由一位著名画家绘制插图。这个计划共有二十期，查普曼每期会出十四镑，买下我们现在叫作连载权的东西，以后出了书还会继续付钱。狄更斯说自己对运动一无所知，不认为自己能按要求写得出书来，但“报酬实在难以抗拒”。不用说，结果就产生了《匹克威克外传》。开头的五期不算成功，但是山姆·维勒这个人物一出现，发行量就立刻开始激增。到了出书的时候，狄更斯就出名了。虽然评论家们还有所保留，但狄更斯的声名已然确立无疑。不妨看看《评论季刊》是如何说他的：“无须预言的神力就可测知他的命运——他已然像火箭一样飞升，也将像棍子一样跌落。”的确，终其一生，虽然公众都在贪婪捧读狄更斯的书，评论家们却一直对他挑剔不断。

一八三六年，《匹克威克外传》第一期出版前几天，狄更斯和他在《晨报纪事》的同事乔治·贺加斯的大女儿凯特结婚了。乔治·贺加斯是六子八女之父，女儿们都是蓝眼睛、娇小丰满、健康明艳的长相。凯特是唯一到了适婚年龄的女儿，这似乎是狄更斯娶她而不是别人的原因。短暂的蜜月期后，他们在弗尼沃旅社安顿下来，并且邀请凯特的漂亮妹妹、十六岁的玛丽和他们同住。狄更斯签了合同要再写一部小说《雾都孤儿》，《匹克威克外传》还在进行中时他就开始了《雾都孤儿》的创作。两本书都是连载，于是他半个月写这本，半个月写那本。大多数小说家都会情不自禁地沉浸于他正在写的人物当中，还会有意控制，不让脑子里产生其他文学想法，狄更斯却明显可以在两个故事中自由转换，这实在是个了不起的本事。

他喜欢上了玛丽。当凯特发现自己怀了孕，不能陪狄更斯到处走动的时候，玛丽就成了他形影不离的人。凯特的孩子出生了，因为她还会再生几个，因此他们把家从弗尼沃旅社搬到了道提街的一处寓所。一天天过去了，玛丽越长越可爱，越长越讨人喜欢。五月的一个晚上，狄更斯带凯特和玛丽去看戏，他们看得高兴，回来时也兴致勃勃。可是突然间玛丽就病倒了，医生来了，可是几小时后玛丽还是死了。狄更斯把她手上的戒指摘下来戴在自己手上，并且至死都戴着这枚戒指。他悲痛难抑。不久后他在日记中写道：“如果现在她还和我们在一起，还是那个迷人、快乐、亲切的伴侣，比任何我知道的人——不管是过去还是将来——都更理解我一切的思想和感情，那么只要这样的幸福继续下去，我将一无所求。可是她走了，我祈求上帝用他的仁慈，有朝一日可以让我与她重聚。”这些话很重要，昭示的意义深远。他还计划死后与她合葬一处。我想他无疑是深深爱上了玛丽，但我们无法得知他自己是否意识到了这一点。

玛丽死时，凯特又怀孕了，妹妹的死使她受了打击，以致流产了。当她身体康复后，狄更斯带着她出国短期旅行，为的是两个人都能恢复精神。无论如何，到了夏天的时候，他就好得很了，可以跟一位埃莉诺·P．肆意调情了。

3

写了《雾都孤儿》、《尼古拉斯·尼克贝》和《老古玩店》的狄更斯稳步走在事业成功的路上。他是个勤奋的人，有好几年的时间都是一本书还没写完就开始写另一本。他写作是为了取悦读者，因此会密切关注公众对每期连载的反应，他的很多小说最初都是以连载形式发表的。有一点很有趣，就是他并没有打算让《马丁·翟述伟》在美国出版，直到销量的不断下降证明这次的连载不像以往的连载那么吸引人。他不是那种认为流行等于羞耻的作家，他的成功是巨大的。但是一个获得成功的文人，他的生活通常不是充满变故，而是一成不变的。他所从事的职业要求他每天必须花一定的时间在工作上，于是他发现了一个适合自己的模式。他认识了不少当时的名人，有文学界、艺术界和社交界的。他被贵妇们提携，他参加聚会，也举办聚会，他旅行，他在公众跟前露面。这基本上就是狄更斯的生活模式。确实，他所享受的成功很少有作家能有幸享受。他似乎精力无限。他不仅能快速连续地写出长篇小说来，他还办杂志、编杂志，甚至在某个短时段内还编过一份日报。他写过相当多数量的随笔，他做讲座，在宴会上发表讲话，后来还举办他作品的朗诵会。他骑马，觉得一天步行二十英里不算什么，他满怀热情地跳舞、装傻，他变魔术逗孩子们玩，还在业余剧团表演。他一直都迷恋戏剧，一度还认真想过要登台表演。他当时曾向一个演员学朗诵、背台词，在镜子前练习如何进屋、落座、鞠躬。可以猜想，当他被介绍给上流社会时，这些技能一定对他起了作用。然而，吹毛求疵者仍然认为他有点粗俗，认为他的穿衣风格过分招摇。在英国，说话口音总是能暴露一个人的出身。而几乎终生都住在伦敦、生活条件一直都不宽裕的狄更斯，很可能一口东区腔。但是他的好相貌、他明亮的眼睛、他充沛的感情、他的活力和愉快的笑声迷住了公众。他有可能被那些阿谀之词夸得晕眩，但他并没有被冲昏了头脑，反而一直保持着一种迷人的谦虚。他是个亲切热情、令人愉快的人。他是那种总能给人带来欢乐的人。

奇怪的是，他虽然具备强大的观察能力，也慢慢和社会上的居高位者熟悉了起来，却始终没能在小说中创造出可信的此类人物。在狄更斯生前，别人对他最常见的指责之一就是他不知道怎么写绅士。因为他曾在律师事务所工作过，因此他笔下的律师和律师手下的职员特点最鲜明，是他笔下的医生和牧师所没有的。他写下层人士和卑贱者最拿手，因为他的童年就是在这些人中度过的。似乎一个小说家最了解的只能是他早年打过交道的那些人，他也只有用他们当原型才能创造得出人物来。一个孩子的一年，一个少年的一年，比一个成年人的一年要长得多，他好像因此被赋予了世界上所有的时间，让他去了解他生活环境中那些人的各种怪癖。“很多英国作家之所以完全不会描写上流社会的生活，理由很可能是因为，”亨利·菲尔丁写道，“他们实际上对上流社会的生活一无所知……这些高级阶层的人们不像人类这个物种的其余成员一样，可以在街道上、商店里和咖啡馆里被人白白看到；他们也不像高级动物那样被展出，你花点钱就能看一次。简而言之，没有以下的这两种资格，即头衔或财富，或没有和以上两者等价的一个令人尊敬的职业：赌徒，谁也别想见到这些上流人士。此外，对世界来说很不幸的是，拥有这些资质的人很少会从事写作这个糟糕的职业，从事这个职业的通常都是那些社会地位更低、更穷的人，因为很多人认为干这行不需要任何储备。”

待到条件一改善，狄更斯一家立刻就搬到了一个比较时髦的街区的一座新房子里，并从著名品牌公司订购了全套的接待室和卧室家具。他在地板上铺了厚绒地毯，窗户上挂上了带花穗的窗帘。他们夫妇雇了一个好厨师、三个女仆和一个男仆，还配了辆车。他们举办晚宴，来的都是贵族和名人。他们的奢侈程度让简·卡莱尔(3)感到震惊，杰弗里勋爵则给他的朋友科克布恩勋爵写信说他在新房子吃了饭，“对一个有家要养，也无非是才富起来的人来说，这顿饭实在太奢侈了”。狄更斯慷慨的天性决定了他喜欢身边围满了人，他卑贱的出身也决定了他就是喜欢奢华，但这也太烧钱了。他父亲、他父亲家、他妻子家，常常都得让他花钱。部分为了支付这些沉重的花销，他创办了他的第一份杂志《韩夫利少爷的钟》，并为助它顺利启动，在其上连载了《老古玩店》。

一八四二年，他把四个孩子留给凯特的妹妹乔治安娜照顾，带凯特去了美国。在他之前和之后，没有一个作家像他那样受到美国人的重视，但他这次行程也不完全成功。一百年前的美国人虽然随时都有可能贬低与欧洲有关的事物，却对任何针对他们自己的批评都敏感无比。一百年前的美国出版界对任何不幸成为“新闻”人物的隐私，都会无情地侵犯。一百年前在美国，那些渴望出名的人把外国名人看成上帝赐给他们站在聚光灯下的良机，当这个外国人拒绝像动物园的猴子一样被对待时，他们就说这个外国人傲慢自负。一百年前，美国是个言论自由的国家，只要这言论没有冒犯到他人的感情或侵害到他人的利益。美国还是个人人都可以有自己观点的国家，只要人人也都赞成别人的观点。对这一切狄更斯都一无所知，因此他犯了严重的错误。没有国际版权法不仅剥夺了英国作家在美国的收益，也损害了美国作家自己的利益。因为可以不付英国作家版税，书商们自然愿意出英国作家的书。又因为他们必须付给美国作家版税，因此他们不愿意出美国作家的书。可是狄更斯竟然在欢迎晚宴上的演说中提到了这一点，他实在太不圆通了。公众的反应很强烈，报纸说他“不是个绅士，只是个唯利是图的流氓”。虽然他仍然被崇拜者们簇拥，甚至在费城时和前来见他的人们握手都握了两小时，但是他的戒指和钻石别针，以及他俗丽的马甲还是激起了好一顿批评，另外有些人认为他的举止实在算不上有教养。但是他胜在自然、不装腔作势，很少有人能抗拒得了他的年轻、英俊与快活。他结交了一些好友，至死都和他们保持着亲密友好的关系。

狄更斯夫妇在经过了精彩、疲累的四个月后回到了英国。孩子们对他们的乔治安娜姨妈已经有了依恋，于是疲惫的旅行者请她留下来和他们同住。乔治安娜十六岁，和当年玛丽来到弗尼沃旅社和新婚的狄更斯夫妇同住时一个年纪，乔治安娜长得也像玛丽，远看都可以被认成玛丽。相似度如此高，以至于“当凯特和她与我同坐时”，狄更斯写道，“我觉得发生的一切就像是个忧郁的梦，而我正从梦中醒来。”乔琪(4)漂亮、迷人，不会装腔作势。她有种模仿的天赋，能让狄更斯大笑不止。随着时间的推移，他越来越依赖她。他们会花很长时间在一起散步，他和她讨论他的文学计划，发现她是个有用、可信赖的誊写员。狄更斯的生活方式极为奢华，很快他就发现自己不幸地陷入了债务之中。他决定把房子出租，带全家——当然包括乔琪在内——去意大利，因为那里的生活成本低，可以紧缩开支。他在意大利待了一年，主要在热那亚。他虽然南南北北旅游了不少地方，但他太狭隘，文化底蕴也缺乏，以至于这段经历没有对他的精神产生什么影响，他仍然是个典型的英国游客。但他发现住在外国很愉快，也很省钱，于是开始在欧陆做长久停留。乔琪作为家庭成员也和他们一起来去。一次，狄更斯一家打算搬去巴黎长住一段时间，于是乔琪就单独和狄更斯先去那里找房，而凯特则留在英国，等他们把一切安排好再去。

凯特的性格温和而忧郁，不是个适应能力强的人。她不喜欢狄更斯带她做的那些旅行，不喜欢和他一起参加的那些聚会，也不喜欢她当女主人的那些聚会。她似乎笨拙、无趣，还相当愚蠢，那些急于想要亲近名作家的大人物很可能觉得忍受名作家乏味的妻子是件非常讨厌的事。让她气恼的是，其中有些人总是把她当成一个无足轻重的人。当名人的妻子不是件容易的事，除非她处事圆通，又有一种很强的幽默感，否则不大可能当得好。两样都没有的话，她就必须爱她丈夫，非常崇拜他，才能认为人们对他而不是对她更感兴趣理属应当。她也必须足够聪明，才能在以下事实中找到安慰，即他爱她，不管他多么不忠实于她，他最终都会回到她这里寻找舒适与安慰。凯特似乎从没爱过狄更斯。当年订婚时，狄更斯就给她写过一封信埋怨她对他冷淡。她跟狄更斯结婚，很可能是因为当时婚姻是唯一对女人开放的职业。或者作为八个女儿中的长女，父母给了她压力，让她接受一桩能给她以未来的求婚。她是个友善温柔的小女人，但却无法满足丈夫的地位对她提出的要求。她在十五年的时间里生了十个孩子，流了四次产。她怀孕时，乔琪陪狄更斯旅行，和他一起参加聚会，并且越来越经常地代替凯特坐在餐桌旁女主人的位置上。我们以为凯特会憎恨这种局面，但我们不知道她是不是真的憎恨。

4

岁月流逝。一八五七年，狄更斯四十五岁了。在他活下来的九个孩子里，大的已经成年，最小的才五岁。他有着世界性的声誉，他是英国最受欢迎的作家，他很有影响力，他活在公众的目光里，这倒很符合他追求戏剧化的本能。一些年前他认识了威尔基·柯林斯，很快他们就发展出非常亲密的友谊。柯林斯比狄更斯年轻十二岁。埃德加·约翰逊曾这样描写柯林斯：“他喜欢美食、香槟和音乐厅，他经常同时和几个女人有着复杂的纠缠，他有趣、愤世嫉俗、好性情，放纵到了近乎粗俗的地步。”对狄更斯来说，柯林斯代表着——仍然引用约翰逊的话——“好玩和自由”。他们一起在英国到处旅游，还同去巴黎找乐子。狄更斯很可能利用了这个机会和碰巧遇到的放荡年轻人——不管这个年轻人是谁——寻了把刺激，就像很多他这个处境的男人都会做的那样。凯特没有给他他所想要的一切，很久以来他已经对她越来越不满意了。“她可爱，温顺，”他写道，“可就是不懂我。”他们才结婚她就开始猜忌他。我怀疑，在他知道她的猜忌毫无理由时，她对他发的那些脾气还好忍受些；可是后来当她的猜忌确有其实时，那些气就不那么好受了。他劝自己说她从来都不适合他。他前进了，她却还在原地。他确信自己无可指责，相信自己是个好父亲，为孩子们做了一切能做的事。事实是，他虽然不太高兴他得养活这么多孩子（他似乎认为凯特一个人应该为生这么多孩子负责），但是孩子们小的时候他还是很喜欢他们的，长大后不知怎么就对他们失去了兴趣。于是，当男孩们到了适当年龄的时候，他就把他们统统打发去了遥远的异国他乡。这些孩子也的确不是怎么有出息的一群。

如果不是因为一个不可预见的意外，狄更斯和他妻子的关系不会有太大改变。就像很多不和谐的夫妻一样，他们之间可能会疏远，但对外人还是会保持一种在一起的假象。这个意外就是狄更斯恋爱了。我曾经说过，狄更斯对舞台情有独钟，他曾不止一次为了慈善的原因在这个或那个剧中业余演出。眼下他受邀在曼彻斯特的一个剧中表演，剧名叫《冰渊》，是柯林斯在他的帮助下写成的。这出戏曾在伦敦的德文郡府当着维多利亚女王夫妇和比利时国王的面成功演出过。他的女儿们曾在其中出演女孩的角色，但是现在他既然同意在曼彻斯特重演，就觉得她们在大剧院里的声音不行，观众听不到，于是决定让专业演员演。这样就安排了一个名叫艾伦·特南的年轻女子出演其中的一个角色。这个小女子年方十八，娇小白皙，眼睛湛蓝。彩排安排在狄更斯家，他是导演。艾伦很崇拜他，急切地想讨好他，他很得意。彩排未完，他就爱上了她。他送给她一只手镯，却不想错送到了他妻子那儿，她当然大闹了一场。狄更斯装出无辜受过的样子，就像那种丈夫们在这种尴尬的节骨眼儿上觉得最方便装出的样子。戏如期上演了，他演主角，一个自我牺牲的北极探险者，演得很动情，全场没有不哭的。为了演戏他还留了络腮胡。

狄更斯和妻子的关系越来越紧张了。那个从来都是那么亲切、好脾气、易相处的他现在除了对乔琪，对每个人都变得喜怒无常、烦躁不安、爱发脾气了。他非常不开心，最后他得出结论：他再也不能和凯特同住了；但他的公众地位又使他害怕公开决裂会造成丑闻。他的焦虑是可以理解的。通过他无比赚钱的圣诞书系列，他比任何人都更加希望让圣诞节成为一个象征性的节日，庆祝的不光是家庭美德，还有团结幸福的家庭生活之美。多年来，他以感人的辞藻让读者相信没有一个地方比得上家。情况很微妙，各种建议都被提了出来。其中之一是他们夫妇还住在同一屋檐下，但是凯特将有自己的房间，和狄更斯分开住，不过她还会在他的聚会上充当女主人，也还会陪他参加公开活动。另一个提议是如果凯特留在伦敦，他就去盖德山庄；而如果他来伦敦，凯特就去盖德山庄。盖德山庄是他刚买的一个房子，在肯特郡。第三个提议是凯特去国外。凯特否决了所有这些提议，最后决定完全分居。凯特被安置在了卡姆登镇边上的一幢小房子里，每年有六百镑收入。不久以后，狄更斯的大儿子查尔斯和他母亲同住了一段时间。

这种安排令人惊讶。我们禁不住疑心，就算凯特性情温顺，可能还愚蠢，可她为什么会接受自己被赶出家门，为什么会同意把孩子留下？她知道狄更斯对艾伦·特南的迷恋，我们本以为她手里有了这张王牌，会想提什么条件就能提什么条件。狄更斯在一封信里提到凯特有个“缺点”，他在另一封当时被不幸出版的信里暗示这个缺点是精神病，这“让他妻子以为她离开会好些”。一般认为这些谨慎的说法其实指向的都是凯特酗酒的事实。如果她的猜忌、觉得自己不胜任、不被需要的屈辱感使她拿起了酒瓶，那也无甚稀奇。而如果她确实酗酒成瘾，那么就可以解释为什么乔琪要来管家看孩子，为什么孩子们留在了家里而他们的母亲却离开了，为什么乔琪会写：“可怜的凯特不能照顾孩子，这对任何人来说都不是个秘密。”她大儿子和她同住的原因大概是要看着她，不让她喝太多。

狄更斯太有名了，他的私事不可能不引人闲话。谣言如丑闻般散布得到处都是。他听见贺加斯家——凯特和乔琪的妈妈和姐妹们——都在说艾伦·特南是他的情妇。他大怒，威胁要把凯特赶出家门，一分钱都不给，以此强迫他们签一个声明，说他们不相信他和那个小演员之间有何不妥。贺加斯家花了两个星期时间才接受被如此威胁。他们一定知道，如果狄更斯把他的威胁付诸实际，凯特可以诉诸法律，他们铁定会赢。而他们不敢让事情发展到这个地步，只能是因为在凯特这方有他们不愿透露的过错。关于乔琪也有很多闲话。她确实是整件事里谜一般的人物，我纳闷是否有人想过要把她作为一出戏的主角。本章早些时候，我提到了玛丽死后狄更斯在日记里写的那些话的重要含义。在我看来，这些话的意思很明确，不仅说他爱上了玛丽，还表示他已经对凯特不满了。当乔琪被邀请去和他们夫妇同住的时候，他被她迷住了，因为她和玛丽长得太像了。他是否也爱上了她？她爱他吗？没人说得清。乔琪相当嫉妒凯特，狄更斯死后，她编选了狄更斯的一些通信，删掉了其中所有赞美凯特的话。但是教会和国家把妻子死后娶妻子的姐妹为妻的做法视如乱伦一般的罪恶，因此她虽然借居狄更斯家长达十五年之久，却可能从未想过在她和这个男人之间还能有超出一奶同胞的姐妹对兄弟的感情。她能获得这样一个名人的信任，还和他建立了这样一种完全的支配关系，可能就够了。整件事最奇怪的部分是当狄更斯热烈地爱上了艾伦·特南时，乔琪居然和她交上了朋友，还欢迎她来盖德山庄。不管她心里是怎么想的，她始终都没说出口。

狄更斯和艾伦·特南的关系被那些知道内情的人私下里谈论着，以至于事情的细节都无法确定。她似乎对他的追求拒绝了一段时间，但是最后屈服于他的坚持。一般认为，狄更斯以查尔斯·特林汉姆的名字在佩卡姆为她租了一所房子，她一直住在那里，直到他死。按照狄更斯女儿凯蒂的说法，狄更斯和艾伦·特南有个儿子。可是关于这个儿子谁也没再听说过更多的事，不妨假设他死于襁褓中了。据说艾伦的屈服并没给狄更斯带来想象的那种欣喜若狂之感。他比她大了二十五岁还不止，不可能不知道她不爱他。世上没有几件事比得不到回报的爱更令人难受了。他在遗嘱中给她留了一千镑，她后来嫁给了一个牧师。她告诉一个名叫贝汉姆的教会朋友，“只要想到”狄更斯强加给她的“亲密”，她就觉得“恶心”。像很多女性一样，她似乎很愿意接受她那个位置的特权，却不明白为什么会有人想要让她作出回报。

大约就在狄更斯和他太太决裂的时候，他开始举办他作品的朗诵会。为此他在英伦三岛巡回演出，并再次去了美国。他的表演天赋使他受益匪浅，他的朗诵表演获得了非常惊人的成功。但是他付出的那些努力，还有他经常的旅行，让他疲惫不堪，人们开始注意到他虽然只有四十多岁，看起来却像个老头一样。朗诵表演不是他唯一的活动。在他和妻子分居一直到他去世的十二年里，他还写了三部长篇小说，办了本极红火的杂志，名叫《一年到头》。毫不奇怪，他的健康每况愈下。他开始被恼人的病痛折磨，他的那些朗诵表演也明显把他累坏了。别人建议他放弃，但他不肯。他喜欢出名，喜欢他一露面就带来的那种轰动，喜欢那种面对面的掌声，喜欢能随意左右听众情绪的能力带给他的刺激。他是否觉得要是艾伦看到他的朗诵会挤满了人，人群如此追捧他，可能会更爱他？他决定最后再做一次巡回演出，但在途中他就病得不行了，只好放弃。他回到盖德山庄，坐下来写《艾德温·德鲁德之谜》。但是因为朗诵会的场次缩减，组织者受到了损失。为了补偿朗诵会的组织者，他又接受了在伦敦安排的十二场朗诵会。这是一八七〇年一月份的事。“圣詹姆斯堂的观众多极了，有时当他出场和退场时，观众会一同起立喝彩。”回到盖德山庄后，他继续写小说。六月的一天，他正单独和乔琪吃饭，不想突然发病了。乔琪派人去叫医生，并把他在伦敦的两个女儿叫了回来。隔天，小点的那个女儿凯蒂被她机智能干的姨妈派去向她妈报告说她爸要死了。随后，凯蒂连同艾伦·特南回到了盖德山庄。之后第二天，也就是一八七〇年六月九号，狄更斯死了，被葬在西敏寺。

5

马修·阿诺德曾在他的一篇著名文章中坚持说，诗歌要想真正优秀需得具备高度的严肃性。他认为乔叟缺乏这种严肃性，因此尽管他对乔叟赞美有加，却拒绝在最伟大的诗人行列中给他留下一席之地。阿诺德太严肃，看待幽默时未免带了丝疑虑。我不认为有谁能说服他承认，拉伯雷的大笑中可能也包含着类似弥尔顿想要向世人昭示天道一样的严肃。但是我明白他的意思，而且我认为这个意思不光适用于诗歌。可能正因为狄更斯的小说缺乏这种高度的严肃性，因此即使其优点众多，仍会使我们有一丝不满。我们今天再读他的小说，会惊讶于他的幼稚，因为我们的脑子里已经有了伟大的法俄小说的印象，而且不光是法俄小说，乔治·艾略特的小说也给我们留下了印象。和这些小说比，狄更斯的小说简直还未成年。但是我们必须记住，我们现在读的并不是他当年写的小说。因为我们已经变了，那些小说也和我们一样变了。我们不可能再次捕捉到这些小说新鲜出炉时狄更斯的同代人读它们的感受。关于这点，我将引用乌娜·蒲柏—亨尼斯书中的一段话加以证明。“亨利·希登斯太太是杰弗里勋爵的一个邻居和朋友。有一次她向杰弗里的书房窥探，发现杰弗里正趴在桌上，他抬起头的时候满眼是泪。她请他原谅，说：‘我不知道你收到了坏消息，或者你有令你悲痛的理由，否则我就不来了。是谁死了吗？’‘是的，确实有人死了，’杰弗里勋爵回答道，‘我知道我这么动情很傻，但我真的是情不自禁。你知道了也一定会难过：小耐尔，博兹的小耐尔死了。’”杰弗里是个苏格兰法官，《爱丁堡评论》的创办者，一个严厉刻薄的评论家。

就我而言，我虽然还是觉得狄更斯的幽默非常有趣，但他的悲怆让我觉得冷，让我提不起兴趣。我会说他感情强烈，但他没有心。我得赶快纠正。他对穷人和受压迫者有一颗慷慨的心和极大的同情，我们还知道，他一直持续有效地关注着社会改革。但他的心是一颗演员的心，我说这话的意思是，他可以强烈地感受到某种情感，他也希望表达这种情感，就像一个悲剧演员能够感受到他想要表达的那种情感一样。“赫库芭(5)对他算得了什么，他又对赫库芭算得了什么？”这让我想起多年前莎拉·伯恩哈特(6)剧团的一个女演员对我说的话。有一次这位大艺术家（莎拉·伯恩哈特）饰演费德尔(7)，正说到她最感人的一段台词时，在所有人看来她悲痛得都要发疯了，结果她发现舞台一侧有几个工作人员正在大声交谈，于是她向那几个人的方向走去。她转身背向观众，做出在悲痛中把脸藏起来的样子，其实她是在向那几个人嘶吼，法语的意思是：别你妈吵了，你们这帮讨厌的浑蛋。然后，她向观众转过身来，做出一副极度悲伤的姿态，继续她那激烈的长篇演说，直至它令人敬畏地结束。观众什么也没察觉到。很难相信她如果不是真的感受到台词的意思，她能如此高贵、悲壮地说出这些台词，但是她的感情是一种专业的感情，就像皮肤一般浅，只关神经，不关心灵，对她的自控毫无作用。我不怀疑狄更斯是真诚的，但那是一种演员的真诚，这可能也就是为什么不管他怎么堆砌痛苦，我们都觉得他的抒情并不发自内心，都不再被他打动。

但我们无权要求一个作家给予他不具备的东西。如果狄更斯缺乏马修·阿诺德所要求的最伟大的诗人应该具备的高度严肃性，他也还有别的很多东西。他是个很伟大的小说家，他的天赋极高，他认为《大卫·科波菲尔》是他所有作品中最好的一部。虽然作家并不总是能对自己的作品做出公正的判断，但狄更斯对此书的判断在我看来却是正确的。我想每个人都知道，《大卫·科波菲尔》在很大程度上带有自传性质，但是狄更斯写的是小说，不是自传，因此他的取材虽然很多来源于他自己的生活，但他只是把这些素材用于小说创作。对于其余部分，他则依赖自己生动的想象力。他从来都不是个阅读者，文学对话使他厌烦，他后来接触到的文学似乎对他无甚作用，没能消除掉他幼时在查塔姆读到的那些书留给他的深刻印象。从长远看来，我认为那些书中对他影响最大的是斯摩莱特的小说。斯摩莱特向读者展示的那些人物与其说高大夸张，不如说色彩艳明；与其说是“人物”，不如说是“气质”。

所以，看人很适合狄更斯的性情特质。麦考伯源自他父亲。约翰·狄更斯在说话上夸夸其谈，在金钱上极不可靠，但是他不傻，也并非无能。相反，他勤奋、温和、亲切。我们知道狄更斯把他写成了什么样。如果福斯塔夫(8)是文学中第一伟大的喜剧角色，麦考伯就是第二伟大的。有人埋怨狄更斯不该给麦考伯安排一个澳大利亚地方法官的体面结局，我认为这种批评不公正。还有评论家认为麦考伯自始至终都应该是一副行事鲁莽、挥霍无度的样子。可是澳大利亚当时是个人烟稀少之地，麦考伯又是个讲究派头、受过教育、说起话来喜欢炫耀夸大的主儿。我看不出为什么他这么个不乏优点的人在这种情况下就不能弄个一官半职。但是狄更斯的厉害之处不只在创造喜剧人物上，斯蒂尔福斯那个圆滑的仆人他也写得很好。此人有一种神秘、邪恶的气质，能让人脊背发凉。尤赖·希普有一种过去叫作“泰晤士河南岸的闹剧感”(9)，但是即便如此，他也一样是个强大、可怕的人物，狄更斯写他的技巧很高超。的确，《大卫·科波菲尔》充满了最多样、最生动、最新颖的人物。文学史上还没有过像麦考伯、辟果提和巴克斯、特莱德、贝特西姨婆和狄克先生、尤赖·希普和他妈那样的人物。他们是狄更斯旺盛想象力的出色创造。他们是那么有活力，那么前后一致，狄更斯对他们的描写又是那么逼真可信，以至于你会边读边情不自禁地信以为真。他们可能并不真实，但是他们鲜活生动。

狄更斯刻画人物的方法通常是夸大其特点、怪癖和弱点，还让他们每个人说一句话或一串话，好把其典型特点深深印在读者的脑子里。他从来不展示人物的发展。整体看来，他的人物开始什么样，最后还什么样。（只有一两个例外，但那时狄更斯所表现的人物性格的变化非常不能令人信服，因为那变化的原因是为了人为地实现大团圆的结局。）如此刻画人物的危险在于合理性的边界似乎被越过，结果就变成了漫画。漫画其实也不错，如果作者给读者看的是一个可以嘲笑的人物，就像你可以嘲笑麦考伯。可是如果作者想让读者同情，漫画就不管用了。狄更斯刻画女性人物从来都不是很成功，除非他可以使其漫画化，比如那个说“我永远都不会抛弃麦考伯先生”的麦考伯太太，再比如贝特西姨婆。朵拉是按狄更斯的初恋玛丽亚·比德内尔刻画的，太傻太幼稚。艾格尼丝是按玛丽和乔琪刻画的，又太好太理智。此外，朵拉和艾格尼丝都极其无趣。小艾米莉在我看来是个失败的形象，狄更斯明显想让我们同情她，可她的结局纯属自找的。她的雄心是想当个“贵妇”，她跟斯蒂尔福斯私奔是因为她以为她能让他娶她，结果她只当了个令他非常不满的情妇：阴郁、爱哭、自怜，时间长了他当然会厌倦她。《大卫·科波菲尔》里最令人不解的女性是罗莎·达特尔。我猜一开始狄更斯是想让她发挥更大作用的，而后来他之所以没这么做，是因为怕会冒犯公众。我只能猜斯蒂尔福斯曾是她的恋人，但是后来抛弃了她，因此她恨他，可又还爱着他，那是一种嫉妒、饥渴、复仇式的爱。狄更斯创造的这个人物到巴尔扎克手里是可以大写特写一番的。在《大卫·科波菲尔》的所有主角里，斯蒂尔福斯是唯一一个“直”写的，取演员们所说一个角色是“直角”的意思。狄更斯给读者提供了一个绝妙的印象，他写了斯蒂尔福斯的魅力、大方、优雅、友好、亲切，他能跟各种人合得来的可爱天赋，他的快活、勇气、自私、没良心、鲁莽、无情。他描绘的这副形象是我们大多数人都认识的一类男人，这类人所到之处都能给人愉悦，可是离开时也都留下了灾难。狄更斯最后给了他一个坏结局，我觉得菲尔丁会更仁慈，因为正如奥诺太太(10)说汤姆·琼斯的那样：“如果女孩们都这么急切，年轻男子也就没什么好指责的了，因为他们所做的无非是天性使然。”今天，小说家不仅要使他的故事情节可信，还得尽可能地逼真。然而狄更斯却不受这样的限制。离开英国多年后，斯蒂尔福斯从葡萄牙坐船回国，居然就在能看得到亚茅斯港时，船沉没被淹死了，而且还正赶上大卫·科波菲尔来此短暂拜访老友。这样的巧合很难令读者信服。如果是为了满足维多利亚时代恶有恶报的要求，斯蒂尔福斯必须死，狄更斯也一定能想出一个更合理的方式。

6

英国文学的一个不幸是济慈死得太早而华兹华斯死得太晚。另一个几乎同样严重的不幸是，就在我们国家涌现出有史以来最具天赋的一批伟大小说家的时期，那时流行的出版方式却助长了他们漫无边际、冗长啰唆、离题漫谈的倾向，对他们的作品造成了伤害，而英国的小说家们又大多天性如此。维多利亚时代的小说家都是些靠笔谋生的劳动者。他们签的合同要求他们必须写出固定字数的十八、二十或二十四期连载，还必须以某种套路安排叙事，以便每期结束的时候能够诱惑读者购买下一期。他们无疑知道他们所讲故事的主线，可我们也知道，他们在出版前会预先写好两三期，然后按需要写剩下的，相信他们的创造力会给他们提供足够的材料填满剩下的页码。而且他们也承认，有时候他们的创作会失败，会没的可写，这时他们只好尽量写。有时还会发生故事写完了，可连载还有两三期没完的情况，他们只好想办法尽量推迟结局的到来。如此一来，他们的小说当然就会不成样子，冗长拖沓，他们也就只好东拉西扯。

狄更斯以第一人称写《大卫·科波菲尔》。这种直截了当的方式对他有利，因为他的故事情节通常都很复杂，有时候读者的注意力会被转移到与故事主线无关的人和事上去。在《大卫·科波菲尔》中，只有一次这样的冗长的离题，那是当他叙述斯特朗医生与其妻、其母和其妻的亲戚的关系时。这段情节与大卫无关，而且这段叙述本身也很无聊。我猜狄更斯描述这个情节是为了处理两次时间上的流逝，第一次是大卫在坎特伯雷上学那段时间，第二次是从大卫对朵拉失望到她死那段时间。狄更斯对这两段时间都不知如何写是好。

狄更斯没有逃脱半自传体小说的作者经常会面临的难题，即他本人就是书中的主角。大卫·科波菲尔十岁时就被他严厉的继父送去干活了，就像狄更斯本人也曾被他亲爸送去鞋油厂一样。大卫不得不忍受和社会地位低于他的同龄小孩混在一起的“屈辱”，而狄更斯在他提供给福斯特的只言片语的自传里，甚至相信自己也遭受过一样的痛苦。狄更斯竭尽所能想要激起读者对他的主人公的同情。在那条奔往多佛尔的路上，为了表现大卫孤注一掷的心情，狄更斯实在是写得太夸张了。大卫去多佛尔是想要寻求他姨婆的庇护，这个姨婆是个可爱有趣的人物，无数读者都认为狄更斯对这段逃亡的叙述非常动人。我这个人心肠较硬。我奇怪这孩子怎么是个傻瓜，让每个遇到他的人都抢他、骗他。他毕竟在工厂干了好几个月，也曾从早到晚地在伦敦游荡过。厂里其他小孩哪怕社会地位再不如他，也能教会他一两样东西。他还和麦考伯家住过一段时间，为他们典当过这样那样的东西，也曾去马夏尔西监狱看过他们。他如果真是狄更斯说的那个聪明孩子，那么哪怕他岁数再小，也一定能学到一些社会知识，也该有足够的机灵保护自己。但是大卫·科波菲尔不光是童年表现无能，成年后也无法应对困难。他面对朵拉时的软弱，他处理普通家庭问题时的缺乏常识，几乎都令人难以忍受。他还无比迟钝，猜不出艾格尼丝爱他。我没法劝自己相信，就像狄更斯告诉我们的那样，他最后居然成了一个成功的作家。如果大卫写小说，我怀疑他写得会更像亨利·伍德太太(11)，而不像狄更斯。很奇怪为什么他的创造者一点都不把自己的魄力、活力和充沛的感情分给他。大卫长得纤瘦漂亮，还有魅力，不然不可能赢得他遇到的每个人的好感。他还诚实、友好、认真，可他真有点傻。他是书里最没趣的一个人。他在苏活区的阁楼上目睹小艾米莉和罗莎·达特尔之间发生如此可怕的一幕，却因为一个最靠不住的理由而没去制止。他在全书中的表现再没有比此时更糟糕、更不中用、更不能应付尴尬局面的了。这一幕提供了一个很好的例子，说明用第一人称写小说可能会使叙述者被迫陷入一个虚假得令人吃惊的窘境，让人觉得一个小说的主人公实在不该沦落至此，让读者有理由生他的气。如果用第三人称，即从全知的视角来叙述，那么这个场景即使还是一样夸张，一样令人反感，但是会变得可信，哪怕只是勉强可信。但是当然，我们读《大卫·科波菲尔》的乐趣并不起于以下信念，即生活是，或者曾经是狄更斯描写的那样。这不是为了贬低狄更斯。小说就像天国一样有很多个房间，一个作家想让你参观哪间，他就可以请你参观哪间。谁活着的理由都不比别人多，但是你必须让自己适应你被带入的那个环境。读《金碗》和《蒙帕纳斯的布布》(12)时要戴不同的眼镜。《大卫·科波菲尔》是对生活的幻想，它有时充满欢乐，有时透出悲伤。它是由一个有着生动想象力和温暖情义的男人用回忆和心愿得偿的希望写成的书。你读这本书时必须像你读莎士比亚的《皆大欢喜》时怀有一样的兴致，而它所提供的乐趣几乎像后者一样让人感到愉快。

(1) 苏活是伦敦西部的一个区，旧时以外国人、妓女和饭馆著称。莱姆豪斯，英文字面意思是“石灰屋”，是伦敦东部一区，旧时为华人聚居地，以贫穷肮脏闻名。

(2) 将债务人拘留于此二十四小时后，如不还债，即送入狱。

(3) 英国哲学家、散文家托马斯·卡莱尔（1795—1881）的妻子。

(4) 乔治安娜的昵称。

(5) 赫库芭是希腊神话中特洛伊国王普里阿摩斯之妻。“赫库芭对他算得了什么，他又对赫库芭算得了什么？”是莎士比亚悲剧《哈姆雷特》中的一句台词。《哈姆雷特》第二幕第二场中有一个“戏中戏”，一个演员男扮女装演出赫库芭悲悼夫君被希腊人杀死的一幕，“他”就指这个男演员。演员离场后，哈姆雷特感叹演员只是表演悲愤，而自己是真悲愤却懦弱地不敢发一言，因此也引出他想用演戏试探他叔叔是否真的杀死他父亲一事。

(6) 莎拉·伯恩哈特（1844—1923），法国著名戏剧演员，最早的世界级明星，以“金色嗓音”以及性格高傲、古怪、多变著称。

(7) 希腊神话中一王后，爱上了她的继子，同名剧以乱伦著称。

(8) 福斯塔夫是莎士比亚笔下一个著名的喜剧角色，曾出现在《亨利四世》、《亨利五世》和《温莎的风流娘儿们》中。他肥胖虚荣爱夸口，终日在小酒馆饮酒，靠偷盗和借钱度日，但同时又不乏思想深度。有一种观点认为他是莎士比亚创造的所有人物中最伟大的一个。

(9) 十九世纪的英国有一种追求耸人听闻以及轰动效应的戏剧风格，一度盛行于泰晤士河南岸的剧院。

(10) “奥诺”的英文是Honour，意思是“名誉”或“贞操”，这里当然语含讥讽。

(11) 指艾伦·伍德（1814—1887），英国女作家，狄更斯的同代人，因家贫而写作，著有三十多本小说，大多很流行。她在澳大利亚的声名甚至超过狄更斯。她的小说笔调被认为“保守、充满基督教色彩”，并不时在小说中使用宗教辞藻。

(12) 法国小说，1901年出版，作者查理—路易·菲利普（1874—1909），写一个妓女的故事。

艾米莉·勃朗特与《呼啸山庄》

1

一七七六年，北爱尔兰唐郡的一个年轻农民修·普朗蒂娶妻埃莉诺·麦克劳埃。次年的圣帕特里克节(1)，他们十个孩子中的长子出生了，取名帕特里克，与爱尔兰的守护神同名。修·普朗蒂似乎既不会读也不会写，因为他连自己的名字怎么拼都不确定。施洗记录中，他的名字被写成了Brunty和Bruntee(2)。他耕种的那一小片土地根本不够他养活他那个大家庭，因此他会去石灰窑打工，年景不好时，还会去邻近的一个地主家打短工。可以猜测，修的大儿子帕特里克就在父亲的土地上干些杂活，直到长大能挣工钱的时候，他就当了一个手摇纺织机的织工。可是他聪明、有野心，不管怎么说吧，到十六岁时，他就已经受到了足够的教育，当起了教师，在他出生地附近的一间乡村学校教书。两年后他在庄柏立洛尼的教区学校找到了一份类似的工作，干了八年。关于当年的事有两种说法：一说是卫理公会(3)的牧师们很欣赏他的能力，希望他能深造当牧师，于是捐了些钱，再加上他之前攒的钱，足够他上剑桥学习了。另一说是他离开教区学校后，去了一个牧师家当家教。正是在这位牧师的帮助下，他进了剑桥大学的圣约翰学院。他那时二十五岁，上大学有点老了。他高大健壮，长得不错，他对自己的相貌也很得意。他靠一份助学金、两份奖学金，还有他做家教获得的报酬维持生活。二十九岁那年，他拿到了学士学位，在英国国教会领了圣职。如果真是卫理公会的牧师们帮他上了剑桥大学的话，他们一定后悔这次投资投错了。

正是在剑桥读书期间，他又把自己的姓氏从入学登记簿上的勃兰特（Branty）改成了勃朗特（Bronte），但是当时他还没有用分音符，即字母e上的那两个点。他被任命为埃塞克斯郡的威泽斯菲尔德地区的副牧师，并在那里爱上了一位玛丽·博德小姐。这位小姐年方十八，家境虽不富有，却也算宽裕。他们订了婚，但是不知为何，勃朗特甩了她，据推测大概是因为他对自己的长处感觉良好，认为再等等的话他还能给自己找个更好的对象。玛丽·博德极受伤害。此举大概在教区里给这位英俊的副牧师引来很多风言风语，因为他离开了威泽斯菲尔德，去了什罗普郡的威灵顿当副牧师，几个月后又去了约克郡的哈茨海德任职。他在此地遇到了一个个子小小、相貌平凡的三十岁女子，名叫玛丽亚·布兰威尔。她每年有五十镑的收入，来自一个体面的中产家庭。帕特里克·勃朗特此时已经三十五了，哪怕长得再帅，说话还带点好听的爱尔兰口音，也找不着更好的伴侣了。于是他求了婚并被接受，在一八一二年结了婚。还在哈茨海德时，勃朗特夫妇就生了两个女儿，玛丽亚和伊丽莎白。后来勃朗特被任命到另一个地方当副牧师，这个地方在布拉德福德附近，他们在这儿又生了四个孩子：夏洛特、帕特里克·布兰威尔、艾米莉和安妮。结婚前一年，勃朗特自费出版了一本诗集，名为《农舍诗歌》，一年后他又出了第二本诗集，名为《乡村吟游诗人》。住在布拉德福德附近时，他还写了本小说，叫《林中小屋》。读过这些作品的人说它们毫无长处。一八二〇年，勃朗特被任命为约克郡一个名叫哈沃斯的村子的“永久副牧师”，他一直在这里做副牧师直到去世，他的野心大概得到了满足。他从未回过爱尔兰去看他留在那里的父母弟妹，但他每年会给母亲寄二十镑，直到母亲去世。

一八二一年，结婚九年后，玛丽亚·勃朗特死了，死于癌症。成了鳏夫的副牧师说服了姨姐伊丽莎白·布兰威尔离开她所居住的彭赞斯来哈沃斯照顾他的六个孩子。但他还想再婚，于是在等待了一段得体的时间后，他写信去问博德太太，也就是十四年前他曾恶劣对待过的那个女孩的母亲，问玛丽·博德是否还单身。几星期后，他收到了回信，之后立刻就写信给玛丽本人。考虑到当时的境况，他的信写得自鸣得意、自以为是、油腔滑调、品味很坏。他居然厚颜无耻地说他的旧爱又一次被激发了，他非常渴望见到她。这信实际等于求婚。她的回信很刺人，但他没有被吓倒，又写了封信。他的不知分寸真是令人吃惊，他说：“随便你怎么想，怎么写，但我毫不怀疑，如果你是我的妻子，你会比现在更幸福，或者比你单身生活更幸福。”（下划线部分为他的原文强调的部分。）在玛丽·博德那儿失败后，他把心思转到了另一处，又向一位伊丽莎白·福里斯小姐求婚，他在布拉德福德附近当副牧师时认识了她，但她也拒绝了。他似乎没想过一个四十五岁、带着六个小孩的鳏夫实在不是什么值得婚配的对象。现在，他好像认识到了这是个白费力气的事，于是放弃了再婚的想法。不管怎样，有伊丽莎白·布兰威尔给他管家和照顾孩子，他已经很该感恩了。

哈沃斯的牧师住所是幢褐色的石头小房子，坐落于陡峭的山崖上，山下就是布局零散的哈沃斯村。牧师住所的房前屋后都有一小片花园，两侧则是墓地。勃朗特姐妹的传记作家们都认为这种环境太压抑。对医生来说那种环境可能确实压抑，但对牧师来说，却有可能觉得身处其中能让人陶冶情操，甚至安慰人心。无论如何，这位牧师的家人一定已经逐渐习惯了这番景象，他们很可能已经不再注意了，就像意大利南方卡普里岛的渔夫很少会注意落日余晖里的维苏威火山或伊斯基亚岛一样。房子的一楼有个客厅，有间勃朗特先生的书房，还有一间厨房和一间储藏室，二楼则有四个卧室和一个厅。除客厅和书房外，全屋都没铺地毯，窗户上也不挂窗帘，因为勃朗特先生最怕着火。地板和楼梯都是石头的，一到冬天格外冰冷潮湿。布兰威尔姨妈因为怕感冒，总是穿着套鞋在屋里走动。还有条小路从房子通向荒野。为使勃朗特姐妹的故事更具悲伤的色彩，作家们总爱把哈沃斯写成永远荒凉、苦寒和沉闷的样子，尽管这种想法大概是无意识的。但是即使是在冬天，哈沃斯也有不少天空湛蓝、阳光灿烂的日子。在这样的日子里，冰冷的空气令人精神振奋，草地、荒野和树林都染上了一层柔和的色彩。我就是在这样的一天去了哈沃斯。那天的乡村笼罩在一层银灰色的薄雾中，轮廓模糊，远远看去无比神秘。掉光了叶子的树木有一种日本版画里的那种树木在冬日里的优雅姿态，路边的山楂树丛挂着白霜，闪着银光。艾米莉·勃朗特的诗和《呼啸山庄》会告诉你沼泽上的春天多么令人激动，它的美多么丰富，它的夏天又是多么迷人。

勃朗特先生爱在荒野上长时间地散步，而且走得很远。晚年时勃朗特先生夸口说他一天能走四十英里。他是个躲避人群的人——换换口味也好，因为作为副牧师，他是个社会动物，爱聚会，爱调情。附近的牧师们有时会下山来和他喝杯茶，此外他除了教会执事和教区居民外，什么人都不见。如果这些人来请他，他会去见他们。如果他们要他去主持宗教仪式，他也会欣然从命。但是他和家人“关系非常紧密”。他自己虽然是个贫穷的爱尔兰农民的儿子，却不让自己的孩子和村里的孩子们接触。孩子们全被他赶到二楼寒冷的小厅里，那是他们的书房。他们在那里阅读，小声说话，生怕打扰了父亲，因为父亲被打扰或不高兴的时候，会一直阴沉着脸保持沉默。上午他教他们功课，布兰威尔姨妈则教女孩们针线活和家务。

即使是在妻子生前，勃朗特先生也习惯在书房里单独用餐，这个习惯他保持了一生。他给出的理由是他消化不良。艾米莉在日记中写道：“晚饭我们将要吃煮牛肉、萝卜、土豆和苹果布丁。”一八四六年夏洛特从曼彻斯特写信说：“爸爸不要求别的，你知道，他就只吃清淡的牛肉和羊肉、茶、面包和黄油。”对于一个长期消化不良的人来说，这似乎不是个好的养生之法。我倾向于认为，假如勃朗特先生单独用餐，那是因为他不喜欢子女的陪伴，如果孩子们打扰到了他，他会很生气。每晚八点钟他会读家庭祈祷词，九点钟闩门上锁。经过孩子们在那儿坐着的房间时，他会嘱咐他们不要太晚睡。上到楼梯一半的拐角处时，他会停下来给钟上发条。

盖斯凯尔夫人认识勃朗特先生几年，得出的结论是他是个自私、易怒、专横的人。而作为夏洛特好友之一的玛丽·泰勒也给她的另一个朋友艾伦·纽西写信说：“我一想起夏洛特为那个自私的老头所做的牺牲就不由得又生气又沮丧。”最近有人想要洗白他，可是再怎么洗白都无法粉饰他给玛丽·博德写的那些信中表现出的厚颜无耻，它们已经全文发表在了克莱门特·肖特的《勃朗特一家及其圈子》的书中了。而且，再怎么洗白也不能让人忘了他对他的助理牧师尼克斯向夏洛特求婚时的态度。我稍后还会再谈到此事。盖斯凯尔夫人写道：“勃朗特太太的保姆告诉我，有一天孩子们都去荒野了，天开始下雨，她怕他们会淋湿，就把朋友给孩子们的彩色靴子找出来，一双双围在厨房的火炉边烘烤一下。可是等孩子们回来后，却发现靴子不见了，只能闻到很强烈的皮子烧焦的气味。原来勃朗特先生进来看见这些鞋，认为它们太花哨奢侈，不适合他的孩子，就都给烧了。任何冒犯他古老的简朴概念的东西他都不放过。很久以前，还有人送给过勃朗特太太一条丝绸裙子，不管是颜色、样式还是材质都不符合他对得体的看法，于是勃朗特太太一次都没穿过。尽管如此，她把裙子放在抽屉里珍藏，而抽屉一般都是上锁的。但是，有一天她在厨房，突然想起她把钥匙落在抽屉上了，同时听到勃朗特先生在楼上，她预感到裙子要出事，就连忙跑上楼，结果发现裙子已经被剪成了碎片。”这故事虽是一面之词，可是保姆没理由编故事。“有一次，他把壁炉前的地毯塞到炉子里，故意放在火上，并且一直待在屋里，哪怕味道很臭也不怕，直到地毯闷烧到彻底不能用为止。还有一次，他拿了几把椅子，硬是用锯子把椅背锯掉，直到最后把椅子弄成了凳子。”还必须加一句才公平，勃朗特先生自己说这些故事都是假的。但是没人怀疑他脾气暴烈，严厉专横。我曾经自问，勃朗特先生这些不可爱的性格是否源于他对生活的失望。正如其他很多出身卑微的人一样，他为了提升自己，脱离自己所在的阶层，接受教育，不得不痛苦挣扎，但他很可能高估了自己的能力。我们知道他对自己的相貌相当得意。他在文学上的努力没有获得成功。他这样常年与逆境搏斗的唯一报偿无非是在约克郡的荒野地区永远当个副牧师。如果这事使他怨恨，那也没什么好奇怪的。

在牧师的那所宅子里，生活的艰苦与孤独被过分夸大了，因为才华横溢的几姐妹似乎对这种生活相当满意。确实，如果她们停下来想想自己父亲的出身，可能会觉得自己非常走运。比起全英国好几百名牧师的女儿，她们的处境既不更好也不更坏，因为那些牧师之女的生活也像她们一样与世隔绝，财产也像她们一样有限。勃朗特家是有邻居的，包括步行距离之内的牧师、乡绅、磨坊主、小业主，她们可能跟他们有过交往。如果她们过着隔绝的生活，那是她们有意为之。她们不富裕，但也不贫穷。勃朗特先生的圣禄给他提供了一个住所和一笔一年两百镑的收入，他妻子一年有五十镑，妻子死后他应该继承了这笔钱。伊丽莎白·布兰威尔来此居住时，也把她那一年五十镑的收入带来了。因此家里一年能支配的钱有三百镑，至少等于今天的一千两百镑。如今的很多牧师，哪怕要交所得税，也会把一年一千两百镑看成很大一笔钱。如今很多牧师的妻子要是有一个女仆都会谢天谢地，而勃朗特家平常就有两个女仆，活儿多的时候还会从村里临时招女孩们来帮忙。

一八二四年，勃朗特先生把四个大一点的女儿送到了考恩桥的一家学校。学校是刚建的，为的是给穷牧师的女儿提供教育。这个地方很不健康，食物很差，管理也很糟。两个大女孩死了，夏洛特和艾米莉的健康也受到了影响。但是幸运的是，一段时间后她们被转移走了。从此，她们的教育似乎就都由姨妈负责给予了。勃朗特先生对他独生子的关心多过对三个女儿的关心。确实，儿子被认为是家里最聪明的那个。勃朗特先生不肯送他去学校，他要亲自教。这个儿子早慧，举止也很吸引人。他的朋友F．H．格兰蒂这样描述他：“他个子太矮，这是他人生的一大考验。他有一头浓密的红发，留着背头，梳得很高，我想是为了增加身高吧。他额头很大，很突出，几乎占了整个脸轮廓的一半，显得很聪明。小眼睛像雪貂一样深陷，眼镜从来不摘，把眼睛隐藏得更深了，鼻子很突出，但是脸的下半部分乏善可陈。他有一种沮丧的神情，从来没有变过，除了在很长时间的间隔后抬眼快速瞥一下。他身材瘦小单薄，第一眼看上去实在不起眼。”他有才华，他的姐妹们都期待他做出一番事业来。他父亲是个阴郁沉默的人，而他则是个有才华、热情健谈的人，他一定是从某个爱尔兰祖先那里继承了社交的天赋和令人愉快的健谈的脾性。如果一个旅行者夜宿黑牛旅店，看来有些孤独，店主会问：“你想有个人陪你喝酒吗，先生？我可以叫帕特里克来。”布兰威尔也总是很愿意帮忙。我应该加一句，多年后夏洛特已经成名，店主被问到此事，不承认他曾这么做过。他说：“布兰威尔永远不用让人叫。”今天你去哈沃斯，还会被指点看黑牛旅店的那个房间，那些温莎式的靠椅，布兰威尔当年就是坐在这样的椅子里和朋友们痛饮烈酒的。

夏洛特不满十六岁时，又一次进了学校，这次去的是罗海德，而且过得很愉快。但是一年后她就回了家，为的是教两个妹妹。虽然正如我已经指出的那样，她们家不像一般以为的那么穷，但是女儿们也没什么指望。勃朗特一死，他的薪俸自然就没了，布兰威尔姨妈会把自己那点钱留给她那个有趣的外甥。于是姐妹几个觉得她们唯一能挣钱养活自己的办法就是训练自己当家庭教师或学校教师，这是当时对那些自视为淑女的女人开放的唯一职业。布兰威尔那时也有十八了，他必须决定自己到底要从事何种职业或是经营何种商业。就像他的姐妹们都能画一样，他也有点画画的才能，他于是想当画家。事情决定了，他要去伦敦的皇家艺术学院学画。他去了，但是什么也没学成。他只是观光，一定也还趁机玩乐了一番，这样过了一段时间后，他又回到了哈沃斯。他尝试过写作，但是没成功。之后他说服他父亲给他在布拉德福德开了一间画室，想给当地人画像挣钱，但是这次也失败了，勃朗特先生把他叫回了家。再后来，他去给巴罗因弗内斯一位名叫波索斯韦特的先生当家庭教师。他似乎在那儿干得不错，但是六个月后，勃朗特先生又把他叫回了家，原因未明。很快，家里给他在利兹和曼彻斯特那趟线上的索尔比桥火车站找了个管理员的工作，他后来又去了莱顿顿脚站当管理员。他感到寂寞无聊，于是狂喝滥饮，终于因为严重的玩忽职守被开除回了家。同时，一八三五年，夏洛特回到罗海德当老师，并把艾米莉带去当学生。但是艾米莉太想家，想得都生了病，又被送了回来。性情更为安静顺从的安妮取代了她的位置。夏洛特在这个职位上干了三年，三年后，她的健康变差，她也回到了家中。

夏洛特二十二岁了。布兰威尔不但让家人发愁，还花了家里好多钱。夏洛特一旦健康好转，立刻就觉得她有义务去找一个保姆兼家庭教师的职位。这不是她喜欢的工作。她和她妹妹都不喜欢小孩，就像她们的父亲不喜欢小孩那样。“我发现想要挡住孩子那种粗鲁的亲密太难了。”她在信中告诉艾伦·纽西。她很不喜欢寄人篱下，时时留心有没有人冒犯她，她不是个容易相处的人。从她的信中可以判断，她的雇主认为自然该她做的事，她却认为不在她分内，须得求她，她才会做。三个月后她离开了，回到了牧师住所，可是两年后她又在布拉德福德附近的罗登给怀特夫妇家做了家庭教师。夏洛特认为他们没有良好的教养。“我能相信吗？W太太是个收税官的女儿，我还肯定W先生的出身也很低。”但她在这个职位上干得挺高兴，不过正如她给自己那位密友艾伦·纽西的信中说的那样：“除了我自己，没人知道家庭教师的生活对我来说多么艰难，因为只有我自己知道，我整个的头脑和天性是多么彻底地厌恶这个职业。”一直以来她都有过想和两个妹妹开一间自己的学校的念头，现在她又打起了这个主意。怀特夫妇鼓励了她，他们似乎是对善良体面的人，但是他们建议她应该先取得一定的资质，这样才能成功。她能读法语，但是不会说，也不懂德语，于是她决定出国学语言。布兰威尔姨妈答应垫付这笔费用，于是勃朗特先生亲自送夏洛特和艾米莉去了布鲁塞尔，以便路上照顾她们。两个女孩——夏洛特二十六岁，艾米莉二十二岁——成了埃热寄宿学校的学生。十个月后，她们被召回了英国，因为布兰威尔姨妈病重。姨妈死了，因为外甥的行为太恶劣，她剥夺了他的继承权，把所有那点钱都留给了外甥女。这笔钱足够她们实现长久以来谈论的办学的想法，但是她们的父亲老了，视力不行了，于是她们决定就在牧师居所办这个学校。夏洛特认为她还没有完全准备好，就接受了埃热先生的邀请，又回到布鲁塞尔埃热先生的学校教英语。她在布鲁塞尔待了一年，之后再次回到哈沃斯。再然后，三姐妹发了入学简介，夏洛特还写信给朋友，请朋友们代为推荐她们即将开办的这所学校。她们从没解释过如何能在牧师住所里给学生提供住宿，因为这里只有四间卧室，而她们自己就都占满了。不过既然一个学生都没招来，这事也就不用解释了。

2

她们自童年起就经常写作。一八四六年，她们自费出版了一本诗集，用的名字是柯勒·贝尔、艾利斯·贝尔和阿克顿·贝尔。出书花了她们五十镑，但只卖掉了两本。然后她们每人都写了一本小说。夏洛特（柯勒·贝尔）写的是《教授》，艾米莉（艾利斯·贝尔）写的是《呼啸山庄》，安妮（阿克顿·贝尔）写的是《艾格妮丝·格雷》。她们被一个又一个出版商拒绝，直到夏洛特的《教授》最终被送到史密斯父子公司。这家公司退回了《教授》，但写信说愿意考虑她写的一个更长一点的小说。可巧她正在写一个更长的小说，而且就快写完了，一个月内就能交稿。史密斯父子公司接受了，这书正是《简·爱》。艾米莉的小说和安妮的小说最终也被一个名叫纽比的出版商接受了，但“条件对两位作者来说无比苛刻”。她们在夏洛特把《简·爱》交给史密斯父子公司前改正了校样。虽然评论界对《简·爱》的评价并不好，但是架不住读者喜欢，这书成了畅销书。一看这样，纽比也试图让公众相信，他以三卷本形式一起出版的《呼啸山庄》和《艾格妮丝·格雷》也是《简·爱》的作者写的。但是《呼啸山庄》和《艾格妮丝·格雷》没给人留下印象，某些评论家还以为它们是柯勒·贝尔早期的不成熟之作。勃朗特先生在经过一番劝说后，答应读一读《简·爱》。当他读完进来喝茶的时候，他说：“女儿们，你们知道夏洛特一直在写一本书吗？而且可能写得还相当不错。”

布兰威尔姨妈死的时候，安妮在索普格林给一位罗宾逊太太的孩子当家庭教师。她的性情亲切柔顺，比起严厉易怒的夏洛特来说，明显更易与人相处，她在这个职位上并非是不开心的。她回哈沃斯参加姨妈的葬礼，回到索普格林时，带去了闲散在家的布兰威尔，让他给罗宾逊家的儿子做家庭教师。这家的先生，埃德蒙·罗宾逊，是个有钱的牧师，虽然年老久病，妻子却相当年轻。布兰威尔爱上了她，尽管她比他大十七岁。他们到底是不是情人并不确定。但是不管他们是不是，他们都被发现了，布兰威尔只好卷铺盖走人。罗宾逊先生命令他“再也不许见他孩子的母亲，再也不许踏入她的家门一步，再也不许给她写信或和她说话”。布兰威尔“咆哮、怒骂、发誓说他离开她活不了，怪她为何不肯离开她丈夫。然后祈祷那个病人快点死掉，说他俩以后会幸福”。布兰威尔一直嗜酒，现下处于悲痛之中更是开始吃起了鸦片。不过他似乎还能和罗宾逊太太联系。在他被开除几个月后，他们似乎又在哈罗盖特见过面。“据说她提议私奔，说她准备好了要放弃她的身份地位，反而是布兰威尔建议再耐心等等。”这话只能是布兰威尔说的，但这无论如何又都是不可能的，因此我们只能说这是一个既愚蠢又自大的年轻人的臆想。突然间他接到一封信，说罗宾逊先生死了。“他简直是一路在跳舞，好像疯了一样，从教堂墓地的这头跳到那头。他太喜欢那个女人了。”有人如此告诉艾米莉的传记作者玛丽·罗宾逊。

“第二天早上他起了床，精心穿好了衣服，准备出发。但他还没出哈沃斯，两个男人就骑着马火速向村子赶来了。他们要见布兰威尔，等到布兰威尔无比激动地赶来时，其中一人下了马，和他一起进了黑牛旅馆。”这人带来了那位寡妇的消息，求他不要再接近她，因为哪怕她再见他一次，她都会失去她的财产以及她对孩子的监护权。这又是他说的，但是由于这封信从未示人，后来还发现罗宾逊先生的遗嘱里并没有这样的规定，因此无从判断他是否说了实话。唯一确定的事实是，罗宾逊太太让他知道她不想再和他来往了，她可能编了这个借口，好使这次的打击对他来说不那么屈辱。勃朗特家很肯定她就是布兰威尔的情人，并把他后来的行为归咎于她的恶劣影响。她可能确实是布兰威尔的情人，但也有可能他夸口的征服根本就没发生过，就像他之前和之后的很多男人那样只是胡夸海口。如果她确实曾经短暂地被他迷住过，我们也没有理由假设她曾想过和他结婚。他继续拼命滥饮。一位曾在他死前照顾他的人对盖斯凯尔夫人说，当他知道自己末日将临时，他想站着死，他坚持要从床上起来。此前他只在床上躺了一天。夏洛特非常难过，她被带离了现场，但是他父亲、安妮和艾米莉留在他身旁，看他站起来。挣扎了二十分钟后，他死了，正如他希望的那样，他是站着死的。

他死后的那个星期天以后，艾米莉就再没有出过门。她感冒了，还咳嗽。病越来越重。夏洛特写信告诉艾伦·纽西说：“我担心她胸疼，有时她做什么动作做得快的时候，还能听到她喘不上气来的声音。她看起来非常非常瘦又苍白。她缄默的性情使我内心非常不安。问她问题没有用，什么回答也得不到。让她吃药更没用，她从来不吃药。”一两个星期后，夏洛特给另一个朋友写信说：“今晚我真希望艾米莉好点了，但是很难确定。她生病时是个真正的坚忍苦修者。她既不求人同情，也绝不接受别人的同情。问她问题，给她帮助，只能让她恼怒。她在痛苦或疾病面前绝不屈服，直到被迫屈服。对于她平常做的家务活，她一项也不愿放弃。你不得不在旁边看着她做不适合的事，还一个字都不敢说……”一天早上，艾米莉像往常一样起来，穿好衣服，开始缝纫。她喘不上气来，眼神呆滞，但是还是继续缝。情况越来越糟。她本来一直都拒绝看医生，但是最后到了中午的时候，她要人去请医生。但是太晚了，下午两点她死了。

夏洛特正在写另一部小说《谢莉》，但是为了照顾安妮，她暂停了写作。安妮得了一种当时叫作奔马痨的病，布兰威尔和艾米莉也都死于这种病。艾米莉死后仅仅五个月，安妮这个温柔的人也死了。《谢莉》直到安妮死后才完成。一八四九年和一八五〇年，夏洛特去了伦敦，在那里颇受重视。她被介绍给萨克雷，乔治·里士满还给她画了像。史密斯父子公司一个名叫詹姆斯·泰勒的人向她求婚，她把此人描述为“严苛粗鲁”的样子。在那之前，已经有两个牧师向她求过婚，都被她拒绝了。还有两三个助理牧师，有她父亲手下的，也有附近牧师手下的，都对她表现出了特别的兴趣。但是她的妹妹艾米莉打消了那些追求者的念头，姐妹们都管她叫“少校”，因为她知道如何有效地对付追求者们。再加上她父亲也不赞成，因此这些追求都没什么结果。但她最终还是嫁给了她父亲的一个助理牧师，此人名叫亚瑟·尼克斯，是一八四四年来的哈沃斯。那年夏洛特给艾伦·纽西写信说起这个人：“我实在发现不了你在他身上发现的那些有趣的善的萌芽，思想狭隘是他一直以来给我留下的主要印象。”两三年后，她把他也归入她所轻蔑的那些助理牧师中。“他们把我看成老姑娘，我却把他们中的每一个人和所有人都看成极其无趣、狭隘、毫无吸引力、更为粗糙的男性性别的样本。”尼克斯是爱尔兰人，他放假回爱尔兰时，夏洛特和她那位经常通信的朋友说：“尼克斯先生还没回来。我很抱歉地说，很多教民都表达了一个愿望，希望他不要再麻烦他自己跨过海峡回来了。”

一八五二年夏洛特给艾伦·纽西写了一封长信，还附了尼克斯的一个便条，她说这个便条“给我心里留下了深深的忧虑……”“爸爸看到或猜到的东西我不会去问，虽然我可以想。他已经生气地注意到了尼克斯所有情绪上低沉的状态，所有要离开出国的威胁，所有健康受损的症状。但他对此几乎毫无同情，只有很多间接的讽刺。周一晚上尼克斯先生在这里喝茶。我虽没有清楚看到，但也模糊感到——就像这段时间以来我虽没看到但都感到的那样——他总那样看是什么意思，他那种狂热的克制又是什么意思。茶点后我像往常一样回到了起居室。尼克斯先生也像往常一样和爸爸坐到八九点钟，然后我听到他打开客厅的门，像是要走。我期待听到前门碰撞的声音，可他在走廊停下，敲了我的房门，电光石火间，我突然意识到他想进来。他进来了，站在我面前。他说了什么话你可以猜得到，但他的样子你不会想到，我也不会忘掉。他从头到脚都在发抖，脸色像死人一样惨白，说话声音很低，热情但是并不顺畅，他使我第一次感到，一个人求爱时如果怀疑得不到回应会是什么样。

“一个人平时像雕像一样，如今却在颤抖、晃动、无能为力，这副样子真的给了我一种奇怪的震撼之感。他告诉我这几个月来他承受了怎样的痛苦，他现在再也承受不了这样的痛苦了，他渴望我能给他一点希望。我只能请他暂时离开，答应第二天一早给他一个答复。我问他是否跟爸爸谈过了。他说他不敢。我想我是半领半推地把他弄出了房间。他走了以后我立刻去找爸爸，告诉他发生的事。接下来，是与这一场合不符的激动和恼怒。如果我爱尼克斯，听到爸爸这样说他，我会受不了。我的血像是沸腾了一般，被一种不公正感烧开了。但是爸爸把自己气到了一种令人无法小视的状态，他太阳穴上的血管像绳索一般凸起，眼睛也突然充血了。我赶快答应说，明早一定给尼克斯一个果断的回绝。”

在三天后的另外一封信中，夏洛特写道：“你问爸爸如何在尼克斯面前自贬尊严。我真希望你在这里看到处于当前情绪下爸爸的样子，那你就会知道了。他对尼克斯的态度就是一种无法转圜的强硬，一种无法压制的轻蔑。他们俩还未面谈过，一切全靠写信。而我必须说，周三爸爸给尼克斯写了一封非常严厉的信。”她还说她父亲“过分夸大了尼克斯的缺钱，他说和尼克斯结婚将是自贬身价，等于抛弃自己。如果我真结婚，他期待我会嫁给一个非常不一样的人”。事实上，勃朗特先生此时的举动就像多年前他对玛丽·博德一样坏。他和尼克斯的关系紧张起来，后者辞去了助理牧师之职。但是继任者们并没能让他满意，最终受不了他抱怨的夏洛特告诉他这事只能怨他自己。他只有让她嫁给尼克斯，一切才能好起来。爸爸继续“非常非常敌意，无比不公平”，但是女儿还是和尼克斯通了信，见了面。他们订了婚，并于一八五四年结了婚。那年她三十八岁，九个月后即死于难产。

于是帕特里克·勃朗特牧师埋葬了妻子、姨姐和六个孩子，一个人在他喜欢的孤独中吃饭，在他日渐衰弱的体力许可下，在沼泽上能走多远就走多远地散步，读报，布道，临睡前给钟上发条。有一张他老年的照片。照片中的他身穿黑西装，系一条很宽的白领巾，白发剪得很短，额头长得不错，鼻子大而直，嘴唇紧闭，镜片后是一双怒气冲冲的眼睛。他最后死在了哈沃斯，享年八十四岁。

3

我的本意是想写艾米莉和《呼啸山庄》，却说了这么多她父亲、哥哥和姐姐夏洛特的事，比她本人说的都多，我自有我的用意。因为在写她家的书里，写得最多的是他们而不是她，艾米莉和安妮几乎都不出现。安妮是个温柔漂亮的小东西，但是无足轻重，才能也不出众。可艾米莉不一样。她古怪、神秘，像影子一样。她从来不会被人直接看到，她更像是在沼泽池塘中映出的倒影。她为人到底如何，你只好从她唯一的那本小说、她的诗、各处对她间接的提及，以及那些散播的逸事中猜测。她是个孤僻、紧张和让人不安的人，如果你听说她沉溺于放纵的快乐，就像她有时在沼泽地上散步时会表现出的那样，你会感到不安。夏洛特有朋友，安妮有朋友，艾米莉没有。她的性格充满矛盾。她严厉、教条、任性、阴郁、愤怒、偏狭，可同时又虔诚、尽责、勤奋、任劳任怨、耐心，且温柔对待她所爱的人。

玛丽·罗宾逊描述十五岁的艾米莉“个高，臂长，发育成熟，步履轻快。穿上她最好的衣服时显得身材纤细，有种女王般的威严，但是当她懒散地在荒野上漫步，对狗打着口哨，或大步流星地走在高低不平的土地上时，又不羁如男孩。总之，她是个又高又瘦、看起来松松垮垮的女孩。她不丑，但五官不端正，皮肤苍白且粗糙。她的暗色头发自然是美的，后来一些年在脑后松松绾成一个高髻也还不错。但在一八三三年，她留的细密小卷却不好看。她的眼睛很美，呈浅褐色”。她也像父兄姐妹们一样戴眼镜。她的鼻子是鹰钩鼻，富有表情的嘴巴大而突出。她穿衣服并不考虑时尚，羊腿袖早就不流行了她还穿着，一条直筒长裙裹在她瘦长的身躯之上。

她和夏洛特一同去了布鲁塞尔。她讨厌布鲁塞尔。朋友们想对这两个女孩表示友好，就在星期天和节假日请她们来家，但她俩太害羞，去的话对她们而言等于受罪。过了一段时间后，邀请者们得出结论：不请她们是更友好的做法。艾米莉对社交场上的闲聊毫无耐心，大部分闲聊当然都很琐碎，无非是为了表示善意，人们之所以加入其中，是因为这是教养所在。艾米莉自己太害羞，不加入，还恼怒那些加入的人。她的害羞中既因为羞怯也因为傲慢。如果说她真腼腆，可她又穿得那么显眼，真害羞的人一般是没有那种展示癖的。她穿着那些古怪的羊腿袖衣服，可能会让人觉得她在故意显示她对普通人的蔑视，虽然她身处他们当中，舌头却像打了结一样地口不能言。

在学校里，每到休息时间，两姐妹总是一起散步，艾米莉紧靠着她姐姐，一般不说话。如果有人和她们说话，都是夏洛特回答，艾米莉几乎不和人说话。她俩比其他女孩大好几岁，她们不喜欢后者的吵闹、兴致勃勃，以及女孩们在那个年龄自然都有的那股傻劲。埃热先生认为艾米莉聪明，但是太固执，遇到和她愿望、理念不同的事时，毫不讲理。他认为她以自我为中心，苛刻，对夏洛特也太专制，但他承认她身上有种不同寻常的东西。她本应是个男人。他说：“她那坚强傲慢的意志绝不会被反对或困难吓倒，也绝不会屈服，除非是对死亡。”

布兰威尔姨妈死后，艾米莉回到哈沃斯，这对她来说是永远的回归，从此她再也没有离开过。她似乎只有在那里才能活在她的梦想中，而这些梦想既是她生活的慰藉，也是她生活的折磨。

她是全家起床最早的，在老弱的女仆泰比下楼前，她就把家里最辛苦的活儿都干了。她熨衣服，做饭的活也大部分是她干的。她烤面包，而且烤得不错。揉面的时候她会扫一眼面前支起来的书。“那些跟她在厨房一起干活的、活儿多时从村里临时雇来的年轻女孩记得，她身边会放一张纸和一支铅笔。灵感来时，她会暂停手上的熨烫和蒸煮的活儿，匆忙在纸上写下一些想法，然后继续干活。据说，她对这些女孩总是热情友好，有时像个小男孩一样开朗快活。她和善亲切，有点男子气，但她面对陌生人时却非常羞怯。如果肉店或面包店的伙计来到厨房门口，她会像鸟一样飞进门厅或客厅，直到听到他们沉重的鞋钉声从路上远去才出来。”她不喜欢男人，对她父亲的助理牧师们也没有平常该有的礼貌，只除了一个人，那就是威廉·魏特曼牧师。他被形容成一个年轻英俊、口才流利、风趣机智的人，并且“外貌、仪态和品味上有点女气”。勃朗特家都管他叫西莉亚·阿米莉亚小姐。艾米莉和他相处得极好。原因不难知道。梅·辛克莱在其名为“勃朗特三姐妹”的书中常用“阳刚”一词来形容艾米莉。罗默·威尔逊谈到她时也说：“那位孤独的父亲是否在她身上看到了自己？是否感到她是家里除他以外唯一的男性？……她早就知道自己心里住着一个男孩，长大后这个男孩变成了男人。”夏洛特小说中的谢莉据说就是以艾米莉为原型创作的，而谢莉的老家庭教师责备她不该老说自己是个男人，这事有点怪。女孩这么说话是不常见的，大家只能猜测这个习惯来自艾米莉。她性格和行为中那些令她的同代人感到不安的东西，今天很容易解释。同性恋在当时不像现在一样能公开讨论——尽管现在讨论的尺度经常大到令人尴尬——但同性恋在当时是存在的，男女都有，就像自古以来一直都有一样。很有可能艾米莉本人、她的家人、她家人的朋友（因为我刚说了她自己没朋友）都不知道她这么怪的原因到底为何。

盖斯凯尔夫人不喜欢她。有人告诉她艾米莉“从没对任何人表现过关心，她的爱都留给了动物”。她喜欢的动物都是野蛮难驯的那种。有人给过她一只名叫“看守”的牛头犬。关于这只狗，盖斯凯尔夫人讲过一个故事：“‘看守’只要和朋友在一起，就会显示出它天性深处的忠诚。但是如果有人用棍子或鞭子打它，也会激起它凶残的兽性。它会立刻扑上去咬住那人的咽喉，而且咬住不松口，直到你死或者我亡的地步。‘看守’在家的一个毛病是喜欢偷偷上楼，把自己黄褐色的四方身体舒舒服服地伸展在床上，还要盖上白色的精美被单。可是牧师家极爱干净，‘看守’的这个毛病又太讨厌，于是艾米莉在泰比的抗议下，宣布它如果下次再犯，她本人将不顾警告，也不顾这只畜生的凶恶本性，使劲打它，打到它不再犯为止。于是一个秋天的黄昏，泰比半是得意、半是颤抖，同时也无比愤怒地赶来告诉艾米莉，‘看守’现在又躺到了最好的床上，正昏昏欲睡地享受呢。夏洛特看到艾米莉脸色惨白，嘴唇紧闭，但她不敢说话干预。任何人看到艾米莉的眼睛在她苍白的脸上那样冒着火，看到她的嘴唇紧闭，显得非常吓人，都不敢开口。她上了楼，夏洛特和泰比则站在楼下昏暗的走廊里，四周布满了夜幕降临时的暗影。艾米莉拽着极不情愿的‘看守’的脖子下了楼，它的后腿一副坚决抵抗的样子，一边野蛮地低吼着。旁观者想说话而不敢说，生怕分散了艾米莉的注意力，使她扭过头来而疏于防范那头发怒的畜生。下楼后她在一个黑暗的角落里站好，把狗松开。没时间拿棍棒了，因为害怕那畜生对着她的脖子咬上致命的一下，她就在它还来不及将她扑倒时，赤手空拳地痛打那狗凶狠的红眼。用赛马的行话来说，她‘惩罚’了它，把它的眼都打肿了。然后这个半瞎的、被打蒙了的畜生被领回它本来的巢穴，而给它肿了的头做热敷、照顾它的不是别人，正是艾米莉。”

夏洛特写到艾米莉时，说：“她当然是公正无私、充满活力的。可是她如果不像我希望的那样驯顺和能接受不同意见，我也必须记得完美本就不是上帝对人类的安排。”艾米莉的脾气阴晴不定，姐妹们怕她似乎不是一点半点。从夏洛特的信中我们可以猜知，艾米莉令她迷惑，也常令她生气，很明显她也不知该如何看待《呼啸山庄》。她不知道她妹妹写了一部惊人的独创之作，和这本书相比，她自己的那些著作都只能说是平凡的。为此书辩护使她感到勉强。当有人提议将它重新出版时，她承担了编辑工作。“我于是迫使自己从头到尾读了一遍，自我妹妹死后，这是我第一次翻开这本书，”她写道，“它的力量再次使我感到敬佩，可也使我感到压抑。读者几乎不被允许拥有一丝纯粹的乐趣，每一缕阳光都仿佛穿过层层阴沉的乌云才倾注下来，每一页都充斥着如电流般的道德激情，而作者却毫不自知。”还有：“如果读她的手稿，她作品的考察者会被如此无情和不可调和的自然的导向力量所震颤，被如此失落和堕落的人类精神所震颤；如果有人抱怨听到某些生动可怕的场景晚上会睡不着觉，白天会心里不平静，那么艾利斯·贝尔会纳闷这是什么意思，会怀疑那个抱怨的人矫情。如果她还活着，她的头脑将会长成一棵茁壮的树——更高，更直，树冠也更纷披阔大——它成熟的果实也将更甘美，更润泽。但对于这样一个头脑，只有时间和经验能起作用，它不接受其他智者的影响。”我倾向于认为夏洛特从来都没有了解过她妹妹。

4

《呼啸山庄》是本非凡的书。大体而言，小说反映时代，不仅写法是当时常见的写法，也符合当时的舆论氛围、作者的道德观以及作者所接受或拒斥的偏见。即使天赋没那么高，年轻的大卫·科波菲尔也可能会写出一本像《简·爱》那样的小说来。亚瑟·潘登尼斯(4)也可能会写出一本类似夏洛特·勃朗特的《维莱特》那样的小说来，虽然劳拉的影响无疑会使他回避写像勃朗特书中那样赤裸裸的、给此书以一种哀怨感觉的性场面。但是《呼啸山庄》是个例外。它和当时的小说截然不同。它是一本很坏的小说，也是一本很好的小说。它很丑，又很美。它既可怕、令人痛苦，又强有力、充满热情。有人认为一个牧师的女儿，一个过着单调隔绝的生活，不认识几个人，也没见过世面的牧师的女儿是不可能写出这样的作品的。我却认为这很荒唐。《呼啸山庄》有种狂野的浪漫，那种浪漫主义远离现实主义的耐心观察，醉心于想象力无拘无束的飞翔，而且有时兴致勃勃、有时却又抑郁忧伤，沉溺于恐怖、神秘、激情和暴力之中。艾米莉·勃朗特的性格如此，她的情感又那样激烈和压抑（我们对她的了解提示了我们这一点），《呼啸山庄》正该是她写得出来的那种书。但是从表面看来，这书更像是她那个无赖哥哥布兰威尔写的，确实也有些人相信是布兰威尔写了此书的部分或者全部。其中有一人名叫弗朗西斯·格兰蒂，他说：“帕特里克·勃朗特告诉我《呼啸山庄》有很大一部分是他写的，他姐姐的话也证实了这一点……我们在莱顿顿脚一起散步时，他常用他那病态的天才独有的古怪想象力博我愉悦，现在这想象力又出现在了小说的书页间，我倾向于认为此书的情节是他的创作而非源于其妹。”有一次，布兰威尔的两个朋友，一个叫蒂尔顿，一个叫莱兰，和他约好了要在通往凯格利的一个路边小旅馆见面，他们要在那儿互相朗读各自的诗歌作品。以下是二十年后蒂尔顿写给哈利法克斯《卫报》的话：“我读了《恶魔女王》的第一幕，但是当布兰威尔把手伸进帽子去找的时候——他常把即兴之作放在此处——他以为他放进去的是诗的手稿，没想到错把几页小说放了进去，用他自己的话说，这部小说是他的‘学徒之作’。他为自己引起的失望感到懊丧，正要把那几页小说放进帽子里，我们却诚挚地请他读读这几页文字，因为我们很好奇，想看看他的小说文笔如何。稍加犹豫后，他答应了我们的请求，并在接下来的一小时内彻底吸引了我们的注意，他每读完一页就把这页放到帽子里。故事在一句话中间戛然而止了，但他口头告诉了我们后续的事，包括人物原型的真名叫什么，但是这些人中有些还在世，我就不对公众指出他们是谁了。他说他还没确定此书最终叫什么，也怕永远都遇不到一个有胆量把它推向公众的出版商。布兰威尔读的这个片段及其中的人物（就其发展而言）正是《呼啸山庄》中的情节和人物，正是夏洛特自信地断言属于她妹妹艾米莉的那部作品。”

这或许是谎言，或许是事实。夏洛特蔑视她弟弟，也在基督教博爱精神允许的范围内恨着她弟弟。但是我们都知道，基督教的博爱是从来都容许很多诚实的恨存在的。这样一来，夏洛特这些未经证实的话就不能被接受了。她可能像人类经常做的那样，劝她自己相信了她想要相信的那些事。这个故事很详尽，没有特殊理由却要编造这样的故事是很怪的。怎么解释？没法解释。据说布兰威尔写了前四章，然后又酗酒又吸毒的他放弃了，艾米莉于是接了过去。有一种观点说这四章写得比后来的章节呆板，我认为这个观点站不住脚。假如这四章真的更浮夸，我认为这是因为艾米莉想要证明洛克伍德是个愚蠢自负的傻瓜，她的这种努力还是很成功的。我毫不怀疑是艾米莉，而且是艾米莉一个人，写了《呼啸山庄》。

必须承认此书写得很差。勃朗特姐妹写得都不怎么好。正如她们的家庭教师身份一样，她们的文字风格浮夸卖弄，“文绉绉”（literatise）一词正是因此才发明的。《呼啸山庄》主要由迪恩太太讲述，她是个像泰比一样什么活都干的约克郡女仆。本来谈话的风格会很适合她，但艾米莉却让她用一种与她的身份极不相符的方式来说话。以下是一个典型的表达：“我试着消除有关这一问题的所有焦虑，通过不断的重复来证明：对于信任的背叛（如果值得用这样一个严重的词的话）将会是最后一次。”艾米莉·勃朗特也许察觉到了，迪恩太太说的一些词句是她这样身份的人不可能知道的。为了解释这点，她说迪恩太太在干活的过程中有机会读书，但是即便如此，她话里的那种自命不凡也一样令人震惊。对她来说，“读信”是“览笺”，“送信”是“致函”，“离开房间”是“退出内室”，她管“她干一天活”叫“她日间的职业”，她“肇始”而不是“开始”。不是“喊叫”，而是“喧嚣聒噪”，人们不是“听”而是“闻”。这真悲哀，一个牧师的女儿如此努力地想要写得像个淑女，可也只不过达到了假斯文的效果。但是我们并不期待《呼啸山庄》写得优雅，这书哪怕写得再优雅也不会比现在更好。正如描绘基督下葬的早期弗兰德斯绘画一样，画面上人物憔悴，脸上表情痛苦，姿态僵硬笨拙，似乎给这一场景增添了一种更大的恐怖和一种真实的残酷。但是比起被提香画得很美的同一题材，弗兰德斯绘画却更见沉痛悲惨。所以在《呼啸山庄》风格化的粗糙语言中，有种东西增强了故事里的激烈情感。

《呼啸山庄》的故事结构也很拙劣。这不奇怪，艾米莉以前从未写过小说，她想讲的这个故事又非常复杂，涉及两代人。这个事情不好办，作者需得给两套人物和两套事件赋予一种统一性，必须小心不让其中一套人物遮蔽了另一套人物的光彩。这一点艾米莉并不成功。自从凯瑟琳·恩肖死后，这书就失去了力量，只除了最后几页还算富有想象力。第二代凯瑟琳是个并不令人满意的角色，艾米莉·勃朗特似乎不知该拿她怎么办才好。很明显，她不能赋予她第一代凯瑟琳的激情与独立，也不能赋予她她父亲那样的愚蠢和软弱。她是个被宠坏了的、没有头脑、任性、没礼貌的小东西。对于她所受的罪，读者不大可能特别同情。她是怎么爱上哈里顿的，过程并不清楚。哈里顿的形象很模糊，除了阴郁英俊，读者对他一无所知。在我看来，写这个故事的作者不得不把很多年间发生的事压缩到读者能接受的一段时间之内，以便读者能一目了然；就像是一个人可以一眼就看清一幅巨大的壁画的全貌一样。我不认为艾米莉·勃朗特曾经深思熟虑过，如何把一种统一性注入一个零散的故事中去，但我猜她一定自问过如何才能使故事连贯，很可能她想到的最好的办法就是让故事中的一个人物对另一个人物讲述这一长串事件。这是个讲故事的便捷方法，而且也不是她发明了这个方法。但这个方法的缺点是无法保持谈话的风格，因为叙述者要讲的事太多，比如描述一下景色等，没有哪个神志正常的人会这么谈话。而且，如果有叙述者（迪恩太太），就必须得有听众（洛克伍德）。一个有经验的小说家确实有可能会找到一种更好的方法写《呼啸山庄》，但是即使艾米莉·勃朗特真的用了一种更好的方法讲述这个故事，我也不认为那是因为她利用了别人的创作。

但是除此以外，我想艾米莉之所以采用这种叙述方法大概也算意料之中。想想她的性格吧，那么极端、病态、害羞和寡言。不这么写还能怎么写呢？写《呼啸山庄》必须要像写《米德尔马契》和《包法利夫人》一样采用全知视角。假如她把这个肆无忌惮的故事讲成她自己的创作，那会撼动她那格格不入、不妥协的高尚品德。此外，她还要不可避免地讲讲希斯克厉夫在离开呼啸山庄后的那几年都干了些什么，怎么受的教育，怎么赚了那么多钱。她讲不了，因为她不知道。她要求读者接受的那些事实是很难令读者相信的，而她则满足于说了就好，说完就不管了。另一个办法是让迪恩太太用第一人称把故事讲给艾米莉·勃朗特听，但我怀疑这样做也会使她与读者的接触太亲密，让她本就战栗的敏感个性承受不了。开头她让洛克伍德讲故事，后来又让迪恩太太给洛克伍德讲故事，这样她就可以躲在双重面具的后面。说到面具，勃朗特先生曾给盖斯凯尔夫人讲过一个颇有意思的故事。孩子们小的时候，他为了发现他们在羞怯外表下隐藏的真正本性，就让他们轮流戴上一个旧面具，好让他们在回答他的提问时能够更自在。他问夏洛特世界上最好的书是什么，夏洛特回答说《圣经》。但是当他问艾米莉他应该如何对待她那讨厌的哥哥布兰威尔时，她却说：“和他讲道理，他要是不听，就用鞭子抽他。”

为什么艾米莉在写这部气势恢宏、热情和令人惊骇的书的时候需要把自己藏起来呢？我认为她在这本书里暴露了她内心最深处的本能。她深深望进自己内心那口孤井，她在那里看到不可明言的秘密，但她作为作家的本能却驱使她卸下负担。据说她的想象力曾被她父亲讲的那些他年轻时候爱尔兰发生的奇特故事所激发；也有人说她在布鲁塞尔求学时曾被她读到的霍夫曼(5)的故事所激发，这些故事在她回到哈沃斯的家中后，坐在火炉边的地毯上，一手搂着“看守”的脖子，一边还在继续读着。我愿意相信，她在德国浪漫主义作家的作品中发现了神秘、暴力和恐怖，因此迎合了她那激烈的性格，但是我认为她在自己灵魂的深处找到了希斯克厉夫和凯瑟琳·恩肖。她就是希斯克厉夫，她就是凯瑟琳·恩肖。她把自己放到她书中的两个主人公身上是否奇怪呢？一点都不。我们没有一个人是浑然一体的，我们心里住着不止一个人，而且他们还经常彼此矛盾。小说家的独特之处就在于他可以把那些将他拼合起来的各类人物在个体人物身上生动地表现出来。而小说家的不幸之处在于在他所创造的人物身上总会包含他自身的一部分，不管这些人物对他的故事来说多么重要。这就是为什么《呼啸山庄》中的二代凯瑟琳不能令人满意的原因了。

我认为艾米莉把她自己的全部都注入希斯克厉夫身上。她把她的狂怒，强烈但受挫的性，没有得到满足的爱，她的嫉妒，她对人类的仇恨和蔑视，她的残酷和虐待狂心理都给了他。读者还记得她曾因一点小事就赤手空拳怒打她那条爱犬的故事，而她很可能从未像爱那条狗那样爱过人类。艾伦·纽西还讲了另外一桩怪事。“她喜欢把夏洛特带到夏洛特一个人怎么也不敢去的地方。夏洛特对未知的动物有种致命的恐惧，可艾米莉就喜欢把她带到这种动物的近旁，告诉她自己做了什么，是怎么做的，然后极其开心地嘲笑她姐姐的恐惧。”我认为艾米莉是以希斯克厉夫的男性之爱、兽性之爱，爱着凯瑟琳·恩肖。我认为正如她嘲笑夏洛特的恐惧一样，当她化身为希斯克厉夫，踢打和践踏恩肖(6)，拿他的头去撞石板地时，她是这样开心大笑的。当她化身为希斯克厉夫，扇小凯瑟琳的脸、骂她，她也是这样大笑的。我想当她欺负、辱骂、恐吓她创造出来的人物时，她就感到了一种放松的刺激，因为在现实生活中，她和人相处时总觉得遭受了同样的屈辱。我认为当她作为凯瑟琳时——这就像她多了一重角色——虽然她和希斯克厉夫对抗，鄙视他，知道他就是一头牲口，但她仍然全身心地爱着他，为自己拥有操控他的能力而欣喜。同时，因为施虐者也是受虐者，她也被他的暴力、野蛮和野性未驯的本性所吸引。她认为他俩是同类，他俩确实也是，如果我对他俩都是艾米莉·勃朗特的假设没错的话。“耐莉，我就是希斯克厉夫。”凯瑟琳叫道，“他永远永远在我心里，他并不是作为一种乐趣，他不见得比我对我自己更有趣些，他就是我自身的存在。”

《呼啸山庄》是个爱情故事，它可能是人类写过的最奇怪的爱情故事，其中一个怪异之处是相爱的人们居然能始终保持贞洁。凯瑟琳热烈地爱着希斯克厉夫，就像希斯克厉夫热烈地爱着她一样。而对埃德加·林顿，凯瑟琳感到的只是一种仁慈的、经常还很绝望的容忍。我们纳闷两个爱得如此痴狂的人为何没有私奔，哪怕他们面临的将是贫困。我们纳闷他们为什么没有变成真正的爱人。可能艾米莉所受的家教让她把通奸看成不可饶恕的原罪，也可能是想到两性性行为让她恶心。我相信勃朗特姐妹俩都是性欲强烈之人。夏洛特相貌平平，肤色灰黄，鼻子很大，还有点歪。她没名没钱的时候得到过几次求婚，在她那个时代，男人们希望妻子结婚时能带来嫁妆。不过美貌不是让女人具有吸引力的唯一条件，何况一个女人如果很美还会让人觉得恐惧。你会欣赏，但是不会感动。如果年轻男人爱上夏洛特这个挑剔、爱批评的女人，那只能是因为他们觉得她有性吸引力，也就是说他们隐约感觉到她性欲强烈。她刚嫁给尼克斯时并不爱他，她认为他狭隘、教条、阴郁、毫不聪明。但是婚后从她的通信中却可以得知，她对他的感觉变了。就她的为人而言，这些信实在轻佻。她爱上了他，他的缺点都不重要了。最可能的解释就是她的那些性欲终于得到了满足。没有理由认为艾米莉的性欲没夏洛特强。

5

一部小说的诞生是桩奇事。据我们目前所知，艾米莉一生只写了一部小说，而一个小说家的第一部小说可能包含心想事成的因素和想象的自传因素。可以认为《呼啸山庄》纯粹是想象的产物。谁知道在那无眠夜晚的漫长守望中，或是夏日里一整天躺在石南花丛中的时候，她曾有过怎样色情的狂想？大家一定注意到了在夏洛特的罗切斯特和艾米莉的希斯克厉夫之间有着怎样家人般的相似。希斯克厉夫可能是个私生子，是罗切斯特家的小儿子和一个爱尔兰下女在利物浦生的。这两个人都黝黑、暴力、面带凶相、暴躁、热烈和神秘。罗切斯特和希斯克厉夫的区别仅仅在于创造了他们，想用他们来满足自己迫切的、受阻的性欲的两姐妹的性情的区别。罗切斯特是一个有着正常本能的女人的梦想，这个女人渴望把自己交付给一个有控制欲的无情男性，而艾米莉则给了希斯克厉夫她自己的阳刚、暴烈和野蛮脾气。姐妹俩创造的这两个粗野、执拗的男人的原型，我猜，是她们的父亲帕特里克·勃朗特牧师。

但是即使真如我所说，艾米莉可能完全是从幻想中创造了《呼啸山庄》，我也并不相信。我会认为，最终产生小说的那些丰饶想法很少如流星般突然从天而降到一个作家的脑子里。绝大多数情况下，这些想法都得自经验，主要是作家个人的情感经验。或者，如果这些经验是由别人告诉作家的，那么这些经验在感情上也必须能吸引人。随后作家的想象力开始如生产般阵痛，人物和事件也逐渐从中生长，直至成品诞生。但是很少有人知道，一个暗示哪怕再小，一件事哪怕看起来再微不足道，也足以擦出火花，点燃作者的创作之火。当你注视一朵仙客来时，当你看到它那心形的叶子包围着好多花，无忧无虑的花瓣带点任性的表情，似乎是随意生长，你会觉得不可思议，因为这样妖娆的美丽、这样艳丽的颜色居然是从一粒比针尖大不了多少的种子里产生的。那么，一粒能催生想象的种子也可以孕育出一本不朽的好书。

在我看来，似乎只有从艾米莉的诗中才能猜测她的感情经历到底是什么，是什么使她写下了《呼啸山庄》，好让她从那残酷的痛苦中寻求解脱。她写了好多诗。她的诗作质量参差不齐：有些平庸，有些感人，有些可爱。她用得最得心应手的韵似乎是赞美诗的韵，就像她周日在哈沃斯教区教堂唱的那些赞美诗一样，但是即使她用韵平庸，也掩盖不住其下强烈的情感。很多诗都出自《冈德尔岛纪事》，那是她和安妮在幼时为了自娱所写的想象中的一个岛的历史，成年后艾米莉还在继续写。之所以如此，可能是因为她觉得这样方便她发泄心中的痛苦。以她秘而不宣的沉默性格，她是不能忍受用别的方式排遣痛苦的。她的其他诗似乎是感情的直接表达。一八四五年，也就是她死前三年，她写了首诗叫《囚徒》。就我们所知，她从未读过任何神秘主义者的作品，可这首诗却描述了一种神秘的体验，要说它没反映个人经历是不可能的。她用的词几乎正是神秘主义者在形容他们在静思中与其神灵结合后返回自我时感到痛苦的情况下所用的那些词：

噢，那抑制多可怕，痛苦多强烈；
当耳朵开始听到，眼睛开始看到；
当脉搏开始跳动，头脑开始再次思考；
当灵魂开始感到肉体，而肉体开始感到锁链。

这些诗句无疑反映了一种体验，一种被深刻感知的体验。为什么有人觉得艾米莉·勃朗特的爱情诗仅仅是文学练习？我认为这些诗清楚地显示出她曾经爱过，曾经被拒绝，曾经深刻地受到伤害。她写这些诗时正值她在哈利法克斯附近的罗山女校教书。那时她十九岁。这可能是她人生中唯一的一次恋爱。也可能正是因此造成的痛苦足以给她在受折磨的情感沃土中埋下了那粒种子，才使她日后写出了那本我们如今都了解了的奇书。但这只不过是猜测。我想不起还有哪本小说把爱的痛苦、狂喜和残酷表现得如此强烈。《呼啸山庄》有很大的缺陷，但是并不要紧，就像倒下的树干、散乱的岩石和吹聚的堆雪虽然会造成阻碍，但却无法阻止阿尔卑斯山的激流从山坡奔腾而下。你无法把《呼啸山庄》与其他书相比，你只能把它与西班牙画家格列柯的伟大画作相比。黑沉沉的乌云下是一片阴暗荒芜的景象，惊雷滚滚，瘦长憔悴的人姿态扭曲，他们似乎为某种非尘世的情感所镇，都屏住了呼吸。一道闪电划过晦暗的天空，为此情此景赋予了一种神秘的恐怖。

(1) 圣帕特里克（385—461）是爱尔兰的守护神，死于三月十七日，三月十七日因此成了一个文化和宗教节日，如今更被当作爱尔兰的国庆日。

(2) 而“勃朗特”的英文拼写则为Brontë。

(3) 1738年由英国人卫斯理兄弟于伦敦创立。卫斯理兄弟以感情丰富的方式讲道，在当时的教会文化中并不受欢迎，特别对当时讲求冷静的英国国教圣公会来说，是很大的极端，因此常被赶出教会外，不允许他们以这种热情的方式在会堂里讲道。

(4) 亚瑟·潘登尼斯是英国作家萨克雷（1811—1863）同名小说的主人公，小说全名为“潘登尼斯的历史：他的幸运与不幸，他的朋友与大敌”，讲一名出身于中产阶级的青年成长为作家的故事，有一定自传性质，常被人拿来与《大卫·科波菲尔》比较。下文的劳拉是书中潘登尼斯幼时的伙伴和成人后的爱人。

(5) 霍夫曼（1776—1822），德国后期浪漫派的重要作家，还有绘画和作曲的才能，他的文学作品内容多神秘怪诞，其自由联想、内心独白、夸张荒诞、多重层次结构的手法和后来的现代主义文学间有着很深的渊源。

(6) 指凯瑟琳的哥哥辛德雷·恩肖。

吉卜林与其短篇小说

（1953）

我在本文中将只谈鲁德亚德·吉卜林的短篇小说，不谈其诗歌，也不谈其政治观点，除非其政治观点直接影响到了小说。

我既然要编一个吉卜林的短篇小说选集，就必须决定是否只选我最喜爱的那些故事。要是只选我喜欢的，我就会把他几乎所有写印度的小说都选进去了，因为在我看来，这些印度故事是他写得最好的短篇。他写印度人或在印度的英国人时最得心应手，写起来轻松、流畅、手法多样，这给了他的印度故事一种特质，一种他写其他题材的小说时不是总能拥有的特质。甚至他最不起眼的印度故事都很可读。它们会给你一种东方的感觉，那种集市的气息，雨季时的沉闷，大地被太阳炙烤的热度，占领军驻扎的军营里的艰苦生活，以及那些联合治理印度大片疆域的英国军官、公务员以及大批小官员过得如此英国，又如此异于英国的另类生活。

很多年前，在吉卜林最享盛名之时，我有时会遇到一些在印度的英国公务员和大学教授，他们说起他时，简直就是语带轻蔑。这有一部分原因是出于不光彩却也自然而然的嫉妒心。这么一个没有社会地位的无名记者居然获得了世界性的知名度，他们当然感到愤愤不平。他们抗议说他不懂印度。可是他们就懂吗？印度不是一个国家，印度是一片大陆。吉卜林似乎确实只了解印度西北部。就像其他明智的作家一样，他把故事的场景安排在他最熟悉的地区。英印(1)批评家们指责吉卜林不写那些他们认为重要的题目。吉卜林的同情心在穆斯林而非印度教徒身上。他对印度教兴趣不大，可印度教却是影响广大印度民众最深的宗教。穆斯林身上有些品质引起了他的钦佩之情，而他说起印度教徒时则很少语带欣赏，他似乎从未想过他们中也有博学之士、杰出的科学家和能干的哲学家。比如，在他看来，孟加拉人是懦夫、混混和吹牛者，是个一遇紧急情况就惊慌失措、逃避责任的人。这很遗憾，不过吉卜林有权按自己的意愿处理他的题材，就像每个作家都有权这么做一样。

但是我感觉，如果我只在本卷中收录吉卜林的印度小说，将不能使读者公平地见识到吉卜林的多种才能，我于是也选了几个以英国为场景的、广受赞誉的故事。

有关吉卜林的生平细节，我将只叙述那些与他的短篇小说有关的，再多就与我的目的不符了。一八六五年吉卜林出生于孟买，父亲在孟买的一所大学做建筑雕塑系教授。五岁多点的时候，他父母带他和他妹妹回了英国，把他俩寄养在一户人家里。可是照顾他们兄妹的那个女人又蠢又恶，两个孩子的日子过得很悲惨。可怜的小男孩总是受欺负、被打骂。多年后，他母亲又一次回国省亲时发现了孩子们的真实处境，这一发现让她惊怒万分，于是带两个孩子离开了那里。十二岁时，吉卜林被送到西侯村上学。学校叫联合服务学院，当时刚成立不久，主要是给那些以后准备参军的官员子弟提供学费低廉的教育，以便他们将来进入军队。学校里有大约两百个男孩，统一安排住在一排宿舍里。这个学校实际什么样与我无关，我在这里只谈一下吉卜林在名曰“斯托基公司”的小说里描写的它的样子。很难有比这更可憎的学校生活了。除了校长和牧师，所有老师都被写成野蛮残忍、头脑狭隘和不能胜任的德行。男孩们号称是绅士的后代，却无任何合乎身份的天资。吉卜林给故事的三个主人公起名为斯托基(2)、火鸡和甲虫。斯托基是首领，他是吉卜林完美理想的化身，是勇敢仗义、足智多谋、富于冒险、斗志高昂的士兵与绅士。甲虫是吉卜林的自画像。这三人表现幽默的方式是通过异常糟糕的恶作剧。吉卜林兴致勃勃地讲述他们的故事。公平地说，他的故事讲得太好，虽然让你读了直起鸡皮疙瘩，但是你一旦开始读就肯定会读完。如果不是因为在我看来，吉卜林在这个他叫作“公司”的学校待的那四年对他影响至深，以至于他后来的整个写作生涯都未能摆脱其影响，我根本就不会愿意多说关于那个学校的事。吉卜林从未能摆脱他当时形成的那些印象、偏见和心态，也没有迹象表明他愿意摆脱。直到最后他都对四年级男生混战扭打、嘲笑作弄和野蛮的恶作剧兴趣不减，对他们用恶作剧取乐津津乐道。他似乎从未想过那个学校是个三流学校，那群男孩是帮烂仔。事实上，多年后当他重新造访这个学校时，他居然写了篇可爱的文章，对那位厉行纪律的老校长大加称颂，对自己在他当年的照管之下获益良多表达了感激之情。

吉卜林未满十七岁时，他在拉合尔(3)当博物馆馆长的父亲给他在当地找了一份工作——在一份名为“军民报”的英文报纸做助理编辑，于是他离开学校回了印度。这是一八八二年的事。他踏入的那个世界与我们今天生活的世界大不相同。大不列颠正处于巅峰时刻，有张地图用粉红色标示出地球表面的大片土地都在维多利亚女王的统治之下。母国无比富有。英国人是这世界的银行家。英国商会将其产品输送到地球最远的角落，而其产品的质量也被广泛认为高于其他任何国家生产的产品的质量。除了这里或那里偶发的一些小小的惩戒性的远征外，帝国内部到处是一派和平景象。英国军队规模虽小却自信，尽管有马朱巴山的战败(4)，英军仍然相信自己能抵挡得住任何可能与之对抗的军队。英国海军也是世界最强的。英国在运动方面同样无人能比，英国人玩的运动项目没人能赢得了。经典马术比赛中，基本没听说过外国马能赢英国马。这种美好局面像是会一直继续下去，没有什么可以将它改变。我们这个岛国的居民信仰上帝，放心相信上帝已经把大英帝国置于了他的特殊保护之下。诚然，爱尔兰人是在自找讨厌。诚然，工厂工人报酬太低，工作过度劳累。但这似乎是国家工业化不可避免的结果，谁也无能为力，那些想要改善工人状况的改革者被认为是些有害的捣蛋者。诚然，农民们住在肮脏简陋的破屋里，挣着少得可怜的工资，但是地主阶级的女施主们对他们心怀善意。她们中很多人都在忙于救助农民的道德福祉事业，在他们生病时会给他们送牛肉汤和小牛蹄肉冻，还给他们的孩子送衣服。人们说这世界总是有穷有富，将来也会一直如此，这事于是就这样算了。

英国人常去欧洲大陆旅游。他们挤满了疗养地、温泉、霍姆堡、埃克斯莱班、巴登巴登。他们冬天去里维埃拉，在戛纳和蒙特卡洛为自己建豪华别墅。一个个大旅馆盖了起来，就为接待他们住宿。他们很有钱，花起来也随便。他们感觉自己是一个单独的种族。他们一到加莱就意识到他们到了“当地人”中间，当然不是像印度人和中国人那样的“当地人”，但是总之是“当地人”。他们单独洗漱，旅游时常自带浴缸，证明自己与众不同。他们健康、好运动、有理智，各方面都高人一等。但他们喜欢在生活习惯和英国人不同的“当地人”中逗留，因为，虽然他们认为法国人轻浮，意大利人懒惰，德国人愚蠢可笑，但是本着天生的善良心地，他们喜欢这些“当地人”，认为这些外国人也喜欢他们。他们从没意识到他们受到的殷勤礼遇，那些鞠躬、微笑和想要取悦他们的想法其实都是因为他们舍得花钱。而在他们背后，这些“当地人”嘲笑他们衣着粗鄙、笨拙愚钝、举止糟糕，嘲笑他们傲慢，嘲笑他们傻得总是被人多收钱，嘲笑他们那种以恩人自居的宽容。只有付出战争的沉重代价才能让他们明白他们错得有多离谱。吉卜林回到拉合尔父母身边时所进入的英印社会，就像他们在不列颠的帝国同胞一样，一丝不少地分享了那种先入为主和沾沾自喜的想法。

吉卜林视力不好，无法参加运动，因此在学校时就有闲暇时间大量阅读和写作。校长似乎被他表现出来的潜力打动了，明智地允许他随意使用自己的藏书。后来吉卜林担任了《军民报》的助理编辑，就开始利用闲暇写一些故事，这些故事后来出版成书，叫“山中寻常事”。对我来说，这些故事的主要趣味在于他生动地描绘了他所打交道的那个世界的模样，那真是一副毁灭性的模样。他笔下没有一个人物对文学、艺术或音乐有任何兴趣。当时有个流行观念，似乎谁要想努力了解印度谁就很可疑。对一个人物，吉卜林曾这样写道：“他对印度人的了解正合适，知道得再多就不好了。”一个专注于工作的人是要被人怀疑的，往好里说这人是个怪人，往坏里说这人就是个讨厌鬼。这种生活空虚无聊，这些人自给自足，想想就让人害怕。他们是什么人？他们是普通的中产阶级，来自普通的英国家庭，是退休的政府公务员、牧师、医生和律师的儿女。他们中，男人头脑空空，参过军或进过大学的等于镀了一层金；而女人们则浅薄、偏狭、故作斯文。她们在无聊的调情中度日，最大乐趣似乎就是从别的女人那里撬走个把男人。大概因为吉卜林写这些故事时恰逢一个假正经的时代，他害怕会惊吓到他的读者，也可能他本就不愿写性，总之这些故事中虽然有很多关于调情的描写，却很少有性交的情节。不管女人们如何鼓励受她们吸引的男人，一到最后关头她们却退缩了。简而言之，她们就是英语里那个带连字符的粗鄙字眼所描述的对象，而法语则会比较文雅地称她们为“妖妇”。

奇怪的是，吉卜林虽然脑子快，善观察，读书多，对这些人的了解只停留在表层。当然，他那时很年轻，《山中寻常事》出版时他才二十二岁。经历了西侯村的野蛮残暴，乍一进入拉合尔博物馆馆长朴实低调的生活圈中时，他自然目眩神迷了。以他毫无经验的眼光看来，这个初相识的世界真是光彩照人，就像小布尔乔亚马塞尔(5)初次得入古尔芒特夫人的高尚圈子时感到的那种目眩神迷一样。但是霍克斯比夫人其实并不像吉卜林想让我们以为的那样机智诙谐。当他让她把一个女人的说话声音比作伦敦地铁驶入伯爵宫站时发出的刹车摩擦声，他就暴露了她沉闷无趣的本质。我们被要求相信她是个上流社会的淑女。可是果真如此的话，她就不会去伯爵宫了，除非是去见个老保姆。而且就算去伯爵宫，她也不该坐地铁，而是该乘双轮马车。

但是《山中寻常事》不只写英印社会，还写了印度生活和士兵生活。只要想想写下这些故事的作者当时才十几岁或二十出头，那么这些故事就表现出了令人震惊的能力。吉卜林说其中最好的故事是他父亲提供的，我想我们可以把这话归为孝心。我觉得作家很少能用得上别人给他的现成故事，就像真实生活中的人被转移到小说中时，很少能保持逼真的感觉一样。作家当然是先从某个地方得来想法，但那些想法不会像穿着甲胄、从父亲的脑袋里蹦出来的雅典娜一样，突然出现在作家的脑海中，立刻就能写。不过有一点确实很奇特：一个小小的暗示，一个模糊的建议，就能赋予作家足够的材料去创作，使他最终建构起一个妥帖的故事来。比如吉卜林后来的一个故事《他祖先的坟墓》。它需要的很可能只是吉卜林在拉合尔认识的某个军官随便说的一句话：“这些当地人真是可笑。有个家伙叫什么什么，他驻扎在北边的比尔人当中。他爷爷曾在那儿管了很多年事，死后埋在那儿。这些呆子不知怎么想的，以为他是老头的化身，以至于他能在这些人中为所欲为。”这就足以把吉卜林那生动的想象力调动起来，写出一篇愉快有趣的故事来。《山中寻常事》质量很不稳定，就像吉卜林的作品一直都时好时坏一样。我想这种情况对于一个短篇小说家而言是不可避免的。写短篇小说是件很容易失去平衡的事，写得好坏并不只取决于作者的构思、表达能力、结构技巧、创作才能与想象，还靠运气。就像在面对一小堆看起来全无区别的米珠时，聪明的日本人会从中随便拿起一个，塞入牡蛎，可是他无法说出它是能长成一颗圆润完美的珍珠呢，还是会变成一个既不美也不值钱的畸形物体。同样，作家对自己的作品并不能作出公平的判断。吉卜林本人对《幽灵人力车》的评价很高。我认为如果他写这个故事的时候能再成熟些，就会知道在对那个男人的行为的辩护上他的理解还是太浅了。如果你先前爱过一个有夫之妇，可是现在不爱了，又爱上了别的女人，想和后者结婚，这种事当然是不幸的，但是这种事确实存在。如果先前那个女人不肯接受现实，要追着你，在路上拦你，眼泪汪汪地骚扰你、求你，最后你开始不耐烦和发脾气，这也并非是不自然的。凯斯—魏兴顿太太是所有小说里最锲而不舍的纠缠者，因为即使她死了，她仍然继续在她的幽灵人力车里骚扰着那个可怜的男人。杰克·潘塞值得我们同情而不是责难。比起那些好写的、似乎可以自己写出来的故事，一个难写的故事，正因为难写，作者才更会予以重新考虑。有时候它根本是个心理错误，作者却没有意识到。有时候他在完成的小说里看到的是他先前在脑子里构思时看到的样子，而不是他已经写下来展示给读者看的样子。不过我们不应该惊讶吉卜林的小说有时很差、很琐碎、不可信，我们反而应该惊讶他的大多数小说都如此优秀。他真的是风格非常多样。

T．S．艾略特先生在他为吉卜林的诗所编的选集的序里似乎暗示，多样性对诗人而言并不是一个值得赞美的品质。我不敢在诗的问题上质疑艾略特先生的看法，但是如果多样性不是诗人的优点，它却绝对是小说家的优点。好的小说家有种特性，一定程度上人人都有这种特性，但小说家更甚，即他不只有一个自我，他是好多自我的奇异组合。或者如果这个说法太荒诞，也可以说小说家的个性中常有好些难以调和的方面。批评家们不明白同一个人怎么能既写了《布鲁格史密斯》，又能写了《退场赞美诗》，于是指责他不真诚。他们这么说才是真的不公正。是吉卜林身体里那个叫甲虫的自我写了《布鲁格史密斯》，而那个叫亚德利—奥德的自我写了《退场赞美诗》。我们大多数人在回顾己身的时候，有时能找到安慰，相信某个只能让我们遗憾的自我——毫无优点的自我——已经消失了。吉卜林的一个奇特之处在于，我们本以为那个叫甲虫的自我会随着吉卜林年龄的增长和阅历的增加而解体，没想到差不多到吉卜林死的那一天，它仍然活力依旧。

儿时在孟买，吉卜林和他的奶妈、仆人说印地语，印地语是他的母语。在自传《关于我自己》一书中，他说当他被带去见父母时，他会把他想说的话从印地语翻译成蹩脚的英语。可以推测，十七岁回印度后他又迅速恢复了印度语言的能力。还是在这本书中，吉卜林无比精彩地讲述了他如何在拉合尔获得写作素材，而且很快他就充分利用了这些素材。作为记者，“我报道大桥和此类工程的开工，这意味着有一两个晚上我要和工程师们待在一起。我报道洪水淹没铁路，这意味着我要和可怜的维修工们在雨中待得更久。我报道乡村节日以及随后爆发的霍乱或天花。我还报道发生在瓦兹尔汗清真寺的社群暴乱。当时，待命的部队耐心躲在木材厂或小巷里，只待命令一下，就冲进去用枪托击打群众的脚。这个号叫、灯火闪耀、沉醉在信条中的城市将被不流血地制服”……经常在晚上，“我会在各种奇怪的地方游荡至天明，比如毫不神秘的小酒馆、赌场和鸦片窝点，也会在路边看木偶戏、地方舞，或者走到瓦兹尔汗清真寺旁的狭窄小道上或者附近的地方，只是为了看看……还有在俱乐部或某个军队食堂喝醉的晚上，在那里，一桌男人已经难受得半疯了，却还有足够的知觉继续喝啤酒、掷骰子，只有啤酒和骰子不会辜负。他们想要纵情享乐，也算享乐到了……我去拉合尔堡的采访让我见识到了那个时代的军人，缅米尔的兵营也让我见识到了，只不过印象不如拉合尔堡深……既然不必考虑立场，我干的这行又要求我这样，我于是可以在四维空间(6)中自由穿梭。我开始理解一个士兵生活中的恐惧，以及那条规定‘罪的代价乃是死’的基督教义使他忍受的那些不必要的折磨。”

我在这本短篇选集中收录的两个故事的主角正是三个士兵：穆尔瓦尼、李尔洛德、奥塞莱斯。这两个故事都极受欢迎。我想，对大多数读者来说，这两个故事的缺点在于它们是用人物独特的方言写成的。作家该在这个方向上走多远不好说。显然，让穆尔瓦尼和奥塞莱斯这样的人像国王学院的教师那样用文雅的语言讲话是荒唐的，但是让他们自始至终说方言也会使叙述显得乏味。最好的办法可能就是用当事人的措辞、语法和词汇，但尽量少地再现其语音的独特之处，以免使读者感到不便。但这不是吉卜林的办法，他从语音上复现了这三个士兵的腔调。谁也挑不出李尔洛德的约克郡腔的毛病，因为吉卜林的父亲是约克郡人，他亲自纠正了李尔洛德的发音。但是批评家们已经说了，穆尔瓦尼的爱尔兰腔和奥塞莱斯的伦敦东区腔都不纯正。吉卜林是个描写高手，叙事精彩，但在我看来，他的对话却不是总能令人信服。他让奥塞莱斯说的某些话是这个人物绝对说不出来的话，就比如奥塞莱斯焉能引用麦考利的《古罗马之歌》？我也不相信一个像丛林男孩的母亲那样教养良好的女人能用“爹爹”这样的儿童用语向他说起他的父亲。有时候，军官们和官员们用的印度词汇太多了，令人难以置信。在我看来，吉卜林笔下的对话只有在他把印度人的谈话翻译成庄严有度的英语时才无可挑剔。读者须谨记，吉卜林儿时和父母说话时，都是不得不把他想说的话从印地语翻译成英语的。这大概是他感觉最自然的语言形式了。

一八八七年，当了五年《军民报》的助理编辑后，吉卜林被派到拉哈尔以南几百英里外的阿拉哈巴德，任职于一份相对更重要的姐妹报——《先锋报》。报纸的所有者想给国内办一份周刊，就让他来当主编。有一整版的版面都给了小说。吉卜林先前写《山中寻常事》时，每篇只限写一千两百字，现在空间够大，他可以写到五千字了。于是他写了“士兵故事、印度故事和女性故事”，其中就有那两篇有影响力又令人毛骨悚然的《兽斑》和《伊姆莱的归来》。

吉卜林这一阶段的短篇小说由惠勒的公司编成了六册平装的集子，收入“印度铁路丛书”中出版。他用这样挣来的钱和预付给他写游记的钱离开了印度，“取道远东和美国”前往英国。这是一八八九年。他已经在印度待了七年。他的小说也已在英国打响，而此时他仍然非常年轻。到达伦敦后，他发现不管他写什么，编辑们都会热切地接受。他在泰晤士河畔的维莱尔斯街住了下来，他在此处写的小说质量最高，他后来的作品虽然常常能达到那种质量，却从未超越它。这些作品包括《在格林豪山上》、《向戴娜·莎德的求爱》、《曾经的那个人》、《未经教会许可的婚姻》和《通道尽头》。新环境似乎使他对印度的回忆更加生动了，这种情况是有可能发生的。当作家生活在他故事发生的环境中，或生活在能启发他创作的人中间时，周围的人和事给他留下的印象太多太强，以至于他的头脑会糊涂起来，会只见森林不见树木。但是离开那里却会把他记忆中多余的细节和微末事件抹去，使他可以俯瞰他的写作题材。于是，多余的材料少了，不会妨碍他了，他就可以给他的小说找到一种形式，最终完成小说。

也就是在这个时候，他写了一个故事，叫《世界上最好的故事》。我觉得这个故事很有趣，因为他在故事中第一次写到了“轮回”。这个主题能吸引他是很自然的，因为印度教对“轮回”的信仰根深蒂固，其深信不疑就像十三世纪基督徒对“基督是童贞女所生以及基督的复活”深信不疑一样。游历过印度的人都会发现，这个信仰不光在没受过教育的人中根深蒂固，在有文化和有阅历的人中也同样如此。你会在谈话中听到、报纸上读到有人说他们记得前世的一些事。吉卜林在这个故事里处理轮回这个主题的方式非常富有想象力。他在一个名为“无线”的不那么著名的故事里又一次回到了这个主题。他在《无线》里充分利用了当时的一个新玩具——一个对那些科学爱好者而言的新玩具。他想让读者相信，他故事里那个得了肺结核、就快要死了的化学家助手有可能会在药物的作用下回想起他的前世来，而他在那一世名叫约翰·济慈。对于任何曾经去过济慈在罗马的那个小房间，曾经俯瞰过通向西班牙广场的那些台阶，也曾看过约瑟夫·塞文为济慈作的画像中那美丽憔悴的面容的人来说，吉卜林的故事真是哀伤无比。看到那个将死的化学家助手，同时还是个恋爱中人，在恍惚中绞尽脑汁地写济慈在《圣艾格尼斯之夜》中写的那些诗句真是刺激。这个故事可爱，讲得也好。

我上文提到过一个迷人的故事《他祖先的坟墓》。它写于《世界上最好的故事》完成六年后，吉卜林又一次在故事中写到了轮回，不过这次他的写法不会让人觉得牵强。因为比尔人，也就是故事发生地的山地居民们，相信故事的主人公，那个年轻的中尉，是他祖父的化身。而那位祖父曾在那些比尔人中生活了很久，直到现在他们还敬重他、回忆他。吉卜林从来没像这次这样成功地创造出一种令人难以定义的特点来，因为找不到更好的词，我们就先称之为“气氛”。

在伦敦的两年是辛苦写作的两年，吉卜林的身体垮了，于是他明智地决定去长途旅行。他再次回到英国时是为了结婚，婚后他带着他的新娘开始了世界之旅。但是因为缺钱，他被迫缩短了旅程，并在妻子家族长期居住的美国的佛蒙特州住了下来。这是一八九二年的夏天，他在佛蒙特断断续续待到一八九六年。这四年间他写了些小说，其中很多小说的质量只有他能达到。也就是在那时他写了《在鲁克》，于是有了莫格利的第一次出场。这是个吉利的灵感，因为后来的两本《丛林之书》就是来自这一灵感，而《丛林之书》是我认为吉卜林伟大、多样的天赋表现得最为淋漓尽致的作品。它们展示了他讲故事的奇妙才能，其中有种微妙的幽默，既浪漫又可信。让动物说话的技巧就像伊索寓言一样古老，甚至更老。我们都知道，拉封丹在运用这一技巧方面既有魅力又很机智，但我认为，要想让读者相信动物说话就像人说话一样自然是个极难的壮举，在完成这个艰巨任务上没人比吉卜林的《丛林之书》更成功了。他还在一篇名为“一个行走的代表”的故事中使用了同一技巧，其中，马能讨论政治，但是这个故事有种明显的说教元素，不算成功。

也正是在这段多产时期，吉卜林写了《丛林男孩》。这个故事深深打动了很多人，虽然它不是我的最爱，但我还是把它收入了这个集子。吉卜林在这个故事里利用了一个概念，这个概念吸引了他之前和之后的小说家们，即两个人会经常做同一个梦。故事的难点在于这个梦必须是个有趣的梦。如果早餐桌上有人坚持要给我们讲他昨晚做的梦，我们会无精打采地听着，在纸上写梦中发生的事也同样容易引起我们的不耐烦。吉卜林以前在《架桥者》中写过梦中发生的事，不过那时篇幅相对少点。我认为他在那篇小说里犯了个错。他要讲的故事很好：一场洪水突然奔流而下，淹了恒河上的一座桥，而这座桥恰好是工人们苦干三年就要竣工的一座桥。两个负责施工的白人心里犹豫，不知道那三座还没完工的桥拱是否能顶得住压力。他们担心如果石船走偏了，桥的梁就会受损。他们已经接到电报说洪水要来了，并且已经带工人苦干了一个晚上，尽他们所能地加固了薄弱之处。所有这一切的叙述都极为有力，细节也极为生动，吉卜林在这方面是个大师。桥顶住了压力，一切都挺好。故事到此就算完了，可吉卜林大概觉得还不够。总工程师芬德雷森因为太焦虑、太忙，什么都没顾上吃，到了第二天晚上他已经累得筋疲力尽，他的印度助手建议他吞点鸦片药丸。随后消息传来，说钢缆船索断了，石船松了。于是芬德雷森和助手跑去岸上，下到一艘石船里，希望能阻止这些石船造成无法弥补的损失。结果他俩都被冲下河，淹得半死，最后冲到了一个岛上。早已筋疲力尽又都吃了鸦片的他们睡着了，做了同一个梦，梦见印度教的神祇们都以动物的形象出现了：格涅沙是头大象，哈努曼是只猴子，最后还有克利须那本尊，然后他们还听见了神们说话。第二天早上两人醒来后获救了。但这个双重的梦是不必要的，而且因为神的对话也是不必要的，因此梦就显得冗长乏味。

在《丛林男孩》中，故事的核心元素一样是不同的人做同样的梦。读者们最应该好好读读这个故事，我希望你们也会和我一样认为吉卜林的这些梦写得很好。这些梦古怪、浪漫、可怕、神秘。如果两个人从童年起就一直做同样的梦，哪怕说不出原因，也理应包含一个极其重大的含义，可最后的结果无非是“男孩遇到了女孩”，难免令人失望。读歌德《浮士德》的第一部也有类似感觉，浮士德就为了看魔鬼在酒窖里玩杂耍和勾引一个卑贱的女仆就出卖了灵魂简直不值得。我很难把《丛林男孩》看成吉卜林最好的故事之一，因为这个故事里的人物实在好得不真实。丛林男孩是一大份产业的继承人。他的父母爱他，教他使枪的护林人宠他，仆人和佃户也都崇拜他。他是神枪手，善骑马，办事勤快，打仗勇敢，手下的士兵也都拥戴他。西北边境一役后，他被授予金十字英勇勋章，成了英军中最年轻的中校。他聪明、清醒、纯洁。他无比完美，好得令人难以置信。虽然我百般挑剔，但我不否认这是个动人的好故事，讲得也不错。不过读这个故事的时候，不能把它看成和真实生活有任何联系，把它看成一个像《睡美人》和《灰姑娘》那样的童话就对了。

正是在那些短期休假中，吉卜林逐渐理解了他在《山中寻常事》中所写的英印社会，但是他当记者时的经历也一定使他清楚地认识到，他在那些小故事里描述的只是英印生活的一个侧面。那样的经历我在前文已经引用了一段，从中可以看出他把那些经历写得有多好。他在执行各项采访任务时的见闻震动了他。我上文提到《架桥者》，它精彩描写了那些薪俸微薄、几乎没有机会得到认可的人，他们奉献青春、力量和健康，尽自己最大的努力把该干的工作干好。而在《征服者威廉》（这小说的名字没起好）中，吉卜林写了两三个相当平凡的普通男人和一个女人——这女人就是小说中的威廉——如何顶着酷暑坚持与饥荒奋战，最后挽救了一群孩子的生命，使他们不至饿死的故事。这是个有关无私和顽强的故事，讲得很冷静。在这两个故事和其他几个故事里，吉卜林写了那些为印度奉献的平凡男女。他们犯了很多错，因为他们是人。其中很多人很蠢，很多人因偏见而顽固，很多人毫无想象力，但他们维护了和平，维持了正义。他们修路，架桥，铺设铁道。他们与饥荒、洪水和疫病抗争。他们救护伤者。如今那些继承了他们职位的人——我不是说那些居高位者，我是说那些职位普通但掌握着许多普通人命运的人——是否还能像前人一样称职胜任呢？还需拭目静观。

《征服者威廉》不光写饥荒，也写爱情。我上文说过，吉卜林会像未驯服的小马驹一样回避写性，他在穆尔瓦尼的故事里偶尔说起过士兵们的情爱。《关于我自己》中也曾愤愤指责当局犯了一个等同犯罪的愚蠢错误，因为当局认为“让集市上的妓女接受检查”是不敬的，“向士兵传授基本的防护措施，以便让他们在与妓女交往时注意”也是不敬的。“官方道德害得我们付出了昂贵的代价，我们的驻印部队每年损失九千个白人，造成他们卧床不起的原因是性病。”但他说这话时关心的不是爱，而是一个正常人想要获得性满足的本能。我只记得吉卜林有两个故事是成功描写了欲望的。一个是《女人之爱》，因此我将它选入本书。这故事内容可怕，可能还很野蛮，但是讲得精彩激烈，结尾也神秘有力，哪怕不解释为何如此结尾。不过批评家们对这个结尾百般挑剔。马蒂斯曾向一名访客展示一幅画作。访客说：“我从未见过这样的女人！”马蒂斯回答：“这不是女人，夫人，这是画。”如果允许画家为达到他想要的效果而对事实进行一定扭曲，那就没有理由不允许小说家也给他自己以同样的自由。让故事有发生的可能性，并非是件一劳永逸的事，要看你能让读者接受到什么程度。吉卜林写的不是官方报告，是小说。如果他想，他有权对小说进行戏剧化的夸张，以达到他想要的效果。如果在现实生活中，他笔下那个贵族出身的士兵对被他诱奸又毁掉的女人说不出吉卜林放到他嘴里的那些话，那也不要紧。故事情节还是可信的，读者也像吉卜林希望的那样受了感动。

另一个吉卜林写了真正的欲望的小说是《未经教会许可的婚姻》。这故事很美很感人。如果有一本选集要我选出吉卜林所有小说中最好的一篇，我会选这篇。吉卜林的其他故事的确更典型，比如《区长》，但在这个故事里，吉卜林达到了小说这一媒介所允许的、小说家都想达到而很难达到的完美。

我写以上文字是想说说《征服者威廉》结尾那个爱情场面。它给了这故事一个美满结局，但却尴尬怪异。两个当事人是相爱的，这点明确无疑，但是他们的爱里没有狂喜，而是相当乏味，已经有了种居家过日子的感觉。他们两位都是明理的好人，如果结了婚，日子会过得不错，但他们的爱情场面像是两个青春期的少男少女。一个十几岁的男生放假回家会这样和他们地方上医生的女儿说话，但是两个办事有效率又刚刚经历了一场痛苦和危险的成年人不会。

如果做一个粗略总结的话，我会说作家在三十五到四十岁之间达到能力的巅峰。不到这会儿他不会明白吉卜林强调为技巧的那种东西，不到这会儿他的作品就会不成熟、把握不准和带有实验性。作家通过从过去的错误中学习，仅仅通过生活这个过程——生活能给他带来阅历和对人性的了解，通过发现自身的局限，知道自己擅长处理什么题材，以及如何才能最好地处理这些题材，最终实现对材料的把握。他有才华，能在接下来的十五年间——幸运的话是二十年间——写出他最好的作品，然后他的才华就消退了。他将失去他盛年时拥有的旺盛的想象力，他已经给了他全部能给的东西。他将继续写作，因为写作是个很好染上又很难中断的习惯，但是他写的东西将会越来越苍白，只能提醒人们他全盛时的荣光。

吉卜林不同，他极其早慧，几乎从一开始就完全具备了那些才能。《山中寻常事》里有些故事太琐碎，他后来可能会觉得不值一写，但是那些故事讲得清楚、生动、感人，写作技巧上无可挑剔。即使有毛病，也是因为作者年轻稚嫩而并非技巧不足。当他才刚二十出头，调到阿拉哈巴德，能有更多篇幅表达自己的时候，他写的那一系列故事就已经绝对可以称得上是大师之作了。及至他初到伦敦，去见《麦克米伦杂志》的编辑，编辑问他多大，他说还有几个月就满二十四岁时，难怪编辑会禁不住大叫“上帝”，那时的他成就已经非常令人震惊了。

可是世间万事皆有代价。世纪末到来时，也就是吉卜林三十五岁时，他已经写出了他最好的作品。我不是说从此他的故事就开始写坏了，他即使想写坏也写不坏。我是说他后来的作品以其自身看虽然不错，但都缺了他早期印度故事里浸润的那种魔力。他只有在想象中重回早期印度生活的场景时才写出了《基姆》，才又重新获得了这种魔力。《基姆》是他的代表作。有一件事最初想来一定很怪，即离开阿拉哈巴德后，除了短期造访他在拉合尔的父母外，吉卜林再没回过印度。毕竟是印度小说给他挣得了巨大的声誉，虽然他自己管这个叫臭名，但是其实是美名。我只能猜他感觉印度给了他所有他能处理的题材。他曾在西印度群岛住过一段时间，之后给我写信，说我应该去那儿看看，因为关于岛上的人有好多故事可写，但是这些故事不是他能写的那种。他一定感到除了他写的那些故事，印度也还有很多故事可写，可是这些故事不是他能写的那种。对他来说，风格早就决定了。

布尔战争来了，吉卜林去了南非。他在印度时对他接触到的那些军官怀着一种幼稚感人又相当荒谬的崇拜。但是这些在马球场、运动会、舞会和野餐时表现得如此洒脱出色的英勇绅士，此时却表现出了一种可怕的无能。因为这次这场仗和他们在印度西北边界上打的那种惩戒性的仗太不一样了。官兵们还是像他知道的那样，一如既往的勇敢，但是军队的指挥不力。他震惊地审视着这场一团糟的倒霉战争。他是否把这看成英帝国伟大根基上的第一条裂缝呢？英帝国是他的骄傲，他的帝国意识让他写诗写文，竭尽所能唤醒同胞。于是他以两个故事——《俘虏》和《他走的那条路》——来攻击当局办事的没效率和军队指挥官的无能。这两个故事都是好故事。如果我没将它们收录到本书中，那是因为它们的宣传意味太浓了，还因为就像所有写时事的小说一样，时间的流逝带走了故事的意义。

我应该提醒读者，我的观点，即吉卜林最好的小说是写印度的小说的观点，绝对不是著名评论家们的观点。他们认为吉卜林在他们所谓的第三阶段里写的小说有种他的印度小说没有的深度、洞察力和同情。在他们看来，吉卜林的最高成就应该是像《强制居住》《战壕里的圣母》《愿望屋》《友好的小溪》那样的小说。《强制居住》是个有魅力的故事，但太无新意。其他三个也足够好，但在我看来也不算非同凡响。写这样的小说无须吉卜林那样的大天才。《不过如此的故事》《普克山的派克》《报答和仙女》是童书，其价值全在给儿童提供了多少乐趣，而这点《不过如此的故事》一定做到了。类似“大象的长鼻子是怎么来的”的故事，孩子们一定是边听边笑。在另外两本书里，派克给小男孩小女孩们讲了很多人物，可以使孩子们对英国历史获得一种浪漫的初级了解。但我不认为这是个巧妙的技巧。故事的构思当然都很好，我最喜欢《在长城上》，其中有个罗马军团的士兵叫帕纳西斯，可是如果能把它直接构思为一个罗马占领不列颠时期发生的故事就更好了。

吉卜林定居英国期间写的唯一一个我无论如何不愿从这个选集中遗漏的小说是《他们》。读这个故事的时候须谨记，吉卜林让故事在其中发生的那个名叫“美丽屋”的乡村大宅，虽然让人想起因为庸俗的承办商追求奇思怪想和矫揉造作的虚饰而得名的“古风茶肆”以及类似的恶俗的名字，却并没有变得惹人讨厌。《他们》是精彩的想象力得到发挥的结果。一八九九年，吉卜林和妻儿去了纽约。在那儿，他和大女儿先是得了感冒，后来发展成肺炎。我们当中年纪够大的人都记得当时电报说吉卜林快死了，这事引发了世界范围的关注。后来他好了，但是女儿却死了。毫无疑问，《他们》是他受丧女之痛的启发而写的。海涅说：“我从我巨大的悲痛中作些小诗。”吉卜林则写了个精致的小故事。有些人觉得这故事意义不明，有些人觉得它太滥情。小说家面临的一个危险是从多情滑到滥情。两者的区别很细微，滥情很可能只是你恰巧不喜欢的多情。吉卜林很会赚人眼泪，但有时在他不是写给孩子而是写孩子的作品里，这些眼泪却很招人讨厌，因为惹人流泪的那些情感太做作了。《他们》没什么意义不明之处，在我看来也毫不滥情。

吉卜林对改变我们文明的那些发明和发现深感兴趣。读者还记得他在《无线》中如何有效利用了无线这一技术。他着迷于机器，而当他迷上一个主题的时候，他就会为之写小说。他花了很大力气搞懂事实。如果他有时犯了错，就像所有作家都会犯错那样，大多数读者也因为不熟悉那些事实而不知道他犯了错。他为了技术细节而沉迷其中，倒不是为了显摆，而是因为乐在其中。他本人固然好争好辩、固执己见，但是作为作家，他却很谦逊，不装腔作势。他像一个欣喜于自己高超而轻松的演奏技巧的音乐会钢琴家一样，他选曲的标准并非曲子本身的音乐价值，而是看曲子是否能给他一个展示他独特天赋的机会。吉卜林在一篇小说里说，他需要时不时打断叙述者，要后者解释他说的那些技术名词。小说的读者却做不到这点，因此到头来还是困惑不解，可是吉卜林颇写了些这样的故事。如果他能不这么一丝不苟，这些小说会好看得多。比如《他们合法的场合》，我猜只有海军军官才能完全明白发生了什么，而且我很乐意相信他们会觉得这故事很好。《零零七》写的是火车。《那艘找到自己的船》写的是一艘航线不定的货船，我想只有火车司机和造船工匠才能读得懂这些故事。《丛林之书》和《马耳他猫》让各式各样的动物开口说话，而且说话的方式让人觉得非常可信。编号为零零七的火车和名为迪姆布拉的船也用了同样的手段。我不觉得这有什么用。我不相信普通读者知道（或者在乎）龙骨翼板是什么，船底长桁、高压气缸或者肋骨框架又是什么。

这些小说展示了吉卜林多面才能的另一面，但我不认为有必要将这类小说收入本书。因为读者的角度经常和作者的角度大不相同，从读者的角度看，小说的目的是娱乐。如此一来，这些小说的价值在我看来就很小了。

我对吉卜林那些写恶作剧、戏弄和醉酒的小说疑虑较多，他是时不时就会写写这类题材的。吉卜林身上有种拉伯雷(7)的气质，而时代的虚伪是要有意避开那种气质的，因此限制了他对恶作剧和醉酒的描写。在《关于我自己》中，他说他有次给他母亲看一篇写女性的小说，可他母亲毁了这篇东西，还写信告诉他说：“你以后切不可如此。”从上下文看，这故事一定写的是通奸。至于是否觉得醉酒好玩，我猜这要看个人癖好。我曾不幸与一群酒鬼同住，在我看来，他们最好时无聊，最坏时恶心，但是有我这种感觉的人明显不多。写酒鬼的故事有着强烈的吸引力，因为有关那个暴饮暴食的无赖布鲁格史密斯和那个烂醉的小军官派克罗夫特的故事非常受读者欢迎。吉卜林觉得这两人很好玩，他为他们写了好几个故事。恶作剧更是直到最近还有着广泛的吸引力。黄金时代的西班牙文学充满了恶作剧，大家都还记得堂吉诃德遭受的那些残酷的恶作剧。维多利亚时期也还觉得恶作剧好玩，从最近新出的一本书里我们得知，哪怕是在最高尚的圈子里，也还是热衷于在恶作剧中找乐子。同样，到底是否觉得恶作剧好玩，取决于各人的秉性。我必须承认，我读吉卜林的这类故事时是会不安的。做出整人之举者的乐不可支让我觉得恼怒，他们不满足于只嘲笑受害者受到的羞辱，他们还会靠到彼此身上，笑得浑身没劲，他们会从椅子上滚下来，尖叫着瘫倒在地，用手抓地毯。甚至还有个故事的叙述者在一家旅馆里订了个房间，为的就是能笑个彻底。只有一个这样的故事让我觉得真的好笑，既然我需要从这类故事中给读者举个例子，那我就把它印到了这本书里，这个故事名叫《有个村子投票赞成地球是方的》。其中的喜剧是丰富的，受害者是该受惩罚的，而那惩罚也是严厉但不残酷的。

迄今为止，我在本文中只是无意地谈到了吉卜林的成功，但他的成功其实是巨大的。自从狄更斯以《匹克威克外传》征服阅读界后就再没有过这样的成功，吉卜林也根本不用苦等成功。早在一八九〇年，亨利·詹姆斯就给史蒂文森(8)写信说吉卜林是“此时的新星”，说他是史蒂文森最大的竞争对手，史蒂文森则给詹姆斯写信说吉卜林“太聪明了，怎么还能活”。他们似乎都被这个詹姆斯称作“年轻怪兽”的人的出现惊到了，他们承认他的才华，但同时又有所保留。“他的早熟和各种天赋让我惊讶，”史蒂文森写道，“可他的多产和仓促又让我警觉……我向来写不出这么放荡的东西，当然也不用为此感到愧疚……我从旁观看，我佩服艳羡，我为自己欣喜。但是为了我们在语言和文学上都有的那种野心的缘故，我又很受伤害……吉卜林当然是有天赋的。仙女教母们在他的洗礼上全都喝醉了：他将如何利用他的天赋呢？”

可是多产在作家身上不是缺点，是优点。所有伟大的作家都多产。当然不是他们的所有作品都有价值，只有平庸之辈才老保持一个水平。伟大作家之所以能时不时写出伟大作品来是因为他们不断在写，吉卜林也不例外。我不认为任何作家能够公正评价同代作家的作品，因为他最喜欢的自然是他自己写的那类作品。让他欣赏自己不具备的那些优点是很难的。詹姆斯和史蒂文森都不是不大方的人，他们承认吉卜林才华非凡，但是以我们对这两位作家的了解，我们可以猜想他们是多么的不安，因为吉卜林的某些作品是那么多愁善感、热情洋溢，而另一些作品又是那么冷酷无情、死气沉沉。

吉卜林当然也有毁谤者。埋头苦干多年却只在文学界勉强占了一席之地的作者们很难容忍这个年轻人——这么一个不知打哪儿冒出来、没有一点社交风度的年轻人居然能赢，明明没付出什么努力，却获得了巨大的成功。正如我们所知道的那样，他们安慰自己，预测说吉卜林既然会像火箭一样蹿起，也会像棍子一样坠落。他们以前也曾这样预测过狄更斯。他们反对吉卜林的理由是说他在小说里写自己写得太多了。但是言归正传，作家们除了写自己还能写什么呢？有时作家会以一种富有欺骗性的坦诚把自己捧给读者，比如斯特恩，或查尔斯·兰姆，这既是他们创作的灵感也是他们创作的支撑。但是不管作家如何想要尽量客观，他写的东西仍然不可避免地彰显他自己的个性。读上十几页的《包法利夫人》，你会情不自禁感受到福楼拜易怒、悲观、病态和以自我为中心的个性。吉卜林的批评家们实在是批评错了，他们不该怨他把自己的性格引入作品中来。他们的真实意思当然是说他们不喜欢吉卜林向他们展现的性格，这是可以理解的。吉卜林的早期作品展现出的特点确实令人讨厌。读者得到的印象是这是个傲慢自夸的年轻人，过分自信，什么都懂。这当然引起了批评者们的敌对，因为这些相当不友善的性格特点显示的是一种自以为高人一等的心理，这样就冒犯了别人的自尊心。

吉卜林被广泛指责为庸俗，巴尔扎克和狄更斯也是如此。我认为这仅仅是因为他们写了生活的某些方面，得罪了那些高雅人士。好在我们现在坚强多了，我们说谁高雅的时候，已经不是在夸他了。但是对吉卜林最荒谬的一个指责是说他的小说都是“奇闻逸事”（anecdote），作出如此指责的批评家们觉得用这个词可以打击到他，他们现在有时也还在这么做。但是如果他们能不怕麻烦查查牛津辞典，就会发现anecdote一词的定义是这样的：“对某一独立事件或单一事件的叙述，因其有趣或惊人而得以被讲述。”而这正是短篇小说的完美定义。圣经中的路得故事、古罗马以弗所妇人的故事、薄伽丘的费德里哥和猎鹰的故事都是奇闻逸事，《羊脂球》、《项链》和《遗产》也都是奇闻逸事。奇闻是小说的骨架，它赋予小说形式与连贯，而作家要做的就是给它以血肉和神经。没有人有义务读小说。如果你不喜欢小说，除非里边有超出故事以外的东西，那也是没办法的事。你可以不喜欢牡蛎，谁也不能因此指责你，但是如果你抱怨牡蛎没有牛排腰子布丁的情感品质就不合理了。挑剔小说只是小说也同样不合理，吉卜林的某些毁谤者就是这么干的。吉卜林很有才华，但他思想并不深刻，实际上我也想不出哪个伟大小说家的思想是深刻的。吉卜林的非凡才华在于会讲并且喜欢讲某种类型的故事，大多数时候他都在很聪明地做他擅长的事。他是个理智的人，如果人家喜欢他的小说，他高兴；如果不喜欢，他也无非耸耸肩算了。

吉卜林另一个被挑错的地方是他不善写人。我认为持这样观点的批评家根本不懂短篇小说里人物塑造的地位。写小说的目的当然可以是为了展示人。福楼拜的《一颗简单的心》和契诃夫的《亲爱的》托尔斯泰就认为很好，虽然纯粹主义者可能会反对，说这些不是短篇小说，而是浓缩的长篇小说。可吉卜林关心的是事件。一篇小说如果关心的是事件，那它对与事件相关的人就无须讲得太多，只要让他们活起来就行了。作家只在他需要的时刻讲到人，人也就不可避免地成了静态的人。如果想展示人的发展，作家需要长篇小说那样的时间和空间才能施展。小说人物中最突出的大概要算于连·索雷尔了，但是司汤达(9)如何能在一篇短篇小说的篇幅内展示这个复杂人物的发展呢？现在，我要说，吉卜林的人物刻画足够扎实，已经达到了他的目的。必须区分“人物”和“个性”(10)。穆尔瓦尼、李尔洛德、奥塞莱斯是“人物”，写他们很容易。而《架桥者》中的芬德雷森和《征服者威廉》中的司各特和威廉则有“个性”，写他们不容易。他们当然是普通人、平常人，但是正是这点给了小说的叙事以意义，吉卜林当然知道这点。丛林男孩的父母不是像吉卜林以为的那样是住在祖产上的有地乡绅，而是一对善良正直的夫妇，来自像阿诺德·班尼特的《五镇》(11)那样的地方，在挣到了一笔足够过舒适生活的钱以后，定居到了乡下。吉卜林虽然写他们的笔触很轻，但他们是鲜活可辨认的人。霍克斯比夫人也不是吉卜林想象的那种时髦、出众的人物，她只是个自我感觉良好的二流小女人，但她绝不是个傀儡，我们都见过她。《区长》中的亚德利—奥德在小说开始后第四页就死了，但吉卜林对他的刻画已经足够，任何人都能按奥布雷《生平小传》(12)的模式写出他的生平事迹来，而且还有可能写得很对。连我自己现在都要快点往下进行了，省得抵制不了诱惑，要在此时此地自己写出一篇来，好证明写人是多么容易。

不久前一个著名作家告诉我他很不喜欢吉卜林的风格，到了无法卒读的地步。的确，吉卜林在世时批评家们似乎觉得他突兀、做作、太跳跃。其中一位说：“必须强调：俚语不是力量，滥用句号不等于干脆。”确实是这样。作家用俚语是为了准确再现对话，是为了在叙事过程中给行文一种对话的感觉。反对俚语的主要原因是俚语的时髦是暂时的，几年就过时，甚至会让人不明所以。当然俚语有时也会进入正式语言，获得一种文学的合法性，哪怕是纯粹主义者也不能再反对使用俚语。吉卜林的句子比当时通常的句子都短。这事现在再也不会让我们吃惊了，因为词典编纂者告诉我们，一句话无非就是由一系列词构成，是对一个完整意思的语法表达。一个写作者如果做到了这点，那他就没什么理由不能给句子画上一个句号，他当然有权这样做。批评起同代人来不留情面的乔治·摩尔(13)就很欣赏吉卜林的风格，认为他的文风铿锵有力，有节奏。“别人写得更美，但是我想不起来谁写得更多……他用完整的语言写，他用圣经的语言写，他用街上的语言写。”吉卜林的词汇丰富，他会根据词的感情色彩、精确性、韵律去选词，他的选择经常出人意料。他知道他想说什么，而且说得坚决。他的文字（我在这里只说他的文字）富于节奏和活力。就像每个作家一样，他有他的习性。有些习性他很快抛弃了，比如他对圣经语句的不得体的痴迷；其余的他保留了。他一生爱用关系词开始句子，这很可惜。说“以前”的时候，他爱用诗意的“ere”，而非更自然的“before”，这也很可惜。他还至少一次把even写成了e’en。这都是些小错。吉卜林打造了一种个人专属的风格，我想今天哪怕还有人做得到，也不会再有人这么做了。但是我看不出有谁能否认吉卜林构建的这个方法非常适合他。他很少沉溺于冗长的描述，但他凭借他犀利、敏锐的观察力，他用他所构建的这种叙述方法，把拥挤但丰富多彩的印度生活极其生动地呈现到了读者面前。

如果我在本文中毫不犹豫地指出了我所认为的吉卜林的缺点，我希望我也清楚表明了他的优点是多么显著。短篇小说不是英国人整体擅长的小说形式，英国人的长篇小说也已表明了英国人爱发散的特点。他们从来对形式都没什么兴趣，简洁也违背他们的天性。但是短篇小说要求形式，发散对短篇小说而言是致命的。短篇小说靠建构，不允许还有问题未了。所有这些特点在吉卜林最好的短篇小说里都具备，这对我们来说真是幸运。鲁德亚德·吉卜林是我国唯一堪与莫泊桑和契诃夫媲美的短篇小说家，他是我们最伟大的写故事的人。我不信未来有谁能与他匹敌，我还肯定他将永远不会被超越。

(1) 所谓“英印”是种简称，原文为Anglo-Indian，字面意思是“英国—印度”，内涵宽泛，指侨居印度的英国人、英印混血儿、印度英语、英印之间等。

(2) 英文意思是聪明狡猾。

(3) 今巴基斯坦城市。

(4) 英军在布尔战争中的一役。布尔人是居住于南非的荷兰、法国和德国人的后裔，“布尔”一词来源于荷兰语，意思是“农民”。布尔战争是英国人和布尔人之间为争夺南非殖民地而展开的战争，最终以英国人的胜利宣告结束。

(5) 指法国作家马塞尔·普鲁斯特（1871—1922），现代文学巨著《追忆逝水年华》的作者。

(6) 所谓第四维空间，一说为时间，一说为意识。

(7) 弗朗索瓦·拉伯雷（约1494—1553），法国作家，代表作为长篇小说《巨人传》。《巨人传》共分五卷，取材于法国民间传说故事，主要写格朗古杰、高康大、庞大固埃三代巨人的活动史，表现出拉伯雷喜欢讽刺、幻想、怪诞、下流玩笑和歌曲的倾向。

(8) 罗伯特·路易斯·史蒂文森（1850—1894），英国作家，代表作为《金银岛》、《绑架》和《化身博士》。

(9) 于连·索雷尔是法国作家司汤达（1783—1842）的代表作《红与黑》（1830）中的主人公，是一个出身低微但是野心勃勃，最终野心破灭、失败身死的青年。

(10) “人物”和“个性”，英文都是character。

(11) 阿诺德·班尼特（1867—1931），英国作家，《五镇故事》是他1905年发表的一部短篇小说集，写他出生和成长的斯塔福郡的五个市镇。班尼特有口吃，同样口吃的毛姆说看班尼特“挣扎着想把话说出口真是痛苦”，但同时认为“如果不是因为口吃使他走向内省，阿诺德不会成为作家”。

(12) 约翰·奥布雷（1626—1697），英国作家、古文物研究者、自然哲学家，最著名的作品是传记文集《生平小传》，描写对象包括弥尔顿、莎士比亚、霍布斯、本·约翰逊、培根等多位十六到十八世纪英国名人。

(13) 乔治·摩尔（1852—1933），爱尔兰作家。其作品受到左拉的自然主义的影响，虽然某些观点把他排斥在英国文学和爱尔兰文学的主流之外，但也有观点认为他是爱尔兰文学史上的第一个现代小说家。

《毛姆短篇小说全集卷一：东方与西方》自序

（1921—1952）

本卷包括三十篇短篇小说，长度相似，程度也相似。第一篇写于一九一九年，最后一篇写于一九三一年。我虽然在很年轻的时候写过一些短篇小说，但后来有很长一段时间，大约至少十二到十五年吧，都在写戏剧，不再写短篇了。但是南海之行意外给我提供了一些主题，那些主题似乎很适合短篇小说这种形式，于是那时，作为一名已经四十开外的新人，我就写了现在叫作“雨”的这篇故事。这篇故事引发了一些骚动，因此且容我把当时的工作笔记抄录在此，《雨》的写作就建立在这些笔记的基础之上，相信本篇序言的读者会有耐心一观。这些笔记是用老掉牙的草率语言写成的，毫不优美，因为上天并未赋予我那种幸运的天赋，即本能地发现那个完美的词来表现一个对象，并找到那个不同寻常却又恰如其分的形容词来描述它。记得当时我正从火奴鲁鲁(1)去帕果帕果(2)。途中我像往常一样，把对那些吸引我注意的同行旅客的印象记了下来，希望将来某个时刻或许会对我有用。以下是我描述汤普森小姐的话：“丰满，有种粗糙的漂亮，大约不过二十七岁。她穿条白裙，戴顶大白帽，脚穿白色长靴，包裹在棉袜里的小腿肚鼓了出来。”我们开船前，火奴鲁鲁的红灯区刚发生了场搜捕，船上的流言说她出来旅行就是为了躲避搜捕。我的笔记继续写道：“W．传教士。是个瘦高男子，有着松松地连到一起的长长的四肢，两腮下陷，颧骨很高，大黑眼睛深陷在眼窝里，嘴唇饱满而感性，头发留得相当长。他有种尸体般惨白的模样，表情让人想起压抑的火。他的手大，手指长，形状不错。他原本浅白的皮肤被热带的阳光烤晒得很黑。W．太太，他妻子。个矮，头发梳得精致，新英格兰人。金边夹鼻眼镜后是不算突出的蓝眼。她的脸长如绵羊，但不会给人愚蠢的感觉，相反，令人感觉她极为警醒。她的行动迅捷如鸟。她最引人注意之处是声音，高亢、尖厉刺耳、没有抑扬变化，落在耳朵里有种生硬的单调，把人的神经刺激得难受，好似一把风钻永不停歇的噪音一般。她全身穿黑，脖子上戴根金链，吊个小十字架。”她告诉我W．是个派到吉尔伯特(3)去的传教士，因其教区所辖岛屿之间相隔很远，他只得经常乘独木舟往返。丈夫不在时她会留在总部处理传教工作。海上经常波涛汹涌，丈夫往返于海上不是没有危险。他是个医生兼传教士。她谈到当地人的堕落时，声音里有种激烈的、故作虔诚的畏惧，什么也无法让她停下来，她告诉我当地人的结婚风俗无比下流、难以形容。她说他们刚来的时候，每个村子里都找不出一个好女孩。她还痛骂跳舞。我和这对传教士夫妇只说过一次话，和汤普森小姐一次话都没说过。以下是小说所据的笔记：“一次搜捕后，一个妓女逃离了火奴鲁鲁，来到了帕果帕果。同时在帕果帕果登陆的还有一个传教士和他的妻子，以及叙述者。所有人都因一场麻疹的突然爆发而不得不滞留在此。传教士发现了她的职业，开始迫害她。他让她难过、愧疚、忏悔，他对她毫不怜悯。他还让总督下令，命她回到火奴鲁鲁。一天早上，他被发现亲手割断了自己的喉管，而她则又一次容光焕发、泰然自若起来。她看着男人们，鄙夷地说：‘肮脏的猪。’”

曾有一位聪明的批评家，他阅读广泛，感觉敏锐，对人情世故也很了解，这在批评家里是很少见的，他在我的小说里发现了莫泊桑的影响。这不奇怪。在我小的时候，莫泊桑被认为是法国最杰出的短篇小说家，我简直是狂热地爱读莫泊桑的作品。从十五岁起，我每次去巴黎都会把大部分的下午时光消磨在奥德翁剧院的走廊上看书，那是我人生中对一件事最为入迷的时光。穿长工作服的店员不管四处闲看的顾客，你可以在那儿看上几个小时书都不被打扰。有一个书架摆满了莫泊桑的书，但是每本要卖三个半法郎，这个价格不是我能负担得起的，因此我只能站着看，往没剪开的书页里看。有时候趁店员不注意的时候，我会匆忙剪开一页，好看得方便些。幸运的是，有些书是廉价版，只卖七十五生丁一本，大多数情况下我走的时候都会买走一本。我就是用这个方法在十八岁前看了所有的好小说。因此当我在那个年纪开始写小说的时候，就会不由自主地选择那些短篇中的杰作作为我的榜样。当然，我也可能不幸选到不如莫泊桑的榜样。

如今莫泊桑的声誉已不比当年，其作品也明显有可予拒斥之处。他是个属于他那个时代的法国人，强烈地反对浪漫派，那时的浪漫派行将在奥克塔夫·弗耶（阿诺德很推崇此人）甜腻腻的感伤和乔治·桑的偏激狂热中终结。莫泊桑是个自然主义者，他不惜一切代价地追求真相，但他求得的真相在我们今天看来未免有点肤浅。他不分析人物，对人物的动机也几乎不感兴趣。他的人物只是行动着，但他不研究他们为何行动。他说：“对我而言，长篇和短篇小说中的心理学，就是通过人物的生活反映他的内心。”这话不错，这是我们都在努力去做的，但是动作本身并不总能表明动机。结果对莫泊桑来说就是人物太简化，这在短篇小说中还算有效，但回想起来却令你无法信服，你会说人比这要复杂。还有一点，就是莫泊桑有个执念，这是个无聊的念头，但是当时的法国人都有这么个念头，即一个男人对自己负有一项义务，他必须和他遇见的每个四十岁以下的女人上床。于是莫泊桑的人物为了满足自尊而放纵性欲。他们就像那些只是因为贵而不是因为饿而吃鱼子酱的人一样。贪欲似乎是唯一强烈影响了他的人物的人类情感。莫泊桑明白这一点，他对此充满恐惧，不过私下里仍对此心怀认同。他稍有些平庸。即便如此，否认莫泊桑的卓越也是愚蠢的。一个作家有权以其最好的作品被人评判。没有哪个作家是完美的，你必须接受其缺点，缺点经常是优点的必要补充。这话应该心怀感激地对那些愿意这么做的后世人说。他们会选取一个作家好的一面而不困于他坏的一面。有时甚至到了过分的地步，非要把明显的缺点说成具有深刻含义，令老实的读者困惑不解。因此你会发现批评家们（也就是后世那令人敬畏的声音）为了给自己贴金，会找出一些微妙的理由解释莎剧中的某些东西，实际上任何剧作家都知道，造成那些问题的原因无非就是仓促、漠视和任性，除此之外别无他解。莫泊桑的小说是好小说，除叙述方式外，故事内容也有趣，即使是在晚餐桌上讲起来也会引人注意，这在我看来绝对是个很大的优点。哪怕你用词再吞吐，表述再无趣，只要你讲的是《羊脂球》、《遗产》或《项链》的故事框架，都一定能调动听你讲故事的人的兴趣。这些故事有开头、中间、结尾，它们并非沿着一条不确定的线索逡巡，以至于让你看不清楚走向，而是毫不犹豫地从展开到高潮画出一条明显有力的弧线。它们可能没有什么伟大的精神内涵，而莫泊桑也志不在此。他认为自己只是个普通人。而且从来没有一个好作家像他那样不把自己当个文人。他不假装自己是个哲学家，他这么做很明智，因为即便当他沉浸于思考时，他的思考也都太普通。他有自己的局限，但仍令人钦佩。他在创造活灵活现的人物方面有着令人震惊的才能。不管篇幅多短，即使在几页纸之内，他也能在你面前树立起半打观察得无比细致、描述得无比生动的人物，让你觉得关于这些人物你已经了解了你所需知道的一切。这些人物轮廓清晰，各具特色，辨识度极高，他们呼吸着生命的气息。他们都不复杂，也奇怪地缺乏我们在人身上发现的那些犹豫不决、意想不到和神秘莫测，实际上为了小说的需要他们被简化了。但他们并非有意被简化，莫泊桑敏锐的双眼看得清楚，但看得不深。很幸运的是他的双眼能看到足以使他达到他想要达到的目标的一切。他对环境的处理是相同的，他的场景设置总是一样准确、简短和有效。他描述的不论是诺曼底的迷人风景，还是八十年代沉闷拥挤的客厅，目的都只有一个，那就是推进故事的发展。在他自己的方法这个层面上，我不认为有谁能超越他。如果现下他的卓越并不明显，那是因为他所写的故事必须和非常不同、更加微妙也更加动人的契诃夫的作品放在一起比较。

契诃夫的短篇小说是年轻作家理所当然应该模仿的榜样，这很好理解。表面看来，写契诃夫型的短篇小说比写莫泊桑型的短篇小说容易。先不论作家讲故事的能力如何，能编造一个本身就有趣的故事已是难事，做到这点要靠天赋，不是靠后天的思考，而且这种天赋很少有人具备。契诃夫有很多天赋，唯独没有这条。如果你想讲他讲的那种类型的故事，你会发现没得可讲。去掉枝节后，他的故事主干是毫无意义、愚蠢空洞的。那些想写故事又想不出情节的人，要是觉得没有情节也能写得出故事，那就太伟大了。如果你能弄出两三个人物来，描述描述他们的相互关系，就这样算了，然后说写小说也不难嘛；如果你能自信地说这就是艺术，那还有什么比这更容易的艺术？

但是我不敢肯定一个作家把技巧建立在缺点的基础上是否明智。我几乎不怀疑假如契诃夫想得到新颖、独创、惊人的情节，他是能写得出这样的小说的，但这不是他的本性。就像所有的好作家一样，他把自己的缺点变成了优点。歌德不是说艺术家只有在认识了自己的缺点之后才能取得巨大的成就吗？如果短篇小说只是散文的一种，涉及的只是或多或少虚构的人物，那就没人比契诃夫写得更好了。但是如果有人认为短篇小说应该是在有限的篇幅内对一连串完整行动的再现，那契诃夫就还有不足。他用以下的话足够清楚地表明了他的看法：“为什么要写一个人为了与世界达成妥协而坐上潜水艇去北极，而此时他心爱的人歇斯底里地尖叫着从钟楼上纵身跃下？这是不对的，这在真实生活中不会发生。作家必须写寻常的事：彼得·谢苗诺维奇如何娶了玛丽亚·伊万诺夫娜。如此而已。”可是也没有理由说作家不可以写不寻常的事。确实，每天都有事发生，但这并不代表每天都发生的事就是最重要的。重温自己熟悉生活的乐趣是这类写作的目的，但这是审美乐趣中最低级的一种。没有戏剧性，并不是短篇小说的优点。莫泊桑选取的是普通人，但他追求的是在他们生活的寻常事中表现出戏剧性。他选取有意义的事件，从中提取所有可能的戏剧成分。这种方法就像别的方法一样值得称道，因为它可以使小说更吸引人。可能性并不是唯一的标准，因为可能性会经常发生变化。曾经被广泛接受的一种可能性是，失散多年的孩子能够因为“血缘的呼唤”而认出父母，女人只要穿上男人的衣服就会变成男人。只要你能让你那个时代的读者接受，可能性就都成立。契诃夫哪怕再有原则，如果那些原则不合他的意，他也不会总是死守原则。让我且举一例：《主教》，这是他最美、最动人的短篇小说之一。它极其温柔地描写了死亡的到来，但却没写令主教死亡的原因。相反，一个技巧更高的小说家会把死因作为小说必不可少的一部分。“与小说无关的一切东西都必须被无情抛弃，”契诃夫在给舒金的建议里这样说，“如果第一章里你说墙上挂着一杆枪，那么第二章或第三章就必须开枪。”所以如果主教吃了腐烂的鱼，几天后死于伤寒，那我们就可以假定腐烂的鱼是他死亡的原因。如果真相如此的话，他就不是死于伤寒，而是死于尸碱中毒，症状就应该和描写的不同。但是契诃夫显然不在乎，他已经决定了，他温柔的好主教必须死。而且出于他的个人目的，他想让主教以某种特定的方式死去。我不明白那些说契诃夫的小说如同生活侧面的人到底是怎么想的，也就是说，我不明白他们是否认为契诃夫的小说表现了真实且典型的生活图景。无论现在还是过去，我都不认为契诃夫的小说表现了真实且典型的生活。我认为他的短篇小说非常生动，那是因为他有一种特殊的才能，但是我认为他写的那些短篇小说却带着一种阴郁、倦怠和消极的病态的成见。我不会因此去责备契诃夫的短篇小说。每个作家都有他自己看待世界的方式，每个作家描述的世界也都是他眼中的世界。模仿生活并非艺术的合理目标，它是一门学问，一种训练，艺术家必须时时臣服于此，尤其是当对生活的风格化已经达到了一种放肆的地步、践踏了常识的时候。对契诃夫来说，生活如同打台球，永远不可能红球落袋，也挽救不了一个看似要输的传球，也无法同时击中两球。如果你能神奇地意外击中一球，那你就几乎一定能量体裁衣，量入为出。他悲叹，没出息的人不会成功，懒散的人不会工作，撒谎的人不会说真话，酒鬼们不会清醒，无知的人也不会有文化。我猜正是这种心态使得他的主人公们多少有些面目模糊。他能在两行之间给你勾勒出一个醒目的人物形象，谁要是能在两行之间就在你面前树立起一个鲜活的人物形象，能做的也无非如此了，但他苦心经营的结果却似乎使他失去了对个体的把握。他故事中的男人们都是影子般的存在，有种模糊的向善冲动，但是没有意志力，得过且过，不诚实，喜欢说漂亮话，经常怀抱伟大理想却没有行动力。他故事中的女人们都爱哭、自甘堕落、低能。她们哪怕知道那是罪过，但是只要有男人提出要求，不管这个男人是谁，她们都会与他私通。不是因为她们有热情，甚至都不是因为她们想要，而是因为她们嫌拒绝麻烦。他只有在描述年轻女孩的时候才似乎有一丝温柔的宠溺。“呜呼！尽管即将毁灭，这些小受害者还是会玩耍。”他被她们的魅力、她们笑声中的欢快、她们的天真和活力所打动，但这一切都带不来好的结果。她们不去试图征服幸福，而是被动地屈服于前行路上的第一个障碍。

如果我斗胆作出以上评价，我请读者不要以为我对契诃夫心怀不敬。不，我对他只有极度的崇拜。我再说一遍，没有一个作家是完美无缺的。崇拜他的优点是好，但是不承认他的不完美，还坚持他的不完美也是优点，长此以往会损害他的声誉。契诃夫的作品可读性极强，这是作家最了不起的优点，我们对这点的强调还远远不够。契诃夫的作品和莫泊桑的一样好读。他们都是职业作家，为了谋生，多少会定期制造出小说来。他们写作如同医生看病人或律师见客户，是日常工作的一部分。他们必须取悦读者。他们不是总有灵感，只有偶尔才能写得出杰作，但他们写的东西也甚少有不能吸引读者注意力的。他们既给报纸写也给杂志写。批评家们有时会把一本短篇小说集说成是杂志小说，并因此在心里诅咒。这是愚蠢的。所有的艺术形式都是因为有需求才被创造出来。如果报纸杂志不出短篇小说，就不会有人写短篇小说了。所有的小说都是杂志小说或报纸小说。作家必须接受某些条件，而且那些条件总是在变，但还从来没有一个好作家是因为只有在某一特定条件下才能为其作品赢得公众而写不出他的最好作品来的。这从来都是些二流作家的借口。契诃夫的一大优点之所以是简洁，我怀疑是因为他惯常为之写作的报纸只能给他有限的版面。契诃夫说过，小说既不应该有开头也不应该有结尾。这话不可能是字面意思。这就像你要求鱼既不应该有头也不应该有尾一样，如果没有头和尾鱼就不是鱼了。实际上契诃夫给小说开头的方法好极了，他会在几行之内很快就给出事实。他对核心陈述有着准确的把握，会直截了当地把它们写下来，但他写得极为精确，你立刻就会知道你要打交道的人是谁，事又是怎么回事。莫泊桑经常给小说开头的方法是先介绍情况，为的是把读者置于某种特定的心境之下。这种方法很危险，只有成功了才行得通。它还有可能会沉闷，有可能使读者失去线索。你已经引起了他对某些人物的兴趣，现在却不告诉他这些人后来怎么样了，反而把他的兴趣转移到了其他人、其他事上。契诃夫崇尚简洁，但在较长篇幅的作品中他却并不总能做到这一点。有人指责他对道德和社会问题麻木不仁，他深受其扰，因此在篇幅足够的情况下，他会抓住时机表明这些问题对他而言就像对任何思想健全的人一样重要。然后他会在冗长的、多少有些乏味的对话中，让他的人物表达他本人坚定的信仰：不管当时情况如何，在不久的将来（比如说一九三四年）俄国人将获得自由，暴政将不再存在，穷人将不再挨饿，幸福、和平以及兄弟般的友爱将到处存在于这个广大的帝国之中。他写的这些题外话可能是由于他受舆论的压力所迫，类似舆论在所有国家都普遍存在，它认为小说家应该是先知、社会改革家和哲学家。在他较短的小说里，契诃夫以一种几乎神奇的方式达到了他所立下的简洁的目标。

除他以外，没人能对地方、风景、对话或（在其有限的篇幅之内）人物写出更令你亲切的感觉。我想这就是“气氛”这个模糊的字眼所指代的东西。契诃夫似乎不用复杂的解释和冗长的描述，只用准确的事实叙述就制造出了这种“气氛”。我想这要归功于他用一种惊人的简单去看待事物的能力。俄国人是些半野蛮人，他们好像还保留着看事物的自然眼光，好像还生活在真空中一般。而我们背靠复杂文化的西方人看事物的眼光，则是一种经历了很多个世纪的漫长文明之后所获得的、联系的眼光。俄国人看事物似乎只见其自身。过去几年间，大多数作家，尤其是那些住在海外的作家，都看到了不少俄国流亡者写的小说，他们徒劳地希望把作品发表，不管发表在哪，只要能挣几个基尼(4)就好。那些小说虽然写的是现在的事，写得却很像契诃夫，而且还不是最好的契诃夫。他们都有那种直接的、真诚的视角，那是一种天赋的能力，那种能力在契诃夫身上发展得最为突出。

但是我还没说在我看来契诃夫最大的优点是什么。我不是批评家，不掌握准确的批评语汇，因此我只能用个人感觉尽量对之进行描述。契诃夫有一种用“气氛”围绕人物的惊人能力，因此他的人物虽不立体，缺乏莫泊桑人物那种粗糙、通常还很野蛮的活力，但他们却有种奇异的、非尘世般的生命力。他们不是被寻常一天的坚硬强光所照亮，而是被一团神秘的灰色所浸润笼罩。他们在这团灰色中活动，好似脱离了躯壳的游魂一般。你恍惚看到的是他们的灵魂。潜意识似乎浮出水面，彼此直接交流，不存在言语的障碍。奇怪徒劳的造物啊，对他们的外在描述如同博物馆中的展品说明卡一样钉在他们身上，他们的举止好似但丁在地狱中行走时身边围绕的那些饱受折磨的灵魂一样神秘。你有种感觉，似乎有一大群失落的灰色人影在一个幽暗的地下世界漫无目的地游荡，使你敬畏，令你不安。我已经说过，契诃夫在创造人物的多样性方面没有太大才能。顶着不同名字、出现在不同环境里的其实是同一群人。当你看到灵魂的时候，那些表面的区别就消失了，每个人都多多少少一样了。他的人物奇特地融入彼此，似乎他们不是各不相同的个体，而是临时虚构的，又似乎他们其实全部都只是彼此的一部分。作家的重要性何在？从长远看，在其独特性。除契诃夫外，我不知道哪个作家曾经如此悲哀地再现了精神与精神之间的联系。正是这点使人感到相形之下，莫泊桑是如此平淡、庸俗。令人惊异的是，这两个伟大作家，莫泊桑和契诃夫，虽然看人的方式非常不同，对人的看法却一模一样。他们一个满足于看肉体，另一个更高贵、更微妙地审视精神，但他们都认为生活无聊、无意义，人类可鄙、可怜、无知。

我希望读者不要不耐烦我在自己短篇小说的序言中竟长篇大论地谈起了这两位伟大的作家。因为作为短篇小说家，莫泊桑和契诃夫的影响直达今日，我们所有在这一艺术形式中耕耘的人最终都必须被他们所设定的标准评价。

就我记忆所及，我是按写作顺序排列本卷中的各篇小说的。我想读者可能会对我是如何从最初的试探发展到了后期的相对确定感兴趣。也就是说，开始时我还只好听命于我的故事，后来我学会了如何安排素材，以达到我想要的结果。虽然除两篇以外，所有篇目都曾在杂志上发表过，但我最初写这些故事却不是为了在杂志上发表。我那时在经济上幸运地处于还不错的独立状态，再加上我认为自己忙于工作已经太久，因此我写短篇是为了从工作中获得放松。经常有人说短篇小说不会比现在强到哪去了，因为杂志编辑坚持它们必须以某种模式写。这不是我的经历。除了《雨》和《书包》外，所有故事都曾在《大都会》杂志上发表过。瑞朗编辑从没给过我压力，那使我能按我希望的方式写。有些故事发表时会被截断，不过这是合理的，因为编辑只能给投稿人一定的版面，再多就负担不起了。但我从未被要求为了迎合读者可能的口味而对文字做哪怕是最小的改动。对我的作品，瑞朗不仅给了一个好价钱，还给了真诚的欣赏，我对后者的珍视一点不比对钱少。我们作家是简单而幼稚的动物，买我们产品的人说的每一个赞美之词我们都很珍视。这些故事大多是以当初偶然记下的笔记为素材成组写的，我当然会把每组中最难写的故事留到最后。所谓难写，是因为一开始并没有完全想好，后来只好依赖想象和经历才能把某些部分敷衍出来。有时那条故事发展的弧线没能自然地呈现，你不得不求助于这种或那种方法才能把它画出来。

我请读者不要被一个事实欺骗，即因为这些故事很多都是以第一人称叙述，就以为它们是我个人的经历。第一人称只是一种为了达到逼真而使用的手法。它有缺陷，因为它可能会让读者以为叙述者不可能知道他所讲述的所有事情。当叙述者用第一人称叙述隔了一层的事，也就是说当他讲的是别人告诉他的事，那么此时他——比如是个警察或者船长——就永远不可能灵巧或详细地表达自己的思想感情。每种传统手法都有其缺点。缺点必须被尽可能掩盖，不能掩盖的只好接受。第一人称的优点是直接，可以使作者只讲他知道的东西，不用假装无所不知。如果一个动机或一件事他不知道，他只需老实承认，如此则可以经常赋予他的故事以一种可信性。若不如此，故事就可能缺乏这种可信性。它还可以使读者和作者间建立起亲密的关系来。既然莫泊桑和契诃夫都努力想做到客观，结果却都变成了赤裸裸的个人化，那么有时在我看来，如果作者无论如何都不能把自己从作品中剥离出去，那还不如尽可能地投入其中。这样做的危险是他有可能太过投入其中，以至于变得无聊无趣，就像一个坚持要控制谈话的谈话者一样。就像所有的传统手法一样，这种传统手法也须谨慎运用。诸君可能已经注意到了，在《雨》的原始笔记中，对叙述者是做过介绍的，但在故事中却省略了。

本卷中有三个故事是别人讲给我听的，我除了使它们合理、连贯和富有戏剧性外，并未做任何改动。这三个故事是《信》、《丛林里的脚印》和《书包》。其他故事都是我编的，正如我通过《雨》所展示的那样，是我偶然在各处遇到了一些人，他们自身，或者我听说的有关他们的一些东西，让我想起了一个适合小说的主题。这就涉及了一个问题，这个问题总是与作者有关，有时也会令公众、令作者的创作原型不舒服：有些作家宣称他们创作人物时，脑子里从来都没有一个原型。我认为他们错了。他们之所以这么想，是因为他们没有足够细心地审视他们从中建构出人物的那些回忆和印象，反而天真地以为这些人物是他们独造的。如果他们能仔细审视一下，就会发现除非他们的人物来自他们读过的某本书——这种做法非常常见——否则就是取材于他们认识或见过的一个或几个人。先前的一些伟大作家从不讳言他们的人物是建立在真人的基础之上。我们知道伟大的沃尔特·司各特爵士，这是一个有着最崇高原则的人。开始时他犀利地刻画他父亲，后来当时光流逝改变了他的脾性时，又能宽容待之。亨利·贝尔(5)至少曾在其一本小说的手稿边缘上写过人物原型的名字。而屠格涅夫则说：“就我个人而言，我应该坦承，我在构思人物时，从来不是先有想法，而是先有真人，一个各种元素可以在其身上达成协调统一的真人。我总是需要先有个地基，好使自己可以坚实地立足其上。”福楼拜也是如此，狄更斯更是随意利用亲朋作为创作原型，在这上面他可以说是声名狼藉。再说儒勒·勒纳尔的《日记》(6)吧，对每个想知道作家如何写作的人来说，此书很有启发。读此书时你更会发现关于他所认识的人的习惯、言语和相貌，勒纳尔是多么仔细地记下了每个小细节。日后写小说时，他会利用到这个精心收集的信息库。在契诃夫的日记里，你会发现明显是为将来所用而记的笔记，而在他朋友的回忆中，也经常会提到那些成为他某些人物原型的人。这种做法实为常见，我应该说是必须和不可避免的，其方便之处显而易见。你如果有个真实原型，就会更能创造出一个有个性的可辨识的人物。想象力无法凭空起作用，它需要感官刺激。一个创造力被某人的某个奇特之处激发的作家，哪怕那奇特或许是只有他一人以为的奇特，如果他不按他所见到的原型的模样描绘那人，他的初衷也会被歪曲。人的性格是黏合在一起的，如果你认为人的高矮对其性格没有影响，于是在写作中把矮子变高，或者把平静温和的那个人写得暴躁易怒，以此来糊弄读者，那么借用西班牙作家巴尔塔沙·葛拉西安的妙语，你就破坏了组成人物性格的那种合理的和谐。如果不是因为其中所涉之人的感情，整件事将会一帆风顺。作家必须考虑人类的虚荣本质及其幸灾乐祸的特点，这是人类最常见也最可恨的缺点之一。假如人们在一本书中识别出了自己的朋友的特征，尤其是当这本书对这个朋友的刻画是负面的，那么哪怕作者都没见过这个人的面，这些人也会高兴地向这个人指出他们心目中他的形象如何。还有，一个人经常会在书中识别出他知道自己身上也有的特征，或者识别出对他居住地的描述，于是他会立刻在幻想中得出结论，说那个被描写的人是他自己。且举一例。我在名为“办事处”的那篇小说里写了一个英国驻外代表，这个人身上有我在西班牙认识的一个英国领事的影子，他死后十年我写了这个故事，但我后来听说沙捞越(7)的一个区代表非常生气，因为他以为我写的是他。我虽然在故事里写到了沙捞越这个地方，但这二人其实毫无共通之处。我不认为有任何作家会想要绝对真实地照抄一个人物。把一笔一画从现实生活中勾画的人物放到虚构的小说里，确实没有什么比这更不明智了。他的价值观全错了，而且奇怪的是，除他自己以外，他没有把故事里的其他人物弄成虚假。他无法让别人信服。这就是为什么很多作家虽然被已故诺思克利夫勋爵独特、强大的个性吸引，却没有一个人能成功地把他写成一个令人信服的人物。作家选择的原型需以作家本人的性情视之，如果他是个有独创性的作家，那么他的所见不必与事实有任何关系。他可以把高个看成矮个，也可以把慷慨大方之人看成贪得无厌之徒。但是同时我还得说，如果他把高个看成高个，这个人就必须一直高下去。他从真人身上只取他所需之物。他把他当成挂衣钩，在上边挂上自己的想象。为了达到他的目的，即真实世界中很少出现的那种合理的和谐，他把原型并不具备的特点赋予了人物，他使人物连贯充实。被创造出来的人物是想象作用于事实之上的结果，是艺术，而未经加工的生活，我们都知道，只不过是这艺术的原材料。奇怪的是，只要有人指控说作家从生活中模仿了这个或那个人物，重点就放在了这个人物的那些不那么令人赞美的品质上。比如你说一个人对他妈很好，却打老婆，大家会立刻大叫：啊，这是布朗，打老婆多可恶，却一刻也不会想到对老娘好得出名的琼斯和罗宾逊。从中我可以得出一个多少有些令人惊人的结论，即我们看朋友，只知其缺点，不知其优点。我曾经说过我和《雨》中的汤普森小姐甚至连话都没说过。这是个世人从不会觉得缺乏活力的人物。虽然我只是众多写作者中的一个，但我的实践大多数作家无疑都有过。因此我不妨再举一例。有一次我受邀和一对夫妇吃饭，去之前别人告诉我的关于他们的情况我马上就会告诉诸君。我想我一直都不知道他们的名字，如果在街上遇见了也绝对认不出来。以下是我当时的笔记：“一个大约五十岁、相当自负的胖大男子。戴夹鼻眼镜，灰白头发，面色红润，蓝眼睛，上唇留着整齐的灰胡子。说话时很自信。他在一个边远地区当驻外代表，对自己地位的重要性相当自负。他鄙视那些屈服于气候和环境的人。他利用在东方的短暂假期，曾经广泛游历过，他知道爪哇、菲律宾、中国沿海以及马来半岛。他非常英国化，非常爱国；经常锻炼。过去喝酒很多，上床时总带着一瓶威士忌。现在他太太完全治好了他，除了水他什么都不喝了。她是个不起眼的小个子女人，轮廓分明，瘦，肤色灰黄，平胸。她穿得很差。她有英国女人所有的偏见。她的家族世代都在二流军团。你要是不知道她使她丈夫完全戒了酒，你会认为她相当不起眼、不重要。”我就是从上述材料里创作了名为“晚会之前”的那篇小说。我不认为任何心地坦诚的人会认为这两个人有理由抱怨他们被利用了。确实，如果我没有遇到他们，我就不会想出这么一篇小说来。但是任何不怕麻烦读了这篇故事的人会发现，给了这故事以灵感的带着一瓶酒上床的情节在故事中已经变得多么不重要了，而以上的介绍固然是这两个主人公形成的基础，但在写作过程中，他们也已发展得和这寥寥几笔的介绍大相径庭了。

“批评家像马蝇一样，让马没法耕田，”契诃夫如此说，“我读对我小说的批评已经有二十多年了，但我从来不记得曾读到过一句有价值的话，或一条有价值的建议。只有一次斯卡比切夫斯基说了句话给我留下了印象。他说我会醉死在沟里。”契诃夫写了二十五年，也被攻击了二十五年。我不知道今天的批评家们天性是否不再如此暴烈了，我只能说，整体而言，当此卷中的短篇小说不时被结集出版的时候，它们得到的评价还不错。但是有一个经常被用来描述它们的词却让我百思不得其解，那就是“能干”，它的使用实在频繁到了令我不安的地步。表面上我可能以为这是表扬，因为干一件事“能干”总比“不能干”更值得夸赞。但是这个词用的是贬义，我又是个好学之人，总想尽可能地提升自我，因此我会自问，批评家们用这个词的时候脑子里到底在想什么。当然我们每个人都不会被所有人喜爱，一个人的写作是对他自身的深刻揭示，自然会招致讨厌他的那些人的反感，这是必然的，这不会让他难过。但是如果一个作家的作品被普遍认为具有一种不吸引很多人的特点，那么这个作家就应该注意了。很明显，我的小说有不为一些人所喜的东西，他们用“能干”这个词似褒实贬的正是这个东西。我觉得这就是我小说形式的确定性。我斗胆提出这个看法，尽管这可能对我而言太过褒奖了，但我的理由是“能干”这一说辞从未在法国被人提出过，而在法国，我的小说在批评家和公众那里获得的成功全部都超过英国。法国人的古典感觉和他们条理清晰的头脑要求小说形式必须严格精确，线索不能散落得到处都是，主题提出来了不能不解决，高潮预见到了不能又避开，否则会让他们恼怒。而在另一方面，这种严格精确在英国人看来却总有些讨厌。我们的伟大小说都是没有形状的，但这不仅不令英国读者不安，还给了他们一种安全感。他们觉得这就是我们知道的生活：恣意、不合逻辑，能把二加二等于四这种令人恼火的想法抛诸脑后。如果我的这个猜测正确，那我真是无能为力，余生只能满足于被人称为“能干”了。我在艺术上的偏向是在法则和秩序一方。我喜欢“合身”的短篇小说。我是直到有很多写戏剧的经验之后才开始严肃地写短篇小说的，而这些经验教会我把短篇小说中没有戏剧价值的东西全部删掉。它教会我事件要接连发生，以便达到我想要的那种高潮。我不是不知道这种方法的缺点。它会产生一种刻板的效果，有时令人不安。你感觉生活的各个部分并非像小说这样全都严丝合缝地吻合在一起。生活中的故事往往胡乱发展，不知从何处开头，也不知在何处结尾，还连个确切的终点都没有。这大约就是契诃夫说的小说不应有开头也不应有结尾的意思吧。当然，有时当你看到人物的行为与其性格完全吻合，事件有条不紊地发生、发生的时机恰在其时，也会给你一种憋闷的感觉。这类小说作者的目的不仅是为了吐露他对人生的感受，还是为了一种形式上的装饰。他为达到自己的目的而建构生活。他遵从自己头脑中的一个设计，一会儿删掉这个，一会儿改变那个。为了于己有利，他按自己的计划歪曲事实。当他达到目的时，他就创造出了一件艺术品。或许生活从他指缝中溜走，然后他就失败了。或许有时候他看起来太假，让你无法相信他，而当你不再相信一个小说家的时候，他就完了。如果他成功了，他会强迫你暂时接受他对宇宙的看法，当你追随他在混沌表面所描绘的那幅图画时，他会给你以乐趣。但他不想证明什么。他画了一张画，并且把这张画放在你面前。你可以拿走，放那儿不要也行。

(1) 即檀香山，美国夏威夷州的首府和港市。

(2) 东萨摩亚首府。

(3) 吉尔伯特群岛位于太平洋中西部，地处美国和澳大利亚的海上交通线的中间。

(4) 英国旧时货币名，是1663年发行的一种金币，一基尼等于二十一先令，于1813年停止流通。

(5) 《红与黑》的作者司汤达的本名。

(6) 儒勒·勒纳尔（1864—1910），法国作家。他在1887到1910年间的日记是内省、讽刺、幽默和怀旧的杰作，毛姆的《作家笔记》就是受到勒纳尔影响的创作。

(7) 马来西亚的一个州。

《毛姆短篇小说全集卷二：满天之下》自序

（1923—1952）

本卷包括了我所有未收入《东方与西方》的短篇小说。它们长度类似，程度类似，收入一卷一起出版正可谓方便至极。此卷小说大多短小。有些是很多年前写的，有些是最近所作。它们曾在杂志上发表，后来也曾出版成书。对第一种我命名为“大都会”，因为它们都曾在《大都会》杂志上发表。若非当时的编辑瑞朗，我根本就不会把这些故事写出来。

一九二〇年我在中国的时候，记录了我所见到的所有能激起我兴趣的事，意图日后能从中拾掇出一段连贯的叙述来，但回家一读，觉得它们自有一种生动，如果硬要详述，反会令它丧失。于是我改了主意，决定原样发表，起名为“在中国屏风上”。不想瑞朗碰巧读到，觉得其中某些笔记可以写成短篇小说。我在本卷中收录了两个这样的短篇：《大班》和《领事》。事实是，如果你是个小说家，那么你遇到的任何奇人怪人都有可能是你写出一篇小说的提示，任何别人眼里的偶然事件都有可能在你这里展示出一种格局来，而你的自然本能将会把这种格局套在这些人事之上。

杂志读者不喜欢读了小说的开头，又读了一会儿小说后，却被告知要翻到一百多少页才能继续读。小说作者也不喜欢这样，因为他们觉得这种打断会干扰读者。除此他们还有种不安的恐惧，怕读者会嫌麻烦不读了。这真是无可奈何。大家都知道杂志的成本高于售价，不靠广告根本生存不了。广告商们以为如果把公告文字和广告内容放在同一页的话，公告会更有可能被读者读到。除此之外，他们还谦虚地，其实是经常错误地，以为广告本身会更有趣一些，因此有插图的那些杂志经常会把一篇小说或文章的开头连同所配的插图放在一页的开头，而把正文和广告放在一起。

读者和作者都不应抱怨。读者付出的费用远比成本低得多，作者挣的也只有广告才能负担得起。作者们应该记住，他们之所以能在杂志上出现其实只是个诱饵。他们的任务就是把广告的空白处填满，间接诱惑读者掏钱买汽车配件、美容用品，或是加入函授课程。幸运的是，这不会影响到他们。从广告商的角度看，最好的短篇小说是那些最能娱乐读者的小说，他们的这种观点众所周知。瑞朗则有这么一种观点，即《大都会》的读者会喜欢读那些不用在广告里找寻其余部分的小说，所以应该至少给读者一个这样的小说，于是他约我写了半打类似《在中国屏风上》的小品文。它们必须足够短小，能印到杂志的对页上，能给插图留下足够空间。

我写的小品文还挺得读者的欢心，于是《大都会》又和我续了约。我一直写到我天生的啰唆打败了我，使我发现我再也无法把字数控制在规定范围内，然后我就不得不停止了。我想我从这段写作中学到了很多，也很高兴我学到了很多。我的困难是我必须把我想说的话压缩到一定字数内，不能超过规定，可同时还要让读者觉得该说的话我都说了。就是这点使得这事既有趣又有利。我一个字都不能浪费，必须简洁。我惊讶地发现原来很多形容词、副词都可以省略而不影响文章的内容或形式。所以人们为使句子平衡，是经常写废话的。而一个很好的练习就是写一个句子，里边不能有一个对意义表达来说不必要的词，同时还得达到整体的平衡。

主题的选择当然必须慎重。选择一个需要复杂发展的主题会徒劳无功。我对完整有种天生的偏好，所以即使是在小篇幅内，也想让我的小说有个确定的结构。我不喜欢不成形的小说。我认为作家只给出他眼中的基本事实是不够的，还应施以某种形式。我所谓的基本事实当然不是单纯的基本事实，而是带有作家个性色彩的事实。这样的小说自然就都是些奇闻逸事。如果故事有趣，讲得也好，小说不会因此受损。故事是小说的基础。作家的折腾经常会把外在于小说的形式强加于它，但是经历一段时间无人问津、宣传造势、故弄玄虚的压力之后，小说会不可避免地掉头回到小说正确的功能上来，即讲好故事。

关于短篇小说的一般情况，我在《东方与西方》的序言中已经知无不言了，现在也没什么要添加的。迄今为止我已经写了大约一百个短篇小说，我发现的一个情况是：不管你想没想出故事来，完成得好还是不好，几乎全靠运气。每条街道的拐角都有故事，但是作家有可能当时不在，无法将它们拾起；或者正在看商店橱窗，没注意就走过了。他还有可能没看清故事全貌就把故事写了出来，又或者故事他在脑子里颠来倒去想了太久，都失去了新鲜感。他还有可能没从最恰当的角度写，以至于没能把故事写到最好。所以一个作家如果能构思出一个故事，还能在它正当成熟的那一刻落笔，又能把其中暗含的一切都写出来，那真是少见又幸运，是在小说这种艺术形式的局限之内所能达到的完美。但是完美很难实现。我想一卷程度适当的选集中所包含的短篇小说要是能差不多接近这一标准就算很好了。读者如果能在一本短篇小说集中发现所选的小说程度大致不差，合上书的时候能觉得好玩、有趣和感动，那就应该知足了。

除一篇以外，我写的所有小说都曾在杂志上发表过，这篇例外之作叫“书包”。当我将它寄给瑞朗时，瑞朗难过而不是愤怒地写信给我说，他对我的作品比对其他作者的宽容度都大，但是如果事关乱伦，他只能拒绝。我无法责备他。他后来在一本短篇小说集中发表了这篇作品，而这个集子收录了他认为在《大都会》任编辑的漫长生涯里他所见过的最好的短篇小说。我知道承认我的小说曾在杂志上发表等于把我自己置于恶评之下，因为把一篇小说叫成杂志小说等于判它有罪。但是当批评家们如此做之时，他们表现出的那种敏锐要少于能够合理地从他们那里期待的，同时他们也没显出他们对文学史有多少了解。因为自从杂志变成一种流行的出版方式以后，作家们就将它视为一种有用的、可向读者展示自己作品的媒介。所有伟大的短篇小说家都曾在杂志上发表过作品，比如巴尔扎克、福楼拜、莫泊桑，又比如契诃夫、亨利·詹姆斯和吉卜林。那些没在杂志上发表过的短篇小说是任何编辑都不会接受的小说，我不认为这种说法有任何轻率之处。因为一篇小说是杂志小说而谴责它是荒谬的。杂志无疑发表过很多不好的小说，但是不好的小说本来就比好的小说多；而编辑，哪怕是一本极有文学主张的杂志的编辑，也经常不得不出一些他不那么看好的小说，因为他看好的他没遇到。还有些流行杂志的编辑认为他们的读者需要某些类型的小说，于是就不接受这个类型之外的东西。他们找得到能写他们想要的那类东西的作者，这类作者通常还会把这类东西写得很好。正是这种固定模式的小说给杂志小说带来了坏名声。毕竟，没有人有义务读杂志小说。不过杂志小说还是给很多人带来了满足感，因为它能在短时间内，让这些人在幻想中经历他们在单调的现实生活中所渴望经历的那种浪漫和冒险。

经常有短篇小说集出版，我也读了不少有关它们的评论，如果允许我从中作出评判，那么在我看来，批评家们之所以犯错，就在于他们总是因为一篇小说构思精良、富有戏剧性，还有个令人意想不到的结局而将它贬低为杂志小说。如果一个大逆转的结局是一篇小说自然而然的结局，那就没什么好谴责的。相反，应该认为这样的结局是小说极大的优点。惊人的结局只有在毫无理由将它硬编出来想要刺激读者时才不好，比如欧·亨利的某些小说。有开头、中间和结尾的故事并不会因为结构齐整而损失了什么。为了做到这一点，所有好小说家都尽了全力。当下的风潮是，作者们在还不十分了解契诃夫的情况下就胡乱模仿契诃夫，于是他们写的故事可以随处开始，又可以没有任何结局地结束。他们觉得如果自己已经描述了一种情绪，或是制造了一种印象，或是刻画了一个人物，那就足够了。这也不算错，但这样写出来的不是小说，我不认为这样的东西能满足读者。读者不喜欢被遗弃在那儿自己琢磨，他希望他的问题能得到回答。这也是我尽力去做的。当我得到一个故事，却又不知其答案，我是不会动笔去写这个故事的。我在《作家笔记》中提到了一个这样的故事。因为我不期待大家读过我所有的书，因此不妨在此处再讲一遍，说不定能娱乐读者。我在印度的时候收到过一封信，写信人我不认识。他在信中讲了一个故事，觉得我能用得上：

两个年轻人在山中的一座茶园干活，因为信件要从很远的地方送来，因此他们很久才能收一次信。其中一个年轻人，我们叫他A吧，每次都能收到许多信，十封、十二封，甚至更多。另一个年轻人B则从来都没有收到过信。他会嫉妒地看着A接过邮包读信，他也想收信，哪怕一封也好。于是有一天，他们正在等信的时候，他对A说：“看，你总是有很多信，我却一封也没有。你要是给我一封信，我就给你五镑钱。”“好啊！”A说。信来了，A把信递给B，对他说：“随便挑吧。”B给了A一张五镑的钞票，把信翻看了一遍，挑出一封，剩下的还给A。晚饭前他们喝威士忌加苏打水的时候，A随意问道：“信里说什么？”“我不告诉你。”B说。A有点吃惊了，问：“那么信是谁写的呢？”“这与你无关。”B说。他们争执了一番，但是B坚持自己的权利，就是不肯告诉A他买的这封信里到底说了些什么。A生起气来。几个星期过去了，他努力劝说B让他看看那封信。B总是拒绝。最后A终于又急又气又好奇，觉得再也受不了了，就去找B，跟B说：“看，这是你的五镑钱，把信还给我吧。”“休想，”B说，“我买的，我付了钱，这是我的信，我不会放弃。”

我在《作家笔记》中说：“假如我属于现代派小说家，我会将故事按原样写下，并且就这样了事，但这违背了我的原则。我希望故事有形式，而在这个故事里，除非你给出确切的结局，不给人合理猜测的余地，否则我就不认为你给了它形式。即使你能做到把读者悬在半空中，你也不会想把自己和他一起悬在半空中。”那个写信人告诉我的这些事激起了很多人的好奇，引得加拿大的一份杂志和英国的《新政治家》杂志在互不知情的情况下，各自悬赏读者，为这个故事征集最好的结局。不过我不认为那些结局有多成功。

我曾读过一篇讲如何写短篇小说的文章。作者的某些观点是有用的，但我认为她的核心观点错了。她说短篇小说的“焦点”应该是塑造人物，故事的存在应该只是为了让人物“活起来”。奇怪的是在说这话前，她又说圣经里的那些寓言故事是有史以来写得最好的短篇小说。我却认为，想要描述浪子和他的兄弟，或那个善良的撒玛利亚人，或那个落入小偷之手的人的性格恐怕很难。实际上圣经对他们都没有性格刻画，我们只能猜测他们是哪种人，因为我们被告知的仅仅是对引出道德训诫必要的那些基本事实。一个短篇小说家是否有一个道德训诫想要指出，这才是他最该做的事。他没有描写和发展人物的余地，他能做的只是给出人物最显著的特点，让人物生动起来，好使他讲的故事具有可信性。有史以来人类就围在篝火旁，或在市场上聚拢起来听人讲故事。想要听故事的欲望就像对财物的占有欲一样，似乎深植于人类这种动物的内心。除了是个讲故事的人，我从来都不假装自己还是别的什么人。讲故事让我觉得好玩，我也讲了很多很多故事。

我写小说迄今已经有五十年了。在这段漫长的时间里，我曾亲眼见过数颗明星羞涩地爬上地平线，从天空中划过，行至中天时燃烧一会儿，闪烁着如同宝石般的光焰，然后就黯然衰落，再也不可能重新升起了。作家有其独特之处要表达，如果你对它展开分析，那就是作家天赋的个性。一个作家在他写作活动的早期会在黑暗中摸索，想要表达他的个性，然后如果他幸运，他就能成功。如果他的个性中有一种丰富性，那么他就可以在很长时间内创造出多样并且富有他个人特色的作品来。可是如果他已经到了老熟的年纪，已经给予了他所能给予的一切，那么他才尽的一天也总会到来。能从取之不尽的人性宝藏中挖掘出来的故事，他已经尽数塑造了；能从他本人个性的各个方面构造出来的角色，他也已经全部构造了。我认为没有人能从纯粹的观察中创造人物，如果人物栩栩如生，那至少在某种程度上表现了作者本人的个性。一代人已经崛起了，他们对他来说很陌生，他只能通过意志力才能明白这个新世界的喜好，他只能充当这个新世界的观察者。但是只有理解还不够，小说家还必须感受，不光是感受某种感情，还应在这种情感中感受。有些小说不写最好，如果他能使自己停止写这些小说，那就算是难得了。如果他能谨慎注意那些迹象的出现——那些迹象会告诉他，他既已说了他该说的话，他就该回归沉默——那他就是个智慧的人。

我已经写出了我最后的故事。

Books and You (Part 1)

One isn’t always as careful of what one says as one should be. When I stated in a book of mine called The Summing Up that young people often came to me for advice on the books they would do well to read, I did not reckon with the consequences. I received a multitude of letters from all manner of persons, asking me what the advice was that I gave. I answered them as best I could, but it is not possible to deal fully with such a matter in a private letter; and as many people seem to desire such guidance as I can offer, it has occurred to me that they might like to have a brief account of what suggestions I have to make from my own experience for pleasant and profitable reading.

The first thing I want to insist on is that reading should be enjoyable. Of course, there are many books that we all have to read, either to pass examinations or to acquire information, from which it is impossible to extract enjoyment. We are reading them for instruction, and the best we can hope is that our need for it will enable us to get through them without tedium. Such books we read with resignation rather than with alacrity. But that is not the sort of reading I have in mind. The books I shall mention in due course will help you neither to get a degree nor to earn your living, they will not teach you to sail a boat or get a stalled motor to run, but they will help you to live more fully. That, however, they cannot do unless you enjoy reading them.

The“you”I address is the adult whose avocations give him a certain leisure and who would like to read the books which cannot without loss be left unread. I do not address the bookworm. He can find his own way. His curiosity leads him along many unfrequented paths and he gathers delight in the discovery of half-forgotten excellence. I wish to deal only with the masterpieces which the consensus of opinion for a long time has accepted as supreme. We are all supposed to have read them; it is a pity that so few of us have. But there are masterpieces which are acknowledged to be such by all the best critics and to which the historians of literature devote considerable space, yet which no ordinary person can now read with enjoyment. They are important to the student, but changing times and changing tastes have robbed them of their savour and it is hard to read them now without an effort of will. Let me give one instance: I have read George Eliot's Adam Bede, but I cannot put my hand on my heart and say that it was with pleasure. I read it from a sense of duty: I finished it with a sigh of relief.

Now of such books as this I mean to say nothing. Every man is his own best critic. Whatever the learned say about a book, however unanimous they are in their praise of it, unless it interests you it is no business of yours. Don’t forget that critics often make mistakes, the history of criticism is full of the blunders the most eminent of them have made, and you who read are the final judge of the value to you of the book you are reading. This, of course, applies to the books I am going to recommend to your attention. We are none of us exactly like everyone else, only rather like, and it would be unreasonable to suppose that the books that have meant a great deal to me should be precisely those that will mean a great deal to you. But they are books that I feel the richer for having read, and I think I should not be quite the man I am if I had not read them. And so I beg of you, if any of you who read these pages are tempted to read the books I suggest and cannot get on with them, just put them down; they will be of no service to you if you do not enjoy them. No one is under an obligation to read poetry or fiction or the miscellaneous literature which is classed as belles-lettres. (I wish I knew the English term for this, but I don’t think there is one.) He must read them for pleasure, and who can claim that what pleases one man must necessarily please another?

But let no one think that pleasure is immoral. Pleasure in itself is a great good, all pleasure, but its consequences may be such that the sensible person eschews certain varieties of it. Nor need pleasure be gross and sensual. They are wise in their generation who have discovered that intellectual pleasure is the most satisfying and the most enduring. It is well to acquire the habit of reading. There are few sports in which you can engage to your own satisfaction after you have passed the prime of life; there are no games except patience, chess problems and crossword puzzles that you can play without someone to play them with you. Reading suffers from no such disadvantages; there is no occupation—except perhaps needlework, but that leaves the restless spirit at liberty—which you can more easily take up at any moment, for any period, and more easily put aside when other calls press upon you; there is no other amusement that can be obtained in these happy days of public libraries and cheap editions at so small a cost. To acquire the habit of reading is to construct for yourself a refuge from almost all the miseries of life. Almost all, I say, for I would not go so far as to pretend that to read a book will assuage the pangs of hunger or still the pain of unrequited love; but half a dozen good detective stories and a hot-water bottle will enable anyone to snap hisfingers at the worst cold in the head. But who is going to acquire the habit of reading for reading's sake, if he is bidden to read books that bore him?

It is more convenient to take the books of which I am now going to speak in chronological order, but I can see no reason why, if you make up your mind to read them, you should do so in that order. I think you would be much better advised to read them according to your fancy; nor do I see even why you should read them one by one. For my own part, Ifind it more agreeable to read four orfive books together. After all, you aren’t in the same mood on one day as on another, nor have you the same eagerness to read a certain book at all hours of the day. We must suit ourselves in these matters, and I have naturally adopted the plan that best suits me. In the morning before I start work I read for a while a book, either of science or philosophy, that requires a fresh and attentive brain. It sets me off for the day. Later on, when my work is done and I feel at ease, but not inclined for mental exercise of a strenuous character, I read history, essays, criticism or biography; and in the evening I read a novel. Besides these, I keep on hand a volume of poetry in case I feel in the mood for that, and by my bedside I have one of those books, too rarely to be found, alas, which you can dip into at any place and stop reading with equanimity at the end of any paragraph.

Now, the first book on my list is Defoe's Moll Flanders. No English novelist has ever achieved a greater verisimilitude thanDefoe; it is hard, indeed, when you read him, to remember that you are reading a work of fiction; it is more like a consummate piece of reporting. You are convinced that his people spoke exactly as he made them speak, and their actions are so plausible that you cannot doubt that this is how, in the circumstances, they behaved. Moll Flanders is not a moral book. It is bustling, coarse and brutal, but it has a robustness that I like to think is in the English character. Defoe had little imagination and not much humour, but he had a wide and varied experience of life and, being an excellent journalist, he had a keen eye for the curious incident and the telling detail. He had no sense of climax, he attempted no pattern; and so the reader is not swept away by a power that he does not seek to resist; he is carried along in the crowd, as it were, and it may be that when he comes to a side street he will slip down it and get away. He may, to put it plainly, after a couple of hundred pages of very much the same sort of thing feel that he has had enough. Well, that's all right. But for my part, I am quite willing to accompany my author till he brings his ribald heroine to the haven of respectability tempered with penitence.

Then I should like you to read Swift's Gulliver's Travels. I am going to deal with Doctor Johnson later on, but here I must note that, speaking of this book, he said: “When once you have thought of big men and little men, it is very easy to do all the rest.”Doctor Johnson was an excellent critic and a very wise man, but here he talked nonsense. Gulliver's Travels has wit and irony, ingenious invention, broad humour, savage satire and vigour. Its style is admirable. No one has ever written this difficult language of ours more compactly, more lucidly and more unaffectedly than Swift. I could wish thatDoctor Johnson had said of him what he said of another: “Whoever wishes to attain an English style, familiar but not coarse and elegant but not ostentatious, must give his days and nights to the volumes of Addison.”He could then have added a third to his pairs of adjectives: virile but not overweening.

Two novels come next. Fielding's Tom Jones is, perhaps, the healthiest novel in English literature. It is a dashing, brave and cheerful book, sturdy and generous; it is, of course, very frank, and Tom Jones, with his good looks and vitality, a friendly fellow whom we should all like to have known, does certain things which the moralist will deplore. But do we care? Not unless we are solemn prigs, for he is disinterested and his heart is golden. Fielding was, unlike Defoe, a conscious artist; his scheme gave him the opportunity to describe a multitude of incidents and to create a great number of personages. They are splendidly alive in a world that is pungent with the bustle and turmoil of reality. Fielding took himself seriously—as, of course, every author should—and there were many subjects of importance on which he felt called upon to deliver himself. At the beginning of each part he puts a dissertation in which he discusses one thing and another. These have humour and sincerity, but for my part I think they can be skipped without disadvantage. I have a notion that no one can read Tom Jones without delight, for it is a manly, wholesome book, without any humbug about it, and it warms the cockles of your heart.

Sterne's Tristram Shandy is a novel of very different character. You might say of it what Doctor Johnson said of Sir Charles Grandison: “If you were to read it for the story, you would hang yourself.”It is a book that, according to your temperament, you will find either as readable as anything you have ever read, or tiresome and affected. It has no unity. It has no coherence. Digression follows upon digression. But it is wonderfully original, funny and pathetic; and it increases your spiritual possessions with half a dozen characters so full of idiosyncrasy and so lovable that once you have come to know them, you feel that not to have known them would have been an irreparable loss. Nor would I have anyone fail to read Sterne's A Sentimental Journey; I have nothing to say of it except that it is enchanting.

Now let us leave fiction for a little. I suppose it is universally acknowledged that Boswell's The Life of Samuel Johnson is the greatest biography in the language. It is a book that you can read with profit and pleasure at any age. You can pick it up at any time, opening it at random, and be sure of entertainment. But to praise such a work at this time of day is absurd. I should like, however, to add to it a book that, to my mind undeservedly, is less well known. This is Boswell's The Journal of a Tour to the Hebrides. The purchase by Colonel Isham of the Boswell manuscripts has resulted in a new and unexpurgated edition of it, for, as I suppose everyone knows, Boswell's manuscript was edited by Malone, who thought it proper to tone it down in accordance with the primly elegant taste of the day, and so left out much that gave the book flavour. It enlarges your knowledge both of Johnson and of Boswell, and if it increases your love and admiration for the sturdy old doctor, it adds also to your respect for his poor biographer who has been so much abused. This is not a writer to be despised who had such a quick eye for an amusing incident, so much appreciation of a racy phrase, and such a rare gift for reproducing the atmosphere of a scene and the liveliness of a conversation.

The figure of Doctor Johnson towers over the eighteenth century, and he has been accepted as representing the English character, with its sterling merits and unhappy defects, at its best. But if we have all read his biography, so that we know him more intimately than we know many of the people we have passed our lives with, few of us have read any of his writings; and yet he produced one work at least which is in the highest degree enjoyable. I know no better book to take on a holiday or to keep at one's bedside than Johnson's Lives of the Poets. It is written with limpidity. It has pungency and humour. It is full of horse sense. Though sometimes his judgments startle us—he found Gray dull and had little good to say of Milton's Lycidas—you delight in them because they are an expression of his own personality. He was as much interested in the men he wrote of as in their works, and though you may not have read a word of these, you can hardly fail to be diverted by the shrewd, lively and tolerant observation with which he portrays their authors.

I come next to a book that I name with hesitation, for, as I must remind the reader, I wish to speak here only of books that one would be the poorer for not having read, and though I have a great fondness for Gibbon's Autobiography, I am not quite sure that it would have made much difference to me not to have read it. I should certainly have lost a keen pleasure, but if I mention it I feel that I should mention also a large number of other works, not so great as the greatest, to be judged by a different standard, and they would need a chapter to themselves. But Gibbon's Autobiography is very readable; it is short, written with the peculiar elegance of which he was master, and it has both dignity and humour. Of the latter I cannot resist giving an example. When he was at Lausanne he fell in love, but his father threatening to disinherit him, he prudently gave up the thought of marrying the object of his affections. He ends his recital of the episode with these words: “I sighed as a lover, I obeyed as a son; and my wound was insensibly healed by time, absence, and the habits of a new life.”I think if the book contained nothing else, it would be worth reading for that delicious sentence.

Now I want to abandon the chronological order to which I have till now roughly adhered, in order to speak of two great novels, David Copperfield and Butler's The Way of All Flesh. This I do, not only because they are to a notable degree in the great tradition of the English novel, but also because they have eminently the features which, when I think of the works I have hitherto summarily considered, seem characteristic of English literature. With the possible exception of Tristram Shandy, all these books have in common something robust, straight-forward, humorous and healthy which, I like to think, is representative of the race. There is no especial subtlety in them and they are somewhat wanting in delicacy. It is a literature of men of action rather than of men of thought. There is a lot of common sense about it, some sentimentality and a great deal of humanity. Of David Copperfield there is nothing to be said but that it is Dickens’ best novel. His defects are here least noticeable and his merits most remarkable. Many long novels have been written since The Way of All Flesh, but I think it is the last English novel to have been written in the grand manner; it is the last, of any importance, that owes nothing to the great novelists of France and Russia. It is a worthy successor of Tom Jones, and its author had in him something of the old lexicographer whom we have agreed to regard as the typical Englishman.

Then I go back to Jane Austen. I would not claim that she is England's greatest novelist; with all his faults of exaggeration, vulgarity, wordiness and sentimentality, Dickens remains that. He was prodigious. He did not describe the world as we know it; he created a world. He had suspense, drama and humour, and thus was able to give the feel of the multifariousness and bustle of life as, so far as I know, only one other novelist, Tolstoy, has done. Out of his immense vitality he fashioned a whole series of characters, diverse, individual, and tremulous with—no, “tremulous”isn’t the right word—turbulent with life. He managed his complicated and often highly improbable stories with a dashing skill that perhaps you must be a novelist thoroughly to appreciate. But Jane Austen is perfect. It is true that her scope is restricted; she deals with a little world of country gentlefolk, clergymen and middle-class persons; but who has equalled her insight into character or surpassed the delicacy and reasonableness with which she probed its depths? She does not need my praise. The only characteristic I would like to impress upon your attention is one which she exhibits with so much ease that you might well take it for granted. Though, on the whole, nothing very much happens in her stories, and she mostly eschews dramatic incident, you are inveigled, I hardly know how, to turn from page to page by the urgent desire to know what is going to happen next; and that is the novelist's essential gift. Without it he is done. I can think of no one who possessed it more fully than Jane Austen. My only difficulty now is to decide which of her few novels especially to recommend. For my part, I like Mansfield Park best. I recognize that its heroine is a little prig and its hero a pompous ass, but I do not care; it is wise, witty and tender, a masterpiece of ironical humour and subtle observation.

At this point I would draw your attention to Hazlitt. His fame has been overshadowed by that of Charles Lamb, but to my mind he was the better essayist. Charles Lamb, a charming, gentle, witty creature whom to know was to love, has always appealed to the affections of his readers. Hazlitt could hardly do that. He was rude, tactless, envious and quarrelsome; a man, in truth, of an unpleasing character; but, unfortunately, it is not always the most worthy men who write the best books. In the end it is the personality of the artist that counts, and for my part Ifind more to interest me in the tormented, striving, acrimonious soul of Hazlitt than in Charles Lamb's patient but somewhat maudlin amiability. As a writer, Hazlitt was vigorous, bold and healthy. What he had to say, he said with decision. His essays are full of meat, and when you have read one of them you feel, not as you do when you have read one of Lamb's, that you have made a meal of savoury kickshaws, but that you have satisfied your appetite with substantial fare. Much of his best work can be found in his Table Talk, but there have been published a number of selections from his essays, and none of these can fail to contain My First Acquaintance with Poets, which, I suppose, is not only the most thrilling piece he ever wrote but the finest essay in the English language.

Now, two more novels: Thackeray's Vanity Fair, and Emily Brontë's Wuthering Heights. I can say little about them, for my space is growing short. Critics nowadays are inclined to carp at Thackeray. Perhaps he was unfortunate in his period. He should have lived and written in our own time, when he would not have been hampered by the conventions which prevented the Victorian novelist from telling the truth, however bitter, as he saw it. His point of view was modern. He was deeply conscious of the mediocrity of human beings and he was interested in the contradictions of their natures. And however much you may deplore his sentimentality and his sermonizing or regret the weakness that led him to defer unduly to the demands of the public, the fact remains that in Becky Sharp he created one of the most real, living and forcible characters in English fiction.

Wuthering Heights is unique. It is an awkward novel to read, because sometimes it so outrages probability that you are completely bewildered; but it is passionate and profoundly moving; it has the depth and power of a great poem. To read it is not like reading a work of fiction, in which, however absorbed, you can remind yourself, if need be, that it is only a story; it is to have a shattering experience in your own life.

I can but name three novels which I think it would be a pity to have left unread. They are George Eliot's Middlemarch, Trollope's The Eustace Diamonds and Meredith's The Egoist.

The reader will have noticed, perhaps with surprise, that hitherto I have said nothing of poetry. I do not think our race has produced either painters, sculptors or composers who can rank with the best of other countries; their achievements have been respectable rather than pre-eminent; but I do not believe it is a racial or national bias that leads me to claim that our poets are supreme. But because poetry is the flower and crown of literature, it cannot afford to be mediocre. I remember Edmund Gosse telling me that he would much rather read a volume of minor verse than an average novel; it took less time, he said, and required no mental effort. Well, I have no use for verse, however accomplished; to me, unless poetry is great, it is nothing, and I would sooner read a newspaper. I cannot read poetry at all times and in all places. I want to be in a particular mood and I want a favourable environment, I like to read poetry in a garden towards the end of a summer day; I like to sit on a cliff with a view of the sea or to lie on a mossy bank in a wood and take out the volume I have brought in my pocket. But even the greatest poets have written a great deal that is tedious to read; many versifiers have written endless volumes and in the end produced no more than two or three poems. I think that is enough to justify them, but I do not want to read so much to gain so little. I like anthologies. The critics, I understand, have a contempt for them; they say that in order to appreciate an author you must read him in full. But I do not read poetry as a critic; I read it as a human being in need of solace, refreshment and peace. I am thankful to the sensitive scholar who has taken the trouble to weed out from the great mass of English poetry what is not so good and has left for my perusal only what is to my purpose. The three best anthologies I know are Palgrave's Golden Treasury, The Oxford Book of English Verse, and the admirable English Galaxy of Shorter Poems, by Gerald Bullett. But we live in the world of to-day and we should not neglect the writings of the poets of our own time. They, too, may have something important to give us. Unfortunately, the only anthology that, to my knowledge, has been made of them is so inadequate that I forbear even to name it.

Of course, everyone must read the great tragedies of Shakespeare. He is not only the greatest poet that ever lived but the glory of our race. But knowing, as I do, these plays pretty well, I wish that someone with taste, knowledge and discretion could be found who would make an anthology of Shakespeare's plays and poems, putting in not only the famous passages with which we should all be familiar but also fragments, single lines even; so that I might have in a convenient volume a book to which I could always turn when I wanted the cream of all poetry. (Since I wrote these lines George Rylands has produced an anthology under the title of The Ages of Man which comes as near fulfilling the wish I have here expressed as, I suppose, anyone can expect. It is a welcome gift to a troubled world.)

Henry Fielding and Tom Jones

1

The difficulty of writing about Henry Fielding, the man, is that very little is known about him. Arthur Murphy, who wrote a short life of him in 1762, only eight years after his death, as an introduction to an edition of his works, seems to have known him, if he knew him at all, only in his later years, and had so little material to work with that, presumably to fill the eighty pages of his essay, he indulged in long and tedious digressions. The facts he tells are few, and subsequent research has shown that they are not always accurate. The last writer to deal at length with Fielding is Dr. Homes Dudden, Master of Pembroke, Oxford. The two stout volumes of his work are a monument of painstaking industry. By giving a lively picture of the political circumstances of the times, and a vivid account of the Young Pretender's disastrous adventure in 1745, he has added colour, depth and substance to the narrative of his hero's checkered career. I don’t believe that there is anything to be said about Henry Fielding that the eminent author has left unsaid.

Fielding was a gentleman born. His father was the third son of John Fielding, a Canon of Salisbury, and he in turn was the fifth son of an Earl of Desmond. The Desmonds were a younger branch of the family of Denbigh, who flattered themselves that they were descended from the Habsburgs. Gibbon, the Gibbon of The Decline and Fall, wrote in his autobiography: “The successors of Charles the Fifth may disclaim their brethren of England; but the romance of Tom Jones, that exquisite picture of human manners, will outlive the palace of the Escorial, and the imperial eagle of the House of Austria.”The phrase has a fine resonance, and it is a pity that the claim of these noble lords has been shown to have no foundation. They spelt their name Feilding, and there is a well-known story that on one occasion the then Earl asked Henry Fielding how this came about; whereupon he answered: “I can only suppose it is because my branch of the family learnt to spell before your lordship's.”

Fielding's father entered the army and served in the wars under Marlborough“with much bravery and reputation.”He married Sarah, the daughter of Sir Henry Gould, a Judge of the King's Bench; and at his country seat, Sharpham Park, near Glastonbury, our author was born in 1707. Two or three years later the Fieldings, who by this time had had two more children, daughters, moved to East Stour in Dorsetshire, a property which the judge had settled on his daughter, and there three more girls and a boy were born. Mrs. Fielding died in 1718, and in the following year Henry went to Eton. Here he made some valuable friends and, if he did not leave, as Arthur Murphy states, “uncommonly well versed in the Greek authors and an early master of the Latin classics, ”he certainly acquired a real love for classical learning. Later in life, when he was ill and poverty-stricken, he found comfort in reading Cicero's De Consolatione; and when, dying, he set out in the ship that took him to Lisbon, he carried with him a volume of Plato.

On leaving Eton, instead of going up to a university, he lived for a while at Salisbury with his grandmother, Lady Gould, the judge being dead; and there, according to Dr. Dudden, read some law and a good deal of miscellaneous literature. He was then a handsome youth, over six feet tall, strong and active, with deep-set eyes, a Roman nose, a short upper lip with an ironical curl to it, and a stubborn, prominent chin. His hair was brown and curly, his teeth white and even. By the time he was eighteen, he gave promise of the sort of man he was going to be. He happened to be staying at Lyme Regis with a trusty servant, ready to“beat, maim or kill”for his master, and there fell in love with a Miss Sarah Andrews, whose considerable fortune added to the charm of her beauty, and he concocted a scheme to carry her off, by main force if necessary, and marry her. It was discovered, and the young woman was hurried away and safely married to a more eligible suitor. For all one knows to the contrary, Fielding spent the next two or three years in London, with an allowance from his grandmother, engaging in the gaieties of the town as agreeably as a well-connected young man can do when he has good looks and charm of manner. In 1728, by the in fluence of his cousin, Lady Mary Wortley-Montagu, and with the help of the charming, but not particularly chaste, actress, Anne Oldfield, a play of Fielding's was put on by Colley Cibber at Drury Lane. It was called Love in Several Masques and was given four performances. Shortly after this, he entered the University of Leyden with an allowance from his father of two hundred pounds a year. But his father had married again and either could not, or would not, continue to pay him the allowance he had promised, so after about a year Fielding was obliged to return to England. He was in such straits then that, as in his light-hearted way he put it himself, he had no choice but to be a hackney coachman or a hackney writer.

Austin Dobson, who wrote his life for The English Men of Letters Series, says that“his inclinations as well as his opportunities led him to the stage.”He had the high spirits, the humour, the keen-witted observation of the contemporary scene, which are needed by the playwright; and he seems to have had besides some ingenuity and a sense of construction. The“inclinations”of which Austin Dobson speaks may very well mean that he had the vicarious exhibitionism which is part of the playwright's make-up, and that he looked upon writing plays as an easy way to make quick money; the“opportunities”may be a delicate way of saying that he was a handsome fellow of exuberant virility and had taken the fancy of a popular actress. To please a leading lady has ever been the surest way for a young dramatist to get his play produced. Between 1729 and 1737 Fielding composed or adapted twenty-six plays, of which at least three greatly pleased the town; and one of which made Swift laugh, a thing that to the best of the Dean's recollection he had only done twice in his life before. Fielding did not do very well when he attempted pure comedy; his great successes seem to have been in a genre which, so far as I know, he devised himself, an entertainment in which there were singing and dancing, brief topical sketches, parodies and allusions to public figures: in fact, something indistinguishable from the revues popular in our own day. According to Arthur Murphy, Fielding's farces“were generally the production of two or three mornings, so great was his facility in writing.”Dr. Dudden looks upon this as an exaggeration. I don’t think it is. Some of these pieces were very short, and I have myself heard of light comedies that were written over a week-end and were none the worse for that. The last two plays Fielding wrote were attacks on the political corruption of the times, and the attacks were effective enough to cause the Ministry to pass a Licensing Act which obliged managers to obtain the Lord Chamberlain's licence to produce a play. This act still obtains to torment British authors. After this, Fielding wrote only rarely for the theatre and, when he did, presumably for no other reason than that he was more than usually hard up.

I will not pretend that I have read his plays, but I have flipped through the pages, reading a scene here and there, and the dialogue seems natural and sprightly. The most amusing bit I have come across is the description which, after the fashion of the day, he gives in the list of Dramatis Personæ in Tom Thumb the Great: “A woman entirely faultless, save that she is a little given to drink.”It is usual to dismiss Fielding's plays as of no account, and doubtless no one would give them a thought if he were not the author of Tom Jones. They lack the literary distinction (such as Congreve's plays have) which the critic, reading them in his library two hundred years later, would like them to have. But plays are written to be acted, not to be read; it is certainly well for them to have literary distinction; but it is not that which makes them good plays, it may (and often does) make them less actable. Fielding's plays have by now lost what merit they had, for the drama depends very much on actuality and so is ephemeral, almost as ephemeral as a newspaper, and Fielding’ plays, as I have said, owed their success to the fact that they were topical; but light as they were, they must have had merit, for neither a young man's wish to write plays, nor pressure brought to bear by a favourite actress, will induce managers to put on play after play unless they please the public. For in this matter the public is the final judge. Unless the manager can gauge their taste, he will go bankrupt. Fielding's plays had at least the merit that the public liked to go to see them. Tom Thumb the Great ran for“upwards of forty nights, ”and Pasquin for sixty, which was as long as The Beggar's Opera had run.

Fielding had no illusions about the worth of his plays, and himself said that he left off writing for the stage when he should have begun. He wrote for money, and had no great respect for the understanding of an audience.“When he had contracted to bring on a play, or a farce, ”says Murphy, “it is well known by many of his friends now living, that he would go home rather late from a tavern and would, the next morning, deliver a scene to the players, written upon the papers which had wrapped the tobacco, in which he so much delighted.”During the rehearsals of a comedy called The Wedding Day, Garrick, who was playing in it, objected to a scene and asked Fielding to cut it.“No, damn ’em, ”said Fielding, “if the scene isn’t a good one let them find it out.”The scene was played, the audience noisily expressed their displeasure, and Garrick retired to the green-room where his author was“indulging his genius and solacing himself with a bottle of champagne. He had by this time drunk pretty plentifully; and cocking his eye at the actor, with streams of tobacco trickling down from the corner of his mouth, ‘What's the matter, Garrick, ’ says he, ‘what are they hissing now?’

“‘Why, the scene that I begged you to retrench; I knew it would not do; and they have so frightened me, that I shall not be able to collect myself the whole night.’

“‘Oh, damn ’em, ’ replies the author, ‘they have found it out, have they?’”

This story is told by Arthur Murphy, and I am bound to say that I doubt its truth. I have known and had dealings with actor-managers, which is what Garrick was, and it does seem to me very unlikely that he would have consented to play a scene which he thought would wreck the play; but the anecdote wouldn’t have been invented unless it had been plausible. It at least indicates how Fielding's friends and boon-companions regarded him.

If I have dwelt on his activity as a playwright, though it was after all not much more than an episode in his career, it is because I think it was important to his development as a novelist. Quite a number of eminent novelists have tried their hands at playwriting, but I cannot think of any that have conspicuously succeeded. The fact is that the techniques are very different, and to have learnt how to write a novel is of no help when it comes to writing a play. The novelist has all the time he wants to develop his theme, he can describe his characters as minutely as he chooses and make their behaviour plain to the reader by relating their motives; if he is skilful, he can give verisimilitude to improbabilities; if he has a gift for narrative, he can gradually work up to a climax which a long preparation makes more striking (a supreme example of this is Clarissa's letter in which she announced her seduction); he does not have to show action, but only to tell it; he can make the persons explain themselves in dialogue for as many pages as he likes. But a play depends on action, and by action, of course, I don’t mean violent action like falling off a precipice or being run over by a bus; such an action as handing a person a glass of water may be of the highest dramatic intensity. The power of attention that an audience has is very limited, and it must be held by a constant succession of incidents; something fresh must be doing all the time; the theme must be presented at once and its development must follow a definite line, without digression into irrelevant bypaths; the dialogue must be crisp and to the point, and it must be so put that the listener can catch its meaning without having to stop and think; the characters must be all of a piece, easily grasped by the eye and the understanding, and however complex, their complexity must be plausible. A play cannot afford loose ends; however slight, its foundation must be secure and its structure solid.

When the playwright, who has acquired the qualities which I have suggested are essential to writing a play which audiences will sit through with pleasure, starts writing novels, he is at an advantage. He has learnt to be brief; he has learnt the value of rapid incident; he has learnt not to linger on the way, but to stick to his point and get on with his story; he has learnt to make his characters display themselves by their words and actions, without the help of description; and so, when he comes to work on the larger canvas which the novel allows, he can not only profit by the advantages peculiar to the form of the novel, but his training as a playwright will enable him to make his novel lively, swift-moving and dramatic. These are excellent qualities, and some very good novelists, whatever their other merits, have not possessed them. I cannot look upon the years Fielding spent writing plays as wasted; I think, on the contrary, the experience he gained then was of value to him when he came to writing novels.

In 1734 Fielding married Charlotte Cradock. She was one of the two daughters of a widow who lived in Salisbury, and nothing is known of her but that she was beautiful and charming. Mrs. Cradock was a worldly, strong-minded woman, who apparently did not approve of Fielding's attentions to her daughter, and she can hardly be blamed for that, since his means of livelihood were uncertain and his connection with the theatre can hardly have inspired a prudent mother with confidence; anyhow, the lovers eloped, and though Mrs. Cradock pursued, “she did not catch up with them in time to stop the marriage.”Fielding has described Charlotte as Sophia in Tom Jones and again as Amelia in the novel of that name, so that the reader of those books can gain a very exact notion of what she looked like in the eyes of her lover and husband. Mrs. Cradock died a year later and left Charlotte fifteen hundred pounds. It came at a fortunate moment, since a play that Fielding had produced early in the year was a disastrous failure, and he was very short of cash. He had been in the habit of staying from time to time on the small estate which had been his mother's, and he went there now with his young wife. He spent the next nine months lavishly entertaining his friends and enjoying the various pursuits which the country offered, and on his return to London with what, it may be supposed, remained of Charlotte's legacy he took the Little Theatre in the Haymarket, and there presently produced the best (they say) and the most successful of his plays—Pasquin; a Dramatic Satire on the Times.

When the Licensing Act became law, and so put an end to his theatrical career, Fielding had a wife and two children and precious little money to support them on. He had to find a means of livelihood. He was thirty-one. He entered the Middle Temple, and though, according to Arthur Murphy, “it happened that the early taste he had taken of pleasure would occasionally return upon him; and conspire with his spirit and vivacity to carry him into the wild enjoyments of the town, ”he worked hard, and he was in due course called to the bar. He was ready to follow his profession with assiduity, but he seems to have had few briefs; and it may well be that the attorneys were suspicious of a man who was known only as a writer of light comedies and political satires. Moreover, within three years of being called, he began to suffer from frequent attacks of gout which prevented him from regularly attending the courts. In order to make money he was obliged to do hack work for the papers. He found time, meanwhile, to write Joseph Andrews, his first novel. Two years later his wife died. Her death left him distracted with grief. Lady Louisa Stuart wrote: “He loved her passionately, and she returned his affection; yet led no happy life, for they were almost always miserably poor, and seldom in a state of quiet and safety. All the world knows what was his imprudence; if ever he possessed a score of pounds nothing could keep him from lavishing it idly, or make him think of tomorrow. Sometimes they were living in decent lodgings with tolerable comfort; sometimes in a wretched garret without necessaries, not to speak of the sponging-houses and hiding places where he was occasionally to be found. His elastic gaiety of spirit carried him through it all; but, meanwhile, care and anxiety were preying upon her more delicate mind, and undermining her constitution. She gradually declined, caught a fever, and died in his arms.”This has an air of truth, and is in part confirmed by Fielding's Amelia. We know that novelists habitually make use of any little experience that they have had, and when Fielding created the character of Billy Booth, he not only drew a portrait of himself and of his wife as Amelia, but utilized various incidents in their married life. Four years after his wife's death he married her maid, Mary Daniel. She was at the time three months pregnant. The marriage shocked his friends, and his sister, who had lived with him since Charlotte's death, left the house. His cousin Lady Mary Wortley-Montagu was haughtily scornful because he could“feel rapture with his cook-maid.”Mary Daniel had few personal charms, but she was an excellent creature and he never spoke of her but with affection and respect. She was a very decent woman, who looked after him well, a good wife and a good mother. She bore him two boys and a girl.

When still a struggling dramatist, Fielding had made advances to Sir Robert Walpole, then all-powerful; but though he dedicated to him with effusive compliments his play, The Modern Husband, the ungrateful minister seems to have been disinclined to do anything for him. He therefore decided that he could do better with the party opposed to Walpole, and forthwith made overtures to Lord Chesterfield, one of its leaders. As Dr. Dudden puts it: “He could hardly have given a broader hint that he was ready to place his wit and humour at the disposal of the opposition, should they be willing to employ him.”Eventually they showed themselves willing, and Fielding was made editor of a paper called The Champion, founded to attack and ridicule Sir Robert and his ministry. Walpole fell in 1742 and, after a brief interlude, was succeeded by Henry Pelham. The party Fielding worked for was now in power, and for some years he edited and wrote for the papers which supported and defended the government. He naturally expected that his services should be rewarded. Among the friends he had made at Eton, and whose friendship he had retained, was George Lyttelton, a member of a distinguished political family (distinguished to the present day) and a generous patron of literature. Lyttelton was made a Lord of the Treasury in Henry Pelham's Government, and in 1784 by his in fluence Fielding was made Justice of the Peace for Westminster. Presently, so that he might discharge his duties more effectively, his jurisdiction was extended over Middlesex, and he established himself with his family in the official residence in Bow Street. He was well fitted for the post by his training as a lawyer, his knowledge of life and his natural gifts. Fielding says that before his accession the job was worth five hundred pounds a year of dirty money, but that he made no more than three hundred a year of clean. Through the Duke of Bedford he was granted a pension out of the public-service money. It is supposed that this was either one or two hundred pounds a year. In 1749 he published Tom Jones, which he must have been writing when he was still editing a paper on behalf of the Government. He received altogether seven hundred pounds for it, and since money at that period was worth five or six times at least what it is worth now, this sum was equivalent to something like four thousand pounds. That would be good payment for a novel to-day.

Fielding's health by now was poor. His attacks of gout were frequent, and he had often to go to Bath to recuperate, or to a cottage he had near London. But he did not cease to write. He wrote pamphlets concerning his office; one, an Enquiry into the Causes of the Late Menace of Robbers is said to have caused the famous Gin Act to be passed; and he wrote Amelia. His industry was indeed amazing. Amelia was published in 1751 and in the same year Fielding undertook to edit still another paper, The Covent Garden Journal. Hishealth grew worse. It was evident that he could no longer perform his duties at Bow Street, and in 1754, after breaking up“a gang of villains and cut-throats”who had become the terror of London, he resigned his office to his half-brother, John Fielding. It looked as though his only chance of life was to seek a milder climate than that of England, and so, in the June of that year, 1754, he left his native country in The Queen of Portugal, Richard Veal, master, for Lisbon. He arrived in August, and two months later died. He was forty-seven years old.

2

When I consider Fielding's life, which from inadequate material I have briefly sketched, I am seized with a singular emotion. He was a man. As you read his novels, and few novelists have put more of themselves into their books than he, you feel the same sort of affection as you feel for someone with whom you have been for years intimate. There is something contemporary about him. There is a sort of Englishman that till recently was far from uncommon. You might meet him in London, at Newmarket, in Leicestershire during the hunting season, at Cowes in August, at Cannes or Monte Carlo in midwinter. He is a gentleman, and he has good manners. He is good-looking, good-natured, friendly and easy to get on with. He is not particularly cultured, but he is tolerant of those who are. He is fond of the girls and is apt to find himself cited as a co-respondent. He is not one of the world's workers, but he sees no reason why he should be. Though he does nothing, he is far from idle. He has an adequate income and is free with his money. If war breaks out, he joins up and his gallantry is conspicuous. There is absolutely no harm in him and everyone likes him. The years pass and youth is over, he is not so well-off any more and life is not so easy as it was. He has had to give up hunting, but he still plays a good game of golf and you are always glad to see him in the card-room of your club. He marries an old flame, a widow with money, and, settling down to middle age, makes her a very good husband. The world to-day has no room for him and, in a few years, his type will be extinct. Such a man, I fancy, was Fielding. But he happened to have the great gift which made him the writer he was and, when he wanted to, he could work hard. He was fond of the bottle and he liked women. When people speak of virtue, it is generally sex they have in mind, but chastity is only a small part of virtue, and perhaps not the chief one. Fielding had strong passions, and he had no hesitation in yielding to them. He was capable of loving tenderly. Now love, not affection, which is a different thing, is rooted in sex, but there can be sexual desire without love. It is only hypocrisy or ignorance that denies it. Sexual desire is an animal instinct, and there is nothing more shameful in it than in thirst or hunger, and no more reason not to satisfy it. If Fielding enjoyed, somewhat promiscuously, the pleasures of sex, he was not worse than most men. Like most of us, he regretted his sins, if sins they are, but when opportunity occurred, committed them again. He was hot-tempered, but kind-hearted, generous and, in a corrupt age honest; an affectionate husband and father; courageous and truthful, and a good friend to his friends, who till his death remained faithful to him. Though tolerant to the faults of others, he hated brutality and double-dealing. He was not puffed up by success and, with the help of a brace of partridges and a bottle of claret, bore adversity with fortitude. He took life as it came, with high spirits and good humour, and enjoyed it to the full. In fact he was very like his own Tom Jones, and not unlike his own Billy Booth. He was a very proper man.

I should, however, tell the reader that the picture I have drawn of Henry Fielding does not at all accord with that drawn by the Master of Pembroke in the monumental work to which I have often referred, and to which I owe much useful information.“Until comparatively recently, ”he writes, “the conception of Fielding which prevailed in the popular imagination was that of a man of brilliant genius, endowed with what is called‘a good heart’ and many amiable qualities, but dissipated and irresponsible, guilty of regrettable follies, and not wholly unstained even by graver vices.”And he has done his best to persuade his readers that Fielding has been grossly maligned.

But this conception, which Dr. Dudden tries to refute, is that which prevailed in Fielding's lifetime. It was held by persons who knew him well. It is true that he was violently attacked in his own day by his political and literary enemies, and it is very likely that the charges that were brought against him were exaggerated; but if charges are to be damaging they must be plausible. For example: the late Sir Stafford Cripps had many bitter enemies who were only too anxious to throw mud at him; they said that he was a turncoat and a traitor to his class; but it would never have occurred to them to say that he was a lecher and a drunkard, since he was well-known to be a man of high moral character and fiercely abstemious. It would only have made them absurd. In the same way, the legends that gather round a famous man may not be true, but they will not be believed unless they are specious. Arthur Murphy relates that on one occasion Fielding, in order to pay the tax-collector, got his publisher to give him an advance and, while taking the money home, met a friend who was in even worse case than himself; so he gave him the money and, when the tax-collector called, sent him the message: “Friendship has called for the money and had it; let the collector call again.”Dr. Dudden shows that there can be no truth in the anecdote; but if it was invented, it is because it was credible. Fielding was accused of being a spendthrift; he probably was; it went with his insouciance, his high spirits, his friendliness, conviviality and indifference to money. He was thus often in debt and probably on occasion haunted by“duns and bumbailiffs”; there is little doubt that when he was at his wit's end for money he applied to his friends for help and they gave it. So did the noble-minded Edmund Burke. As a playwright, Fielding had lived for years in theatrical circles, and the theatre has in no country, either in the past or the present, been regarded as a favourable place to teach the young a rigid continence. Anne Oldfield, by whose influence Fielding had his first play produced, was buried in Westminster Abbey; but since she had been kept by two gentlemen, and had had two illegitimate children, permission to honour her with a monument was refused. It would be strange if she did not grant her favours to the handsome youth that Fielding then was; and, since he was pretty well penniless, it would not be surprising if she had helped him with some of the funds she received from her protectors. It may be that his poverty, but not his will, consented. If in his youth he was much given to wenching, he was no different from most young men in his day (and ours) who had his opportunities and advantages. And, doubtless, he spent“many anight drinking deep in taverns.”Whatever philosophers may aver, common sense is pretty well agreed that there is a different morality for youth and age, and a different one according to the station in life. It would be reprehensible for a doctor of divinity to engage in promiscuous fornication, but natural for a young man to do so; and it would be unpardonable for the master of a college to get drunk, but to be expected on occasion, and not really disapproved, in an undergraduate.

Fielding's enemies accuse him of being a political hireling. He was. He was quite ready to put his great gifts at the service of Sir Robert Walpole and, when he found they were not wanted, he was equally ready to put them at the service of his enemies. That demanded no particular sacrifice of principle, since at that time the only real difference between the Government and the Opposition was that the Government enjoyed the emoluments of office and the Opposition did not. Corruption was universal, and great lords were as willing to change sides when it was to their advantage as was Fielding when it was a question of bread and butter. It should be said to his credit that when Walpole discovered he was dangerous, and offered to give him his own terms if he would desert the Opposition, he refused. It was also intelligent of him, for not so long afterwards Walpole fell! Fielding had a number of friends in the higher ranks of society, and friends eminent in the arts, but from his writings it seems certain that he enjoyed the company of the low and disreputable. He was severely censured for this, but it seems to me that he could not have described with such wonderful vivacity scenes of what is called low-life unless he had himself taken part in them, and enjoyed it. Common opinion in his own day decided that Fielding was licentious and profligate. The evidence that he was is too great to be ignored. If he had been the respectable, chaste, abstemious creature that the Master of Pembroke would have us believe, it is surely very unlikely that he would have written Tom Jones. I think what has misled Dr. Dudden, in his perhaps meritorious attempt to whitewash Fielding, is that it has not occurred to him that contradictory, and even mutually exclusive, qualities may exist in the same man and somehow or other form a tolerably plausible harmony. That is natural enough in one who has led a sheltered, academic life. Because Fielding was generous, good-hearted, upright, kindly, affectionate and honest, it has seemed to the Master impossible that he should have been at the same time a spendthrift who would cadge a dinner and a guinea from his rich friends, who would haunt taverns and drink to the ruin of his health, and who would engage in sexual congress whenever he had the chance. Dr. Dudden states that, as long as his first wife lived, Fielding was absolutely faithful to her. How does he know? Certainly Fielding loved her, he loved her passionately, but he would not have been the first loving husband who, when the circumstances were propitious, had a flutter on the side; and it is very probable that after such an occurrence, like his own Captain Booth in similar circumstances, he bitterly regretted it; but that did not prevent him from transgressing again when the opportunity offered.

In one of her letters Lady Mary Wortley-Montagu wrote: “I am sorry for H. Fielding's death, not only as I shall read no more of his writings, but I believe he lost more than others, as no man enjoyed life more than he did, though few had less reason to do so, the highest of his preferment being raking in the lowest sinks of vice and misery. I should think it a nobler and less nauseous employment to be one of the staff officers that conduct the nocturnal weddings. His happy constitution (even when he had, with great pains, half demolished it) made him forget everything when he was before a venison pasty, or over a flask of champagne; and I am persuaded he has known more happy moments than any prince upon earth.”

3

There are people who cannot read Tom Jones. I am not thinking of those who never read anything but the newspapers and the illustrated weeklies, or of those who never read anything but detective stories; I am thinking of those who would not demur if you classed them as members of the intelligentsia, of those who read and re-read Pride and Prejudice with delight, Middlemarch with self-complacency, and The Golden Bowl with reverence. The chances are that it has never even occurred to them to read Tom Jones; but, sometimes, they have tried and not been able to get on with it. It bores them. Now it is no good saying that they ought to like it. There is no ought about the matter. You read a novel for its entertainment, and, I repeat, if it does not give you that, it has nothing to give you at all. No one has the right to blame you because you don’t find it interesting, any more than anyone has the right to blame you because you don’t like oysters. I cannot but ask myself, however, what it is that puts readers off a book which Gibbon described as an exquisite picture of human manners, which Walter Scott praised as truth and human nature itself, which Dickens admired and profited by, and of which Thackeray wrote: “The novel of Tom Jones is indeed exquisite; as a work of construction quite a wonder; the by-play of wisdom, the power of observation, the multiplied felicitous turns and thoughts, the varied character of the great comic epic, keep the reader in a perpetual admiration and curiosity.”Is it that they cannot interest themselves in the way of life, the manners and customs, of persons who lived two hundred years ago? Is it the style? It is easy and natural. It has been said, I forget by whom, Fielding's friend, Lord Chesterfield, perhaps, that a good style should resemble the conversation of cultivated man. That is precisely what Fielding's style does. He is talking to the reader and telling him the story of Tom Jones as he might tell it over the dinner-table with a bottle of wine to a number of friends. He does not mince his words. The beautiful and virtuous Sophia was apparently quite used to hearing such words as“whore, ”“bastard, ”“strumpet, ”and that which, for a reason hard to guess, Fielding writes“b…ch.”In fact, there were moments when her father, Squire Western, applied them very freely to her.

The conversational method of writing a novel, the method in which the author takes you into his confidence, telling you what he feels about the creatures of his invention and the situations in which he has placed them has its dangers. The author is always at your elbow, and so hinders your immediate communication with the persons of his story. He is apt to irritate you sometimes by moralizing and once he starts to digress, is apt to be tedious. You do not want to hear what he has to say on some moral or social point; you want him to get on with his story. Fielding's digressions are nearly always sensible or amusing; they are brief, and he has the grace to apologize for them. His good nature shines through them. When Thackeray unwisely imitated him in this, he was priggish, sanctimonious and, you cannot but suspect, insincere.

Fielding prefaced each of the books into which Tom Jones is divided with an essay. Some critics have greatly admired them, and have looked upon them as adding to the excellence of the novel. I can only suppose that is because they were not interested in it as a novel. An essayist takes a subject and discusses it. If his subject is new to you, he may tell you something that you didn’t know before, but new subjects are hard to find and, in general, he expects to interest you by his own attitude and the characteristic way in which he regards things. That is to say, he expects to interest you in himself. But that is not what you want to do when you read a novel. You don’t care about the author; he is there to tell you a story and introduce you to a group of characters. The reader of a novel should want to know what happens next to the persons in whom the author has interested him and, if he doesn’t, there is no reason for him to read the novel at all. For the novel, I can never repeat too often, is not to be looked upon as a medium of instruction or edification, but as a source of intelligent diversion. It appears that Fielding wrote the essays with which he introduced the successive books of Tom Jones after he had finished the novel. They have hardly anything to do with the books they introduce; they gave him, he admits, a lot of trouble, and one wonders why he wrote them at all. He cannot have been unaware that many readers would look upon his novel as low, none too moral, and possibly even bawdy; and it may be that by them he thought to give it a certain elevation. These essays are sensible, and sometimes uncommonly shrewd; and when you know the novel well, you can read them with a certain amount of pleasure; but anyone who is reading Tom Jones for the first time is well advised to skip them. The plot of Tom Jones has been much admired. I learn from Dr. Dudden that Coleridge exclaimed: “What a master of composition Fielding was!”Scott and Thackeray were equally enthusiastic. Dr. Dudden quotes the latter as follows: “Moral or immoral, let any man examine this romance as a work of art merely, and it must strike him as the most astonishing production of human ingenuity. There is not an incident ever so trifling but advances the story, grows out of former incidents, and is connected with the whole. Such a literary providence, if we may use such a word, is not to be seen in any other work of fiction. You might cut out half of Don Quixote, or add, transpose, or alter any given romance of Walter Scott, and neither would suffer. Roderick Random and heroes of that sort run through a series of adventures, at the end of which the fiddles are brought, and there is a marriage. But the history of Tom Jones connected the very first page with the very last, and it is marvelous to think how the author could have built and carried all the structure in his brain, as he must have done, before he put it on paper.”

There is some exaggeration here. Tom Jones is fashioned on the model of the Spanish picaresque novels and of Gil Blas, and the simple structure depends on the nature of the genre: the hero for one reason or another leaves his home, has a variety of adventures on his travels, mixes with all sorts and conditions of men, has his ups and downs of fortune, and in the end achieves prosperity and marries a charming wife. Fielding, following his models, interrupted his narrative with stories that had nothing to do with it. This was an unhappy device that authors adopted not only, I think, for the reason I give in my first chapter, because they had to furnish a certain amount of matter to the bookseller and a story or two served to fill up; but partly, also, because they feared that a long string of adventures would prove tedious, and felt it would give the reader a fillip if they provided him here and there with a tale; and partly because if they were minded to write a short story, there was no other way to put it before the public. The critics chid, but the practice died hard, and, as we know, Dickens resorted to it in The Pickwick Papers. The reader of Tom Jones can without loss skip the story of The Man of the Hill and Mrs. Fitzherbert's narrative. Nor is Thackeray quite accurate in saying that there is not an incident that does not advance the story and grow out of former incidents. Tom Jones's encounter with the gipsies leads to nothing; and the introduction of Mrs. Hunt, and her proposal of marriage to Tom, is very unnecessary. The incident of the hundred-pound bill has no use and is, besides, grossly, fantastically improbable. Thackeray marvelled that Fielding could have carried all the structure in his brain before he began to put it on paper. I don’t believe that he did anything of the sort, any more than Thackeray did before he began to write Vanity Fair. I think it much more probable that, with the main lines of his novel in his mind, Fielding invented the incidents as he went along. For the most part they are happily devised. Fielding was as little concerned with probability as the picaresque novelists who wrote before him, and the most unlikely events occur, the most outrageous coincidences bring people together; yet he bustles you along with such gusto that you have hardly time, and in any case little inclination, to protest. The characters are painted in primary colours with a slap-dash bravura, and if they somewhat lack subtlety, they make up for it by animation. They are sharply individualized, and if they are drawn with some exaggeration, that was the fashion of the day, and perhaps their exaggeration is no greater than comedy allows. I am afraid Mr. Allworthy is a little too good to be true, but here Fielding failed, as every novelist since has failed who has attempted to depict a perfectly virtuous man. Experience seems to show that it is impossible not to make him a trifle stupid. One is impatient with a character who is so good that he lets himself be imposed upon by all and sundry. Mr. Allworthy is said to have been a portrait of Ralph Allen of Prior Park. If this is so, and the portrait is accurate, it only shows that a character taken straight from life is never quite convincing in a piece offiction.

Blifil, on the other hand, has been thought too bad to be true. Fielding hated deceit and hypocrisy, and his detestation of Blifil was such that it may be he laid on his colours with too heavy a hand; but Blifil, a mean, sneaking, self-seeking, cold-blooded fish, is not an uncommon type. The fear of being found out is the only thing that keeps him from being an utter scoundrel. But I think we should have believed more in Blifil if he had not been so transparent. He is repellent. He is not alive, as Uriah Heep is alive, and I have asked myself whether Fielding did not deliberately underwrite him from an instinctive feeling that if he gave him a more active and prominent role, he would make him so powerful and sinister a figure as to overshadow his hero.

On its appearance, Tom Jones was an immediate success with the public, but the critics were on the whole severe. Some of the objections were rather touchingly absurd: Lady Luxborough, for instance, complained that the characters were too like the persons“one meets with in the world.”It was on its supposed immorality, however, that the novel was generally condemned. Hannah More in her memoirs relates that she never saw Dr. Johnson angry with her but once, and that was when she alluded to some witty passage in Tom Jones.“I am shocked to hear you quote from so vicious a book, ”he said.“I am sorry to hear you have read it: a confession which no modest lady should ever make. I scarcely know a more corrupt work.”Now, I should say that a modest lady would do very well to read the book before marriage. It will tell her pretty well all she needs to know about the facts of life, and a lot about men which cannot fail to be useful to her before entering upon that difficult state. But no one has ever looked upon Dr. Johnson as devoid of prejudice. He would allow no literary merit to Fielding, and once described him as a blockhead. When Boswell demurred, he said: “What I mean by his being a blockhead is that he was a barren rascal.”“Will you not allow, Sir, that he draws very natural pictures of human life?”answered Boswell.“Why, Sir, it is of very low life. Richardson used to say that had he not known who Fielding was he should have believed that he was an ostler.”We are used to low life in fiction now, and there is nothing in Tom Jones that the novelists of our own day have not made us familiar with. Dr. Johnson might have remembered that in Sophia Western Fielding drew a charming and tender portrait of as delightful a young woman as ever enchanted a reader of fiction. She is simple but not silly, virtuous but no prude; she has character, determination and courage; she has a loving heart and she is beautiful. Lady Mary Wortley-Montagu, who very properly thought that Tom Jones was Fielding's masterpiece, regretted that he did not perceive that he had made his hero a scoundrel. I suppose that she referred to the incident that has been looked upon as the most reprehensible in the career of Mr. Jones. Lady Bellaston took a fancy to him, and found him not unprepared to gratify her desires, for he regarded it as a part of good breeding to behave with“gallantry”with a woman who showed an inclination for sexual commerce; he hadn’t a penny in his pocket, not even a shilling in his pocket to pay for a chair to convey him to her abode, and Lady Bellaston was rich. With a generosity unusual with women, who are apt to be lavish with the money of others, but careful with their own, she handsomely relieved his necessities. Well, it is doubtless not a pretty thing for a man to accept money from a woman; it is also an unprofitable one, because rich ladies in these circumstances demand much more than their money's worth; but morally it is no more shocking than for a woman to accept money from a man, and it is only foolishness on the part of common opinion to regard it as such. Our own day has found it necessary to invent a term, gigolo, to describe the male who turns his personal attractiveness into a source of profit; so Tom's lack of delicacy, however reprehensible, can hardly be regarded as unique. I have no doubt that the gigolo flourished as hardily under the reign of George the Second as he did under that of George the Fifth. It was characteristic, and to Tom Jones's credit, that on the very day on which Lady Bellaston had given him fifty pounds for passing the night with her, he was so moved by a hard-luck story, which his landlady told him about some relations of hers, that he handed her his purse and told her to take what she thought needful to relieve their distress. Tom Jones was honestly, sincerely and deeply in love with the charming Sophia, and yet felt no qualms about indulging in the pleasures of the flesh with any woman who was attractive and facile. He loved Sophia none the less for these episodes. Fielding was much too sensible to make his hero more continent than the normal man. He knew we should all be more virtuous if we were as prudent at night as we are in the morning. Nor was Sophia unreasonably vexed when she heard of these adventures. That in this particular she showed common sense unusual to her sex is surely one of the most engaging of her traits. It was well said by Austin Dobson, though with no elegance of style, that Fielding“made no pretence to produce models of perfection, but pictures of ordinary humanity, rather perhaps in the rough than in the polished, the natural than the artificial, his desire is to do this with absolute truthfulness, neither extenuating nor disguising defects and shortcomings.”That is what the realist strives to do and, throughout history, he has always been more or less violently attacked for it. For this the two main reasons, so far as I know, are as follows: there is a vast number of people, especially among the elderly, the well-to-do, the privileged, who take up the attitude: “Of course we know that there is a lot of crime and immorality in the world, poverty and unhappiness, but we don’t want to read about it. Why should we make ourselves uncomfortable? It is not as though we could do anything about it. After all, there always have been rich and poor in the world.”Another sort of people have other reasons for condemning the realist. They admit that there are vice and wickedness in the world, cruelty and oppression; but, they ask, is this proper matter for fiction? Is it well that the young should read about things which their elders know, but deplore, and may they not be corrupted by reading stories which are suggestive if not actually obscene? Surely fiction is better employed in showing how much beauty, kindness, self-sacrifice, generosity and heroism there is in the world. The answer the realist makes is that he is interested in telling the truth, as he sees it, about the world he has come in contact with. He does not believe in the unalloyed goodness of human beings; he thinks them a mixture of good and bad; and he is tolerant to idiosyncrasies of human nature which conventional morality reprobates, but which he accepts as human, natural, and therefore to be palliated. He hopes that he depicts the good in his characters as faithfully as the bad in them, and it is not his fault if his readers are more interested in their vices than in their virtues. That is a curious trait in the human animal for which he cannot be held responsible. If, however, he is honest with himself, he will admit that vice can be painted in colours that glow, whereas virtue seems to bear a hue that is somewhat dun. If you asked him how he could defend himself against the charge of corrupting the young, he would answer that it is very well for the young to learn what sort of a world it is that they will have to cope with. The result may be disastrous if they expect too much. If the realist can teach them to expect little from others; to realize from the beginning that each one's main interest is in himself; if he can teach them that, in some way or other, they will have to pay for everything they get, be it place, fortune, honour, love, reputation; and that a great part of wisdom is not to pay for anything more than it is worth, he will have done more than all the pedagogues and preachers to enable them to make the best of this difficult business of living. He will add, however, that he is not a pedagogue or a preacher, but, he hopes, an artist.

Jane Austen and Pride and Prejudice

1

The events of Jane Austen's life can be told very briefly. The Austens were an old family whose fortunes, like those of many of the greatest families in England, had been founded on the wool trade, which was at one time the country's staple industry; and having made money, again like others of greater importance, they had bought land and so, in course of time, joined the ranks of the landed gentry. But the branch of the family to which Jane Austen belonged seems to have inherited very little of such wealth as its other members possessed. It had come down in the world. Jane's father, George Austen, was the son of William Austen, a surgeon of Tonbridge, a profession which at the beginning of the eighteenth century was regarded no more highly than the attorney's; and, as we know from Persuasion, even in Jane Austen's day, an attorney was a person of no social consequence. It shocks Lady Russell, “the widow only of a knight, ”that Miss Elliot, the daughter of a baronet, should have social relations with Mrs. Clay, daughter of an attorney, “who ought to have been nothing to her but the object of distant civility.”William Austen, the surgeon, died early, and his brother, Francis Austen, sent the orphaned boy to Tonbridge School and afterwards to St. John's College, Oxford. These facts I learn from Dr. Chapman's Clark Lectures, which he has published under the title Jane Austen: Facts and Problems. For all that follows I am indebted to this admirable book.

George Austen became a fellow of his college and, on taking orders, was presented with the living of Steventon, in Hampshire, by a kinsman, Thomas Knight of Godmersham. Two years later, George Austen's uncle bought him the near-by living of Deane. Since we are told nothing of this generous man, we may surmise that, like Mr. Gardner in Pride and Prejudice, he was in trade.

The Rev. George Austen married Cassandra Leigh, the daughter of Thomas Leigh, a Fellow of All Souls and incumbent of the living of Harpsden near Henley. She was what was known in my youth as well-connected; that is to say, like the Hares of Hurstmonceaux, she was distantly related to members of the landed gentry and the aristocracy. It was a step up for the surgeon's son. Eight children were born of the marriage, two daughters, Cassandra and Jane, and six sons. To add to his income, the rector of Steventon took pupils, and his sons were educated at home. Two went to St. John's College, Oxford, because through their mother they were Founder's kin; of one, George by name, nothing is known, and Dr. Chapman suggests that he was deaf and dumb; two others entered the Navy and had careers of distinction: the lucky one was Edward, who was adopted by Thomas Knight and inherited his estates in Kent and Hampshire.

Jane, Mrs. Austen's younger daughter, was born in 1775. When she was twenty-six, her father resigned his living in favour of his eldest son, who had taken orders, and moved to Bath. He died in 1805, and some months later his widow and daughters settled in Southampton. It was while there that, after paying a call with her mother, Jane wrote to her sister Cassandra: “We found only Mrs. Lance at home, and whether she boasts any offspring besides a grand pianoforte did not appear…They live in a handsome style and are rich, and she seems to like to be rich; we gave her to understand that we were far from being so; she will soon feel that we are not worth her acquaintance.”Mrs. Austen was indeed left badly off, but her sons added enough to her income to enable her to live in tolerable comfort. Edward, after making the Grand Tour, married Elizabeth, daughter of Sir Brook Bridges, Bart. of Goodnestone; and three years after Thomas Knight's death in 1794, his widow made over to him Godmersham and Chawton and retired to Canterbury with an annuity. A good many years later, Edward offered his mother a house on either of his estates; she chose Chawton; and there, with occasional visits, sometimes lasting for many weeks, to friends and relations, Jane lived till illness obliged her to go to Winchester in order to put herself in the hands of better doctors than could be found in the country. At Winchester in 1817 she died. She was buried in the Cathedral.

2

Jane Austen is said to have been in person very attractive: “Her figure was rather tall and slender, her step light and firm, and her whole appearance expressive of health and animation. In complexion she was a clear brunette with a rich colour; she had full round cheeks with mouth and nose small and well-formed, bright hazel eyes, and brown hair forming natural curls close round her face.”The only portrait of her I have seen shows a fat-faced young woman with undistinguished features, large round eyes and an obtrusive bust; but it may be that the artist did her less than justice.

Jane was greatly attached to her sister. As girls and women they were very much together and, indeed, shared the same bedroom till Jane's death. When Cassandra was sent to school, Jane went with her because, though too young to profit by such instruction as the seminary for young ladies provided, she would have been wretched without her.“If Cassandra were going to have her head cut off, ”said her mother, “Jane would insist on sharing her fate.”“Cassandra was handsomer than Jane, of a colder and calmer disposition, less demonstrative and of a less sunny nature; but she had the merit of always having her temper under command, but Jane had the happiness of a temper that never required to be commanded.”Most of Jane's letters that have remained were written to Cassandra when one or other of the sisters was staying away. Many of her warmest admirers have found them paltry, and have thought they showed that she was cold and unfeeling and that her interests were trivial. I am surprised. They are very natural. Jane Austen never imagined that anyone but Cassandra would read them, and she told her just the sort of things that she knew would interest her. She told her what people were wearing, and how much she had paid for the flowered muslin she had bought, what acquaintances she had made, what old friends she had met and what gossip she had heard.

Of late years, several collections of letters by eminent authors have been published, and for my part, when I read them, I am now and then disposed to suspect that the writers had at the back of their minds the notion that one day they might find their way into print. And when I learn that they had kept copies of their letters, the suspicion is changed into certainty. When André Gide wished to publish his correspondence with Claudel, and Claudel, who perhaps didn’t wish it to be published, told him that Gide's letters had been destroyed, Gide answered that it was no matter as he had kept copies of them. André Gide has told us himself that when he discovered that his wife had burned his love letters to her, he cried for a week, since he had looked upon them as the summit of his literary achievement and his chief claim on the attention of posterity. Whenever Dickens went on a journey, he wrote long letters to his friends in which he described eloquently the sights he had seen; and which, as John Forster, his first biographer, justly observes, might well have been printed without the alteration of a single word. People were more patient in those days; still, one would have thought it a disappointment to receive a letter from your friend, who gave you word pictures of mountains and monuments when you would have been glad to know whether he had run across anyone of interest, what parties he had been to and whether he had been able to get you the books, neck-cloths or handkerchiefs you had asked him to bring home.

In one of her letters to Cassandra, Jane said: “I have now attained the true art of letter-writing, which we are always told is to express on paper exactly what one would say to the same person by word of mouth. I have been talking to you almost as fast as I could the whole of this letter.”Of course she was quite right; that is the art of letter-writing. She attained it with consummate ease, and since she says that her conversation was exactly like her letters, and her letters are full of witty, ironical and malicious remarks, we may be pretty sure that her conversation was delightful. She hardly ever wrote a letter that had not a smile or a laugh in it, and for the delectation of the reader I will give some examples of her manner:

Single women have a dreadful propensity for being poor, which is one very strong argument in favour of matrimony.

Only think of Mrs. Holder being dead! Poor woman, she has done the only thing in the world she could possibly do to make one cease to abuse her.

Mrs. Hale, of Sherborne, was brought to bed yesterday of a dead child, some weeks before she expected, owing to a fright. I suppose she happened unawares to look at her husband.

The death of Mrs. W. K. we had seen. I had no idea that anybody liked her, and therefore felt nothing for any survivor, but I am now feeling away on her husband's account and think he had better marry Miss Sharpe.

I respect Mrs. Chamberlayne for doing her hair well, but cannot feel a more tender sentiment. Miss Langley is like any other short girl with a broad nose and wide mouth, fashionable dress and exposed bosom. Admiral Stanhope is a gentlemanlike man, but then his legs are too short and his tail too long.

Eliza has seen Lord Craven at Barton, and probably by this time at Kentbury, where he was expected for one day this week. She found his manners very pleasing indeed. The little flaw of having a mistress now living with him at Ashdown Park seems to be the only unpleasing circumstance about him.

Mr. W. is about five or six and twenty, not ill-looking and not agreeable. He is certainly no addition. A sort of cool, gentlemanlike manner, but very silent. They say his name is Henry, a proof how unequally the gifts of fortune are bestowed. I have seen many a John and Thomas much more agreeable.

Mrs. Richard Harvey is going to be married, but as it is a great secret, and only known to half the neighbourhood, you must not mention it.

Dr. Hale is in such very deep mourning that either his mother, his wife or himself must be dead.

Miss Austen was fond of dancing and she gave Cassandra an account of the balls she went to:

There were only twelve dances, of which I danced nine, and was merely prevented from dancing the rest by want of a partner.

There was one gentleman, an officer of the Cheshire, a very good-looking young man, who, I was told, wanted very much to be introduced to me; but as he did not want it quite enough to take much trouble in effecting it, we never could bring it about.

There were few beauties, and such as there were, were not very handsome. Miss Iremonger did not look well and Mrs. Blunt was the only one much admired. She appeared exactly as she did in September, with the same broad face, diamond bandeau, white shoes, pink husband and fat neck.

Charles Powlett gave a dance on Thursday to the great disturbance of all his neighbours, of course, who you know take a most lively interest in the state of his finances, and live in hopes of his being soon ruined. His wife is discovered to be everything that the neighbourhood would wish her to be, silly and cross as well as extravagant.

A relation of the Austens seems to have given occasion to gossip owing to the behaviour of a certain Dr. Mant, behaviour such that his wife retired to her mother's, whereupon Jane wrote: “But as Dr. M. is a clergyman their attachment, however immoral, has a decorous air.”

Miss Austen had a sharp tongue and a prodigious sense of humour. She liked to laugh, and she liked to make others laugh. It is asking too much of the humorist to expect him—or her—to keep a good thing to himself when he thinks of it. And, heaven knows, it is hard to be funny without being sometimes a little malicious. There is not much kick in the milk of human kindness. Jane had a keen appreciation of the absurdity of others, their pretensions, their affectations and their insincerities; and it is to her credit that they amused rather than annoyed her. She was too amiable to say things to people that would pain them, but she certainly saw no harm in amusing herself at their expense with Cassandra. I see no ill nature even in the most biting of her remarks; her humour was based, as humour should be, on observation and mother-wit. But when there was occasion for it, Miss Austen could be serious. Though Edward Austen inherited from Thomas Knight estates in Kent and in Hampshire, he lived for the most part at Godmersham Park, near Canterbury, and here Cassandra and Jane came in turn to stay, sometimes for as long as three months. His eldest daughter, Fanny, was Jane's favourite niece. She eventually married Sir Edward Knatchbull, whose son was raised to the peerage and assumed the title of Lord Brabourne. It was he who first published Jane Austen's letters. There are two which she wrote to Fanny, when that young person was considering how to cope with the attentions of a young man who wanted to marry her. They are admirable both for their cool sense and their tenderness.

It was a shock to Jane Austen's many admirers when, a few years ago, Mr. Peter Quennell published in The Cornhill a letter which Fanny, by this time Lady Knatchbull, many years later wrote to her younger sister, Mrs. Rice, in which she spoke of her famous aunt. It is so surprising, but so characteristic of the period that, having received permission from the late Lord Brabourne to do so, I here reprint it. The italics mark the words the writer underlined. Since Edward Austen in 1812 changed his name to Knight, it may be worth while to point out that the Mrs. Knight Lady Knatchbull refers to is the widow of Thomas Knight. From the way the letter begins, it is evident that Mrs. Rice was uneasy about some things she had heard that reflected on her Aunt Jane's gentility, and had written to enquire whether they were by any frightful chance true. Lady Knatchbull replied as follows:

Yes my love it is very true that Aunt Jane from various circumstances was not so refined as she ought to have been from her talent, and if she had lived fifty years later she would have been in many respects more suitable to our more refined tastes. They were not rich＆the people around with whom they chiefly mixed, were not at all high bred, or in short anything more than mediocre＆they of course tho’ superior in mental powers＆cultivation were on the same level as far as refinement goes—but I think in later life their intercourse with Mrs. Knight (who was very fond＆kind to them) improved them both＆Aunt Jane was too clever not to put aside all possible signs of“commonness”(if such an expression is allowable)＆teach herself to be more refined at least in intercourse with people in general. Both the aunts (Cassandra and Jane) were brought up in the most complete ignorance of the World＆its ways (I mean as to fashion etc.)＆if it had not been for Papa's marriage which brought them into Kent, ＆the kindness of Mrs. Knight, who used often to have one or other of the sisters staying with her, they would have been, tho’ not less clever and agreeable in themselves, very much below par as to good society and its ways. If you hate all this I beg yr’ pardon, but I felt it at my pen's end＆it chose to come along＆speak the truth. It is now nearly dressing time…

…I am ever beloved Sister yours most affec.

F.C.K.

This letter has excited the indignation of Jane's devotees, and they have claimed that Lady Knatchbull was senile when she wrote it. There is nothing in the letter to suggest that; nor, surely, would Mrs. Rice have written to make the enquiry had she thought her sister in no condition to answer it. It has seemed to the devotees dreadfully ungrateful that Fanny, whom Jane doted on, should have expressed herself in such terms. There they show themselves ingenuous. It is regrettable, but it is a fact, that children do not look upon their parents, or their relations belonging to another generation, with the same degree of affection as their parents, or relations, look upon them. Parents and relations are very unwise to expect it. Jane, as we know, never married, and she gave Fanny something of the mother-love she would, had she married, have bestowed on her own children. She was fond of children, and was a favourite with them; they liked her playful ways and the long circumstantial stories she told them. She and Fanny became fast friends. Fanny could talk to her in a way that perhaps she couldn’t with her father, occupied with the pursuits of the country squire that he had become, or with her mother, who was continuously giving birth to offspring. But children have sharp eyes, and are apt to judge cruelly. When Edward Austen inherited Godmersham and Chawton, he rose in the world, and his marriage allied him with the best families of the County. We know nothing of what Jane and Cassandra thought of his wife. Dr. Chapman tolerantly suggests that it was her loss which made Edward feel“that he ought to do more for his mother and sisters, and induced him to offer them a cottage on one or other of his estates.”He had been in possession of them for twelve years. It seems to me more likely that his wife thought they did enough for the members of his family if they were asked at intervals to pay them visits, and did not welcome the notion of having them permanently settled on her doorstep; and it was her death that freed him to do what he liked with his own property. If this were so, it cannot have escaped Jane's sharp eyes, and may well have suggested those passages in Sense and Sensibility in which she describes John Dashwood's treatment of his stepmother and her daughters. Jane and Cassandra were poor relations. If they were asked to spend long periods with their rich brother and his wife, with Mrs. Knight at Canterbury, with Lady Bridges, Elizabeth Knight's mother, at Goodnestone, it was a kindness of which their hosts were not improbably conscious. Few of us are so well constituted that we can do others a good turn without taking some credit to ourselves. When Jane went to stay with the elder Mrs. Knight, she always gave her a“tip”at the end of her visit, which Jane accepted with alacrity, and in one of her letters to Cassandra she tells her that her brother Edward had given Fanny and her a present of five pounds. Quite a nice little present to give to a young daughter, kindly to give to a governess, but only patronizing to give to a sister.

I am sure that Mrs. Knight, Lady Bridges, Edward and his wife, were very kind to Jane, and liked her, as how could they fail to, but it is not unreasonable to suppose that they thought the two sisters not quite up to the mark. They were provincial. There was still in the eighteenth century a good deal of difference between the people who lived for at least part of the year in London and those who never left the country. The difference provided the writers of comedy with their most fruitful material. Bingley's sisters in Pride and Prejudice despised the Misses Bennet for their want of style, and Elizabeth Bennet on the other hand, had little patience for what she considered their affectations. The Misses Bennet were a step higher in the social scale than the Misses Austen, because Mr. Bennet was a landed proprietor, though not a rich one, whereas the Rev. George Austen was a poor country parson.

It would not be strange if, with her upbringing, Jane was a trifle wanting in the elegances valued by the ladies of Kent; and if that were so, and it had escaped the sharp eyes of Fanny, we may be sure that her mother would have remarked on it. Jane was frank and outspoken, and I daresay often indulged in a blunt humour which those humourless females failed to appreciate. We can imagine their embarrassment if she said to them what she wrote to Cassandra, that she had a good eye for an adulteress. She was born in 1775. That is only twenty-five years after the publication of Tom Jones, and there is no reason to suppose that in the interval the manners of the country had greatly changed. Jane's may well have been such as Lady Knatchbull, fifty years later, considered, “below par as to good society and its ways.”When Jane went to stay with Mrs. Knight at Canterbury, it is probable, from what Lady Knatchbull says, that the elder lady gave her hints on behaviour which made her more“refined.”It may be on that account that in her novels she lays so much stress on good breeding. A novelist to-day, writing of the same class as she did, would take that for granted. For my part, I can see nothing to blame in Lady Knatchbull's letter. Her pen's end“chose to come along and speak the truth.”And what of it? It does not offend me in the least to guess that Jane spoke with a Hampshire accent, that her manners lacked a certain polish, and that her home-made dresses were in bad taste. We know, indeed, from Caroline Austen's Memoir, that the family were agreed that the sisters, notwithstanding their interest in clothes, did not dress well; but whether dowdily or unsuitably is not stated. The members of the family who have written about Jane Austen have been at pains to give it greater social consequence than in point of fact belonged to it. This was unnecessary. The Austens were nice, honest, worthy people, belonging to the fringe of the upper-middle class, and they were perhaps a little more conscious of their position than if it had been more assured. The sisters were at ease, as Lady Knatchbull observed, with the people with whom they chiefly consorted, and they, according to her, were not at all high-bred. When they were confronted with persons of somewhat higher station, like Bingley's sisters, women of fashion, they were apt to protect themselves by being critical. Of the Rev. George Austen we know nothing. His wife seems to have been a good, rather silly woman, who was constantly troubled with ailments which her daughters appear to have treated with kindness not unmingled with irony. She lived to hard upon ninety. The boys, till they went out into the world, presumably indulged in such sport as the country provided and, when they could borrow a horse, rode to hounds.

Austen-Leigh was Jane's first biographer. There is a passage in his book from which, by the exercise of a little imagination, we can get some idea of the sort of life she led during the long quiet years she spent in Hampshire.“It may be asserted as a general truth, ”he writes, “that less was left to the charge and discretion of servants, and more was done, or superintended by the masters and mistresses. With regard to the mistresses, it is, I believe, generally understood that…they took a personal part in the higher branches of cookery, as well as in the concoction of home-made wines, and distilling of herbs for domestic medicine…Ladies did not disdain to spin thread out of which the household linen was woven. Some ladies liked to wash with their own hands their choice china after breakfast and tea.”From the letters one gathers that sometimes the Austens were without a servant at all, and at others had to make do with a slip of a girl who knew nothing. Cassandra did the cooking, not because ladies“left less to the charge and discretion of servants, ”but because there was no servant to do it. The Austens were neither poor nor rich. Mrs. Austen and her daughters made most of their own clothes, and the girls made their brothers’ shirts. They made their mead at home, and Mrs. Austen cured the household hams. Pleasures were simple and the great excitement was a ball given by one of the more affluent neighbours. There were in England, in that long-past time, hundreds of families who lived such quiet, humdrum and decent lives: is it not strange that one of them, without rhyme or reason, should have produced a greatly gifted novelist?

3

Jane was very human. In her youth she loved dancing and flirting and theatricals. She liked young men to be good-looking. She took a healthy interest in gowns, bonnets and scarves. She was a fine needlewoman, “both plain and ornamental, ”and this must have stood her in good stead when she was making over an old gown and using part of a discarded skirt to fashion a new cap. Her brother Henry in his Memoir says: “Jane Austen was successful in everything that she attempted with her fingers. None of us could throw spilikins in so perfect a circle, or take them off with so steady a hand. Her performances with cup and ball were marvellous. The one used at Chawton was an easy one, and she has been known to catch it on the point a hundred times in succession, till her hand was weary. She sometimes found a resource in that simple game, when unable, from weakness in her eyes, to read or write long together.”

It is a charming picture.

No one could describe Jane Austen as a blue-stocking, a type with which she had no sympathy, but it is plain that she was far from being an uncultivated woman. She was, in fact, as well instructed as any woman of her time and station. Dr. Chapman, the great authority on her novels, has made a list of the books she is known to have read. It is an imposing one. Of course she read novels, the novels of Fanny Burney, Miss Edgeworth and those of Mrs. Radcliffe (of The Mysteries of Udolpho); and she read novels translated from French and German (among others, Goethe's Sorrows of Werther); and whatever novels she could get from the circulating library at Bath or Southampton. But she was interested not only in fiction. She knew her Shakespeare well and, among the moderns, she read Scott and Byron, but her favourite poet seems to have been Cowper. It is natural that his cool, elegant and sensible verse should have appealed to her. She read Johnson and Boswell, and a good deal of history, besides miscellaneous literature of various kinds. She was fond of reading aloud, and is said to have had a pleasant voice.

She read sermons, and was particularly fond of Sherlock's, a divine born in the seventeenth century. That is not so surprising as at first sight appears. In my early youth I lived in a country vicarage, and in the study several shelves were closely packed with handsomely-bound collections of sermons. If they were published, it was presumably because they sold; and if they sold, it was because people read them. Jane Austen was pious without being devout. Of course she went to church on Sundays, and partook of communion; and doubtless both at Steventon and Godmersham, family prayers were read morning and evening. But, as Dr. Chapman says: “It was admittedly not an age of religious ferment.”Just as we take a bath every day and wash our teeth morning and evening, and only feel at ease if we have done so; so, I should think, Miss Austen, like most others of her generation, having with proper unction performed her religious duties, put away the matters with which religion is concerned, as one puts away an article of clothing one does not for the moment want, and, for the rest of the day and week, gave her whole mind with an untroubled conscience to secular affairs.“The evangelists were not yet.”A gentleman's younger son was properly provided for by taking orders and being given a family living. It was unnecessary that he should have a vocation, but desirable that the house he was to live in should be commodious and the income adequate. But taking orders, it was only right that he should perform the duties of his profession. Jane Austen certainly believed that a clergyman should“live among his parishioners and prove himself by constant attention their well-wisher and friend.”That is what her brother Henry had done; he was witty and gay, the most brilliant of her brothers; he went into business and for some years greatly prospered; eventually, however, he went bankrupt. He then took orders, and was an exemplary parish priest.

Jane Austen shared the opinions common in her day and, so far as one can tell from her books and letters, was satisfied with the conditions that prevailed. She had no doubt that social distinctions were of importance, and she found it natural that there should be rich and poor. Young men, as was right and proper, obtained advancement in the service of the King by the influence of powerful friends. A woman's business was to marry, for love certainly, but in satisfactory conditions. This was in the order of things, and there is no sign that Miss Austen saw anything in it to object to. In one of her letters to Cassandra she remarks: “Carlo and his wife live in the most private manner imaginable at Portsmouth, without keeping a servant of any kind. What a prodigious amount of virtue she must have to marry under such circumstances.”The vulgar squalor in which Fanny Price's family lived, owing to her mother's imprudent marriage, was an object-lesson to show how careful a young woman should be.

4

Jane Austen's novels are pure entertainment. If you happen to believe that to entertain should be the novelist's main endeavour, you must put her in a class by herself. Greater novels than hers have been written, War and Peace, for example, and The Brothers Karamazov; but you must be fresh and alert to read them with profit. No matter if you are tired and dispirited, Jane Austen's enchant.

At the time she wrote, it was thought far from ladylike for a woman to do so. Monk Lewis observed: “I have an aversion, a pity and contempt for all female scribblers. The needle, not the pen, is the instrument they should handle, and the only one they ever use dexterously.”The novel was a form held in scant esteem, and Miss Austen was herself not a little perturbed that Sir Walter Scott, a poet, should write fiction. She was“careful that her occupation should not be suspected by servants, or visitors, or any person beyond her family party. She wrote upon small sheets of paper which could easily be put away, or covered with a piece of blotting paper. There was between the front door and the offices, a swing door which creaked when it was opened; but she objected to having this little inconvenience remedied, because it gave her notice when anyone was coming.”Her eldest brother, James never even told his son, then a boy at school, that the books he read with delight were by his Aunt Jane; and her brother Henry in his Memoir states: “No accumulation of fame would have induced her, had she lived, to affix her name to any productions of her pen, ”So her first book to be published, Sense and Sensibility was described on the title pages as“by a Lady.”

It was not the first she completed. That was a novel called First Impressions. Her father wrote to a publisher offering for publication, at the author's expense or otherwise, a“manuscript novel, comprising three volumes; about the length of Miss Burney's Evelina.”The offer was refused by return of post. First Impressions was begun during the winter of 1796 and finished in August 1797; it is generally supposed to have been substantially the same book as sixteen years later was issued as Pride and Prejudice. Then, in quick succession she wrote Sense and Sensibility and Northanger Abbey, but had no better luck with them, though after five years a Mr. Richard Crosby bought the latter, then called Susan, for ten pounds. He never published it, and eventually sold it back for what he had paid: since Miss Austen's novels were published anonymously, he had no notion that the book, with which he had parted for so small a sum, was by the successful and popular author of Pride and Prejudice. She seems to have written little but a fragment, The Watsons, between 1798, when she finished Northanger Abbey, and 1809. It is a long time for a writer of such creative power to remain silent, and it has been suggested that the cause was a love affair that occupied her to the exclusion of other interests. We are told that, when staying with her mother and sister at a seaside resort in Devonshire, “she became acquainted with a gentleman, whose charm of person, mind and manners was such that Cassandra thought him worthy to possess and likely to win her sister's love. When they parted he expressed his intention of soon seeing them again; and Cassandra felt no doubt as to his motives. But they never again met. Within a short time, they heard of his sudden death.”The acquaintance was short, and the author of the Memoir adds that he is unable to say“whether her feelings were of such a nature as to affect her happiness.”I do not for my part think they were. I do not believe that Miss Austen was capable of being very much in love. If she had been, she would surely have attributed to her heroines a greater warmth of emotion than in fact she did. There is no passion in their love. Their inclinations are tempered with prudence and controlled by common sense. Real love has no truck with these estimable qualities. Take Persuasion: Jane states that Anne Elliot and Wentworth fell deeply in love with one another. There, I think, she deceived herself and deceives her readers. On Wentworth's side it was certainly what Stendhal called amour passion, but on Anne's no more than what he called amour goût. They became engaged. Anne allows herself to be persuaded by that interfering snob, Lady Russell, that it would be imprudent to marry a poor man, a naval officer, who might be killed in the war. If she had been deeply in love with Wentworth, she would surely have taken the risk. It was not a very great one, for on her marriage she was to receive her share of her mother's fortune; this share amounted to rather more than three thousand pounds, equivalent now to over twelve thousand; so in any case she would not have been penniless. She might very well, like Captain Benwick and Miss Hargreaves, have remained engaged to Wentworth till he got his command and so was able to marry her. Anne Elliot broke off her engagement because Lady Russell persuaded her that she might make a better match if she waited, and it was not till no suitor, whom she was prepared to marry, presented himself that she discovered how much she loved Wentworth. We may be pretty sure that Jane Austen thought her behaviour natural and reasonable.

The most plausible explanation of her long silence is that she was discouraged by her inability to find a publisher. Her close relations, to whom she read her novels, were charmed by them, but she was as sensible as she was modest, and she may well have decided that their appeal was only to persons who were fond of her, and had, perhaps, a shrewd idea who the models of her characters were. The author of the Memoir rejects emphatically that she had such models, and Dr. Chapman seems to agree with him. They are claiming for Jane Austen a power of invention which is frankly incredible. All the greatest novelists, Stendhal and Balzac, Tolstoy and Turgenev, Dickens and Thackeray, have had models from whom they created their characters. It is true that Jane said: “I am too proud of my gentlemen to admit that they were only Mr. A, or Colonel B.”There the significant word is only. As with every other novelist, by the time her imagination had worked on the person who had suggested the character, he was to all intents and purposes her own creation; but that is not to say that he was not evolved from an original Mr. A. or Colonel B.

Be that as it may, in 1809, in which year Jane settled with her mother and sister in the quiet of Chawton, she set about revising her old manuscripts, and in 1811 Sense and Sensibility at last appeared. By then it was no longer outrageous for a woman to write. Professor Spurgeon, in a lecture on Jane Austen delivered to the Royal Society of Literature, quotes a preface to Original Letters from India by Eliza Fay. This lady had been urged to publish them in 1782, but public opinion was so averse“to female authorship”that she declined. But writing in 1816, she said: “Since then a considerable change has gradually taken place in public sentiment, and its development; we have now not only as in former days a number of women who do honour to their sex as literary characters, but many unpretending females, who fearless of the critical perils that once attended the voyage, venture to launch their little barks on the vast ocean through which amusement or instruction is conveyed to a reading public.”

Pride and Prejudice was published in 1813. Jane Austen sold the copyright for one hundred and ten pounds.

Besides the three novels already mentioned, she wrote three more, Mansfield Park, Emma and Persuasion. On these few books her fame rests, and her fame is secure. She had to wait a long time to get a book published, but she no sooner did than her charming gifts were recognized. Since then, the most eminent persons have agreed to praise her. I will only quote what Sir Walter Scott had to say; it is characteristically generous: “That young lady had a talent for describing the involvements, feelings and characters of ordinary life which is to me the most wonderful I have ever met with. The big bow-wow I can do myself like anyone going; but the exquisite touch which renders commonplace things and characters interesting from the truth of the description and the sentiment is denied to me.”

It is odd that Sir Walter should have omitted to make mention of the young lady's most precious talent: her observation was searching and her sentiment edifying, but it was her humour that gave point to her observation and a prim liveliness to her sentiment. Her range was narrow. She wrote very much the same sort of story in all her books, and there is no great variety in her characters. They are very much the same persons, seen from a somewhat different point of view. She had common sense in a high degree, and no one knew better than she her limitations. Her experience of life was confined to a small circle of provincial society, and that is what she was content to deal with. She wrote only of what she knew. As was first pointed out by Dr. Chapman, she never attempted to reproduce a conversation of men when by themselves, which in the nature of things she could never have heard.

It has been noticed that though she lived through some of the most stirring events of the world's history, the French Revolution, the Terror, the rise and fall of Napoleon, she made no reference to them in her novels. She has on this account been blamed for an undue detachment. It should be remembered that in her day it was not polite for women to occupy themselves with politics, that was a matter for men to deal with; few women even read the newspapers; but there is no reason to suppose that, because she did not write about these events, she was not affected by them. She was fond of her family, two of her brothers were in the Navy, often enough in danger, and her letters show that they were much on her mind. But did she not display her good sense in not writing about such matters? She was too modest to suppose that her novels would be read long after her death; but if that had been her aim, she could not have acted more wisely than she did in avoiding to deal with affairs which from the literary standpoint were of passing interest. Already, the novels concerned with the Second World War, that have been written in the last few years, are as dead as mutton. They were as ephemeral as the newspapers that day by day told us what was happening.

Most novelists have their ups and downs. Miss Austen is the only exception I know to prove the rule that only the mediocre maintain an equal level, a level of mediocrity. She is never more than a little below her best. Even in Sense and Sensibility and Northanger Abbey, in which there is much to cavil at, there is more to delight. Each of the others has its devoted, and even fanatic, admirers. Macaulay thought Mansfield Park her greatest achievement; other readers, equally illustrious, have preferred Emma; Disraeli read Pride and Prejudice seventeen times; to-day, many look upon Persuasion as her most finished work. The great mass of readers, I believe, has accepted Pride and Prejudice as her masterpiece, and in such a case I think it well to accept their judgment. What makes a classic is not that it is praised by critics, expounded by professors and studied in schools, but that large numbers of readers, generation after generation, have found pleasure and spiritual profit in reading it.

I myself think that Pride and Prejudice is on the whole the most satisfactory of all the novels. Its first sentence puts you in good humour: “It is a truth universally acknowledged, that a single man in possession of a good fortune, must be in want of a wife.”It sets the note, and the good humour it induces remains with you till, with regret, you have reached the last page. Emma is the only one of Miss Austen's novels that I find long-winded. I can take no great interest in the love affair of Frank Churchill and Jane Fairfax; and, though Miss Bates is immensely amusing, don’t we get a little too much of her? The heroine is a snob, and the way she patronizes those whom she looks upon as her social inferiors is repulsive. But we must not blame Miss Austen for that: we must remember that we of to-day do not read the same novel that was read by the readers of her day. Changes in manners and customs have wrought changes in our outlook; in some ways we are narrower than our forebears, in others more liberal; an attitude, which even a hundred years ago was general, now affects us with malaise. We judge the books we read by our own prepossessions and our own standards of behaviour. That is unfair, but inevitable. In Mansfield Park the hero and heroine, Fanny and Edmund, are intolerable prigs; and all my sympathies go out to the unscrupulous, sprightly and charming Henry and Mary Crawford. I cannot understand why Sir Thomas Bertram should have been enraged when, on his return from overseas, he found his family amusing themselves with private theatricals. Since Jane herself thoroughly enjoyed them, one cannot see why she found his anger justifiable. Persuasion has a rare charm, and though one may wish that Anne were a little less matter-of-fact, a little more disinterested, a little more impulsive—in fact a little less old-maidish—except for the incident on the Cobb at Lyme Regis, I should be forced to look upon it as the most perfect of the six. Jane Austen had no particular gift for inventing incident of an unusual character, and this one seems to me a very clumsy contrivance. Louisa Musgrove runs up some steep steps, and is“jumped down”by her admirer, Captain Wentworth. He misses her, she falls on her head and is stunned. If he were going to give her his hands, as we are told he had been in the habit of doing in“jumping her off”a stile, even if the Cobb then were twice as high as it is now, she could not have been more than six feet from the ground and, as she was jumping down, it is impossible that she should have fallen on her head. In any case, she would have fallen against the stalwart sailor and, though perhaps shaken and frightened, could hardly have hurt herself. Anyhow, she was unconscious, and the fuss that ensued is unbelievable. Captain Wentworth, who has seen action and made a fortune from prize-money, is paralyzed with horror. The immediately subsequent behaviour of all concerned is so idiotic that I find it hard to believe that Miss Austen, who was able to take the illnesses and death of her friends and relations with quiet fortitude, did not look upon it as uncommonly foolish.

Professor Garrod, a learned and witty critic, has said that Jane Austen was incapable of writing a story, by which, he explains, he means a sequence of happenings, either romantic or uncommon. But that is not what Jane Austen had a talent for, and not what she tried to do. She had too much sense, and too sprightly a humour, to be romantic, and she was interested not in the uncommon, but in the common. She made it uncommon by the keenness of her observation, her irony and her playful wit. By a story most of us mean a connected and coherent narrative with a beginning, a middle and an end. Pride and Prejudice begins in the right place, with the arrival on the scene of the two young men whose love for Elizabeth Bennet and her sister Jane provide the novel with its plot, and it ends in the right place with their marriage. It is the traditional happy ending. This kind of ending has excited the scorn of the sophisticated, and of course it is true that many, perhaps most, marriages are not happy, and further, that marriage concludes nothing; it is merely an introduction to another order of experience. Many authors have in consequence started their novels with marriage and dealt with its outcome. It is their right. But there is something to be said for the simple people who look upon marriage as a satisfactory conclusion to a work of fiction. They do so because they have an instinctive feeling that, by mating, a man and a woman have fulfilled their biological function; the interest which it is natural to feel in the steps that have led to this consummation, the birth of love, the obstacles, the misunderstandings, the avowals, now yields to its result, their issue, which is the generation that will succeed them. To nature, each couple is but a link in a chain, and the only importance of the link is that another link may be added to it. This is the novelist's justification for the happy ending. In Pride and Prejudice, the reader's satisfaction is considerably enhanced by the knowledge that the bridegroom has a substantial income and will take his bride to a fine house, surrounded by a park, and furnished throughout with expensive and elegant furniture.

Pride and Prejudice is a very well-constructed book. The incidents follow one another naturally, and one's sense of probability is nowhere outraged. It is perhaps odd that Elizabeth and Jane should be well-bred and well-behaved, whereas their mother and their three younger sisters should be, as Lady Knatchbull put it, “very much below par as to good society and its ways”; but that this should be so was essential to the story. I have allowed myself to wonder that Miss Austen did not avoid this stumbling-block by making Elizabeth and Jane the daughters of a first marriage of Mr. Bennet and making the Mrs. Bennet of the novel his second wife and the mother of the three younger daughters. She liked Elizabeth best of all her heroines.“I must confess, ”she wrote, “that I think her as delightful a creature as ever appeared in print.”If, as some have thought, she was herself the original for her portrait of Elizabeth; and she has certainly given her her own gaiety, high spirit and courage, wit and readiness, good sense and right feeling; it is perhaps not rash to suppose that when she drew the placid, kindly and beautiful Jane Bennet she had in mind her sister Cassandra. Darcy has been generally regarded as a fearful cad. His first offence was his disinclination to dance with people he didn’t know, and didn’t want to know, at a public ball to which he had gone with a party. Not a very heinous one. It was unfortunate that Elizabeth should overhear the derogatory terms in which he spoke of her to Bingley, but he could not know that she was listening, and his excuse might have been that his friend was badgering him to do what he had no wish to. It is true that when Darcy proposes to Elizabeth it is with an unpardonable insolence, but pride, pride of birth and position, was the predominant trait of his character, and without it there would have been no story to tell. The manner of his proposal, moreover, gave Jane Austen opportunity for the most dramatic scene in the book; it is conceivable that, with the experience she gained later, she might have been able to indicate Darcy's feelings, very natural and comprehensible feelings, in such a way as to antagonize Elizabeth, without putting into his mouth speeches so outrageous as to shock the reader. There is, perhaps, some exaggeration in the drawing of Lady Catherine and Mr. Collins, but to my mind little more than comedy allows. Comedy sees life in a light more sparkling, but colder, than that of common day, and a touch of exaggeration, that is of farce, is often no disadvantage. A discreet admixture of farce, like a sprinkle of sugar on strawberries, may well make comedy more palatable. With regard to Lady Catherine, one must remember that in Miss Austen's day rank gave its possessors a sense of immense superiority over persons of inferior station; and they not only expected to be treated by them with the utmost deference, but were. In my own youth I knew great ladies whose sense of importance, though not quite so blatant, was not far removed from Lady Catherine's. And as for Mr. Collins, who has not known, even to-day, men with that combination of obsequiousness and pomposity? That they have learnt to screen it with a front of geniality only makes it more odious.

Jane Austen was not a great stylist, but she wrote plainly and without affection. I think the influence of Dr. Johnson may be discerned in the structure of her sentences. She is apt to use the word of Latin origin, rather than the homely English one. It gives her phrase a slight formality which is far from unpleasant; indeed, it often adds point to a witty remark, and a demure savour to a malicious one. Her dialogue is probably as natural as dialogue could then be. To us it may seem somewhat stilted. Jane Bennet, speaking of her lover's sisters, says: “They were certainly no friends to his acquaintance with me, which I cannot wonder at, since he might have chosen so much more advantageously in many respects.”It may, of course, be that these were the very words she uttered; I think it unlikely. It is obviously not how a modern novelist would phrase the same remark. To set down on paper speech exactly as it is spoken is very tedious, and some arrangement of it is certainly necessary. It is only of late years, comparatively, that novelists, striving for verisimilitude, have been at pains to make their dialogue as colloquial as possible: I suspect that it was a convention of the past to cause persons of education to express themselves with a balance, and with a grammatical correctness, which cannot commonly have been at their command, and I presume readers accepted it as natural.

Allowing, then, for the slight formality of Miss Austen's dialogue, we must admit that she invariably made the person of her stories speak in character. I have only noticed one occasion upon which she slipped up: “Anne smiled and said, ‘My idea of good company, Mr. Elliot, is the company of clever, well-informed people, who have a great deal of conversation; that is what I call good company.’‘You are mistaken, ’ said he gently, ‘that is not good company that is the best.’”

Mr. Elliot had faults of character; but if he was capable of making so admirable a reply to Anne's remark, he must have had qualities with which his creator did not see fit to acquaint us. For my part, I am so charmed with it that I would have been content to see her marry him rather than the stodgy Captain Wentworth. It is true that Mr. Elliot had married a woman“of inferior station”for her money, and neglected her; and his treatment of Mrs. Smith was ungenerous; but, after all, we only have her side of the story, and it may be that, had we been given a chance to hear his, we should have found his conduct pardonable.

There is one merit which Miss Austen has, and which I have almost omitted to mention. She is wonderfully readable—more readable than some greater and more famous novelists. She deals, as Walter Scott said, with commonplace things, “the involvements, feelings and characters of ordinary life”; nothing very much happens in her books and yet, when you come to the bottom of a page, you eagerly turn it to learn what will happen next. Nothing very much does and again you eagerly turn the page. The novelist who has the power to achieve this has the most precious gift a novelist can possess.

Charles Dickens and David Copperfield

1

Charles Dickens, though far from tall, was graceful and of a pleasing appearance. A portrait of him, painted by Maclise when he was twenty-seven, is in the National Portrait Gallery. He is seated in a handsome chair at a writing-table, with a small, elegant hand resting lightly on a manuscript. He is grandly dressed, and wears a vast satin neck-cloth. His brown hair is curled, and falls well below the ears down each side of his face. His eyes are fine; and the thoughtful expression he wears is such as an admiring public might expect of a very successful young author. What the portrait does not show is the animation, the shining light, the activity of heart and mind, which those who came in contact with him saw in his countenance. He was always something of a dandy, and in his youth favoured velvet coats, gay waistcoats, coloured neck-cloths and white hats; but he never quite achieved the effect he sought: people were surprised and even shocked by his dress, which they described as both slip-shod and flashy.

His grandfather, William Dickens, began life as a footman, married a housemaid and eventually became steward at Crewe Hall, the seat of John Crewe, Member of Parliament for Chester. William Dickens had two sons, William and John; but the only one that concerns us is John, first because he was the father of England's greatest novelist, and secondly because he served as a model for his son's greatest creation, Mr. Micawber. William Dickens died, and his widow stayed on at Crewe Hall as housekeeper. After thirty-five years she was pensioned off, and, perhaps to be near her two sons, went to live in London. The Crewes educated her fatherless boys, and provided them with a means of livelihood. They got John a post in the Navy Pay Office. There he made friends with a fellow-clerk and presently married his sister, Elizabeth Barrow. From the beginning of his married life he appears to have been in financial trouble, and he was always ready to borrow money from anyone who was foolish enough to lend it. But he was kind-hearted and generous, no fool, industrious, though perhaps but fitfully; and he evidently had a taste for good wine, since the second time he was arrested for debt, it was at the suit of a wine-merchant. He is described in later life as an old buck who dressed well and was for ever fingering the large bunch of seals attached to his watch.

Charles, the first son, but second child, of John and Elizabeth Dickens, was born in 1812 at Portsea. Two years later his father was transferred to London, and three years after that to Chatham. There the little boy was put to school, and there he began to read. His father had collected a few books, Tom Jones, The Vicar of Wakefield, Gil Blas, Don Quixote, Roderick Random, Peregrine Pickle; Charles read and re-read them. His own novels show how great and persistent an influence they had on him.

In 1822 John Dickens, who by this time had five children, was moved back to London. Charles was left at Chatham to continue his schooling, and did not rejoin his family for some months. He found them settled in Camden Town on the outskirts of the city, in a house which he was later to describe as the home of the Micawbers. John Dickens, though earning a little more than three hundred pounds a year, which to-day would be equivalent to at least four times as much, was apparently in more than usually desperate straits, and it would seem that there was not enough money to send little Charles to school again. To the boy's disgust, he was put to minding the children, cleaning the boots, brushing the clothes and helping the maid Mrs. Dickens had brought with her from Chatham with the housework. In the intervals he roamed about Camden Town, “a desolate place surrounded byfields and ditches, ”and the neighbouring Somers Town and Kentish Town, and sometimes he was taken farther afield and got a glimpse of Soho and Limehouse.

Things grew so bad that Mrs. Dickens decided to open a school for the children of parents living in India; she borrowed money, presumably from her mother-in-law, and had handbills printed for distribution, which her own children were sent to push into letter-boxes in the neighbourhood. Naturally enough, no pupils were brought. Debts meanwhile grew more and more pressing. Charles was sent to pawn whatever articles they had on which cash could be raised; the books, the precious books which meant so much to him, were sold. Then James Lamert, vaguely related by marriage to Mrs. Dickens, offered Charles a job at six shillings a week in a blacking factory, of which he was part-owner. His parents thankfully accepted the offer, but it cut the boy to the quick that they should be so manifestly relieved to get him off their hands. He was twelve years old. Shortly afterwards, John Dickens was arrested for debt and taken to the Marshalsea; and there his wife, after pawning the little that was left to pawn, joined him with her children. The prison was filthy, insanitary and crowded, for not only was it occupied by the prisoners, but by the families they might, if they chose, bring with them; though whether they were allowed to do this to alleviate the hardships of prison life or because the unfortunate creatures had nowhere else to go, I do not know. If a debtor had money, loss of liberty was the worst of the inconveniences he had to endure, and this loss in some cases might be mitigated: particular prisoners were permitted, on observing certain conditions, to reside outside the prison walls. In the past, the warden was in the habit of practising outrageous extortion on the prisoners and often treated them with barbarous cruelty; but by the time John Dickens was consigned to jail, the worst abuses had been done away with, and he was able to make himself sufficiently comfortable. The faithful little maid lived out and came in daily to help with the children and prepare meals. He still had his salary of six pounds a week, but made no attempt to pay his debt; and it may be supposed that, content to be out of reach of his other creditors, he did not especially care to be released. He soon recovered his usual spirits. The other debtors“made him chairman of the committee by which they regulated the internal economy of the prison, ”and presently he was on cordial terms with everyone from the turnkeys to the meanest inmate. The biographers have been puzzled by the fact that John Dickens continued meanwhile to receive his wages. The only explanation appears to be that since government clerks were appointed by influence, such an accident as being imprisoned for debt was not considered so grave a matter as to call for the drastic step of cutting off a salary.

At the beginning of his father's imprisonment, Charles lodged in Camden Town; but since this was a long way from the blacking factory, which was at Hungerford Stairs, Charing Cross, John Dickens found him a room in Lant Street, Southwark, which was near the Marshalsea. He was then able to breakfast and sup with his family. The work he was put to do was not hard; it consisted in washing the bottles, labelling them and tying them up. In April, 1824, Mrs. William Dickens, the Crewes’ old housekeeper, died and left her savings to her two sons. John Dickens's debt was paid (by his brother), and he regained his freedom. He settled his family once more in Camden Town, and went back to work at the Navy Pay Office. Charles continued to wash bottles at the factory for a while, but then John Dickens quarrelled with James Lamert, “quarrelled by letter, ”wrote Charles later, “for I took the letter from my father to him which caused the explosion.”James Lamert told Charles that his father had insulted him, and that he must go.“With a relief so strange that it was like oppression, I went home.”His mother tried to smooth things down, so that Charles should retain his job and the weekly wage, seven shillings by then, which she still sorely needed; and for this he never forgave her.“I never afterwards forgot, I never shall forget, I never can forget that my mother was warm for my being sent back, ”he added. John Dickens, however, would not hear of it, and sent his son to a school, very grandly called the Wellington House Academy, in the Hampstead Road. He stayed there two and a half years.

It is difficult to make out how long the boy spent at the blacking factory: he was there early in February and was back with his family by June, so that at the outside he could not have been at the factory for more than four months. It appears, however, to have made a deep impression upon him, and he came to look upon the experience as so humiliating that he could not bear to speak of it. When John Forster, his intimate friend and first biographer, by chance hit upon some inkling of it, Dickens told him that he had touched upon a matter so painful that“even at the present hour, ”and this was twenty-five years later, “he could never lose the remembrance of it while he remembered anything.”

We are so used to hearing eminent politicians and captains of industry boast of having in their early youth washed dishes and sold newspapers, that it is hard for us to understand why Charles Dickens should have worked himself up into looking upon it as a great injury that his parents had done him when they sent him to the blacking factory, and a secret so shameful that it must be concealed. He was a merry, mischievous, alert boy, and already knew a good deal of the seamy side of life. From an early age he had seen to what a pass his father's improvidence reduced the family. They were poor people, and they lived as poor people. At Camden Town he was put to sweep and scrub; he was sent to pawn a coat or a trinket to buy food for dinner; and like any other boy, he must have played in the streets with boys of the same sort as himself. He went to work at an age when at the time it was usual for boys of his class to go to work, and at a fair wage. His six shillings a week, presently raised to seven, was worth at least twenty-five to thirty shillings to-day. For a short time he had to feed himself on that, but later, when he lodged near enough to the Marshalsea to have breakfast and supper with his family, he only had to pay for his dinner. The boys he worked with were friendly, and it is hard to see why he should have found it such a degradation to consort with them. He had from time to time been taken to see his grandmother in Oxford Street, and he could hardly have helped knowing that she had spent her life in“service.”It may be that John Dickens was a bit of a snob and made pretensions that had no basis, but a lad of twelve surely has little sense of social distinctions. One must suppose, further, that if Charles was sophisticated enough to think himself a cut above the other boys at the factory, he would be smart enough to understand how necessary his earnings were to his family. One would have expected it to be a source of pride to him that he was become a wage-earner.

As a result, one may presume, of Forster's discovery, Dickens wrote, and gave Forster the fragment of autobiography from which the details of this episode in his life have been made known to us. As his imagination went to work on his recollections, he was filled, I suspect, with pity for the little boy he had been; he gave him the pain, the disgust, the mortification which he thought he, famous, affluent, beloved, would have felt if he had been in the little boy's place. And seeing it all so vividly, his generous heart bled, his eyes were dim with tears, as he wrote of the poor lad's loneliness and his misery at being betrayed by those in whom he had put his trust. I do not think he consciously exaggerated; he couldn’t help exaggerating: his talent, his genius if you like, was based on exaggeration. It was by dwelling upon, and emphasizing, the comic elements in Mr. Micawber's character that he excited his readers’ laughter; and it was by intensifying the pathos of Little Nell's slow decline that he reduced them to tears. He would not have been the novelist he was, if he had failed to make his account of the four months he spent at the blacking factory as moving as he alone knew how to make it; and, as everyone knows, he used it again to harrowing effect in David Copperfield. For my part, I do not believe that the experience caused him anything like the suffering that in after years, when he was famous and respectable, a social as well as a public figure, he persuaded himself that it had; and I believe even less that, as biographers and critics have thought, it had a decisive effect on his life and work.

While still at the Marshalsea, John Dickens, fearing that as an insolvent debtor he would lose his job in the Navy Pay Office, solicited the head of his department to recommend him for a superannuation grant on the ground of his ill health; and eventually, in consideration of his twenty years’ service and six children, he was granted“on compassionate grounds, ”a pension of one hundred and forty pounds a year. This was little enough for such a man as John Dickens to support a family and he had to find some means of adding to his income. He had somehow acquired a knowledge of shorthand; and with the help of his brother-in-law, who had connections with the press, he got employment as a parliamentary reporter. Charles remained at school till, at fifteen, he went to work as an errand-boy in a lawyer's office. He does not seem to have considered this beneath his dignity. He had joined what we now call the white-collar class. A few weeks later, his father managed to get him engaged as a clerk in another lawyer's office at ten shillings a week, which in course of time rose to fifteen shillings. He found the life dull and, with the hope of bettering himself, studied shorthand—to such purpose that after eighteen months he was sufficiently competent to set up as a reporter in the Consistory Court of Doctors’ Commons. By the time he was twenty, he was qualified to report the debates in the House of Commons, and soon gained the reputation of being“the fastest and most accurate man in the Gallery.”

Meanwhile, he had fallen in love with Maria Beadnell, the pretty daughter of a bank clerk. They met first when Charles was seventeen. Maria was a flirtatious young person, and she seems to have given him a good deal of encouragement. There may even have been a secret engagement between them. She was flattered and amused to have a lover, but Charles was penniless, and she can never have intended to marry him. When after two years the affair came to an end, and in true romantic fashion they returned one another's presents and letters, Charles thought his heart would break. They did not meet again till many years later. Maria Beadnell, long a married woman, dined with the celebrated Mr. Dickens and his wife: she was fat, commonplace and stupid. She served then as the model for Flora Finching in Little Dorrit. She had already served as the model for Dora in David Copperfield.

In order to be near the paper for which he was working, Dickens had taken lodgings in one of the dingy streets off the Strand, but finding them unsatisfactory, he presently rented unfurnished rooms in Furnival's Inn. But before he could furnish these, his father was again arrested for debt, and he had to provide money for his keep at the sponging-house.“As it had to be assumed that John Dickens would not rejoin his family for some time, ”Charles took cheap lodgings for his family and camped out with his brother Frederick, whom he took to live with him, in the“three-pair back”at Furnival's Inn.“Just because he was open-hearted as well as open-handed, ”wrote the late Una Pope-Hennessy in her very readable biography of Charles Dickens, “and seemed able to deal with difficulties of the kind easily, it became the custom in his family, and later on in his wife's family, to expect him to find money and appointments for as spineless a set of people as ever breadwinner was saddled with.”

2

When he had been working for a year or so in the Gallery of the House of Commons, Dickens began to write a series of sketches of London life; the first were published in The Monthly Magazine, and later ones in The Morning Chronicle; he was paid nothing for them, but they attracted the attention of a publisher named Macrone, and on the author's twenty-fourth birthday they were issued in two volumes, with illustrations by Cruickshank, under the title Sketches by Boz. Macrone paid him one hundred and fifty pounds for the first edition. The book was well reviewed, and within a short time brought him an offer of further work. There was a vogue at the time for anecdotic novels of a humorous character, which were issued in monthly parts at a shilling, with comic illustrations. They were the remote ancestors of the funnies of our own time, and they had the same prodigious popularity. One day a partner in the firm of Chapman and Hall called upon Dickens to ask him to write a narrative about a club of amateur sportsmen to serve as a vehicle for the illustrations of a well-known artist. There were to be twenty numbers, and he offered fourteen pounds a month for what we should now call the serial rights, with further payments when later they were published as a book. Dickens protested that he knew nothing about sport and did not think he could write to order, but“the emolument was too tempting to resist.”I need hardly say that the result was The Posthumous Papers of the Pickwick Club. The first five numbers had no great success, but with the introduction of Sam Weller the circulation leaped up. By the time the work appeared in book-form, Charles Dickens was famous. Though the critics made their reservations, his reputation was made. It is well to record that The Quarterly Review, speaking of him, said that“it required no gift of prophecy to foretell his fate—he has risen like a rocket and he will come down like a stick.”But indeed, throughout his career, while the public devoured his books, the critics carped.

A couple of days before the appearance of the first number of The Pickwick Papers, in 1836, Dickens married Kate, the eldest daughter of George Hogarth, a colleague of Dickens on The Morning Chronicle. George Hogarth was the father of six sons and eight daughters. The daughters were small, plump, fresh-coloured and blue-eyed. Kate was the only one of marriageable age. That seems to have been the reason why Dickens married her rather than one of the others. After a short honeymoon, they settled down in Furnival's Inn and invited Kate's pretty sister, Mary Hogarth, a girl of sixteen, to live with them. Dickens accepted a contract to write another novel, Oliver Twist, and he started it while still at work on The Pickwick Papers. This also was to appear in monthly numbers, and he devoted a fortnight to one and a fortnight to the other. Most novelists are so absorbed in the characters which are at the moment engaging their attention that, by no effort of will, they thrust back into their unconscious what other literary ideas they have had in mind; and that Dickens should have been able to switch, apparently with ease, from one story to another is an amazing feat.

He took a fancy to Mary Hogarth, and when Kate found herself with child and, could not go about with him, Mary became his constant companion. Kate's baby was born, and as she might be expected to have several more, a move was made from Furnival's Inn to a house in Doughty Street. Mary grew every day more lovely and more delightful. One May evening, Dickens took Kate and Mary to a play; they enjoyed themselves and came home in high spirits. Mary was taken ill. A doctor was sent for. In a few hours she was dead. Dickens took the ring from her finger and put it on his own. He wore it till his death. He was prostrated with grief. Not long after, he wrote in his diary: “If she were with us now, the same winning, happy, amiable companion, sympathizing with all my thoughts and feelings more than anyone I know ever did or will, I think I should have nothing to wish for but a continuance of such happiness. But she is gone, and pray God I may one day, through his mercy, rejoin her.”These are significant words, and they tell us a great deal. He arranged to be buried by Mary's side. I think there can be no doubt that he had fallen deeply in love with her. We shall never know whether he was aware of it.

At the time of Mary's death, Kate was once more pregnant, and the shock brought on a miscarriage. When she was well enough, Charles took her for a short trip abroad so that they might both recover their spirits. By the summer he, at all events, had sufficiently done so to have a boisterous flirtation with a certain Eleanor P.

3

With Oliver Twist, Nicholas Nickleby and The Old Curiosity Shop, Dickens was soundly launched on his triumphant career. He was a hard worker, and for several years started to write a new book long before he had finished with the old one. He wrote to please and kept his eye on the public reaction to the monthly numbers, in which many of his novels appeared, and it is interesting to learn that he had no intention of sending Martin Chuzzlewit to America till the declining sales showed that his numbers were not so attractive as usual. He was not the sort of author who looks upon popularity as something to be ashamed of. His success was enormous. But the life of a literary man, who has achieved it, is not as a rule eventful. It follows a uniform pattern. His profession obliges him to devote a certain number of hours a day to his work, and he discovers a routine to suit him. He is brought into contact with the celebrated people of the day, literary, artistic and polite. He is taken up by great ladies. He goes to parties and gives parties. He travels. He makes public appearances. This, broadly, was the pattern of Dickens's life. The success he enjoyed, indeed, was such as has been the fortune of few authors to experience. His energy seemed inexhaustible. Not only did he produce long novels in quick succession, he founded and edited magazines and, for a short period, even edited a daily paper; he wrote a quantity of occasional pieces; he delivered lectures, he spoke at banquets, and later gave readings of his works. He rode, he thought nothing of walking twenty miles a day, he danced and played the fool with gusto, he did conjuring tricks to amuse his children, he acted in amateur theatricals. He had always been fascinated by the theatre, and once had seriously thought of going on the stage; at that time, he took lessons in elocution from an actor, learned parts by heart and practised before a mirror how to enter a room, sit down on a chair and make a bow. One must suppose that these accomplishments were useful to him when he was introduced into the world of fashion. The censorious, notwithstanding, thought him faintly vulgar and his mode of dress showy. Accent in England has always“placed”a man, and it is likely enough that Dickens, who had lived almost all his life in London, and in very modest circumstances, had something of a cockney accent. But he charmed by his good looks, the brightness of his eyes, his exuberance, vivacity and joyous laugh. He may have been dazzled by the adulation of which he was the object, but his head was not turned. He retained an attractive modesty. He was a genial, delightful, affectionate creature. He was one of those persons who, when they come into a room, bring with them delight.

Oddly enough, though he had an immense power of observation and, in course of time, came to be on familiar terms with persons in the higher ranks of society, he never succeeded in his novels in making such characters as he created in those walks of life quite credible. One of the commonest charges against him, during his lifetime, was that he couldn’t draw a gentleman. His lawyers and lawyer's clerks, whom he had known when he worked in an office, have a distinctiveness of feature which is lacking in his doctors and parsons; he was at his best when dealing with the ragtag and bobtail among whom his boyhood was spent. It looks as though a novelist can only know intimately enough, to use them with profit as models for creatures of his own invention, the persons with whom he has been connected at an early age. A child's year, a boy's year, is much, much longer than the year of a grown-up man, and he is thus given what seems like all the time in the world to make himself aware of the idiosyncrasies of the people who form his environment.“One reason why many English writers have totally failed in describing the manners of upper life, ”wrote Henry Fielding, “may possibly be, that in reality they knew nothing of it.…Now it happens that this higher order of mortals is not to be seen, like all the rest of the human species, for nothing, in the streets, shops, and coffee houses: nor are they shown, like the upper ranks of animals, for so much a-piece. In short, this is a sight to which no persons are admitted without one or other of these qualifications, viz., either title or fortune, or, what is equivalent to both, the honourable profession of gamester. And, very unluckily for the world, persons so qualified very seldom care to take upon themselves the bad trade of writing; which is generally entered upon by the lower and poorer sort, as it is a trade which many think requires no kind of store to set up with.”

As soon as circumstances permitted, the Dickenses moved into a new house in a more fashionable quarter, and ordered from firms of repute complete suites for the reception rooms and bedrooms. Thick pile carpets were laid on the floors and festooned curtains adorned the windows. They engaged a good cook, three maids and a manservant. They set up a carriage. They gave dinner parties, to which noble and distinguished people came. The profusion somewhat shocked Jane Carlyle, and Lord Jeffrey wrote to his friend, Lord Cockburn, that he had dined in the new house and had“a rather too sumptuous dinner for a man with a family and only beginning to be rich.”It was part of the generosity of Dickens's spirit that he liked to surround himself with people and, after the meanness of his origins, it is only natural that it should have pleased him to be lavish. But it cost money. His father, and his father's family, his wife's family, were a constant drain on him. It was partly to meet his heavy expenses that he founded the first of his magazines, Master Humphrey's Clock, and to give it a good send-off published The Old Curiosity Shop in it.

In 1842, leaving the four children in the care of Georgina Hogarth, Kate's sister, but taking Kate with him, he went to America. He was lionized as no author has ever been before or since. But the trip was not a complete success. A hundred years ago, the people of the United States, though ready enough to disparage things European, were exceedingly sensitive of any criticism of themselves. A hundred years ago, the press of the United States was ruthless in its invasion of the privacy of any hapless person who was“news.”A hundred years ago, in the United States the publicity-minded looked upon the distinguished foreigner as a God-given opportunity to get into the limelight, and called him conceited and supercilious, when he showed a disinclination to be treated like a monkey in a zoo. A hundred years ago, the United States was a land where speech was free, so long as it did not offend the susceptibilities or affect the interests of other people, and where everyone was entitled to his own opinions, so long as they agreed with those of everyone else. Of all this Charles Dickens was ignorant, and he made bad blunders. The absence of an International Copyright not only deprived English authors of any profit in the United States from the sale of their books, but also damaged American authors, since the booksellers very naturally preferred to publish books by English authors, which they could get for nothing, rather than books by American authors for which they had to pay. But it was tactless of Dickens to introduce the subject in the speeches he made at the banquets given for him on his arrival. The reaction was violent, and the newspapers described him as“no gentleman, but a mercenary scoundrel.”Though he was mobbed by admirers, and at Philadelphia shook hands for two hours with the crowd who wanted to meet him, his rings and diamond pins, his gaudy waistcoats, excited a good deal of criticism, and there were some who found his behaviour far from well-bred. But he was natural and unpretending, and few in the end could resist his youth, comely looks and gaiety. He made some good friends, with whom he remained on affectionate terms till his death.

The Dickenses returned to England after four eventful, but exhausting, months. The children had grown attached to their Aunt Georgina, and the weary travellers asked her to make her home with them. She was sixteen, the age of Mary when she went to live at Furnival's Inn with the newly-married couple, and so like her that from a distance she might have been taken for her. The resemblance was so strong“that when she and Kate and I are sitting together, ”wrote Dickens, “I seem to think that what has happened is a melancholy dream from which I am just awakening.”Georgy was pretty, attractive and unassuming. She had a gift of mimicry by means of which she could make Dickens roar with laughter. In course of time, he came to depend more and more on her. They took long walks together, and he discussed his literary plans with her. He found her a useful and reliable amanuensis. The style of living Dickens had adopted was expensive, and soon he found himself uncomfortably in debt. He decided to let his house and take his family, including Georgy of course, to Italy, where living was cheap and he could retrench. He spent a year there, chiefly at Genoa, and though he did a good deal of sightseeing up and down the country, he was too insular, and his culture too tenuous, for the experience to have any spiritual effect on him. He remained the typical British tourist. But having discovered how pleasant (and economical) it was to live abroad, Dickens began to spend long periods on the Continent. Georgy, as one of the family, went with them. On one occasion, when they were going to settle in Paris for a considerable time, she went there alone with Charles to find an apartment, while Kate waited in England till they had made everything ready for her.

Kate was of a placid and melancholy disposition. She was not adaptable, and liked neither the journeys Charles took her on, the parties she went to with him, nor the parties at which she acted as hostess. She was clumsy, colourless and rather stupid, it would appear; and it is likely enough that the great and important persons, who were eager to enjoy the celebrated author's company, found it a nuisance to have to put up with his dull wife. Some of them, to her annoyance, persistently treated her as a cipher. It is not easy to be the wife of a distinguished man. She is unlikely to make a good job of it, unless she has tact and a lively sense of humour. In default of these, she must love her husband, and sufficiently admire him to find it natural that people should be more interested in him than in her. She must be clever enough to find solace in the fact that he loves her and, whatever his intellectual infidelities may be, in the end returns to her for comfort and reassurance. Kate does not appear ever to have been in love with Dickens. There is a letter he wrote to her during their engagement in which he reproaches her for her coldness. It may be that she married him because at that time marriage was the only occupation open to a woman, or it may be that, as the eldest of eight daughters, some pressure was put upon her by her parents to embrace an offer that provided for her future. She was a kindly, gentle little thing, but incapable of meeting the claims which her husband's eminence made on her. In fifteen years she gave birth to ten children, and had four miscarriages. During her pregnancies, Georgy accompanied Dickens on the jaunts he was fond of taking, went to parties with him, and increasingly presided at his table in Kate's place. One would have expected Kate to resent the situation: we do not know that she did.

4

The years passed. In 1857 Charles Dickens was forty-five. Of his nine surviving children, the elder ones were grown up, the youngest was five. His reputation was world-wide and he was the most popular author in England. He was influential. He lived, as greatly appealed to his theatrical instincts, in the public eye. Some years before, he had made the acquaintance of Wilkie Collins, and the acquaintance quickly ripened into a close friendship. Collins was twelve years younger than Dickens. Mr. Edgar Johnson thus writes of him: “He loved rich food, champagne and music halls; he was often involved in intricate tangles with several women at once; he was amusing, cynical, good-humoured, unrestrained to the point of vulgarity.”For Dickens, Wilkie Collins stood, again quoting Mr. Johnson, “for fun and freedom.”They travelled about England together and went to Paris to have a lark. It is likely enough that Dickens took the opportunity, as many a man in his place would do, to have a little flutter with any young person of easy virtue who was at hand. Kate had not given him all he expected, and for a long time he had been increasingly dissatisfied with her.“She is amiable and complying, ”he wrote, “but nothing on earth would make her understand me.”From early in their marriage she had been jealous of him. I suspect he found the scenes she made him easier to bear when he knew that she had no reason to be jealous, than later when she surely had. He persuaded himself then that she had never suited him. He had developed, but she had remained what she was at the beginning. Dickens was convinced that he had nothing to reproach himself with. He was assured that he had been a good father, and had done everything possible for his children. The fact is that, though none too pleased at having to provide for so many, for which he seems to have thought that Kate alone was to blame, he liked them well enough when they were small; but as they grew up, he somewhat lost interest in them, and at a suitable age packed the boys off to remote parts of the world. It is true that they were scarcely a promising lot.

But it is likely that, but for an unforeseen accident, nothing very much would have changed the relations between Dickens and his wife. Like many another uncongenial couple, they might have drifted apart, and yet to the world retained a semblance of unity. Dickens fell in love. He had, as I have said, a passion for the stage, and on more than one occasion had given amateur performances of one play or another for charitable purposes. At the time with which I am now dealing, he was asked to give some performances in Manchester of a play, The Frozen Deep, which Wilkie Collins had written with his help, and which had been performed at Devonshire House with great success before the Queen, the Prince Consort and the King of the Belgians. But when he agreed to repeat the play at Manchester, since he did not think his daughters, who had taken the girls’ parts before, would be heard in a big theatre, he decided that their parts should be acted by professionals. A young woman called Ellen Ternan was engaged for one of them. She was eighteen. She was small and fair, and her eyes were blue. The rehearsals took place in Dickens's house, and he directed the play. He was flattered by Ellen's adoring attitude and by her pathetic desire to please him. Before the rehearsals were over, he was in love with her. He gave her a bracelet, which by mistake was delivered to his wife, and she naturally made him a scene. Charles seems to have adopted the attitude of injured innocence which a husband, in such an awkward juncture, finds it most convenient to adopt. The play was produced, and he played the leading part, that of a self-sacrificing arctic explorer, with such pathos that there was not a dry eye in the house. He had grown a beard to play it.

The relations between Dickens and his wife grew more and more tense. He, who had always been so genial, so good-humoured, so easy to get on with, now was moody, restless and out of temper with everyone—but Georgy. He was very unhappy. At last he came to the conclusion that he could live with Kate no longer; but his position with the public was such that he was fearful of the scandal that an open break might cause. His anxiety is comprehensible. By his immensely profitable Christmas Books he had done more than anyone to make Christmas the symbolic festival to celebrate the domestic virtues, and the beauty of a united and happy family life. For years he had assured his readers in moving terms that there was no place like home. The situation was delicate. Various suggestions were made. One was that Kate should have her own suite of rooms apart from his, act as hostess at his parties and accompany him to public functions. Another was that she should stay in London while he was at Gad's Hill (a house in Kent Dickens had recently bought), and stay at Gad's Hill when he was in London. A third was that she should settle abroad. All these proposals she rejected, and finally a complete separation was decided on. Kate was installed in a little house on the edge of Camden Town with an income of six hundred a year. A little later, Dickens's eldest son, Charles, went to live with her for a period.

The arrangement is surprising. One cannot but wonder why, placid as she was and stupid as she may have been, Kate allowed herself to be driven from her own house, and why she consented to leave her children behind. She knew of Charles's infatuation with Ellen Ternan, and one would have supposed that, with this trump-card in her hand, she could have made what terms she chose. In one of his letters Dickens refers to a“weakness”of Kate's, and in another letter, unfortunately published at the time, he alludes to a mental disorder“which caused his wife to think that she would be better away.”It is generally believed that these were discreet references to the fact that Kate drank. It would not be strange if her jealousy, her sense of inadequacy, the mortification of feeling that she was not wanted, had driven her to the bottle. If she was become a confirmed alcoholic, it would explain why Georgy should have managed the house and looked after the children, why they should have remained at home when their mother left it, why Georgy could write that“Poor Kate's incapacity for looking after children was no secret to anyone.”It may be that her eldest son went to live with her to see that she did not tipple over much.

Dickens was far too celebrated for his private affairs not to give rise to gossip. Scandalous rumours were spread abroad. He heard that the Hogarths, Kate's and Georgy's mother and sister, were saying that Ellen Ternan was his mistress. He was furious and forced them, by threatening to turn Kate out of her house without a penny, to sign a declaration that they did not believe there was anything reprehensible in his relations with the little actress. The Hogarths took a fortnight before they could bring themselves to be thus blackmailed. They must have known that, if he carried out his threat, Kate could go to law with a cast-iron case; if they dared not let things go to such lengths, it can surely only have been because there were faults on Kate's side which they were unwilling to have divulged. There was also a good deal of talk about Georgy. She is, indeed, the enigmatic figure in the whole affair. I wonder that no one has been tempted to make her the central figure of a play. Earlier in this chapter I remarked on the significance of what Dickens wrote in his diary after Mary's death. This made it clear, it seemed to me, not only that he had been in love with her, but was already dissatisfied with Kate. And when Georgy came to live with them, he was charmed with her because of her astonishing resemblance to Mary. Did he then fall in love with her too? Did she love him? No one can tell. Georgy was jealous enough of Kate to cut out all sentences in praise of her when, after Charles's death, she edited a selection of his letters; but the attitude of Church and State towards marriage with a deceased wife's sister had given any connection of the sort an incestuous aspect, and it may never have entered her head that there could be more between herself and the man in whose house she had lived for fifteen years than the fond affection a sister might ligitimately feel for a brother by blood. Perhaps it was enough for her to be in the confidence of so famous a man, and to have established a complete ascendancy over him. The strangest part of it all is that when Charles fell passionately in love with Ellen Ternan, Georgy made a friend of her and welcomed her at Gad's Hill. Whatever she felt, she kept to herself.

The connection between Charles Dickens and Ellen Ternan was dealt with, by those in a position to know, so discreetly that the details are uncertain. It seems that she resisted his advances for some time, but in the end yielded to his insistence. It is believed that under the name of Charles Tringham he took a house for her at Peckham, and there she lived till his death. According to his daughter Katie, he had a son by her; since nothing more was heard of him it is presumed that he died in infancy. But Ellen's surrender, it is said, did not bring Dickens the radiant bliss he expected; he was more than twenty-five years older than she was, and he could not but have known that she was not in love with him. Few pains are harder to bear than those of an unrequited passion. He left her a thousand pounds in his will, and she married a parson. She told a clerical friend, a certain Canon Benham, that she“loathed the very thought of the intimacy”Dickens had forced upon her. Like many another member of the gentle sex, she seems to have been ready enough to accept the perquisites of her position, but saw no reason why she should be asked to give anything in return.

At about the time of the break with his wife, Dickens began to give readings of his work, and for this purpose travelled over the British Isles and again went to the United States. His histrionic gift served him well, and his success was spectacular. But the effort he exerted, and the constant journeys, wore him out, and people began to notice that, though still in his forties, he looked an old man. These readings were not his only activity: during the twelve years between the separation and his death he wrote three long novels and conducted an immensely popular magazine called All the Year Round. It is not surprising that his health failed. He began to suffer from tiresome ailments, and it was evident that the lectures were wearing him out. He was advised to give them up, but he wouldn’t; he loved the publicity, the excitement that attended his appearances, the face-to-face applause, the thrill of power that he felt as he swayed an audience to his will. And is it not just possible that he felt it might make Ellen fonder of him when she saw the adulation of the crowds that thronged his lectures? He decided to make a final tour, but was taken so ill in the middle of it that he had to abandon it. He went back to Gad's Hill and sat down to write The Mystery of Edwin Drood. But to make up to his managers for the readings he had had to cut short, he arranged to give twelve more in London. This was in January 1870.“The audiences at St. James's Hall were immense and sometimes they rose and cheered in a body as he entered and when he left.”Back at Gad's Hill, he resumed work on his novel. One day in June, while he was dining alone with Georgy, he was taken ill. She sent for the doctor, and for his two daughters who were in London, and next day the younger one, Katie, was despatched by her resourceful and competent aunt to break the news to his wife that he was dying. Katie returned to Gad's Hill with Ellen Ternan. He died the day after, June 9, 1870, and was buried in Westminster Abbey.

5

In a famous essay, Matthew Arnold insists that poetry to be truly excellent must have a high seriousness, and because he finds it lacking in Chaucer, refuses him, though praising him handsomely, a place among the greatest poets. Arnold was too austere not to look upon humour without a faint misgiving, and I don’t suppose he could ever have been brought to admit that there might be as high a seriousness in Rabelais’ laughter as in Milton's desire to justify the works of God to man. But I see his point, and it does not apply only to poetry. It may be that it is because this high seriousness is lacking in Dickens's novels that, for all their great merits, they leave us faintly dissatisfied. When we read them now with the great French and Russian novels in mind, and not only theirs, but George Eliot's, we are taken aback by their naiveté. In comparison with them, Dickens's are scarcely adult. But, of course, we must remember that we do not read the novels he wrote. We have changed, and they have changed with us. It is impossible for us to recapture the emotions with which his contemporaries read them, as they came hot from the press. In this connection, I will quote a passage from Una Pope-Hennessy's book: “Mrs. Henry Siddons, a neighbour and friend of Lord Jeffrey, peeped into his library and saw Jeffrey with his head on the table. He raised it with his eyes suffused with tears. She begged to be excused, saying, ‘I had no idea that you had any bad news or cause of grief or I would not have come. Is anyone dead?’‘Yes, indeed, ’ replied Lord Jeffrey.‘I’m a great goose to have given away so, but I could not help it. You’ll be sorry to hear that little Nelly, Boz's little Nelly is dead.’”Jeffrey was a Scottish judge, a founder of The Edinburgh Review and a severe, caustic critic.

For my part, Ifind myself still immensely amused by Dickens's humour, but his pathos leaves me cold. I am inclined to say that he had strong emotions, but no heart. I hasten to qualify that. He had a generous heart, a passionate sympathy with the poor and oppressed, and as we know, he took a persistent and effective interest in social reform. But it was an actor's heart, by which I mean that he could feel intensely an emotion that he wished to depict in the same way as an actor playing a tragic part can feel the emotion he represents.“What's Hecuba to him or he to Hecuba?”Here I am reminded of something an actress, at one time in Sarah Bernhardt's Company, told me many years ago. The great artist was playing Phèdre and, in the midst of one of her most moving speeches, when to all appearance she was distraught with anguish, she became aware that some persons standing in one of the wings were loudly talking; she moved towards them and, turning away from the audience as though in her misery to hide her face, hissed out what was the French equivalent to: Stop that bloody row, you lousy bastards; and then, turning back with a magnificent gesture of woe, went on with her tirade to its impressive end. The audience had noticed nothing. It is hard to believe that she could have given expression so noble and tragic to the words she had to utter unless she had truly felt them; but her emotion was a professional emotion, skin-deep, an affair of nerves rather than of heart which had no effect on her self-possession. I have no doubt that Dickens was sincere, but it was an actor's sincerity; and that, perhaps, is why now, no matter how he piled up the agony, we feel that his pathos was not quite genuine and so are no longer moved by it.

But we have no right to ask of an author more than he can give, and if Dickens lacked that high seriousness which Matthew Arnold demanded of the greatest poets, he had much else. He was a very great novelist. He had enormous gifts. He thought David Copperfield the best of all his books. An author is not always a good judge of his own work, but in this case Dickens's judgment seems to me correct. David Copperfield, as I suppose everyone knows, is in great part autobiographical; but Dickens was writing a novel, not an autobiography, and though he drew much of his material from his own life, he made only such use of it as suited his purpose. For the rest, he fell back on his vivid imagination. He was never much of a reader, literary conversation bored him, and such acquaintance with literature as he made later in life seems to have had little effect in lessening the very strong impressions he had received from the works he first read as a boy at Chatham. Of these it was, I think, the novels of Smollett that in the long run chiefly influenced him. The figures Smollett presents to the reader are not so much larger than life as more highly coloured. They are“humours”rather than characters.

So to see people well suited the idiosyncrasy of Dickens's temper. Mr. Micawber was drawn from his father. John Dickens was grandiloquent in speech and shifty in money matters, but he was no fool and far from incompetent; he was industrious, kindly and affectionate. We know what Dickens made of him. If Falstaff is the greatest comic character in literature, Mr. Micawber is the greatest but one. Dickens has been blamed, to my mind unjustly, for making him end up as a respectable magistrate in Australia, and some critics have thought that he should have remained reckless and improvident to the end. Australia was a sparsely settled country. Mr. Micawber was a man of fine presence, of some education and of flamboyant address; I do not see why, in that environment and with those advantages, he should not have attained official position. But it was not only in his creation of comic characters that Dickens was masterly. Steerforth's smooth servant is admirably drawn; he has a mysterious, sinister quality which sends cold shivers down one's back. Uriah Heep smacks of what used to be called transpontine melodrama; but for all that he is a powerful, horrifying figure, and he is most skilfully presented. Indeed, David Copperfield is filled with characters of the most astonishing variety, vividness and originality. There never were such people as the Micawbers, Peggotty and Barkis, Traddles, Betsy Trotwood and Mr. Dick, Uriah Heep and his mother: they are the fantastic inventions of Dickens's exultant imagination; but they have so much vigour, they are so consistent, they are presented with so much verisimilitude and with so much conviction, that while you read, you cannot but believe in them. They may not be real; they are very much alive.

Dickens's general method of creating character was to exaggerate the traits, peculiarities, foibles of his models and to put into the mouth of each one some phrase, or string of phrases, which stamped his quintessence on the reader's mind. He never showed the development of characters and, on the whole, what his creatures were at the beginning they remain at the end. (There are in Dickens's work one or two exceptions, but the change of nature he has indicated is highly unconvincing; it is occasioned to bring about a happy ending.) The danger of drawing character in this way is that the limits of plausibility may be exceeded, and the result is caricature. Caricature is all very well when the author presents you with a character at whom you can laugh, as you can at Mr. Micawber, but it will not serve when he expects you to sympathize. Dickens was never particularly successful with his female characters unless, like Mrs. Micawber, with her“I will never desert Mr. Micawber, ”and Betsy Trotwood, they were caricatured. Dora, drawn after Dickens's first love, Maria Beadnell, is too silly and too childish; Agnes, drawn after Mary and Georgy Hogarth, is too good and too sensible: they are both fearfully tiresome. Little Em’ly seems to me a failure. Dickens evidently meant us to feel pity for her: she only got what she asked for. Her ambition was to be a“lady, ”and in the hope, presumably, that she would be able to get Steerforth to marry her, she ran away with him. She seems to have made him a most unsatisfactory mistress, sullen, tearful and sorry for herself; and it is no wonder that he grew tired of her. The most baffling female character in David Copperfield is Rosa Dartle. I suspect that Dickens meant to make greater use of her in his story than he did, and if he did not do so, it was because he feared to offend his public. I can only suppose that Steerforth had been her lover and she hated him because he had abandoned her, but notwithstanding, loved him still with a jealous, hungry, vindictive love. Dickens here invented a character that Balzac would have made much of. Of the leading actors in David Copperfield, Steerforth is the only one that is drawn“straight, ”using the word as actors do when they speak of a“straight part.”Dickens has given the reader an admirable impression of Steerforth's charm, grace and elegance, his friendliness, his kindliness, his amiable gift of being able to get on with all kinds of people, his gaiety, his courage, his selfishness, his unscrupulousness, his recklessness, his callousness. He has drawn here a portrait of the sort of man that most of us have known, who gives delight wherever he goes and leaves disaster behind him. Dickens brought him to a bad end. Fielding, I think, would have been more lenient; for, as Mrs. Honour, speaking of Tom Jones, put it: “And when wenches are so coming, young men are not so much to be blamed neither; for to be sure they do no more than what is natural.”To-day, the novelist is under the necessity of making the events he relates not only likely, but so far as possible inevitable. Dickens was under no such constraint. That Steerforth, coming from Portugal by sea after an absence from England of some years, should be wrecked and drowned in sight of Yarmouth just when David Copperfield had gone there on a brief visit to his old friends, is a coincidence that really puts too great a strain on the reader's credulity. If Steerforth had to die in order to satisfy the Victorian demand that vice should be punished, Dickens might surely have thought of a more plausible way of bringing this about.

6

It was a misfortune for English literature that Keats died too soon and Wordsworth too late; it was a misfortune almost as serious that, just at the time when the greatest novelists our country has produced were in full possession of their gifts, the methods of publication then prevalent encouraged, to the detriment of their production, the tendency to diffuseness and prolixity and digression to which by their nature English novelists have for the most part been inclined. The Victorian novelists were working men who lived by their pen. They had to accept contracts to provide a definite amount of copy for eighteen, twenty or twenty-four numbers, and they had so to arrange their narrative as to end each number in such a way as to induce the reader to buy the following one. They doubtless had in mind the main lines of the story they set out to tell, but we know that they were satisfied if they had two or three numbers written before publication started. They wrote the rest as they were needed, trusting that their invention would provide them with enough material to fill the requisite number of pages; and we know, from their own admissions, that on occasion their invention failed them and they had to make the best job they could when they had nothing to write about. Sometimes it happened that their story was finished when there were perhaps two or three numbers still to be written, and then they had to use any device they could think of to delay the conclusion. Naturally their novels were shapeless and long-winded; they were forced to digression and prolixity.

Dickens wrote David Copperfield in the first person. This straightforward method served him well, since his plots were often complicated, and the reader's interest was sometimes diverted to characters and incidents that have no bearing on the story's course. In David Copperfield there is only one major digression of this kind, and that is the account of Dr. Strong's relations with his wife, his mother and his wife's cousin; it does not concern David and is in itself tedious. I surmise that he used this episode to cover on two occasions a lapse of time which otherwise he didn’t know what to do with: the first was the years that David spent at school at Canterbury, and the second was the period between David's disappointment with Dora and her death.

Dickens did not escape the danger that confronts the author of a semi-biographical novel in which himself is the principal character. David Copperfield at the age of ten was put to work by his stern stepfather, as Charles Dickens was by his father, and suffered from the“degradation”of having to mix with boys of his own age, whom he did not consider his social equals, in the same way as Dickens, in the fragment of autobiography which he gave to Forster, persuaded himself that he had suffered. Dickens did all he could to excite the reader's sympathy for his hero, and indeed, on the celebrated journey to Dover, when David ran away in order to seek the protection of his aunt Betsy Trotwood, a delightful, amusing character, he loads his dice without scruple. Innumerable readers have found the narration of this escapade wonderfully pathetic. I am made of sterner stuff. I am surprised that the little boy should have been such a ninny as to let everyone he came across rob and cheat him. After all, he had been in the factory for some months and had wandered about London early and late; one would have thought that the other boys at the factory, even though they were not up to his social standard, would have taught him a thing or two; he had lived with the Micawbers and pawned their bits and pieces for them, and had visited them at the Marshalsea: if he had really been the bright boy he is described to be, even at that tender age he would surely have acquired some knowledge of the world and enough sharpness to fend for himself. But it is not only in his childhood that David Copperfield shows himself sadly incompetent. He is incapable of coping with a difficulty. His weakness with Dora, his lack of common sense in dealing with the ordinary problems of domestic life, are almost more than one can bear; and he is so obtuse that he does not guess that Agnes is in love with him. I cannot persuade myself that in the end he became the successful novelist we are told he did. If he wrote novels, I suspect that they were more like those of Mrs. Henry Wood than those of Charles Dickens. It is strange that his creator should have given him none of his own drive, vitality and exuberance. David was slim and good-looking; and he had charm, or he would not have attracted the affection of almost everyone he encountered; he was honest, kindly and conscientious; but he was surely a bit of a fool. He remains the least interesting person in the book. Nowhere does he show himself in so poor a light, so feckless, so incapable of dealing with an awkward situation, as in the monstrous scene between Little Em’ly and Rosa Dartle in the attic in Soho which David witnesses but, for the very flimsiest reason, makes no attempt to stop. This scene affords a good example of how the method of writing a novel in the first person may result in the narrator being forced into a position so shockingly false, so unworthy of a hero of fiction, that the reader is justly indignant with him. If described in the third person, from the standpoint of omniscience, the scene would still have been melodramatic and repellent, but, even though with difficulty, credible. But of course the pleasure one gets from reading David Copperfield does not arise from any persuasion one may have that life is, or ever was, anything like what Dickens describes. That is not to depreciate him. Fiction, like the kingdom of heaven, has many mansions, and the author may invite you to visit whichever he chooses. One has just as much right to exist as another, but you must suit yourselves to the surroundings into which you are led. You must put on different spectacles to read The Golden Bowl and to read Bubu de Montparnasse. David Copperfield is a fantastication, sometimes gay, sometimes pathetic, on life, composed out of recollections and wish-fulfilments by a man of lively imagination and warm feelings. You must read it in the same spirit as you read As You Like It. It provides an entertainment almost as delightful.

Emily Brontë and Wuthering Heights

1

Hugh Prunty, a young peasant-farmer in County Down, in 1776 married Elinor McClory; and on St. Patrick's Day in the following year, the eldest of his ten children was born and given the name of Ireland's patron saint. It looks as though he could neither read nor write, for he seems to have been uncertain how his name was spelt. In the baptismal register it is given as Brunty and Bruntee. The small-holding he farmed was insufficient to provide for his large family, and he worked in a lime-kiln and, when things were slack, as a labourer on the estate of one of the neighbouring gentry. It may be supposed that Patrick, his eldest son, did odd jobs about his father's bit of land till he was old enough to earn a wage. Then he became a hand-loom weaver. But he was a clever lad, and ambitious; and, somehow or other, by the time he was sixteen he had got enough education to become a teacher at a village school near his birthplace. Two years later he got a similar job at the parish school at Drumballyroney, and held it for eight years. There are two accounts of what happened then: one states that Methodist ministers, impressed by his ability and expecting him to train himself for the Ministry, subscribed a few pounds which, added to the little he had saved, enabled him to go to Cambridge; another states that he left the parish school to become a tutor in a clergyman's family, and it was with his help that he entered St. John's College. He was then twenty-five, old to enter a university, a tall, very strong young man, handsome and vain of his good looks. He subsisted on a scholarship, two exhibitions and what he was able to earn by coaching. He took his B.A. at the age of twenty-nine, and was ordained in the Church of England. If the Methodist ministers really helped him to go to Cambridge, they must have felt that they had made a bad investment.

It was while he was at Cambridge that Patrick Branty, as his surname is spelt in the list of admissions, changed it to Bronte, but it was not till later that he adopted the diæresis, and signed himself Patrick Brontë. He was appointed to a curacy at Withersfield in Essex and there fell in love with a Miss Mary Burder. She was eighteen and, though not rich, well off. They became engaged. For some reason that has remained obscure, Mr. Brontë jilted her, and it has been supposed that, having a good opinion of his advantages, he thought that by waiting he could do better for himself. Mary Burder was bitterly hurt. It may be that the handsome curate's behaviour caused a good deal of acid comment in the parish, for he left Withersfield and took a curacy at Wellington in Shropshire and, after a few months, another at Hartshead in Yorkshire. There he met a plain little woman of thirty called Maria Branwell. She had fifty pounds a year of her own and belonged to a respectable middle-class family; Patrick Brontë was thirty-five and perhaps thought that by then, notwithstanding his good looks and agreeable brogue, this was about as well as he could expect to do for himself. He proposed, was accepted and in 1812 the couple were married. While still at Hartshead Mrs. Brontë had two children, and they were named Maria and Elizabeth. Then Mr. Brontë was appointed to still another curacy, this time near Bradford, and here Mrs. Brontë had four more children. They were named Charlotte, Patrick Branwell, Emily and Anne. A year before his marriage, Mr. Brontë had published at his own expense a volume of verse entitled Cottage Poems, and a year after that another, The Rural Minstrel. While living near Bradford he wrote a novel, called The Cottage in the Wood. People who have read these productions say that they are devoid of merit. In 1820 Mr. Brontë was appointed to the“perpetual curacy”of Haworth, a Yorkshire village, and there he remained, his ambitions, one may suppose, satisfied, till his death. He never went back to Ireland to see the parents, brothers and sisters he had left there, but as long as she lived he sent his mother twenty pounds a year.

In 1821, after nine years of marriage, Maria Brontë died of cancer. The widower persuaded his sister-in-law, Elizabeth Branwell, to leave Penzance, where she lived, to come and look after his six children; but he wanted to marry again, and after a decent interval he wrote to Mrs. Burder, mother of the girl he had treated so ill fourteen years before, to enquire whether she was still single. After some weeks he received a reply and forthwith wrote to Mary herself. The letter is smug, self-complacent, unctuous and, considering the facts, in execrable taste. He had the impudence to say that his ancient love was rekindled and that he had a longing desire to see her. It was in effect a proposal of marriage. Her reply was stinging, but, undeterred, he wrote again. With amazing tactlessness he told her: “You may think and write as you please, but I have not the least doubt that if you had been mine you would have been happier than you now are, or can be as one in single life.”(The italics are his.) Having failed with Mary Burder, he turned his thoughts in another direction. It does not seem to have occurred to him that a widower of forty-five, with six young children, was no great catch. He made an offer to Miss Elizabeth Frith, whom he had known when he was a curate near Bradford, but she also refused him; upon which he seems to have given it up as a bad job. It was, at all events, something to be thankful for that Elizabeth Branwell was there to look after the house and take care of the children.

Haworth Parsonage was a small brownstone house on the brow of the steep hill down which the village straggled. There was a tiny strip of garden in front of it and behind, and, on either side, the graveyard. Biographers of the Brontës have thought this depressing, and to a doctor it might have been, but a clergyman may well have thought it an edifying and even consoling sight; anyhow, this particular clergyman's family must have grown so accustomed to it that in all probability they noticed it as little as the fisherman at Capri notices the view of Vesuvius or of Ischia in the setting sun. There was a parlour, a study for Mr. Brontë, a kitchen and a storeroom on the ground floor, and four bedrooms and a lobby on the floor above. There were no carpets, except in the parlour and the study, and no curtains to the windows because Mr. Brontë had the greatest dread of fire. The floors and the stairs were of stone, cold and damp in winter, and Miss Branwell, for fear of catching cold, always went about the house in pattens. A narrow pathway led from the house to the moor. With the idea, perhaps barely conscious, of making the story of the Brontës more poignant, it has been customary for authors to write as though it were always bleak, bitter cold and dreary at Haworth. But of course, even in winter there were days of blue sky and brilliant sunshine, when the frosty air was invigorating, and meadows, moor and woods were painted in the tender colours of pastel. On such a day I went to Haworth. The countryside was bathed in a haze of silver-grey so that the distance, its outlines dim, was mysterious. The leafless trees had the elegance of trees in a wintry scene in a Japanese print, and the hawthorn hedges by the roadside glistened white with hoar frost. Emily's poems and Wuthering Heights tell you how thrilling the spring was on the moor, and how rich in beauty and how sensuous in summer.

Mr. Brontë walked long and far on the moor. In his old age he boasted that he had been able to walk forty miles a day. He was a man who shunned company—somewhat of a change, for as a curate he had been a social creature, fond of parties and flirtations; and, with the exception of the neighbouring parsons who sometimes came down the hills to drink a dish of tea, he saw no one but the church-wardens and his parishioners. If these sent for him he went to see them, and if they asked a service he was glad to do it, but he and his family“kept themselves very close.”He, the son of a poverty-stricken Irish peasant, would not let his children associate with the village children, and they were driven to sit in the cold little lobby on the first floor, which was their study, reading or whispering low in order not to disturb their father, who, when annoyed or displeased, maintained a sullen silence. He gave them their lessons in the morning, and Miss Branwell taught them sewing and housework.

Even before his wife's death, Mr. Brontë had taken to having his meals in his study by himself, and this habit he retained for the rest of his life. The reason given for this is that he suffered from indigestion. Emily wrote in a diary: “We are going to have for dinner boiled beef, turnips, potatoes and apple pudding.”And in 1846 Charlotte wrote from Manchester: “Papa requires nothing you know but plain beef and mutton, tea and bread and butter.”This does not seem a very good régime for someone who suffers from chronic dyspepsia. I am inclined to think that if Mr. Brontë took his meals by himself, it was because he did not much care for the company of his children and was irritable when they interrupted him. At eight o’clock at night he read family prayers, and at nine locked and barred the front door. As he passed the room in which his children were sitting, he told them not to sit up late and, halfway up the stairs, stopped to wind the clock.

Mrs. Gaskell knew Mr. Brontë for several years, and the conclusion she came to was that he was selfish, irascible and domineering; and Mary Taylor, one of Charlotte's intimate friends, wrote to another of her friends, Ellen Nussey: “I can never think without gloomy anger of Charlotte's sacrifices to the selfish old man.”Of late, attempts have been made to whitewash him. But no whitewashing can get over the letters he wrote to Mary Burder. They are published in full in Clement Shorter's The Brontës and their Circle. Nor can whitewashing get over his behaviour when his curate, Mr. Nicholls, proposed to Charlotte. I will come to that later. Mrs. Gaskell writes as follows: “Mrs. Brontë's nurse told me that one day when the children had been on the moors, and rain had come on, she thought they would be wet, and accordingly she rummaged out some coloured boots which had been given them by a friend. These little pairs she ranged round the kitchen fire to warm; but when the children came back, the boots were nowhere to be found; only a very strong odour of burnt leather was perceived. Mr. Brontë had come in and seen them; they were too gay and luxurious for his children; so he had put them into the fire. He spared nothing that offended his antique simplicity. Long before this, someone had given Mrs. Brontë a silk gown; either the make, the colour, or the material was not according to his notions of consistent propriety, and Mrs. Brontë in consequence had never worn it. But, for all that, she kept it treasured up in her drawers, which were generally locked. One day, however, while in the kitchen, she remembered that she had left the key in her drawer, and hearing Mr. Brontë upstairs, she augured some ill of her dress, and, running up in haste, she found it cut into shreds.”The story is circumstantial, but it is hard to see why the nurse should have invented it.“Once he got the hearthrug, and stuffing it up the grate, deliberately set it on fire, and remained in the room in spite of the stench, until it had smouldered and shrivelled away into uselessness. Another time he took some chairs, and sawed away at the backs till they were reduced to the condition of stools.”It is only fair to add that Mr. Brontë declared that these stories were untrue. But no one had doubted that he had a violent temper, nor that he was stern and peremptory. I have asked myself whether these unamiable traits of Mr. Brontë's may not be ascribed to his disappointment with life. Like many another man of humble origins who has had a galling struggle to raise himself above the class in which he was born and to get an education, he may well have had an exaggerated opinion of his abilities. We know that he was vain of his good looks. His literary efforts had met with no success. It would not be strange if it embittered him to realize that the only reward he had got for his long tussle with adversity was a perpetual curacy in the wilds of Yorkshire.

The hardships and loneliness of life at the parsonage have been made too much of. The talented sisters seem to have been quite satisfied with it; and indeed, if they ever stopped to consider their father's origin, they may well have thought themselves far from unlucky. They were neither better nor worse off than hundreds of parsons’ daughters all over England, whose lives were as isolated and whose means as limited. The Brontës had neighbours, clergymen within walking distance, gentry, mill-owners and manufacturers in a small way, with whom they might have consorted; and if they lived secluded lives it was by choice. They were not rich, but neither were they poor. Mr. Brontë's benefice provided him with a house and two hundred pounds a year, his wife had fifty pounds a year which, on her death, he presumably inherited, and Elizabeth Branwell, when she came to live at Haworth, brought her fifty pounds a year with her. The household thus had three hundred pounds a year to dispose of, which at that time was worth at least twelve hundred pounds now. Many a clergyman to-day, even with income-tax as it is, would look upon such a sum as riches. Many a clergyman's wife to-day would be thankful to have one maid: the Brontës generally had two, and whenever there was pressure of work, girls were brought in from the village to help.

In 1824 Mr. Brontë took his four elder daughters to a school at Cowan Bridge. It had been recently established to give an education to the daughters of poor clergymen. The place was unhealthy, the food bad and the administration incompetent. The two elder girls died, and Charlotte and Emily, whose health was affected, were, fortunately for themselves, after a like while, removed. Such schooling as they got, from then on, seems to have been given them by their aunt. Mr. Brontë thought more of his son than of the three girls and, indeed, Branwell was looked upon as the clever one of the family. Mr. Brontë would not send him to school, but undertook his education himself. The boy had a precocious talent, and his manners were engaging. His friend, F. H. Grundy, thus describes him: “He was insignificantly small—one of his life's trials. He had a mass of red hair, which he wore brushed high off his forehead—to help his height, I fancy—a great, bumpy, intellectual forehead, nearly half the size of the whole facial contour; small ferrety eyes, deep sunk and still further hidden by the never removed spectacles, prominent nose, but weak lower features. He had a downcast look, which never varied, save for a rapid momentary glance at long intervals. Small and thin of person, he was the reverse of attractive at first sight.”He had parts, and his sisters admired him and expected him to do great things. He was a brilliant, eager talker, and from some Irish ancestor, for his father was a morose, silent man, he had inherited a gift for social intercourse and an agreeable loquacity. When a traveller, putting up for the night at the Black Bull, seemed lonely, the landlord would ask him: “Do you want someone to help you with your bottle, sir? If so, I’ll send up for Patrick.”Branwell was always glad to be of service. I should add that when years later, Charlotte Brontë then being famous, the landlord was asked about this, he denied that he had ever done anything of the kind: “Branwell, ”he said, “never needed to be sent for.”You are still shown at Haworth the room at the Black Bull, with its windsor chairs, in which Branwell tippled with his friends.

When Charlotte was just under sixteen, she went to school once more, this time at Roe Head, and was happy there; but after a year she came home again to teach her two younger sisters. Though the family, as I have pointed out, were not so poor as has been made out, the girls had nothing to look forward to. Mr. Brontë's stipend would naturally cease at his death, and Miss Branwell was leaving the little money she had to her amusing nephew; they decided, therefore, that the only way they could earn a living was by training themselves to be governesses or school-mistresses. At that time there was no other calling open to women who looked upon themselves as ladies. Branwell, by now, was eighteen and a decision had to be made on what trade or profession he was to adopt. He had some facility for drawing, as his sisters had too, and he was eager to become a painter. It was settled that he should go to London and study at the Royal Academy. He went, but nothing came of the project, and after a while, which he spent in sightseeing and presumably having as good a time as he could, he returned to Haworth. He tried writing, but with no success; then he persuaded his father to set him up in a studio in Bradford where he might earn a living by painting portraits of the local people; but this failed too, and Mr. Brontë called him home. Then he became tutor to a Mr. Postlethwaite at Barrow-in-Furness. He seems to have done well enough there, but, for reasons unknown, after six months Mr. Brontë brought him back to Haworth. Presently, a job was found for him as clerk-in-charge at the station of Sowerby Bridge on the Leeds and Manchester Railway, and later at Luddenden Foot. He was bored and lonely, he drank too much, and eventually was discharged for gross neglect of his duties. Meanwhile, in 1835, Charlotte had returned to Roe Head as a teacher, and taken Emily with her as a pupil. But Emily became so desperately homesick that she fell ill, and had to be sent home. Anne, who was of a calmer, more submissive temper, took her place. Charlotte held her job for three years, at the end of which, her health failing, she too went home.

She was twenty-two. Branwell was not only a source of worry, but a source of expense; and Charlotte, as soon as she was well enough, felt herself obliged to take a situation as a nursery governess. It was not work she liked. Neither she nor her sisters liked children, any more than their father did.“Ifind it so hard to repel the rude familiarity of children, ”she wrote to Ellen Nussey. She hated to be in a dependent position, and was continually on the lookout for affronts. She was not an easy person to get on with, and so far as one can judge from her letters, seems to have expected to be asked to do as a favour what her employers quite naturally thought they could demand as a right. She left after three months and returned to the parsonage, but some two years later took another situation with a Mr. and Mrs. White at Rawdon, near Bradford. Charlotte did not think them refined.“Well can I believe that Mrs. W. has been an exciseman's daughter, and I am convinced also that Mr. W.'s extraction is very low.”She was, however, fairly happy in this place, but, as she wrote to the same intimate friend: “No one but myself can tell how hard a governess's life is to me—for no one but myself is aware how utterly averse my whole mind and nature are for the employment.”She had long been toying with the idea of keeping a school of her own, with her two sisters, and now she took it up again; the Whites, who seem to have been very kind, decent people, encouraged her, but suggested that before she could hope to be successful she must acquire certain qualifications. Though she could read French, she could not speak it, and knew no German, so she decided that she must go abroad to learn languages. Miss Branwell was persuaded to advance money for the cost of this; and then Charlotte and Emily, with Mr. Brontë to look after them on the journey, set out for Brussels. The two girls, Charlotte being then twenty-six, Emily twenty-two, became pupils at the Pensionnat Héger. After ten months they were recalled to England by the illness of Miss Branwell. She died, and having disinherited Branwell, owing to his bad behaviour, left the little she had to her nieces. It was enough for them to carry out the plan they had so long discussed of having a school of their own; but since their father was old and his sight failing, they made up their minds to set it up at the parsonage. Charlotte did not think she was sufficiently equipped, and so accepted Monsieur Héger's offer to go back to Brussels and teach English at his school. She spent a year there and on her return to Haworth the three sisters issued prospectuses, and Charlotte wrote to her friends asking them to recommend the school they intended to start. How they expected to house pupils in the parsonage which had only four bedrooms, all of which they occupied themselves, has never been explained, and as no pupils came it certainly never will be.

2

They had been writing off and on since they were children, and in 1846 the three of them published a volume of verse at their own expense under the names of Currer, Ellis and Acton Bell. It cost them fifty pounds, and two copies were sold. Each of them then wrote a novel. Charlotte's (Currer Bell) was called The Professor, Emily's (Ellis Bell) Wuthering Heights and Anne's (Acton Bell) Agnes Grey. They were refused by publisher after publisher; but when Smith, Elder＆Co., to whom Charlotte's The Professor had finally been sent, returned it, they wrote to say that they would be glad to consider a longer novel by her. She was finishing one, and within a month was able to send it to the publishers. They accepted it. It was called Jane Eyre. Emily's novel, and Anne's, had also at last been accepted by a publisher, Newby by name, “on terms somewhat impoverishing to the two authors, ”and they had corrected the proofs before Charlotte sent Jane Eyre to Smith, Elder＆Co. Though the reviews of Jane Eyre were not particularly good, readers liked it and it became a best-seller. Mr. Newby, upon this, tried to persuade the public that Wuthering Heights and Agnes Grey, which he then published together in three volumes, were by the author of Jane Eyre. They made, however, no impression, and indeed were regarded by a number of critics as early and immature work by Currer Bell. Mr. Brontë had consented, after some persuasion, to read Jane Eyre. When he came in to tea, after finishing it, he said: “Girls, do you know Charlotte has been writing a book, and it is much better than likely?”

At the time of Miss Branwell's death, Anne was in a situation at Thorpe Green as governess to the children of a certain Mrs. Robinson. Her nature was sweet and gentle, and she was apparently better able to get on with people than the exacting and prickly Charlotte. She was not unhappy in her situation. She went back to Haworth for her aunt's funeral, and on her return to Thorpe Green took with her Branwell, then idling at home, as tutor to Mrs. Robinson's son. Mr. Edmund Robinson, a wealthy clergyman, was an elderly invalid with a youngish wife, and Branwell, though she was seventeen years older than he, fell in love with her. What their relations were is uncertain. Anyhow, whatever they were, they were discovered. Branwell was sent packing, and Mr. Robinson ordered him“never to see again the mother of his children, never set foot in her house, never write or speak to her.”Branwell“stormed, raved, swore he could not live without her; cried out against her for staying with her husband. Then prayed the sick man might die soon; they would yet be happy.”Branwell had always drunk too much; now in his distress he took to eating opium. It seems, however, that he was able to communicate with Mrs. Robinson, and, some months after his dismissal, they appear to have met at Harrogate.“It is said that she proposed flight together, ready to forfeit all her grandeur. It was Branwell who advised patience and a little longer waiting.”Since this can only have been told by Branwell himself, and is in any case very unlikely to be true, we may accept it as an invention of a young man who was both silly and conceited. Suddenly he received a letter to announce the death of Mr. Robinson; “he fair danced down the churchyard as if he was out of his mind; he was so fond of that woman, ”someone told Mary Robinson, Emily's biographer.

“The next morning he rose, dressed himself with care and prepared for a journey; but before he had even set out from Haworth, two men came riding to the village post-haste. They sent for Branwell and when he arrived, in a great state of excitement, one of the riders dismounted and went with him into the Black Bull.”He brought a message from the widow begging him not to come near her again, for if she even saw him once she would lose her fortune and the custody of her children. This is what he told, but since the letter was never produced and it has been discovered that Mr. Robinson's will contained no such clause, there is no knowing whether he told the truth. The only thing sure is that Mrs. Robinson let him know that she wanted to have nothing more to do with him, and it may be that she made up this excuse to render the blow less mortifying. The Brontë family were convinced that she had been Branwell's mistress, and ascribed his consequent behaviour to her evil influence. It is possible that she was, but it is just as possible that, like many a man before and after him, he boasted of a conquest he had never made. But if she had been for a brief period infatuated with him, there is no reason to suppose that it had ever entered her head to marry him. He proceeded to drink himself to death. When he knew the end was near, one who attended him in his last illness told Mrs. Gaskell that, wanting to stand up to die, he insisted upon getting up. He had only been in bed a day. Charlotte was so upset that she had to be led away, but her father, Anne and Emily looked on while he rose to his feet and after a struggle that lasted twenty minutes died, as he wished, standing.

Emily never went out of doors after the Sunday following his death. She had a cold and a cough. It grew worse, and Charlotte wrote to Ellen Nussey: “I fear she has pain in the chest, and I sometimes catch a shortness in her breathing, when she has moved at all quickly. She looks very, very thin and pale. Her reserved nature causes me great uneasiness of mind. It is useless to question her; you get no answer. It is still more useless to recommend remedies; they are never adopted.”A week or two later, Charlotte wrote to another friend: “I would fain hope that Emily is a little better this evening, but it is difficult to ascertain this. She is a real stoic in illness; she neither seeks nor will accept sympathy. To put any questions, to offer any aid, is to annoy; she will not yield a step before pain or sickness till forced; not one of her ordinary avocations will she voluntarily renounce. You must look on and see her do what she is unfit to do, and not dare say a word…”One morning Emily got up as usual, dressed herself and began to sew; she was short of breath and her eyes were glazed, but she went on working. She grew steadily worse. She had always refused to see a doctor, but at last, at midday asked that one should be sent for. It was too late. At two she died.

Charlotte was at work on another novel, Shirley, but she put it aside to nurse Anne, who was attacked by what was then known as galloping consumption, the disease from which Branwell and Emily had died, and did not finish it till after the gentle creature's death only five months after Emily's. She went to London in 1849 and 1850, and was made much of; she was introduced to Thackeray and had her portrait painted by George Richmond. A Mr. James Taylor, a member of the firm of Smith, Elder, whom she described as a stern and abrupt little man, asked her to marry him, but she refused. Before that, two young clergymen had proposed to her, only to be rejected, and two or three curates, her father's or those of neigh bouring parsons, had shown her marked attention; but Emily discouraged suitors (her sisters called her the Major, because of the effective way she dealt with them), and her father disapproved, so that nothing had come of it. It was, however, a curate of her father's whom she at last married. This was the Rev. Arthur Nicholls. He went to Haworth in 1844. Writing to Ellen Nussey in that year, she said of him: “I cannot for my life see those interesting germs of goodness you discovered; his narrowness of mind always strikes me chiefly.”And, a couple of years later, she included him in her sweeping contempt of curates in general.“They regard me as an old maid, and I regard them, one and all, as highly uninteresting, narrow and unattractive specimens of the coarser sex.”Mr. Nicholls, an Irishman, went to Ireland on his holiday, and Charlotte wrote to her usual correspondent: “Mr. Nicholls is not yet returned. I am sorry to say that many of the parishioners express a desire that he should not trouble himself to recross the Channel.”

In 1852 Charlotte wrote a long letter to Ellen Nussey. She enclosed a note from Mr. Nicholls which, she said, “has left on my mind a feeling of deep concern…”“What papa has seen or guessed I will not inquire, though I may conjecture. He has irritably noticed all Mr. Nicholls's low spirits, all his threats of expatriation, all his symptoms of impaired health—noticed them with little sympathy and much indirect sarcasm. On Monday evening Mr. Nicholls was here to tea. I vaguely felt without clearly seeing, as without seeing I have felt for some time, the meaning of his constant looks, and strange feverish restraint. After tea I withdrew to the dining-room as usual. As usual Mr. Nicholls sat with papa till between eight and nine o’clock; I then heard him open the parlour door as if going. I expected the clash of the front door. He stopped in the passage; he tapped; like lightning it flashed on me what was coming. He entered; he stood before me. What his words were you can guess; his manner you can hardly realize, nor can I forget it. Shaking from head to foot, looking deadly pale, speaking low, vehemently, yet with difficulty, he made me for the first time feel what it costs a man to declare affection where he doubts response.

“The spectacle of one ordinarily so statue-like thus trembling, stirred, and overcome, gave me a kind of strange shock. He spoke of sufferings he had borne for months, of sufferings he could endure no longer, and craved leave for some hope. I could only entreat him to leave me then and promise a reply on the morrow. I asked him if he had spoken to papa. He said he dared not. I think I half led, half put him out of the room. When he was gone I immediately went to papa, and told him what had taken place. Agitation and anger disproportionate to the occasion ensued; if I had loved Mr. Nicholls, and had heard such epithets applied to him as were used, it would have transported me past my patience; as it was, my blood boiled with a sense of injustice. But papa worked himself into a state not to be tri fled with; the veins on his temples started up like whipcord, and his eyes became suddenly bloodshot. I made haste to promise that Mr. Nicholls should on the morrow have a distinct refusal.”

In another letter, dated three days later, Charlotte writes: “You ask how papa demeans himself to Mr. Nicholls. I only wish you were here to see papa in his present mood: you would know something of him. He just treats him with a hardness not to be bent, and a contempt not to be propitiated. The two have had no interview as yet; all has been done by letter. Papa wrote, I must say, a most cruel note to Mr. Nicholls on Wednesday.”She went on to say that her father thought“a little too much about his want of money; he says the match would be a degradation, that I should be throwing myself away, that he expects me, if I marry at all, to do very differently.”Mr. Brontë, in fact, behaved as badly as he had behaved years before to Mary Burder. Relations between Mr. Brontë and Mr. Nicholls grew so strained that the latter resigned his curacy. But his successors at Haworth did not give Mr. Brontë satisfaction, and Charlotte, at last exasperated by his complaints, told him that he had only himself to blame. He had only to let her marry Mr. Nicholls and all would be well. Papa continued“very, very hostile, bitterly unjust, ”but she saw and corresponded with Mr. Nicholls. They became engaged and in 1854 were married. She was then thirty-eight. She died in childbirth nine months later.

So the Rev. Patrick Brontë, having buried his wife, her sister and his six children, was left to eat his dinner alone in the solitude he liked, walk on the moors as far as his waning strength permitted, read the papers, preach his sermons and wind up the clock on his way to bed. There is a photograph of him in his old age. A man in a black suit with an immense white choker round his neck, with white hair cut short, a fine brow and a large straight nose, a tight mouth and ill-tempered eyes behind his spectacles. He died at Haworth at the age of eighty-four.

3

It is not without intention that in writing of Emily Brontë and Wuthering Heights, I have said so much more about her father, her brother and her sister Charlotte than about her; for in the books written about the family it is of them that we hear most. Emily and Anne hardly come into the picture. Anne was a gentle, pretty little thing, but insignificant; and her talent was small. Emily was very different. She is a strange, mysterious and shadowy figure. She is never seen directly, but reflected, as it were, in a moorland pool. You have to guess what sort of woman she was from her one novel, her poems, from an allusion here and there and from scattered anecdotes. She was aloof, an intense, uncomfortable creature; and when you hear of her given over to unrestrained gaiety, as on walks over the moor she sometimes was, it makes you uneasy. Charlotte had friends, Anne had friends, Emily had none. Her character was full of contradictions. She was harsh, dogmatic, self-willed, sullen, angry and intolerant; and she was pious, dutiful, hard-working, uncomplaining, tender to those she loved and patient.

Mary Robinson describes her at fifteen as“a tall, long-armed girl, full grown, elastic as to tread; with a slight figure that looked queenly in her best dresses, but loose and boyish when she slouched over the moors, whistling the dogs, and taking long strides over the rough earth. A tall, thin, loose-jointed girl—not ugly, but with irregular features and a pallid thick complexion. Her dark hair was naturally beautiful, and in later days looked well, loosely fastened with a tall comb at the back of her head; but in 1833 she wore it in an unbecoming tight curl and frizz. She had beautiful eyes of a hazel colour.”Like her father, her brother and her sisters, she wore spectacles. She had an aquiline nose and a large, expressive, prominent mouth. She dressed regardless of fashion, with leg-of-mutton sleeves long after they had ceased to be worn; in straight long skirts clinging to her lanky figure.

She went to Brussels with Charlotte. She hated it. Friends, wishing to be nice to the two girls, asked them to spend Sundays and holidays at their house, but they were so shy that to go was agony for them, and after a while their hosts came to the conclusion that it was kinder not to invite them. Emily had no patience with social small talk, which of course is for the most part trivial; it is merely an expression of general amiability, and people take part in it because they have good manners. Emily was too shy to take part in it and was irritated by those who did. There was in her shyness both diffidence and arrogance. If she was so retiring, it is strange that she should have made herself so conspicuous in her dress. The very shy not uncommonly have in them a streak of exhibitionism, and it may occur to one that she wore those absurd leg-of-mutton sleeves to flaunt her contempt for the commonplace people in whose company she was tongue-tied.

At school, during the hours of recreation, the two sisters always walked together, Emily leaning heavily on her sister, and generally in silence. When they were spoken to, Charlotte answered. Emily rarely spoke to anyone. They were both of them several years older than the rest of the girls, and they disliked their noisiness, their high spirits and the sillinesses natural to their age. Monsieur Héger found Emily intelligent, but so stubborn that she would listen to no reason when it interfered with her wishes or beliefs. He found her egotistical, exacting and, with Charlotte, tyrannical. But he recognized that there was something unusual in her. She should have been a man, he said: “Her strong, imperious will would never have been daunted by opposition or difficulty; never have given way but with life.”

When Emily went back to Haworth after Miss Branwell's death, it was for good. She never left it again. It looks as though only there was she able to live the reveries which were the solace and the torment of her life.

She got up in the morning before anyone else and did the roughest part of the day's work before Tabby, the maid, who was old and frail, came down. She did the household ironing and most of the cooking. She made the bread, and the bread was good. While kneading the dough, she would glance at the book propped up before her.“Those who worked with her in the kitchen, young girls called in to help in stress of business, remember how she would keep a scrap of paper, a pencil at her side, and how when the moment came that she could pause in her cooking or her ironing, she would jot down some impatient thought and then resume her work. With these girls she was always friendly and hearty—pleasant, sometimes quite jovial like a boy! So genial and kind, a little masculine, ‘say my informants, ’ but of strangers she was exceedingly timid, and if the butcher's boy or the baker's man came to the kitchen door she would be off like a bird into the hall or the parlour till she heard their hobnails clumping down the path.”She disliked men, and with one exception, was not even ordinarily polite to her father's curates; this was the Rev. William Weightman. He is described as young and fair, eloquent and witty; and there was about him“a certain girlishness of looks, manner and taste.”He was known in the family as Miss Celia Amelia. Emily got on famously with him. It is not difficult to know why. May Sinclair, in her book called The Three Brontës, constantly uses the word virile when she speaks of her. Romer Wilson, speaking of Emily, asks: “Did the lonely father see himself in her and feel that she was the only other male spirit in his house?…She early knew the boy in herself, and later knew the man.”Shirley, in Charlotte's novel, is understood to have been modelled on Emily; it is curious that Shirley's old governess should reprove her for constantly speaking of herself as though she were a male; it is not a usual thing for a girl to do, and one can only suppose that it was a habit of Emily's. Much in her character and behaviour that disconcerted her contemporaries can to-day be easily explained. Homosexuality was not at that period openly discussed as it is now, often to an embarrassing extent, but it existed, both in men and women, as it has always done, and it may well be that neither Emily herself, her family nor her family's friends, for, as I have said, she had none of her own, recognized what made her so strange.

Mrs. Gaskell did not like her. Someone told her that Emily“never showed regard to any human creature; all her love was reserved for animals.”She liked them wild and intractable. She was given a bulldog called Keeper, and concerning him, Mrs. Gaskell tells a curious story: “Keeper was faithful to the depths of his nature so long as he was with friends; but he who struck him with stick or whip, roused the relentless nature of the brute, who flew at his throat forthwith, and held him there till one or the other was at the point of death. Now Keeper's household fault was this. He loved to steal upstairs, and stretch his square, tawny limbs on the comfortable beds, covered over with delicate white counterpanes. But the cleanliness of the parsonage arrangements was perfect; and this habit of Keeper's was so objectionable, that Emily, in reply to Tabby's remonstrances, declared that, if he was found again transgressing, she herself, in defiance of warning and his well-known ferocity of nature, would beat him so severely that he would never offend again. In the gathering dusk of an autumn evening Tabby came, half-triumphantly, half-tremblingly, but in great wrath, to tell Emily that Keeper was lying on the best bed, in drowsy voluptuousness. Charlotte saw Emily's whitening face and set mouth, but dared not speak to interfere, no one dared when Emily's eyes glowed in that manner out of the paleness of her face, and when her lips were compressed into stone. She went upstairs, and Tabby and Charlotte stood in the gloomy passage below, full of the dark shadows of the coming night. Downstairs came Emily, dragging after her the unwilling Keeper, his hind legs set in a heavy attitude of resistance, held by the ‘skuft of his neck, ’ but growling low and savagely all the time. The watchers would fain have spoken, but durst not, for fear of taking off Emily's attention, and causing her to avert her head for a moment from the enraged brute. She let him go, planted in a dark corner at the bottom of the stairs; no time was there to fetch stick or rod, for fear of the strangling clutch at her throat—her bare clenched fist struck against his red fierce eyes, before he had time to make his spring, and in the language of the turf, she ‘punished’ him till his eyes were swelled up, and the half-blind stupefied beast was led to his accustomed lair, to have his swollen head fomented and cared for by the very Emily herself.”

Charlotte wrote of her: “Disinterested and energetic she certainly is; but if she be not quite so tractable and open to conviction as I could wish, I must remember perfection is not the lot of humanity.”Emily's temper was uncertain and her sisters appear to have been not a little afraid of her. From Charlotte's letters one gathers that she was puzzled and often irritated by Emily, and it is plain that she didn’t know what to make of Wuthering Heights; she had no notion that her sister had produced a book of astonishing originality, and one compared with which her own were commonplace. She felt constrained to apologize for it. When it was proposed to republish it, she undertook to edit it.“I am likewise compelling myself to read it over, for the first time of opening the book since my sister's death, ”she wrote.“Its power fills me with renewed admiration; but yet I am oppressed: the reader is scarcely permitted a taste of unalloyed pleasure, every beam of sunshine is poured down through black bars of threatening cloud; every page is surcharged with a sort of moral electricity; and the writer was unconscious of it.”And again: “If the auditor of her work, when read in manuscript, shuddered under the guiding influence of natures so relentless and so implacable—of spirits so lost and fallen; if it was complained that the mere hearing of certain vivid and fearful scenes banished sleep by night, and disturbed mental peace by day, Ellis Bell would wonder what was meant, and suspect the complainant of affectation. Had she but lived, her mind would of itself have grown like a strong tree—loftier, straighter, wider-spreading—and its matured fruits would have attained a mellower ripeness and sunnier bloom; but on that mind time and experience alone could work; to the influence of other intellects it was not amenable.”One is inclined to think that Charlotte never knew her sister.

4

Wuthering Heights is an extraordinary book. For the most part, novels betray their period, not only in the manner of writing common to the time at which they were written, but also by their concurrence with the climate of opinion of their day, the moral outlook of their authors, the prejudices they accept or reject. Young David Copperfield might very well have written (though with less talent) the same sort of novel as Jane Eyre, and Arthur Pendennis might have written a novel something like Villette, though the influence of Laura would doubtless have led him to eschew the naked sexuality which gives Charlotte Brontë's book its poignancy. But Wuthering Heights is an exception. It is related in no way to the fiction of the time. It is a very bad novel. It is a very good one. It is ugly. It has beauty. It is a terrible, an agonizing, a powerful and a passionate book. Some have thought it impossible that a clergyman's daughter who led a retired humdrum life, and knew few people and nothing of the world, could have written it. This seems to me absurd. Wuthering Heights is wildly romantic: now, romanticism eschews the patient observation of realism; it revels in the unbridled flight of the imagination and indulges, sometimes with gusto, sometimes with gloom, in horror, mystery, passion and violence. Given Emily Brontë's character, and fierce, repressed emotions, which what we know of her suggests, Wuthering Heights is just the sort of book one would have expected her to write. But on the face of it, it is much more the sort of book that her scapegrace brother Branwell might have written, and a number of people have been able to persuade themselves that he had in whole or in part done so. One of them, Francis Grundy, wrote: “Patrick Brontë declared to me, and what his sister said bore out the assertion, that he wrote a great part of Wuthering Heights himself….The weird fancies of diseased genius with which he used to entertain me on our long walks at Luddenden Foot, reappear in the pages of the novel, and I am inclined to believe that the very plot was his invention rather than his sister's.”On one occasion two of Branwell's friends, Dearden and Leyland by name, arranged to meet him at an inn on the road to Keighley to read their poetical effusions to one another; and this is what Dearden some twenty years later wrote to the Halifax Guardian: “I read the firs tact of the Demon Queen; but when Branwell dived into his hat—the usual receptacle of his fugitive scraps—where he supposed he had deposited his manuscript poem, he found he had by mistake placed there a number of stray leaves of a novel on which he had been trying his ‘prentice hand.’ Chagrined at the disappointment he had caused, he was about to return the papers to his hat, when both friends earnestly pressed him to read them, as they felt a curiosity to see how he could wield the pen of a novelist. After some hesitation, he complied with the request, and riveted our attention for about an hour, dropping each sheet, when read, into his hat. The story broke off abruptly in the middle of a sentence, and he gave us the sequel, viva voce, together with the real names of the prototypes of his characters, but, as some of these persons are still living, I refrain from pointing them out to the public. He said he had not yet fixed upon a title for the production, and was afraid he would never be able to meet with a publisher who would have the hardihood to usher it into the world. The scene of the fragment which Branwell read, and the characters introduced in it—so far as they developed—were the same as those in Wuthering Heights, which Charlotte confidently asserts was the production of her sister Emily.”

Now this is either a pack of lies, or it is true. Charlotte despised and, within the bounds of Christian charity, hated her brother; but as we know, Christian charity has always been able to make allowances for a lot of good honest hatred, and Charlotte's unsupported word cannot be accepted. She may have persuaded herself, as people often do, to believe what she wanted to believe. The story is circumstantial, and it is odd that anyone should, for no particular reason, have invented it. What is the explanation? There is none. It has been suggested that Branwell wrote the first four chapters, and then, drunk and doped as he was, gave it up, whereupon Emily took it over. The argument that these chapters are written in a more stilted manner than the subsequent ones does not, to my mind, hold water; and if there is in them a somewhat greater pomposity in the writing, I should ascribe it to a not unsuccessful attempt on Emily's part to show that Lockwood was a silly, conceited ape. I have no doubt at all that Emily, and Emily alone, wrote Wuthering Heights.

It must be admitted that it is badly written. The Brontë sisters did not write well. Like the governesses they were, they affected the turgid and pedantic style for which the word literatise has been coined. The main part of the story is told by Mrs. Dean, a Yorkshire maid of all work like the Brontës’ Tabby; a conversational style would have been suitable; Emily makes her express herself as no human being could. Here is a typical utterance: “I tried to smooth away all disquietude on the subject, by affirming, with frequent iteration, that that betrayal of trust, if it merited so harsh an appellation, should be the last.”Emily Brontë seems to have been aware that she was putting into Mrs. Dean's mouth words that it was unlikely she would have known, and to explain it, makes her say that in the course of her service she has had the opportunity to read books, but, even at that, the pretentiousness of her discourse is appalling. She does not read a letter, she peruses an epistle; she doesn’t send a letter, but a missive. She does not leave a room, she quits a chamber. She calls her day's work her diurnal occupation. She commences rather than begins. People don’t shout or yell, they vociferate; nor do they listen, they hearken. There is pathos in this parson's daughter striving so hard to write in a lady-like way, only to succeed in being genteel. Yet one would not wish Wuthering Heights to have been written with grace: it would be none the better for being better written. Just as in one of those early Flemish pictures of the burial of Christ the anguished grimaces of the emaciated creatures concerned, their stiff, ungainly gestures, seem to add a greater horror, a matter-of-fact brutality, to the scene, which makes it more poignant, more tragic, than when the same event is pictured in beauty by Titian; so there is in this uncouth stylization of the language something which strangely heightens the violent passion of the story.

Wuthering Heights is clumsily constructed. That is not surprising, for Emily Brontë had never written a novel before, and she had a complicated story to tell, dealing with two generations. This is a difficult thing to do because the author has to give some sort of unity to two sets of characters and two sets of events; and he must be careful not to allow the interest of one to overshadow the interest of the other. This Emily did not succeed in doing. After the death of Catherine Earnshaw there is, until you come to the last finely imaginative pages, some loss of power. The younger Catherine is an unsatisfactory character, and Emily Brontë seems not to have known what to make of her; obviously she could not give her the passionate independence of the older Catherine, nor the foolish weakness of her father. She is a spoilt, silly, wilful and ill-mannered creature; and you cannot greatly pity her sufferings. The steps are not made clear which led to her falling in love with young Hareton. He is a shadowy figure, and you know no more of him than that he was sullen and handsome. The author of such a story as I am now considering has also to compress the passage of years into a period of time that can be accepted by the reader with a comprehensive glance, as one seizes in a single view the whole of a vast fresco. I do not suppose that Emily Brontë deliberately thought out how to get a unity of impression into a straggling story, but I think she must have asked herself how to make it coherent; and it may have occurred to her that she could best do this by making one character narrate the long succession of events to another. It is a convenient way of telling a story, and she did not invent it. Its disadvantage is that it is impossible to maintain anything like a conversational manner when the narrator has to tell a number of things, descriptions of scenery for instance, which no sane person would think of doing. And of course if you have a narrator (Mrs. Dean) you must have a listener (Lockwood). It is possible that an experienced novelist might have found a better way of telling the story of Wuthering Heights, but I cannot believe that if Emily Brontë used it, it was because she was working on a foundation of someone else's invention.

But more than that, I think the method she adopted might have been expected of her, when you consider her extreme, her morbid, shyness and her reticence. What were the alternatives? One was to write the novel from the standpoint of omniscience, as, for instance, Middlemarch and Madame Bovary are written. I think it would have shocked her harsh, uncompromising virtue to tell the outrageous story as a creation of her own; and if she had, moreover, she could hardly have avoided giving some account of Heathcliff during the few years he spent away from Wuthering Heights—years in which he managed to acquire an education and make quite a lot of money. She couldn’t do this, because she simply didn’t know how he had done it. The fact the reader is asked to accept is hard to believe, and she was content to state it and leave it at that. Another alternative was to have the story narrated to her, Emily Brontë, by Mrs. Dean, say, and tell it then in the first person; but I suspect that that, too, would have brought her into a contact with the reader too close for her quivering sensitivity. By having the story in its beginning told by Lockwood, and unfolded to Lockwood by Mrs. Dean, she hid herself behind, as it were, a double mask. Mr. Brontë told Mrs. Gaskell a story which in this connection has significance. When his children were young, he, desiring to find out something of their natures which their timidity concealed from him, made each in turn put on an old mask, under cover of which they could answer more freely the questions he put to them. When he asked Charlotte what was the best book in the world, she answered: The Bible; but when he asked Emily what he had best do with her troublesome brother Branwell, she said: “Reason with him; and when he won’t listen to reason, whip him.”

And why did Emily need to hide herself when she wrote this powerful, passionate and terrible book? I think because she disclosed in it her innermost instincts. She looked deep into the well of loneliness in her heart, and saw there unavowable secrets of which, notwithstanding, her impulse as a writer drove her to unburden herself. It is said that her imagination was kindled by the weird stories her father used to tell of the Ireland of his youth, and by the tales of Hoffmann which she learned to read when she went to school in Belgium, and which she continued to read, we are told, back at the parsonage, seated on a hearthrug by the fire with her arm around Keeper's neck. I am willing to believe that she found in the stories of mystery, violence and horror of the German romantic writers something that appealed to her own fierce nature; but I think she found Heathcliff and Catherine Earnshaw in the hidden depths of her own soul. I think she was herself Heathcliff, I think she was herself Catherine Earnshaw. Is it strange that she should have put herself into the two chief characters of her book? Not at all. We are none of us all of a piece; more than one person dwells within us, often in uncanny companionship with his fellows; and the peculiarity of the writer of fiction is that he has the power to objectify the diverse persons of which he is compounded in individual characters: his misfortune is that he cannot bring to life characters, however necessary to his story they may be, in which there is no part of himself. That is why the younger Catherine in Wuthering Heights is unsatisfactory.

I think Emily put the whole of herself into Heathcliff. She gave him her violent rage, her sexuality, vehement but frustrated, her passion of unsatisfied love, her jealousy, her hatred and contempt of human beings, her cruelty, her sadism. The reader will remember the incident when, with so little reason, she beat with her naked fist the face of the dog she loved, as perhaps she loved no human being. There is another curious circumstance related by Ellen Nussey.“She enjoyed leading Charlotte where she would not dare to go of her own free will. Charlotte had a mortal dread of unknown animals, and it was Emily's pleasure to lead her into close vicinity, and then tell her of how and what she had done, laughing at her horror with great amusement.”I think Emily loved Catherine Earnshaw with Heathcliff's masculine, animal love; I think she laughed, as she had laughed at Charlotte's fears, when, as Heathcliff, she kicked and trampled on Earnshaw and dashed his head against the stone flags, and I think when, as Heathcliff, she hit the younger Catherine in the face and heaped humiliations upon her, she laughed. I think it gave her a thrill of release when she bullied, reviled and browbeat the persons of her invention, because in real life she suffered such bitter mortification in the company of her fellow-creatures; and I think, as Catherine, doubling the roles, as it were, though she fought Heathcliff, though she despised him, though she knew him for the beast he was, she loved him with her body and soul, she exulted in her power over him, and since there is in the sadist something of the masochist too, she was fascinated by his violence, his brutality and his untamed nature. She felt they were kin, as indeed they were, if I am right in supposing they were both Emily Brontë.“Nelly, I am Heathcliff, ”Catherine cried.“He's always in my mind: not as a pleasure, any more than I am always a pleasure to myself, but as my own being.”

Wuthering Heights is a love story, perhaps the strangest that was ever written, and not the least strange part of it is that the lovers remain chaste. Catherine was passionately in love with Heathcliff, as passionately in love with him as Heathcliff was with her. For Edgar Linton, Catherine felt only a kindly, and often exasperated, tolerance. One wonders why those two people who were consumed with love did not, whatever the poverty that might have faced them, run away together. One wonders why they didn’t become real lovers. It may be that Emily's upbringing caused her to look upon adultery as an unforgivable sin, or it may be that the idea of sexual intercourse between the sexes filled her with disgust. I believe both the sisters were highly sexed. Charlotte was plain, with a sallow skin and a large nose on one side of her face. She had proposals of marriage when she was obscure and penniless, and at that period a man expected his wife to bring a portion with her. But beauty is not the only thing that makes a woman attractive; indeed, great beauty is often somewhat chilling: you admire, but are not moved. If young men fell in love with Charlotte, a captious and critical young woman, it can surely have only been because they found her sexually attractive, which means that they felt obscurely that she was highly sexed. She was not in love with Mr. Nicholls when she married him; she thought him narrow, dogmatic, sullen and far from intelligent. It is clear from her letters that after she married him she felt very differently towards him; for her they are positively skittish. She fell in love with him, and his defects ceased to matter. The most probable explanation is that those sexual desires of hers were at last satisfied. There is no reason to suppose that Emily was less highly sexed than Charlotte.

5

The genesis of a novel is a very curious affair. In a novelist's first novel, and Emily, so far as we know, wrote but one, it is not unlikely that there will be something of wish-fulfilment and something of imagined autobiography. It is conceivable that Wuthering Heights is the product of pure fantasy. Who can tell what erotic reveries Emily had during the long watches of her sleepless nights, or when she lay all the summer day among the flowering heather? Everybody must have noticed how strong the family likeness is between Charlotte's Rochester and Emily's Heathcliff. Heathcliff might be a by-blow, the bastard a younger son in the Rochester family might have had by an Irish biddy met in Liverpool. Both men are swarthy, violent, hard-featured, fierce, passionate and mysterious. They differ only as differed the natures of the two sisters who constructed them to satisfy their urgent, thwarted desires for sexual satisfaction. But Rochester is the dream of the woman of normal instincts, who hankers to give herself to the domineering, ruthless male; Emily gave Heathcliff her own masculinity, her violence and her savage temper. But the primary model on which the sisters created these two uncouth, difficult men, was, I surmise, their father, the Rev. Patrick Brontë.

But though, as I have said, it is conceivable that Emily constructed Wuthering Heights entirely out of her own fantasies, I do not believe it. I should have thought that it was only very rarely that the fruitful idea which will give rise to a fiction, comes to an author, like a falling star, out of the blue; for the most part, it comes to him from an experience, generally emotional, of his own, or if it is told him by another, emotionally appealing; and then, his imagination in travail, character and incidents little by little grow out of it, until at length the finished work comes into being. Few people, however, know how small a hint, how trivial to all appearances an occurrence may be, that will serve to set the spark that will kindle the author's invention, when you look at the cyclamen with its heart-shaped leaves surrounding a profusion of flowers, their careless petals wearing a wilful look as though they grew at haphazard, it seems incredible that this luscious beauty, this rich colour, should have come from a seed hardly larger than a pin's head. So it may be with the productive seed that will give rise to an immortal book.

It seems to me that one only has to read Emily Brontë's poemsto guess what the emotional experience was that led her to seek release from cruel pain by writing Wuthering Heights. She wrote a good deal of verse. It is uneven; some of it is commonplace, some of it moving, some of it lovely. She seems to have been most at home with the metres of the hymns which she sang of a Sunday in the parish church at Haworth, but the commonplace metres she used do not veil the intense emotion beneath. Many of the poems belong to the Gondal Chronicles, that long history of an imaginary island with which she and Anne amused themselves when they were children, and which Emily continued to write when she was a grown woman. It may be that she found this a convenient way to deliver her tortured heart of emotions which, with her natural secretiveness, she could not have borne to set out in any other way. Other poems seem to be the direct expression of feeling. In 1845, three years before her death, she wrote a poem called The Prisoner. So far as is known, she had never read the works of any of the mystics, yet in these verses she so describes the mystical experience that it is impossible to believe that they do not tell of what she knew from personal acquaintance. She uses almost the very words that the mystics use when they describe the anguish felt on the return from union with the Infinite:

Oh dreadful is the check—intense the agony—
When the ear begins to hear, the eye begins to see;
When the pulse begins to throb, the brain to think again;
The soul to feel the flesh, and the flesh to feel the chain.

These lines surely reflect a felt, a deeply felt, experience. Why should one suppose that Emily Brontë's love poems were no more than a literary exercise? I should have thought they pointed very clearly to her having fallen in love, to her love having been repulsed, and then to her having been bitterly hurt. She wrote these particular poems when she was teaching at a girls’ school at Law Hill, near Halifax. She was nineteen. It may be that for the only time in her life she loved. It may be that the unhappiness it caused her sufficed to implant the seed in the fruitful soil of her tortured sensibility, which enabled her to create the strange book we know. But this is no more than conjecture. I can think of no other novel in which the pain, the ecstasy, the ruthlessness of love have been so powerfully set forth. Wuthering Heights has great faults, but they do not matter; they matter as little as the fallen tree-trunks, the strewn rocks, the snow-drifts which impede, but do not stem, the alpine torrent in its tumultuous course down the mountainside. You cannot liken Wuthering Heights to any other book. You can liken it only to one of those great pictures of El Greco in which in a sombre arid landscape, under clouds heavy with thunder, long, emaciated figures in contorted attitudes, spellbound by an unearthly emotion, hold their breath. A streak of lightning, flitting across the leaden sky, gives a mysterious terror to the scene.

Choice of Kipling's Best (Introduction) (1953)

In this essay it is my business to deal only with Rudyard Kipling's short stories. I am not concerned with his verse nor, except in so far as they sometimes directly affected his stories, with his political opinions.

In making a selection of them I have had to decide whether I should choose only those I most liked. In that case I should have chosen nearly all the Indian stories. For in them to my mind he was at his best. When he wrote stories about Indians and about the British in India he felt himself at home and he wrote with an ease, a freedom, a variety of invention which gave them a quality which in stories in which the subject matter was different he did not always attain. Even the slightest of them are readable. They give you the tang of the East, the smell of the bazaars, the torpor of the rains, the heat of the sun-scorched earth, the rough life of the barracks in which the occupying troops were quartered, and the other life, so English and yet so alien to the English way, led by the officers, the Indian Civilians and the swarm of minor officials who combined to administer that vast territory.

A great many years ago, when Kipling was still at the height of his popularity, I used sometimes to meet Indian Civilians and professors at Indian universities who spoke of him with something very like contempt. That was partly due to an ignoble but natural jealousy. They resented it that this obscure journalist, of no social consequence, should have achieved world-wide renown. They protested that he did not know India. Which of them did? India is not a country, it is a continent. It is true that Kipling seems to have been intimately acquainted only with the North-West. Like any other sensible writer he placed the scene of his stories in the region he knew best. His Anglo-Indian critics blamed him because he had not dealt with this and that subject which they thought important. His sympathies lay with the Muslims rather than with the Hindus. He took but a very casual interest in Hinduism and the religion which has so deep-rooted an influence on the great mass of the teeming populations of India. There were qualities in the Muslims that aroused his admiration: he seldom spoke of the Hindus with appreciation. It never seems to have occurred to him that there were among them men of erudition, distinguished scientists and able philosophers. The Bengali, for instance, to him was a coward, a muddler, a braggart, who lost his head in an emergency and shirked responsibility. This is a pity, but it was Kipling's right, as it is of every author, to deal with the subjects that appealed to him.

But I felt that if in this volume I confined myself to Kipling's Indian stories I should not give the reader a fair impression of his varied talent. I have therefore included a few stories with an English setting which have been very widely admired.

It is not to my purpose to give more biographical details of Kipling's life than seem to me useful in my consideration of his short stories. He was born in 1865 at Bombay, where his father was Professor of Architectural Sculpture. When a little more than five his parents took him with his younger sister back to England and placed the two of them in a family where, owing to the unkindness and stupidity of the woman who looked after them, they were miserably unhappy. The wretched little boy was nagged, bullied and beaten. When his mother, after some years, once more came home she was deeply shocked by what she discovered and took the two children away. At the age of twelve Kipling was sent to a school at Westward Ho! It was called the United Services College and had been recently founded to provide education at a small cost for the sons of officers who were to be prepared to go into the army. There were about two hundred boys and they were herded together in a row of lodging-houses. Now, what the school was really like has nothing to do with me; I am only concerned with the picture Kipling has drawn of it in the work of fiction to which he gave the title Stalky＆Co. A more odious picture of school life can seldom have been drawn. With the exception of the headmaster and the chaplain the masters are represented as savage, brutal, narrow-minded and incompetent. The boys, supposedly the sons of gentlemen, were devoid of any decent instincts. To the three lads with whom these stories deal Kipling gave the names of Stalky, Turkey and Beetle. Stalky was the ringleader. He remained Kipling's ideal of the gallant, resourceful, adventurous, high-spirited soldier and gentleman. Beetle was Kipling's portrait of himself. The three of them exercised their humour in practical jokes of a singular nastiness. Kipling has narrated them with immense gusto and it is only just to say that the stories are so brilliantly told that though it may give you goose flesh to read them, when you have once begun you will read them to the end. I should not have dwelt on them at all if it were not plain to me that the influence Kipling was exposed to during the four years he spent at what he called“the Coll”gained a hold on him which throughout his career he never outgrew. He was never quite able to rid himself of the impressions, the prejudices, the spiritual posture he then acquired. Indeed there is no sign that he wanted to. He retained to the end his relish for the rough and tumble, the ragging, the brutal horseplay of fourth-form schoolboys and their delight in practical jokes. It never seems to have occurred to him that the school was third-rate and the boys a rotten lot. In fact after visiting it many years later he wrote a charming account of it, in which he paid a glowing tribute to that harsh disciplinarian, his old headmaster, and expressed his gratitude for the great benefits he had received during the period he had spent under his care.

When Kipling was a little less than seventeen, his father, who was then curator of the museum at Lahore, got him a job as assistant editor of the English paper, The Civil and Military Gazette, which was published in that city, and he left school to return to India. This was in 1882. The world he entered was very different from the world we live in now. Great Britain was at the height of her power. A map showed in pink vast stretches of the earth's surface under the sovereignty of Queen Victoria. The mother country was immensely rich. The British were the world's bankers. British commerce sent its products to the uttermost parts of the earth, and their quality was generally acknowledged to be higher than those manufactured by any other nation. Peace reigned except for small punitive expeditions here and there. The army, though small, was confident (notwithstanding the reverse on Majuba Hill) that it could hold its own against any force that was likely to be brought against it. The British navy was the greatest in the world. In sport the British were supreme. None could compete with them in the games they played, and in the classic races it was almost unheard-of that a horse from abroad should win. It looked as though nothing could ever change this happy state of things. The inhabitants of these islands of ours trusted in God, and God, they were assured, had taken the British Empire under his particular protection. It is true that the Irish were making a nuisance of themselves. It is true that the factory workers were underpaid and overworked. But that seemed an inevitable consequence of the industrialisation of the country and there was nothing to do about it. The reformers who tried to improve their lot were regarded as mischievous troublemakers. It is true that the agricultural labourers lived in miserable hovels and earned a pitiful wage, but the Ladies Bountiful of the landowners were kind to them. Many of them occupied themselves with their moral welfare, sent them beef tea and calves-foot jelly when they were ill and often clothes for their children. People said there always had been rich and poor in the world and always would be, and that seemed to settle the matter.

The British travelled a great deal on the Continent. They crowded the health resorts, Spa, Vichy, Homburg, Aix-les-Bains and Baden-Baden. In winter they went to the Riviera. They built themselves sumptuous villas at Cannes and Monte Carlo. Vast hotels were erected to accommodate them. They had plenty of money and they spent it freely. They felt that they were a race apart and no sooner had they landed at Calais than it was borne in upon them that they were now among natives, not of course natives as were the Indians or the Chinese, but—natives. They alone washed, and the baths that they frequently travelled with were a tangible proof that they were not as others. They were healthy, athletic, sensible, and in every way superior. Because they enjoyed their sojourn among the natives whose habits were so curiously un-English, because, though they thought them frivolous (the French), lazy (the Italians), stupid but funny (the Germans), with the kindness of heart natural to them, they liked them. And they in turn thought that these foreigners liked them. It never entered their heads that the courtesy which they received, the bows, the smiles, the desire to please were owing to their lavish spending, and that behind their backs the“natives”mocked them for their uncouth dress, their gawkiness, their bad manners, their insolence, their silliness in letting themselves be consistently overcharged, their patronising tolerance; and it required disastrous wars for it to dawn upon them how greatly they had been mistaken. The Anglo-Indian society into which Kipling was introduced when he joined his parents at Lahore shared to the full the prepossessions and the self-complacency of their fellow-subjects in Britain.

Since his short sight prevented him from playing games, Kipling had had the leisure at school to read a great deal and to write. The headmaster seems to have been impressed by the promise he showed and had the good sense to give him the run of his own library. He wrote the stories which he afterwards published in book form as Plain Tales from the Hills during such leisure as his duties as sub-editor of The Civil and Military Gazette allowed him. To me their chief interest is in the picture they give of the society with which he was dealing. It is a devastating one. There is no sign that any of the persons he wrote about took any interest in art, literature or music. The notion seems to have been prevalent that there was something fishy about a man who took pains to learn about things Indian. Of one character Kipling wrote: “he knew as much about Indians as it is good for a man to know.”A man who was absorbed in his work appears to have been regarded with misgiving; at best he was eccentric, at worst a bore. The life described was empty and frivolous. The self-sufficiency of these people is fearful to contemplate. And what sort of people were they? They were ordinary middle-class people, who came from modest homes in England, sons and daughters of retired government servants and of parsons, doctors and lawyers. The men were empty-headed; such of them as were in the army or had been to universities had acquired a certain polish; but the women were shallow, provincial and genteel. They spent their time in idle flirtation and their chief amusement seems to have been to get some man away from another woman. Perhaps because Kipling wrote in a prudish period which made him afraid of shocking his readers, perhaps from an innate disinclination to treat of sex, though in these stories there is a great deal of philandering, it very rarely led to sexual intercourse. Whatever encouragement these women gave the men whom they attracted, when it came to a showdown they drew back. They were, in short, what is described in English by a coarse hyphenated word, and in France, more elegantly, by allumeuses.

It is surprising that Kipling, with his quick mind and wonderful power of observation, with his wide reading, should have taken these people at their face value. He was, of course, very young. Plain Tales from the Hills was published when he was only twenty-two. It is perhaps natural that, coming straight from the brutalities of Westward Ho! to the unpretentious establishment of the curator of the Lahore museum, he should have been dazzled on his first acquaintance with a society that to his inexperienced eyes had glamour. So was the little bourgeois Marcel dazzled when he first gained admittance to the exclusive circle of Madame de Guermantes. Mrs. Hauksbee was neither so brilliant nor so witty as Kipling would have us think. He reveals her essential drabness when he makes her compare a woman's voice to the grinding brakes of an underground train coming into Earl's Court station. We are asked to believe that she was a woman of fashion. If she had been she would never have gone to Earl's Court except to see an old nurse and then not by underground, but in a hansom cab.

But Plain Tales from the Hills is not only concerned with Anglo-Indian society. The volume contains stories of Indian life and stories of the soldiery. When you consider that they were written when their author was still in his teens or only just out of them they show an astonishing competence. Kipling said that the best of them were provided for him by his father. I think we may ascribe this statement to filial piety. I believe it to be very seldom that an author can make use of a story given to him ready made, as seldom indeed as a person in real life can be transferred to fiction just as he is and maintain an air of verisimilitude. Of course the author gets his ideas from somewhere, they don’t spring out of his head like Pallas-Athene from the head of her sire in perfect panoply, ready to be written down. But it is curious how small a hint, how vague a suggestion, will be enough to give the author's invention the material to work upon and enable him in due course to construct a properly disposed story. Take, for instance, the later story, The Tomb of his Ancestors. It may very well have needed no more than such a casual remark from one of the officers Kipling had known at Lahore as: “Funny chaps these natives are. There was a feller called So-and-So who was stationed up country among the Bhils, whose grandfather had kept them in order for donkeys’ years and was buried there, and they got it into their thick heads that he was a reincarnation of the old man, and he could do anything he liked with them.”That would have been quite enough to set Kipling's vivid imagination to work upon what turned out to be an amusing and delightful tale. Plain Tales from the Hills is very uneven, as indeed Kipling's work always was. That I believe to be inevitable in a writer of short stories. It is a ticklish thing to write a short story and whether it is good or bad depends on more than the author's conception, power of expression, skill in construction, invention and imagination: it depends also on luck. So the clever Japanese, taking from his little pile of seed pearls, all to his eyes indistinguishable from one another, the first that comes to hand and inserting it into the oyster, cannot tell whether it will turn into a perfect, rounded pearl or a misshapen object neither of beauty nor of value. Nor is the author a good judge of his own work. Kipling had a high opinion of The Phantom ’Rickshaw. I think if he had been more sophisticated when he wrote it, it might have occurred to him that there was more to be said in extenuation of the man's behaviour than he apprehended. It is very unfortunate that you should fall out of love with a married woman with whom you have had an affair and fall in love with someone else and want to marry her. But such things happen. And when the woman won’t accept the situation, but pursues you and waylays you and pesters you with tears and supplications it is not unnatural that at last you should grow impatient and lose your temper. Mrs. Keith-Wessington is the most persistent crampon in fiction, for even after her death she continued to harry the wretched man in her phantom ’rickshaw. Jack Pansay deserves our sympathy rather than our censure. Because a story has been difficult to write an author may well think better of it than of a story that has seemed to write itself, sometimes there is a psychological error at the basis of it which he has not noticed, and sometimes he sees in the finished story what he saw in his mind's eye when he conceived it rather than what he has presented to the reader. But we should not be surprised that Kipling sometimes wrote stories which were poor, unconvincing or trivial; we should wonder rather that he wrote so many of such excellence. He was wonderfully various.

In the essay Mr. T. S. Eliot wrote to preface his selection of Kipling's verse he seems to suggest that variety is not a laudable quality in a poet. I would not venture to dispute any opinion of Mr. Eliot's on a question in which poetry is concerned, but though variety may not be a merit in a poet, it surely is in a writer offiction. The good writer offiction has the peculiarity, shared to a degree by all men, but in him more abundant, that he has not only one self, but is a queer mixture of several, or, if that seems an extravagant way of putting it, that there are several, often discordant aspects of his personality. The critics could not understand how the same man could write“Brugglesmith”and“Recessional”, and so accused him of insincerity. They were unjust. It was the self called Beetle who wrote“Brugglesmith”and the self called Yardley-Orde who wrote Recessional. When most of us look back on ourselves we can sometimes find consolation in believing that a self in us which we can only deplore has, generally through no merit of ours, perished. The strange thing about Kipling is that the self called Beetle which one would have thought increasing age and the experience of life would have caused to disintegrate, remained alive in all its strength almost to his dying day.

As a child at Bombay Kipling had spoken Hindustani with his ayah and the servants as his native language and in Something of Myself he has told that when he was taken to see his parents he translated what he had to say into broken English. It may be supposed that on his return to India he quickly recovered his old knowledge of the language. In the same book he has related in terms that couldn’t be bettered how at Lahore he got the material which so soon afterwards he was to make effective use of. As a reporter“I described openings of big bridges and suchlike, which meant a night to two with the engineers; floods on railways—more nights in the wet with wretched heads of repair gangs; village festivals and consequent outbreaks of cholera or smallpox; communal riots under the shadow of the Mosque of Wazir Khan, where the patient waiting troops lay in timber-yards or side-alleys till the order came to go in and hit the crowds on the feet with the gunbutt, and the growling, flaring, creed-drunk city would be brought to hand without effusion of blood”…. Often at night“I would wander till dawn in all manner of odd places—liquor-shops, gambling-and opium-dens, which are not a bit mysterious, wayside entertainments such as puppet-shows, native dances; or in and about the narrow gullies under the Mosque of Wazir Khan for the sheer sake of looking…And there were‘wet’ nights too at the Club or one Mess, when a tableful of boys, half crazed with discomfort, but with just sense enough to stick to beer and bones which seldom betray, tried to rejoice and somehow succeeded…I got to meet the soldiery of those days in visits to Fort Lahore and, in a less degree, at Mian Mir Cantonments…. Having no position to consider, and my trade enforcing it, I could move at will in the fourth dimension. I came to realize the bare horrors of the private's life, and the unnecessary torments he endured on account of the Christian doctrine that lays it down that‘the wages of sin is death.’”

I have included in this selection two stories in which figure the three privates, Mulvaney, Learoyd and Ortheris. They have been immensely popular. I think they have the disadvantage for most readers that they are written in the peculiar dialect of the speakers. It is no easy matter to decide how far an author should go in this direction. Manifestly it would be absurd to make men like Mulvaney and Ortheris deliver themselves in the cultured language of a don at King's, but to make them speak consistently in dialect may well make a narrative tedious. Perhaps the best plan is to use the turns of phrase, the grammar and the vocabulary of the persons concerned, but to reproduce peculiarities of pronunciation so sparingly as not to incommode the reader. That was not, however, Kipling's way. He reproduced the accents of his three soldiers phonetically. No one has found fault with Learoyd's Yorkshire, which was corrected by Kipling's father, himself a Yorkshireman; but critics have claimed that neither Mulvaney's Irish nor Ortheris's cockney was real. Kipling was a master of description and could relate incident brilliantly, but it does not seem to me that his dialogue was always plausible. He put into the mouth of Ortheris expressions he could never have used and one may well ask oneself how on earth he came by a quotation from Macaulay's Lays of Ancient Rome. I cannot believe that a well-bred woman such as the Brushwood Boy's mother is supposed to be would speak to him of his father as“the pater.”Sometimes the language used by the officers and officials in Indian is unconvincingly hearty. To my mind Kipling's dialogue is only beyond reproach when he is translating into measured, dignified English the speech of Indians. The reader will remember that as a child talking with his parents he had to translate what he had to say from Hindustani into English: it may be that that was the form of speech that came most naturally to him.

In 1887 Kipling, after five years as sub-editor of The Civil and Military Gazette, was sent to Allahabad, several hundred miles to the south, to work on the much more important sister-paper, The Pioneer. The proprietors were starting a weekly edition for home, and he was given the editorship. An entire page was devoted to fiction. The Plain Tales from the Hills had been restricted to twelve hundred words, but now he was allotted sufficient space to write stories up to five thousand. He wrote“soldier tales, Indian tales, and tales of the opposite sex.”Among them were such powerful but gruesome stories as The Mark of the Beast and The Return of Imray.

The stories Kipling wrote during this period were published in six paper-covered volumes in Wheeler's Indian Railway Library, and with the money he thus earned and a commission to write travel sketches he left India for England“by way of the Far East and the United States.”This was in 1889. He had spent seven years in India. His stories had become known in England and when he arrived in London, still a very young man, he found editors eager to accept whatever he wrote. He settled down in Villiers Street, Strand. The stories he produced there are of the highest quality, a quality which later he often achieved but never surpassed. Among them are On Greenhow Hill, The Courting of Dinah Shadd, The Man Who Was, Without Benefit of Clergy and At the End of the Passage. It looks as though the new surroundings in which he found himself brought into greater vividness his recollections of India. That is a likely enough thing to happen. When an author is living in the scene of his story, perhaps among the people who have suggested the characters of his invention, he may well find himself bewildered by the mass of his impressions. He cannot see the wood for the trees. But absence will erase from his memory redundant details and inessential facts. He will get then a bird's-eye view, as it were, of his subject and so, with less material to embarrass him, can get the form into his story which completes it.

It was then too that he wrote the tale which he called“The Finest Story in the World.”It is interesting because he dealt in it, for the first time, I think, with metempsychosis. It was natural that the theme should interest him, for the belief in it is ingrained in the Hindu sensibility. It is as little a matter of doubt to the people of India as were the Virgin Birth of Christ and the Resurrection to the Christians of the thirteenth century. No one can have travelled in India without discovering how deep-rooted the belief is not only among the uneducated, but among men of culture and of experience in world affairs. One hears in conversation, or reads in the papers, of men who claim to remember something of their past lives. In this story Kipling has dealt with it with great imaginative power. He returned to it in a story which is less well-known called“Wireless.”In this he made effective use of what was then a new toy for the scientifically minded amateur to persuade the reader of the possibility that the chemist's assistant of his tale, dying of tuberculosis, might under the effect of a drug recall that past life of his in which he was John Keats. To anyone who has stood in the little room in Rome overlooking the steps that lead down to the Piazza di Spagna and seen the drawing Joseph Severn made of the emaciated, beautiful head of the dead poet, Kipling's story is wonderfully pathetic. It is thrilling to watch the dying chemist's assistant, in love too, worrying out in a trancelike state, lines that Keats wrote in The Eve of St. Agnes. It is a lovely story admirably told.

Six years later Kipling, in the entrancing tale The Tomb of his Ancestors, to which I have already referred, took up once more the theme of metempsychosis, and this time in such a way as not to outrage probability. It is the Bhils, the mountain tribes among whom the story is set, who believe that the young subaltern, its hero, is a reincarnation of his grandfather who spent many years in their midst and whose memory they still revere. Kipling never succeeded better in creating that indefinable quality which for want of a better word we call atmosphere.

After spending two years in London, years of hard work, Kipling's health broke down, and he very sensibly decided to take the rest of a long journey. He returned to England to be married and with his bride started off on a tour of the world, but financial difficulties obliged him to cut it short, and he settled down in Vermont where his wife's family had long been established. This was in the summer of 1892. He stayed there off and on till 1896. During those four years he wrote a number of stories many of which were of a quality which only he could reach. It was then that he wrote In the Rukh in which Mowgli makes his first appearance. It was a propitious inspiration, for from it sprang the two Jungle Books in which, to my mind, his great and varied gifts found their most brilliant expression. They show his wonderful talent for telling a story, they have a delicate humour and they are romantic and plausible. The device of making animals talk is as old as Aesop's fables, and for all I know much older, and La Fontaine, as we know, employed it with charm and wit, but I think no one has performed the difficult feat of persuading the reader that it is as natural for animals to speak as for human beings more triumphantly than Kipling has done in The Jungle Books. He had used the same device in the story called A Walking Delegate in which horses indulge in political discussion, but there is in the story an obviously didactic element which prevents it from being successful.

It was during these fertile years that Kipling wrote The Brushwood Boy, a story which has deeply impressed so many people that, though it is not one of my favourites, I have thought it well to print it in this selection. He availed himself in this of a notion which has attracted writers of fiction both before and after him, the notion, namely, of two persons systematically dreaming the same dreams. The difficulty of it lies in making the dreams interesting. We listen restlessly when someone at the breakfast table insists on telling us of the dream he had during the night, and a dream described on paper is apt to arouse in us the same impatience. Kipling had before done the same sort of thing, though on a smaller scale, in The Bridge-Builders. There I think he made a mistake. He had a good story to tell. It is about a flood that suddenly rushes down on a bridge over the Ganges which, after three years of strenuous labour, is on the point of completion. There is doubt in the minds of the two white men in charge of the operations whether three of the spans, still unfinished, will stand the strain, and they fear that if the stone-boats go adrift the girders will be damaged. They have received by telegram warning that the flood is on the way, and with their army of workmen spend an agonized night doing what they can to strengthen the weak places. All this is described with force and the telling detail of which Kipling was a master. The bridge stands the strain and all is well. That is all. It may be that Kipling thought it wasn’t enough. Findlayson, the chief engineer, has been too anxious and too fully occupied to bother about eating anything and by the second night is all in. His lascar aide persuades him to swallow some opium pills. Then news comes that a wire hawser has snapped and the stone-boats are loose. Findlayson and the lascar rush down to the bank and get into one of the stone-boats in the hope of preventing them from doing irreparable injury. The pair are swept down the river and landed half-drowned on an island. Exhausted and doped they fall asleep and dream the same dream in which they see the Hindu Gods in animal form, Ganesh the elephant, Hanuman the ape and finally Krishna himself, and hear them talk. When the two wake in the morning they are rescued. But the double dream is needless and because the conversation of the Gods is needless too it is tedious.

In The Brushwood Boy the identical dreams are an essential element in the story. It is here for the reader to read and I hope he will agree with me that Kipling has described these dreams with felicity. They are strange, romantic, frightening and mysterious. The long series of dreams which these two people have shared from their childhood seems, though you don’t quite know why, so significant of something of high import that it is somewhat of a disappointment that such amazing occurrences should result in no more than“boy meets girl.”It is of course the same difficulty that confronts the reader of the first part of Goethe's Faust. It seems hardly worth while for Faust to have bartered his soul to see Mephistopheles do conjuring tricks in a wine-cellar and to effect the seduction of a lowly maid. I find it difficult to look upon The Brushwood Boy as one of Kipling's best stories. The persons concerned in it are really too good to be true. The Brushwood Boy is heir to a fine estate. He is idolized by his parents, by the keeper who taught him to shoot, by the servants, by the tenants. He is a good shot, a good rider, a hard worker, a brave soldier adored by his men, and after a battle on the North-West Frontier is awarded a D.S.O. and becomes the youngest major in the British army. He is clever, sober and chaste. He is perfect and incredible. But though I carp I cannot deny that it remains a good and moving story admirably told. One must look upon it not as a tale that has any relation to real life, but as much of a fairy story as The Sleeping Beauty or Cinderella.

It was on his short periods of leave that Kipling came to know that Anglo-Indian society which he wrote about in Plain Tales from the Hills, but his experiences as a reporter, so well set forth in the passage I quoted earlier in this essay, surely made it plain to him that in those little stories he had described but one aspect of Anglo-Indian life. What he saw on his various assignments deeply impressed him. I have already spoken of The Bridge-Builders with its fine account of those men who on little pay, with small chance of recognition, gave their youth, their strength, their health to do to the best of their ability the job it was their business to do. In the unfortunately named William the Conqueror Kipling has written a tale in which he shows how two or three ordinary, rather commonplace men, and a woman, the William of the story, fought a disastrous famine all through the hot weather and saved a horde of children from dying of starvation. It is a tale of selfless, stubborn tenacity soberly narrated. In these two stories and in several more, Kipling has told of the obscure men and women who devoted their lives to the service of India. They made many mistakes, for they were but human. Many were stupid. Many were hidebound with prejudice. Many were unimaginative. They kept the peace. They administered justice. They built the roads, the bridges, the railways. They fought famine, flood and pestilence. They treated the sick. It remains to be seen whether those who have succeeded them, not in high place, but in those modest situations in the hands of whose occupants the lot of the common man depends will make as good a job of it as they did.

William the Conqueror is not only the story of a famine; it is a love story as well. I have mentioned the fact that Kipling seems to have shied away, like an unbroken colt, from any treatment of sex. In the Mulvaney stories he makes casual reference to the amours of the soldiery and in Something of Myself he has an indignant passage in which he remarks on the stupid and criminal folly of the authorities who counted it impious“that bazaar prostitutes should be inspected; or that the men should be taught elementary precautions in their dealings with them. This official virtue cost our army in India nine thousand expensive white men a year always laid up from venereal disease.”But he is concerned then not with love, but with an instinct of normal man that demands its satisfaction. I can only remember two stories in which Kipling has attempted (successfully) to represent passion. One is“Love-o’-Women, ”which for this reason I have inserted in this book. It is a terrible, perhaps brutal story, but it is finely and vigorously told, and the end, mysterious and left unexplained though it be, is powerful. Critics have found fault with this end. Matisse once showed a picture of his to a visitor who exclaimed: “I’ve never seen a woman like that”, to which he replied: “It isn’t a woman, madam, it's a picture.”If the painter is permitted certain distortions to achieve the effect he is aiming at, there can be no reason why the writer of fiction should not accord himself the same freedom. Probability is not something settled once for all; it is what you can get your readers to accept as such. Kipling was not writing an official report, he was writing a story. It was his right to make it dramatically effective, if that is what he wanted to do, and if the gentleman-ranker of the story might not have said in real life to the woman he had seduced and ruined the words Kipling has put into his mouth, that is no matter. It is plausible and the reader is moved as Kipling intended him to be.

The other story in which Kipling has depicted genuine passion is Without Benefit of Clergy. It is a beautiful and pathetic tale. If I had to choose for an anthology the best story Kipling ever wrote, this I believe is the one I would choose. Other stories are more characteristic, The Head of the District, for instance, but in this one he has come as near as the medium allows to what the story-teller aims at, but can hardly hope to achieve—perfection.

I have been led to write the above on account of the love scene which gives William the Conqueror its happy ending. It is strangely embarrassing. The two persons concerned are in love with one another; that is made clear; but there is nothing of ecstasy in their love, it is a rather humdrum affair, with already a kind of domestic quality about it. They are two very nice sensible people who will make a good job of married life. The love scene is adolescent. You would expect a schoolboy home for the holidays to talk like that with the local doctor's young daughter, not two grown, efficient persons who have just gone through a harrowing and dangerous experience.

As a rough generalization I would suggest that an author reaches the height of his powers when he is between thirty-five and forty. It takes him till then to learn what Kipling made a point of calling his trade. Till then his work is immature, tentative and experimental. By profiting by past mistakes, by the mere process of living, which brings him experience and a knowledge of human nature, by discovering his own limitations and learning what subjects he is competent to deal with and how best to deal with them, he acquires command over his medium. He is in possession of such talent as he has. He will produce the best work he is capable of for perhaps fifteen years, for twenty if he is lucky, and then his powers gradually dwindle. He loses the vigour of imagination which he had in his prime. He has given all he had to give. He will go on writing, for writing is a habit easy to contract, but hard to break, but what he writes will be only an increasingly pale reminder of what he wrote at his prime.

It was different with Kipling. He was immensely precocious. He was in full possession of his powers almost from the very beginning. Some of the stories in Plain Tales from the Hills are so trivial that later in life he would probably not have thought them worth writing, but they are told clearly, vividly and effectively. Technically there is no fault to find with them. Such faults as they have are owing to the callowness of his youth and not to his want of skill. And when, only just out of his teens, he was transferred to Allahabad and was able to express himself at greater length he wrote a series of tales which can justly be described as masterly. On his first arrival in London, the editor of Macmillan's Magazine, whom he had gone to see, asked him how old he was. It is no wonder that when Kipling told him that in a few months he would be twenty-four, he cried‘My God!’ His accomplishment by then was truly amazing.

But all things have to be paid for in this world. By the end of the century, that is by the time Kipling was thirty-five, he had written his best stories. I do not mean that after that he wrote bad stories, he couldn’t have done that if he’d tried, they were well enough in their way, but they lacked the magic with which the early Indian stories had been infused. It was only when, returning in fancy to the scene of his early life in India, he wrote Kim, that he regained it. Kim is his masterpiece. It must seem strange at first that Kipling after leaving Allahabad never went back to India except for a short visit to his parents at Lahore. After all it was his Indian stories that had brought him his immense fame. He himself called it notoriety, but it was fame. I can only suppose that he felt India had given him all the subjects he could deal with. Once, after he had spent a period in the West Indies he sent me a message to say that I should do well to go there, for there were plenty of stories to be written about the people of the islands, but they were not the sort of stories he could write. He must have felt that there were plenty of stories in India besides those he had written, but that they too were not the sort of stories he could write. For him the vein was worked out.

The Boer War came to pass and Kipling went to South Africa. In India he had conceived a boyish, touching if rather absurd admiration for the officers with whom he was brought in contact. But these gallant gentlemen who cut so fine a figure on the polo field, at gymkhanas, dances and picnics, showed a horrifying incapacity when it came to waging a war very different from the punitive expeditions they had conducted on the North-West Frontier. Officers and men were as brave as he had always thought them, but they were ill led. He surveyed the muddle of that unhappy war with consternation. Did he see that this was the first rent in that great fabric, the British Empire, which was his pride and to the awareness of which he had done so much, in verse and prose, to awaken his fellow-subjects? He wrote two stories, The Captive and The Way that He Took, in which he attacked the inefficiency of the authorities at home and the incompetence of the officers in command. They are good stories, and if I have not given them a place in this volume it is because of the strong element of propaganda in them and because like all stories that have a topical interest the passage of time has deprived them of significance.

I should warn the reader that my opinion that Kipling's best stories are those of which the scene is laid in India is by no means shared by eminent critics. They think those Kipling wrote in what they call his third period show a depth, an insight and a compassion of which they deplore the lack in his Indian tales. For them the height of his achievement is to be found in such stories as An Habitation Enforced, A Madonna of the Trenches, The Wish House and Friendly Brook. An Habitation Enforced is a charming story, but surely rather obvious; and though the other three are good enough they do not seem to me remarkable. It did not need an author of Kipling's great gifts to write them. Just So Stories, Puck of Pook's Hill and Rewards and Fairies are children's books and their worth must be judged by the pleasure they afforded children. This Just So Stories must have done. One can almost hear the squeals of laughter with which they listened to the story of how the elephant got his trunk. In the two other books Puck appears to a little boy and a little girl and produces for their instruction various characters by means of whom they may gain an elementary and romantic acquaintance with English history. I don’t think this was a happy device. The stories are of course well contrived; I like best On the Great Wall, in which Parnesius, the Roman legionary, appears, but I should have liked it better if it had been a straightforward reconstruction of an episode in the Roman occupation of Britain.

The only story Kipling wrote after he settled down in England that I would on no account leave out of this selection is“They.”(In reading it you must keep in mind that his use of the House Beautiful for the country house in which the events he relates take place, reminding one of Ye Olde TeaShoppe and horrors of the same sort, had not been made obnoxious by the vulgar purveyors of whimsy and the pretty-pretty.)“They”is a fine and deeply moving effort of the imagination. In 1899 Kipling went with his wife and children to New York, and he and his elder daughter caught colds which turned into pneumonia. Those of us who are old enough can remember the world-wide concern when the cables told us that Kipling lay at death's door. He recovered, but his daughter died. It cannot be doubted that“They”was inspired by his enduring grief at her loss. Heine said: “Out of my great griefs I make these little songs.”Kipling wrote an exquisite story. Some people have found it obscure and others sentimental. One of the hazards that confront the writer offiction is the danger of slipping from sentiment into sentimentality. The distinction between the two is fine. It may be that sentimentality is merely sentiment that you don’t happen to like. Kipling had the gift of drawing tears, but sometimes, in his stories not for children, but about children, they are tears you resent, for the emotion that draws them is mawkish. There is nothing obscure in“They”and to my mind nothing sentimental.

Kipling was deeply interested in the invention and discoveries which were then transforming our civilization. The reader will remember what effective use he made of wireless in the story of that name. He was fascinated by machines and when he was fascinated by a subject he wrote stories about it. He took a great deal of trouble to get his facts right, and if sometimes he made mistakes, as all authors do, the facts were so unfamiliar to most readers that they did not know. He indulged in technical details for their own sake, not to show off, since though argumentative and self-opinionated as a man, he was modest and unassuming as an author, but for the fun of it. He was like a concert pianist rejoicing in the brilliant ease of his execution who chooses a piece not because of its musical value, but because it gives him an opportunity to exercise his special gift. In one of his stories Kipling says that he had to interrupt the narrator over and over again to ask him to explain his technical terms. The reader of these stories, and he wrote a number of them, unable to do this, remains perplexed. They would be more readable if their author had been less meticulous. In“Their Lawful Occasions, ”for instance, I surmise that only a naval officer could fully understand what goes on, and I am quite prepared to believe that he would find it a jolly good yarn. .007 is a story about a locomotive, The Ship that Found Herself, a story about an ocean tramp; I think you would have to be respectively an engine-driver and a ship-builder to read them with comprehension. In The Jungle Books, and indeed in The Maltese Cat, Kipling made the various animals concerned talk in a highly convincing manner; he used the same device in the locomotive numbered .007 and in the ship named Dimbula. I do not think with advantage. I cannot believe that the ordinary reader knows (or cares) what a garboard strake is, or a bilge-stringer, a high-pressure cylinder or a web-flame.

These stories show another side of Kipling's varied talent, but I have not thought it necessary to include any of them in this selection. The object of fiction (from the reader's standpoint from which the author's may often be very different) is entertainment; and as such to my mind their value is small.

I have been more doubtful about those stories concerned with practical joking, ragging, and drunkenness which he wrote from time to time. There was a Rabelaisian streak in him which the hypocrisy of the times, with its deliberate turning away from what are known as the facts of life, constrained him to express in the description of horseplay and inebriation. In Something of Myself he tells how he showed a story about the“opposite sex”to his mother, who“abolished it”and wrote to him: “Never you do that again.”From the context one may conclude that it dealt with adultery. Whether you find drunkenness amusing depends, I suppose, on your personal idiosyncrasies. It has been my ill-fortune to live much among drunkards, and for my part I have found them boring at their best and disgusting at their worst. But it is evident that this feeling of mine is rare. That stories dealing with drunkards have a strong allure is shown by the popularity of Brugglesmith, a crapulous ruffian, and of Pyecroft, a sottish petty officer, who amused Kipling so much that he wrote several tales about him. Practical joking, till the very recent past, seems to have had an appeal that was universal. Spanish literature of the Golden Age is full of it and everyone remembers the cruel practical jokes that were played on Don Quixote. In the Victorian Age it was still thought funny and from a recently published book we may learn that it was practised with delight in the highest circles. Here again it depends on your temperament whether it amuses you or whether it doesn’t. I must confess that I read Kipling's stories which deal with this subject with discomfort. And the hilarity which overcomes the perpetrators of the exploit grates upon me; they are not content with laughing at the humiliation of their victim; they lean against one another helpless with laughter, they roll off their chairs, they collapse shrieking, they claw the carpet; and in one story the narrator takes a room at an inn so that he may have his laugh out. There is only one of these tales that I have found frankly amusing and since I thought it only right to give the reader at least one example of this kind of story I have printed it in this volume. It is called The Village that Voted the Earth Was Flat. Here the comedy is rich, the victim deserves his punishment, and his punishment is severe without being brutal.

I have in this essay only referred casually to Kipling's success. It was enormous. Nothing like it had been seen since Dickens took the reading world by storm with The Pickwick Papers. Nor did he have to wait for it. Already in 1890 Henry James was writing to Stevenson that Kipling, “the star of the hour, ”was Stevenson's nearest rival and Stevenson was writing to Henry James that Kipling was“too clever to live.”It looks as though they were both a trifle taken aback by the appearance of this“infant monster”as James called him. They acknowledged his brilliant parts, but with reservations.“He amazes me by his precocity and various endowment, ”wrote Stevenson.“But he alarms me by his copiousness and haste...I was never capable of—and surely never guilty of—such a debauch of production…I look on, I admire, I rejoice for myself; but in a kind of ambition we all have for our tongue and literature I am wounded….Certainly Kipling has gifts; the fairy godmothers were all tipsy at his christening: what will he do with them?”

But copiousness is not a defect in a writer; it is a merit. All the greatest authors have had it. Of course not all their production is of value; only the mediocre can sustain a constant level. It is because the great authors wrote a great deal that now and then they produced great works. Kipling was no exception. I don’t believe any writer is a good judge of the writing of his contemporaries, for he naturally likes best the sort of thing he does himself. It is difficult for him to appreciate merits that he does not possess. Stevenson and James were not ungenerous men and they recognized Kipling's great abilities, but from what we know of them we can guess how disconcerted they were by the boisterous exuberance and the sentimentality of some of his tales and the brutality and grimness of others.

Of course Kipling had his detractors. The plodding writers who after years of labour had achieved but a modest place in the literary world found it hard to bear that this young man, coming from nowhere, without any of the social graces, should win, apparently with little effort, so spectacular a success; and as we know, they consoled themselves by prophesying (as once before they had of Dickens) that as he had come up like a rocket he would go down like the stick. It was objected to Kipling that he put too much of himself into his stories. But when you come down to brass tacks what else has an author to give you but himself? Sometimes, like Sterne for instance, or Charles Lamb, he gives you himself with a beguiling frankness, it is both the inspiration and the mainstay of his creativity; but even though he tries his best to be objective what he writes is inevitably infused with his ego. You cannot read a dozen pages of Madame Bovary without receiving a strong impression of Flaubert's irascible, pessimistic, morbid and self-centred personality. Kipling's critics were wrong to blame him for introducing his personality into his stories. What they meant of course was that they did not like the personality he presented to them; and that is understandable. In his early work he exhibited characteristics which were offensive. You received the impression of a bumptious, arrogant young man, extravagantly cock-sure and knowing; and this necessarily excited the antagonism of his critics. For such an assumption of superiority as these rather unamiable traits indicate affronts one's self-esteem.

Kipling was widely accused of vulgarity: so were Balzac and Dickens; I think only because they dealt with aspects of life that offended persons of refinement. We are tougher now: when we call someone refined we do not think we are paying him a compliment. But one of the most absurd charges brought against him was that his stories were anecdotes, which the critics who made it thought was to condemn him (as they sometimes still do); but if they had troubled to consult the Oxford Dictionary they would have seen that a meaning it gives to the word is: “The narration of a detached incident, or of a single event, told as being in itself interesting or striking.”That is a perfect definition of a short story. The story of Ruth, the story of the Matron of Ephesus, Boccaccio's story of Federigo degli Alberighi and his falcon are all anecdotes. So are Boule de Suif, La Parure and L’Héritage. An anecdote is the bony structure of a story which gives it form and coherence and which the author clothes with flesh, blood and nerves. No one is obliged to read stories, and if you don’t like them unless there is something in them more than a story, there is nothing to do about it. You may not like oysters, no one can blame you for that, but it is unreasonable to condemn them because they don’t possess the emotional quality of a beefsteak and kidney pudding. It is equally unreasonable to find fault with a story because it is only a story. That is just what some of Kipling's detractors have done. He was a very talented man, but not a profound thinker—indeed I cannot think of any great novelist who was; he had a consummate gift for telling a certain kind of story and he enjoyed telling it. He was wise enough for the most part to do what he could do best. As he was a sensible man, he was no doubt pleased when people liked his stories and took it with a shrug of the shoulders when they didn’t.

Another fault found with him was that he had little power of characterization. I don’t think the critics who did this quite understood the place of characterization in a short story. Of course you can write a story with the intention of displaying a character. Flaubert did it in Un Coeur Simple and Chekhov in The Darling, which Tolstoi thought so well of; though a purist might object that they are not short stories, but potted novels. Kipling was concerned with incident. In a tale so concerned you need only tell enough about the persons who take part in it to bring them to life; you show them at the moment you are occupied with; they are inevitably static. To show the development of character an author needs the passage of time and the elbow-room of a novel. Perhaps the most remarkable character in fiction is Julien Sorel, but how could Stendhal have shown the development of his complicated character in a short story? Now, I suggest that Kipling drew his characters quite firmly enough for his purpose. There is a distinction to be made between“characters”and character. Mulvaney, Ortheris and Learoyd are“characters.”It is easy enough to create them. Findlayson in The Bridge-Builders, and Scott and William in William the Conqueror have character; and to delineate that is much more difficult. It is true that they are very ordinary, commonplace people, but that gives point to the narrative, and surely Kipling was well aware of it. The father and mother of the Brushwood Boy are not, as Kipling thought, “County, ”landed gentry living on an ancestral estate, but a nice, worthy couple from Arnold Bennett's Five Towns who, after amassing a competence, had settled down in the country. Though lightly sketched, they are alive, recognizable human beings. Mrs. Hauksbee was not the fashionable and distinguished creature he thought her, she was a rather second-rate little woman with a very good opinion of herself, but she is far from a lay-figure. We have all met her. Yardley-Orde in The Head of the District dies four pages after the story opens, but so sufficiently has Kipling characterized him that anyone could write his life-history, after the pattern of one of Aubrey's Lives, with a very fair chance that it would be accurate. I hurry on so that I may not yield to the temptation of writing it here and now to show how easily it could be done.

A distinguished author not long ago told me that he disliked Kipling's style so much that he could not read him. The critics of his own day seem to have found it abrupt, jerky and mannered. One of them said that“it must be insisted that slang is not strength, nor does the abuse of the full stop ensure crispness.”True. An author uses slang to reproduce conversation accurately and in the course of his narrative to give his prose a conversational air. The chief objection to it is that its vogue is transitory and in a few years it is dated and may even be incomprehensible. Sometimes of course it passes into the language and then gains a literary validity so that not even a purist can object to its use. Kipling wrote in shorter sentences than were at that time usual. That can no longer surprise us, and since the lexicographers tell us that a sentence is a series of words, forming the grammatically complete expression of a single thought, there seems no reason why, when an author has done just this, he should not point the fact with a full stop. He is indeed right to do so. George Moore, no lenient critic of his contemporaries, admired Kipling's style for its sonority and its rhythm.“Others have written more beautifully, but no one that I can call to mind has written so copiously…. He writes with the whole language, with the language of the Bible, and with the language of the street.”Kipling's vocabulary was rich. He chose his words, often very unexpected words, for their colour, their precision, their cadence. He knew what he wanted to say and said it incisively. His prose, with which alone I am concerned, had pace and vigour. Like every other author he had his mannerisms. Some, like his unseemly addiction to biblical phrases, he quickly discarded; others he retained. He continued throughout his life to begin a sentence with a relative. Which was a pity. He continued to make deplorable use of the poetic ere when it would have been more natural to say before. Once at least he wrote e’en for even. These are minor points. Kipling has so made his style his own that I don’t suppose anyone to-day would care to write like him, even if he could, but I don’t see how one can deny that the instrument he constructed was admirably suited to the purpose to which he put it. He seldom indulged in long descriptions, but with his seeing eye and quick perception he was able by means of this instrument to put before the reader with extreme vividness the crowded Indian scene in all its fantastic variety.

If in this essay I have not hesitated to point out what seemed to me Kipling's defects, I hope I have made it plain how great I think were his merits. The short story is not a form of fiction in which the English have on the whole excelled. The English, as their novels show, are inclined to diffuseness. They have never been much interested in form. Succinctness goes against their grain. But the short story demands form. It demands succinctness. Diffuseness kills it. It depends on construction. It does not admit of loose ends. It must be complete in itself. All these qualities you will find in Kipling's stories when he was at his magnificent best, and this, happily for us, he was in story after story. Rudyard Kipling is the only writer of short stories our country has produced who can stand comparison with Guy de Maupassant and Chekhov. He is our greatest story writer. I can’t believe he will ever be equalled. I am sure he can never be excelled.

The Complete Short Stories of W. Somerset Maugham Volume I—East and West (Preface) (1921—1952)

This book contains thirty stories. They are all about the same length and on the same scale. The first was written in 1919 and the last in 1931. Though in early youth I had written a number of short stories, for a long time, twelve or fifteen years at least, occupied with the drama, I had ceased to do so; and when a journey to the South Seas unexpectedly provided me with themes that seemed to suit this medium, it was as a beginner of over forty that I wrote the story which is now called Rain. Since it caused some little stir the reader of this preface will perhaps have patience with me if I transcribe the working notes, made at the time, on which it was constructed. They are written in hackneyed and slipshod phrases, without grace; for nature has not endowed me with the happy gift of hitting instinctively upon the perfect word to indicate an object and the unusual but apt adjective to describe it. I was travelling from Honolulu to Pago Pago and, hoping they might at some time be of service, I jotted down as usual my impressions of such of my fellow-passengers as attracted my attention. This is what I said of Miss Thompson: “Plump, pretty in a coarse fashion, perhaps not more than twenty-seven. She wore a white dress and a large white hat, long white boots from which the calves bulged in cotton stockings.”There had been a raid on the Red Light district in Honolulu just before we sailed and the gossip of the ship spread the report that she was making the journey to escape arrest. My notes go on: “W. The Missionary. He was a tall thin man, with long limbs loosely jointed, he had hollow cheeks and high cheek bones, his fine, large, dark eyes were deep in their sockets, he had full sensual lips, he wore his hair rather long. He had a cadaverous air and a look of suppressed fire. His hands were large, with long fingers, rather finely shaped. His naturally pale skin was deeply burned by the tropical sun. Mrs. W. His Wife. She was a little woman with her hair very elaborately done, New England; not prominent blue eyes behind gold-rimmed pince-nez, her face was long like a sheep's, but she gave no impression of foolishness, rather of extreme alertness. She had the quick movements of a bird. The most noticeable thing about her was her voice, high, metallic, and without inflection; it fell on the ear with a hard monotony, irritating to the nerves like the ceaseless clamour of a pneumatic drill. She was dressed in black and wore round her neck a gold chain from which hung a small cross.”She told me that W. was a missionary on the Gilberts and his district consisting of widely separated islands he frequently had to go distances by canoe. During this time she remained at headquarters and managed the mission. Often the seas were very rough and the journeys were not without peril. He was a medical missionary. She spoke of the depravity of the natives in a voice which nothing could hush, but with a vehement, unctuous horror, telling me of their marriage customs which were obscene beyond description. She said, when first they went it was impossible to find a single good girl in any of the villages. She inveighed against dancing. I talked with the missionary and his wife but once, and with Miss Thompson not at all. Here is the note for the story: “A prostitute, flying from Honolulu after a raid, lands at Pago Pago. There lands there also a missionary and his wife. Also the narrator. All are obliged to stay there owing to an outbreak of measles. The missionary finding out her profession persecutes her. He reduces her to misery, shame, and repentance, he has no mercy on her. He induces the governor to order her return to Honolulu. One morning he is found with his throat cut by his own hand and she is once more radiant and self-possessed. She looks at men and scornfully exclaims: ‘dirty pigs.’”

An intelligent critic, who combines wide reading and a sensitive taste with a knowledge of the world rare among those who follow his calling, has found in my stories the influence of Guy de Maupassant. That is not strange. When I was a boy he was considered the best short story writer in France and I read his works with avidity. From the age of fifteen whenever I went to Paris I spent most of my afternoons poring over the books in the galleries of the Odéon I have never passed more enchanted hours. The attendants in their long smocks were indifferent to the people who sauntered about looking at the books and they would let you read for hours without bothering. There was a shelf filled with the works of Guy de Maupassant, but they cost three francs fifty a volume and that was not a sum I was prepared to spend. I had to read as best I could standing up and peering between the uncut pages. Sometimes when no attendant was looking I would hastily cut a page and thus read more conveniently. Fortunately some of them were issued in a cheap edition at seventy-five centimes and I seldom came away without one of these. In this manner, before I was eighteen, I had read all the best stories. It is natural enough that when at that age I began writing stories myself I should unconsciously have chosen those little masterpieces as a model. I might very well have hit upon a worse.

Maupassant's reputation does not stand as high as it did, and it is evident now that there is much in his work to repel. He was a Frenchman of his period in violent reaction against the romantic age which was finishing in the saccharine sentimentality of Octave Feuillet (admired by Matthew Arnold) and in the impetuous slop of George Sand. He was a naturalist, aiming at truth at all costs, but the truth he achieved looks to us now a trifle superficial. He does not analyze his characters. He takes little interest in the reason why. They act, but wherefore he does not know.“For me, ”he says, “psychology in a novel or in a story consists in this: to show the inner man by his life.”That is very well, that is what we all try to do, but the gesture will not by itself always indicate the motive. The result with Maupassant was a simplification of character which is effective enough in a short story, but on reflection leaves you unconvinced. There is more in men than that, you say. Again, he was obsessed by the tiresome notion, common then to his countrymen, that it was a duty a man owed himself to hop into bed with everywoman under forty that he met. His characters indulge their sexual desire to gratify their self-esteem. They are like the people who eat caviar when they are not hungry because it is expensive. Perhaps the only human emotion that affects his characters with passion is avarice. This he can understand; it fills him with horror, but notwithstanding he has a sneaking sympathy with it. He was slightly common. But for all this it would be foolish to deny his excellence. An author has the right to be judged by his best work. No author is perfect. You must accept his defects; they are often the necessary complement of his merits; and this may be said in gratitude to posterity that it is very willing to do this. It takes what is good in a writer and is not troubled by what is bad. It goes so far sometimes, to the confusion of the candid reader, as to claim a profound significance for obvious faults. So you will see the critics (the awe-inspiring voice of posterity)find subtle reasons to explain to his credit something in a play of Shakespeare's that any dramatist could tell them needed no other explanation than haste, indifference or wilfulness. Maupassant's stories are good stories. The anecdote is interesting apart from the narration so that it would secure attention if it were told over the dinner-table; and that seems to me a very great merit indeed. However halting your words and insipid your rendering, you could not fail to interest your listeners if you told them the bare story of Boule de Suif, L’H ritage or La Parure. These stories have a beginning, a middle and an end. They do not wander along an uncertain line so that you cannot see whither they are leading, but follow without hesitation, from exposition to climax, a bold and vigorous curve. It may be that they have no great spiritual significance. Maupassant did not aim at that. He looked upon himself as a plain man; no good writer was ever less a man of letters. He did not pretend to be a philosopher, and here he was well-advised, for when he indulges in reflection he is commonplace. But within his limits he is admirable. He has an astonishing capacity for creating living people. He can afford little space, but in a few pages can set before you half a dozen persons so sharply seen and vividly described that you know all about them that you need. Their outline is clear; they are distinguishable from one another; and they breathe the breath of life. They have no complexity, they lack strangely the indecision, the unexpectedness, the mystery that we see in human beings; they are in fact simplified for the purposes of the story. But they are not deliberately simplified: those keen eyes of his saw clearly, but they did not see profoundly; it is a happy chance that they saw all that was necessary for him to achieve the aim he had in view. He treats the surroundings in the same way, he sets his scene accurately, briefly and effectively; but whether he is describing the charming landscape of Normandy or the stuffy, overcrowded drawing-rooms of the eighties his object is the same, to get on with the story. On his own lines I do not think that Maupassant is likely to be surpassed. If his excellence is not at the moment so apparent it is because what he wrote must now stand comparison with the very different, more subtle and moving work of Chekhov.

His stories are the models that young writers naturally take. This is understandable. On the face of it, it is easier to write stories like Chekhov's than stories like Maupassant's. To invent a story interesting in itself apart from the telling is a difficult thing, the power to do it is a gift of nature, it cannot be acquired by taking thought, and it is a gift that very few people have. Chekhov had many gifts, but not this one. If you try to tell one of his stories you will find that there is nothing to tell. The anecdote, stripped of its trimmings, is insignificant and often inane. It was grand for people who wanted to write a story and couldn’t think of a plot to discover that you could very well manage without one. If you could take two or three persons, describe their mutual relations and leave it at that, why then it wasn’t so hard to write a story; and if you could flatter yourself that this really was art, what could be more charming?

But I am not quite sure that it is wise to found a technique on a writer's defects. I have little doubt that Chekhov would have written stories with an ingenious, original and striking plot if he had been able to think of them. It was not in his temperament. Like all good writers he made a merit of his limitations. Was it not Goethe who said that an artist only achieves greatness when he recognizes them? If a short story is a piece of prose dealing with more or less imaginary persons no one wrote better short stories than Chekhov. If, however, as some think, it should be the representation of an action, complete in itself and of a certain limited length, he leaves something to be desired. He put his own idea clearly enough in these words: “Why write about a man getting into a submarine and going to the North Pole to reconcile himself to the world, while his beloved at that moment throws herself with a hysterical shriek from the belfry? All this is untrue and does not happen in real life. One must write about simple things: how Peter Semionovitch married Maria Ivanovna. That is all.”But there is no reason why a writer should not make a story of an unusual incident. The fact that something happens every day does not make it more important. The pleasure of recognition, which is the pleasure thus aimed at, is the lowest of the aesthetic pleasures. It is not a merit in a story that it is undramatic. Maupassant chose very ordinary people and sought to show what there was of drama in the common happenings of their lives. He chose the significant incident and extracted from it all the drama possible. It is a method as praiseworthy as another; it tends to make a story more absorbing. Probability is not the only test; and probability is a constantly changing thing. At one time it was accepted that the“call of the blood”should enable long-lost children to recognize their parents and that a woman only had to get into men's clothes to pass as a man. Probability is what you can get the readers of your time to swallow. Nor did Chekhov, notwithstanding his principles, adhere to his canon unless it suited him. Take one of the most beautiful and touching of his stories, The Bishop. It describes the approach of death with great tenderness, but there is no reason for the Bishop to die, and a better technician would have made the cause of death an integral part of the story.“Everything that has no relation to the story must be ruthlessly thrown away, ”he says in his advice to Schoukin.“If in the first chapter you say that a gun hung on the wall, in the second or third chapter it must without fail be discharged.”So when the Bishop eats some tainted fish and a few days later dies of typhoid we may suppose that it was the tainted fish that killed him. If that is so he did not die of typhoid, but of ptomaine poisoning, and the symptoms were not as described. But of course Chekhov did not care. He was determined that his good and gentle bishop should die and for his own purposes he wanted him to die in a particular way. I do not understand the people who say of Chekhov's stories that they are slices of life, I do not understand, that is, if they mean that they offer a true and typical picture of life. I do not believe they do that, nor do I believe they ever did. I think they are marvellously lifelike, owing to the writer's peculiar talent, but I think they are deliberately chosen to square with the prepossessions of a sick, sad and overworked, gray-minded man. I do not blame them for that. Every writer sees the world in his own way and gives you his own picture of it. The imitation of life is not a reasonable aim of art; it is a discipline to which the artist from time to time subjects himself when the stylization of life has reached an extravagance that outrages common sense. For Chekhov life is like a game of billiards in which you never pot the red, bring off a losing hazard or make a cannon, and should you by a miraculous chance get a fluke you will almost certainly cut the cloth. He sighs sadly because the futile do not succeed, the idle do not work, liars do not speak the truth, drunkards are not sober and the ignorant have no culture. I suppose that it is this attitude that makes his chief characters somewhat indistinct. He can give you a striking portrait of a man in two lines, as much as can be said of anyone in two lines to set before you a living person, but with elaboration he seems to lose his grasp of the individual. His men are shadowy creatures, with vague impulses to good, but without will-power, shiftless, untruthful, fond of fine words, often with great ideals, but with no power of action. His women are lachrymose, slatternly and feeble-minded. Though they think it a sin they will commit fornication with anyone who asks them, not because they have passion, not even because they want to, but because it is too much trouble to refuse. It is only in his description of young girls that he seems touched with a tender indulgence.“Alas! regardless of their doom, the little victims play.”He is moved by their charm, the gaiety of their laughter, their ingenuousness and their vitality; but it all leads to nothing. They make no effort to conquer their happiness, but yield passively to the first obstacle in the way.

But if I have ventured to make these observations I beg the reader not to think that I have anything but a very great admiration for Chekhov. No writer, I repeat, is faultless. It is well to admire him for his merits. Not to recognize his imperfections, but rather to insist that they are excellencies, can in the long run only hurt his reputation. Chekhov is extremely readable. That is a writer's supreme virtue and one upon which sufficient stress is often not laid. He shared it with Maupassant. Both of them were professional writers who turned out stories at more or less regular intervals to earn their living. They wrote as a doctor visits his patients or a solicitor sees his clients. It was part of the day's work. They had to please their readers. They were not always inspired, it was only now and then that they produced a masterpiece, but it is very seldom that they wrote anything that did not hold the reader's attention to the last line. They both wrote for papers and magazines. Sometimes a critic will describe a book of short stories as magazine stories and thus in his own mind damn them. That is foolish. No form of art is produced unless there is a demand for it and if newspapers and magazines did not publish short stories they would not be written. All stories are magazine stories or newspaper stories. The writers must accept certain (but constantly changing) conditions; it has never been shown yet that a good writer was unable to write his best owing to the conditions under which alone he could gain a public for his work. That has never been anything but an excuse of the second-rate. I suspect that Chekhov's great merit of concision is due to the fact that the newspapers for which he habitually wrote could only give him a certain amount of space. He said that stories should have neither a beginning nor an end. He could not have meant that literally. You might as well ask of afish that it should have neither head nor tail. It would not be afish if it hadn’t. The way Chekhov in reality begins a story is wonderfully good. He gives the facts at once, in a few lines; he has an unerring feeling for the essential statements, and he sets them down baldly, but with great precision, so that you know at once whom you have to deal with and what the circumstances are. Maupassant often started his stories with an introduction designed to put the reader in a certain frame of mind. It is a dangerous method only justified by success. It may be dull. It may throw the reader off the scent; you have won his interest in certain characters and then instead of being told what you would like to know about them, your interest is claimed for other people in other circumstances. Chekhov preached compactness, in his longer stories he did not always achieve it. He was distressed by the charge brought against him that he was indifferent to moral and sociological questions and when he had ample space at his command he seized the opportunity to show that they meant as much to him as to any other right-thinking person. Then in long and somewhat tedious conversations he would make his characters express his own conviction that, whatever the conditions of things might be then, at some not far distant date (say 1934) the Russians would be free, tyranny would exist no longer, the poor would hunger no more and happiness, peace and brotherly love rule in the vast empire. But these were aberrations forced upon him by the pressure of opinion (common in all countries) that the writer of fiction should be a prophet, a social reformer and a philosopher. In his shorter stories Chekhov attained the concision he aimed at in a manner that is almost miraculous.

And no one had a greater gift than he for giving you the intimate feeling of a place, a landscape, a conversation or (within his limited range) a character. I suppose this is what people mean by the vague word atmosphere. Chekhov seems to have achieved it very simply, without elaborate explanation or long description, by a precise narration of facts; and I think it was due with him to a power of seeing things with amazing naivety. The Russians are a semi-barbarous people and they seem to have retained the power of seeing things naturally, as though they existed in a vacuum; while we in the West, with our complicated culture behind us, see things with the associations they have gathered during long centuries of civilization. They almost seem to see the thing in itself. Most writers, especially those living abroad, have in the last few years been shown numbers of stories by Russian refugees who vainly hope to earn a few guineas by placing them somewhere. Though dealing with the present day they might very well be stories by Chekhov not at his best; they all have that direct, sincere vision. It is a national gift. In no one was it more acutely developed than in Chekhov.

But I have not yet pointed out what to my mind is Chekhov's greatest merit. Since I am not a critic and do not know the proper critical expressions I am obliged to describe this as best I can in terms of my own feeling. Chekhov had an amazing power of surrounding people with air so that, though he does not put them before you in the round and they lack the coarse, often brutal vitality of Maupassant's figures, they live with a strange and unearthly life. They are not lit by the hard light of common day but suffused in a mysterious grayness. They move in this as though they were disembodied spirits. It is their souls that you seem to see. The subconscious seems to come to the surface and they communicate with one another directly without the impediment of speech. Strange, futile creatures, with descriptions of their outward seeming tacked on them like a card on an exhibit in a museum, they move as mysteriously as the tortured souls who crowded about Dante when he walked in Hell. You have the feeling of a vast, gray, lost throng wandering aimless in some dim underworld. It fills you with awe and with uneasiness. I have hinted that Chekhov had no great talent for inventing a multiplicity of persons. Under different names, with different environment, the same characters recur. It is as though, when you looked at the soul, the superficial difference vanishes and everyone is more or less the same. His people seem strangely to slip into one another as though they were not distinct individuals, but temporary fictions, and as though in truth they were all part of one another. The importance of a writer in the long run rests on his uniqueness. I do not know that anyone but Chekhov has so poignantly been able to represent spirit communing with spirit. It is this that makes one feel that Maupassant in comparison is obvious and vulgar. The strange, the terrible thing is that, looking at man in their different ways, these two great writers, Maupassant and Chekhov, saw eye to eye. One was content to look upon the flesh, the other, more nobly and subtly, surveyed the spirit; but they agreed that life was tedious and insignificant and that men were base, unintelligent and pitiful.

I hope the reader will not be impatient with me because in an introduction to my own stories I have dwelt at length on these remarkable writers. Maupassant and Chekhov are the two authors of short stories whose influence survives to the present day and all of us who cultivate the medium must in the end be judged by the standards they have set.

So far as I could remember it I have placed the stories in this volume in the order in which they were written. I thought it might possibly interest the reader to see how I had progressed from the tentativeness of the first ones, when I was very much at the mercy of my anecdote, to the relative certainty of the later ones when I had learnt so to arrange my material as to attain the result I wanted. Though all but two have been published in a magazine these stories were not written with that end in view. When I began to write them I was fortunately in a position of decent independence and I wrote them as a relief from work which I thought I had been too long concerned with. It is often said that stories are no better than they are because the editors of magazines insist on their being written to a certain pattern. This has not been my experience. All but Rain and The Book-Bag were published in the Cosmopolitan magazine and Ray Long, the Editor, never put pressure on me to write other than as I wished. Sometimes the stories were cut and this is reasonable since no editor can afford one contributor more than a certain amount of space; but I was never asked to make the smallest alteration to suit what might be supposed to be the taste of the readers. Ray Long paid me for them not only with good money, but with generous appreciation. I did not value this less. We authors are simple, childish creatures and we treasure a word of praise from those who buy our wares. Most of them were written in groups from notes made as they occurred to me, and in each group I left naturally enough to the last those that seemed most difficult to write. A story is difficult to write when you do not know all about it from the beginning, but for part of it must trust to our imagination and experience. Sometimes the curve does not intuitively present itself and you have to resort to this method and that to get the appropriate line.

I beg the reader not to be deceived by the fact that a good many of these stories are told in the first person into thinking that they are experiences of my own. This is merely a device to gain verisimilitude. It is one that has its defects, for it may strike the reader that the narrator could not know all the events he sets forth; and when he tells a story in the first person at one remove, when he reports, I mean, a story that someone tells him, it may very well seem that the speaker, a police officer, for example, or a sea-captain, could never have expressed himself with such facility and with such elaboration. Every convention has its disadvantages. These must be as far as possible disguised and what cannot be disguised must be accepted. The advantage of this one is its directness. It makes it possible for the writer to tell no more than he knows. Making no claim to omniscience, he can frankly say when a motive or an occurrence is unknown to him, and thus often give his story a plausibility that it might otherwise lack. It tends also to put the reader on intimate terms with the author. Since Maupassant and Chekhov, who tried so hard to be objective, nevertheless are so nakedly personal, it has sometimes seemed to me that if the author can in no way keep himself out of his work it might be better if he put in as much of himself as possible. The danger is that he may put in too much and thus be as boring as a talker who insists on monopolizing the conversation. Like all conventions this one must be used with discretion. The reader may have observed that in the original note of Rain the narrator was introduced, but in the story as written omitted.

Three of the stories in this volume were told me and I had nothing to do but make them probable, coherent and dramatic. They are The Letter, Footprints in the Jungle and The Book-Bag. The rest were invented, as I have shown Rain was, by the accident of my happening upon persons here and there, who in themselves or from something I heard about them suggested a theme that seemed suitable for a short story. This brings me to a topic that has always concerned writers and that has at times given the public, the writer's raw material, some uneasiness. There are authors who state that they never have a living model in mind when they create a character. I think they are mistaken. They are of this opinion because they have not scrutinized with sufficient care the recollections and impressions upon which they have constructed the person who, they fondly imagine, is of their invention. If they did they would discover that, unless he was taken from some book they had read, a practice by no means uncommon, he was suggested by one or more persons they had at one time known or seen. The great writers of the past made no secret of the fact that their characters were founded on living people. We know that the good Sir Walter Scott, a man of the highest principles, portrayed his father, with sharpness first and then, when the passage of years had changed his temper, with tolerance; Henri Beyle, in the manuscript of at least one of his novels, has written in at the side the names of the real persons who were his models; and this is what Turgenev himself says: “For my part, I ought to confess that I never attempted to create a type without having, not an idea, but a living person, in whom the various elements were harmonized together, to work from. I have always needed some groundwork on which I could treadfirmly.”With Flaubert it is the same story; that Dickens used his friends and relations freely is notorious; and if you read the Journal of Jules Renard, a most instructive book to anyone who wishes to know how a writer works, you will see the care with which he set down every little detail about the habits, ways of speech and appearance of the persons he knew. When he came to write a novel he made use of this storehouse of carefully collected information. In Chekhov's diary you will find notes which were obviously made for use at some future time, and in the recollections of his friends there are frequent references to the persons who were the originals of certain of his characters. It looks as though the practice were very common. I should have said it was necessary and inevitable. Its convenience is obvious. You are much more likely to depict a character who is a recognizable human being, with his own individuality, if you have a living model. The imagination can create nothing out of the void. It needs the stimulus of sensation. The writer whose creative faculty has been moved by something peculiar in a person (peculiar perhaps only to the writer) falsifies his idea if he attempts to describe that person other than as he sees him. Character hangs together and if you try to throw people off the scent, by making a short man tall for example (as though stature had no effect on character) or by making him choleric when he has the concomitant traits of an equable temper, you will destroy the plausible harmony (to use the beautiful phrase of Baltasar Gracian) of which it consists. The whole affair would be plain sailing if it were not for the feelings of the persons concerned. The writer has to consider the vanity of the human race and the Schadenfreude which is one of its commonest and most detestable failings. A man's friends will find pleasure in recognizing him in a book and though the author may never even have seen him will point out to him, especially if it is un flattering, what they consider his living image. Often someone will recognize a trait he knows in himself or a description of the place he lives in and in his conceit jumps to the conclusion that the character described is a portrait of himself. Thus in the story called The Outstation the Resident was suggested by a British Consul I had once known in Spain and it was written ten years after his death, but I have heard that the Resident of a district in Sarawak, which I described in the story, was much affronted because he thought I had had him in mind. The two men had not a trait in common. I do not suppose any writer attempts to draw an exact portrait. Nothing, indeed, is so unwise as to put into a work of fiction a person drawn line by line from life. His values are all wrong, and, strangely enough, he does not make the other characters in the story seem false, but himself. He never convinces. That is why the many writers who have been attracted by the singular and powerful figure of the late Lord Northcliffe have never succeeded in presenting a credible personage. The model a writer chooses is seen through his own temperament and if he is a writer of any originality what he sees need have little relation with the facts. He may see a tall man short or a generous one avaricious; but, I repeat, if he sees him tall, tall he must remain. He takes only what he wants of the living man. He uses him as a peg on which to hang his own fancies. To achieve his end (the plausible harmony that nature so seldom provides) he gives him traits that the model does not possess. He makes him coherent and substantial. The created character, the result of imagination founded on fact, is art, and life in the raw, as we know, is of this only the material. The odd thing is that when the charge is made that an author has copied this person or the other from life, emphasis is laid only on his less praiseworthy characteristics. If you say of a character that he is kind to his mother, but beats his wife, everyone will cry: Ah, that's Brown, how beastly to say he beats his wife; and no one thinks for a moment of Jones and Robinson who are notoriously kind to their mothers. I draw from this the somewhat surprising conclusion that we know our friends by their vices and not by their virtues. I have stated that I never even spoke to Miss Thompson in Rain. This is a character that the world has not found wanting in vividness. Though but one of a multitude of writers my practice is doubtless common to most, so that I may be permitted to give another instance of it. I was once asked to meet at dinner two persons, a husband and wife, of whom I was told only what the reader will shortly read. I think I never knew their names. I should certainly not recognize them if I met them in the street. Here are the notes I made at the time.“A stout, rather pompous man of fifty, with pince-nez, gray-haired, a florid complexion, blue eyes, a neat gray moustache. He talks with assurance. He is resident of an outlying district and is somewhat impressed with the importance of his position. He despises the men who have let themselves go under the influence of the climate and the surroundings. He has travelled extensively during his short leaves in the East and knows Java, the Philippines, the coast of China and the Malay Peninsula. He is very British, very patriotic; he takes a great deal of exercise. He has been a very heavy drinker and always took a bottle of whisky to bed with him. His wife has entirely cured him and now he drinks nothing but water. She is a little insignificant woman, with sharp features, thin, with a sallow skin and a flat chest. She is very badly dressed. She has all the prejudices of an Englishwoman. All her family for generations have been in second-rate regiments. Except that you know that she has caused her husband to cease drinking entirely you would think her quite colourless and unimportant.”On these materials I invented the story which is called Before the Party. I do not believe that any candid person could think that these two people had cause for complaint because they had been made use of. It is true that I should never have thought of the story if I had not met them, but anyone who takes the trouble to read it will see how insignificant was the incident (the taking of the bottle to bed) that suggested it and how differently the two chief characters have in the course of writing developed from the brief sketch which was their foundation.

“Critics are like horse-flies which prevent the horse from ploughing, ”said Chekhov.“For over twenty years I have read criticisms of my stories, and I do not remember a single remark of any value or one word of valuable advice. Only once Skabichevsky wrote something which made an impression on me. He said I would die in a ditch, drunk.”He was writing for twenty-five years and during that time his writing was constantly attacked. I do not know whether the critics of the present day are naturally of a less ferocious temper; I must allow that on the whole the judgment that has been passed on the stories in this volume when from time to time a collection has been published in book form has been favourable. One epithet, however, has been much applied to them, which has puzzled me; they have been described with disconcerting frequency as“competent.”Now on the face of it I might have thought this laudatory, for to do a thing competently is certainly more deserving of praise than to do it incompetently, but the adjective has been used in a disparaging sense and, anxious to learn and if possible to improve, I have asked myself what was in the mind of the critics who thus employed it. Of course none of us is liked by everybody and it is necessary that a man's writing, which is so intimate a revelation of himself, should be repulsive to persons who are naturally antagonistic to the creature he is. This should leave him unperturbed. But when an author's work is somewhat commonly found to have a quality that is unattractive to many it is sensible of him to give the matter his attention. There is evidently something that a number of people do not like in my stories and it is this they try to express when they damn them with the faint praise of competence. I have a notion that it is the definiteness of their form. I hazard the suggestion (perhaps unduly flattering to myself) because this particular criticism has never been made in France where my stories have had with the critics and the public much greater success than they have had in England. The French, with their classical sense and their orderly minds, demand a precise form and are exasperated by a work in which the ends are left lying about, themes are propounded and not resolved and a climax is foreseen and then eluded. This precision on the other hand has always been slightly antipathetic to the English. Our great novels have been shapeless and this, far from disconcerting their readers, has given them a sense of security. This is the life we know, they have thought, with its arbitrariness and inconsequence; we can put out of our minds the irritating thought that two and two make four. If I am right in this surmise I can do nothing about it and I must resign myself to being called competent for the rest of my days. My prepossessions in the arts are on the side of law and order. I like a story that fits. I did not take to writing stories seriously till I had had much experience as a dramatist, and this experience taught me to leave out everything that did not serve the dramatic value of my story. It taught me to make incident follow incident in such a manner as to lead up to the climax I had in mind. I am not unaware of the disadvantages of this method. It gives a tightness of effect that is sometimes disconcerting. You feel that life does not dovetail into its various parts with such neatness. In life stories straggle, they begin nowhere and tail off without a point. That is probably what Chekhov meant when he said that stories should have neither a beginning nor an end. It is certain that sometimes it gives you a sensation of airlessness when you see persons who behave so exactly according to character, and incidents that fall into place with such perfect convenience. The story-teller of this kind aims not only at giving his own feelings about life, but at a formal decoration. He arranges life to suit his purposes. He follows a design in his mind, leaving out this and changing that; he distorts facts to his advantage, according to his plan; and when he attains his object produces a work of art. It may be that life slips through his fingers; then he has failed; it may be that he seems sometimes so artificial that you cannot believe him, and when you do not believe a story-teller he is done. When he succeeds he has forced you for a time to accept his view of the universe and has given you the pleasure of following out the pattern he has drawn on the surface of chaos. But he seeks to prove nothing. He paints a picture and sets it before you. You can take it or leave it.

The Complete Short Stories of W. Somerset Maugham Volume II—The World Over (Preface) (1923—1952)

This book contains all the stories I have written that are not included in East and West. The tales in that collection were of about the same length and written on the same scale and so it seemed convenient to publish them together in a single volume. Most of the stories which I have now gathered together are very much shorter. Some were written many years ago, others more recently. They appeared in magazines and were afterwards issued in book form. To the first lot I gave the title of Cosmopolitans, because they were offered to the public in the Cosmopolitan magazine, and except for Ray Long, who was then its editor, would never have been written.

When I was in China in 1920, I took notes of whatever I saw that excited my interest, with the intention of making a connected narrative out of them; but when I came home and read them it seemed to me that they had a vividness which I might easily lose if I tried to elaborate them. So I changed my mind and decided to publish them as they stood under the title: On a Chinese Screen. Ray Long chanced to read this and it occurred to him that some of my notes might well be taken for short stories. I have included two of them, “The Taipan”and“The Consul, ”in this volume. The fact is that if you are a story-teller any curious person you meet has a way of suggesting a story, and incidents that to others will seem quite haphazard have a way of presenting themselves to you with the pattern your natural instinct has impressed on them.

Magazine readers do not like starting a story and, after reading for a while, being told to turn to page one hundred and something. Writers do not like it either, for they think the interruption disturbs the reader and they have besides an uneasy fear that sometimes he will not take the trouble and so leave their story unfinished. There is no help for it. Everyone should know that a magazine costs more to produce than it is sold for, and could not exist but for the advertisements. The advertisers think that their announcements are more likely to be read if they are on the same page as matter which they modestly, but often mistakenly, think of greater interest. So in the illustrated periodicals it has been found advisable to put the beginning of a story or an article, with the picture that purports to illustrate it, at the beginning and the continuation with the advertisements later on.

Neither readers nor writers should complain. Readers get something for far less than cost price and writers are paid sums for their productions which only the advertisements render possible. They should remember that they are only there as bait. Their office is to fill blank spaces and indirectly induce their readers to buy motor accessories, aids to beauty and join correspondence courses. Fortunately this need not affect them. The best story from the advertisers’ standpoint (and they make their views felt on this question) is the story that gives readers most entertainment. Ray Long conceived the notion that the readers of the Cosmopolitan would like it if they were given at least one story that they could read without having to hunt for the continuation among the advertisements, and he commissioned me to write half a dozen sketches of the same sort as those in On a Chinese Screen. They were to be short enough to print on opposite pages of the magazine and leave plenty of room for illustration.

The sketches I wrote pleased and the commission was renewed. I went on writing them until my natural verbosity got the better of me and I found myself no longer able to keep my stories within the limits imposed upon me. Then I had to stop. I think I learned a good deal from the writing of them and I am glad that I did. My difficulty was to compress what I had to tell into a number of words which must not be exceeded and yet leave the reader with the impression that I had told all there was to tell. It was this that made the enterprise amusing. It was also salutary. I could not afford to waste a word. I had to be succinct. I was surprised to find how many adverbs and adjectives I could leave out without any harm to the matter or the manner. One often writes needless words because they give the phrase balance. It was very good practice to try to get it into a sentence without using a word that was not necessary to the sense.

The matter, of course, had to be chosen with discretion; it would have been futile to take a theme that demanded elaborate development. I have a natural predilection for completeness, so that even in the little space at my disposal I wanted my story to have a certain structure. I do not care for the shapeless story. To my mind it is not enough when the writer gives you the plain facts seen through his own eyes (which means of course that they are not plain facts, but facts coloured by his own idiosyncrasy); I think he should impose a pattern on them. Naturally these stories are anecdotes. If stories are interesting and well told they are none the worse for that. The anecdote is the basis of fiction. The restlessness of writers forces upon fiction from time to time forms that are foreign to it, but when it has been oppressed for a period by obscurity, propaganda or affectation, it reverts, and returns inevitably to the proper function of fiction, which is to tell an interesting story.

In the preface to East and West I said pretty well all I had to say about the short story in general. I have nothing to add to that. I have written now nearly a hundred stories and one thing I have discovered is that whether you hit upon a story or not, whether it comes off or not, is very much a matter of luck. Stories are lying about at every street corner, but the writer may not be there at the moment they are waiting to be picked up or he may be looking at a shop window and pass them unnoticed. He may write them before he has seen all there is to see in them or he may turn them over in his mind so long that they have lost their freshness. He may not have seen them from the exact standpoint at which they can be written to their best advantage. It is a rare and happy event when he conceives the idea of a story, writes it at the precise moment when it is ripe, and treats it in such a way as to get out of it all that it implicitly contains. Then it will be within its limitations perfect. But perfection is seldom achieved. I think a volume of modest dimensions would contain all the short stories which even closely approach it. The reader should be satisfied if in any collection of these short pieces of fiction he finds a general level of competence and on closing the book feels that he has been amused, interested and moved.

With one exception all the stories I have written have been published in magazines. The exception is a story called“The Book-Bag.”When I sent it to Ray Long he wrote to me, in sorrow rather than in anger, that he had gone further with me than with any other author, but when it came to incest he had to draw the line. I could not blame him. He published the tale later in a collection of what he thought in his long career as editor of the Cosmopolitan were the best short stories that had ever been offered him. I know that in admitting that my stories have been published in magazines I lay myself open to critical depreciation, for to describe a tale as a magazine story is to condemn it. But when the critics do this they show less acumen than may reasonably be expected of them. Nor do they show much knowledge of literary history. For ever since magazines became a popular form of publication authors have found them a useful medium to put their work before readers. All the greatest short-story writers have published their stories in magazines, Balzac, Flaubert and Maupassant; Chekhov, Henry James, Rudyard Kipling. I do not think it rash to say that the only short stories that have not been published in a magazine are the stories that no editor would accept. So to damn a story because it is a magazine story is absurd. The magazines doubtless publish a great many bad stories, but then more bad stories are written than good ones, and an editor, even of a magazine with literary pretensions, is often obliged to print a story of which he doesn’t think highly because he can get nothing better. Some editors of popular magazines think their readers demand a certain type of story and will take nothing else; and they manage to find writers who can turn out the sort of thing they want and often make a very good job of it. This is the machine-made article that has given the magazine story a bad name. But after all, no one is obliged to read it. It gives satisfaction to many people since it allows them for a brief period to experience in fancy the romance and adventure which in the monotony of their lives they crave for.

But if I may judge from the reviews I have read of the volumes of short stories that are frequently published, where the critics to my mind err is when they dismiss stories as magazine stories because they are well constructed, dramatic and have a surprise ending. There is nothing to be condemned in a surprise ending if it is the natural end of a story. On the contrary it is an excellence. It is only bad when, as in some of O. Henry's stories, it is dragged in without reason to give the reader a kick. Nor is a story any the worse for being neatly built, with a beginning, a middle and an end. All good story writers have done their best to achieve this. It is the fashion of to-day for writers, under the influence of an inadequate acquaintance with Chekhov, to write stories that begin anywhere and end inconclusively. They think it enough if they have described a mood, or given an impression, or drawn a character. That is all very well, but it is not a story, and I do not think it satisfies the reader. He does not like to be left wondering. He wants to have his questions answered. That is what I have tried to do, and when a story was suggested to me of which I didn’t know the answer I forbore to write it. One such story I wrote about in A Writer's Notebook, and since I don’t expect everyone to have read everything I have written I think it may amuse the reader if I here repeat it. When I was in India I received a letter from a man unknown to me in which he told me the following incident in the belief that I might be able to make use of it:

Two young fellows were working on a tea plantation in the hills and the mail had to be fetched from a long way off so that they only got it at rather long intervals. One of the young fellows, let us call him A, got a lot of letters by every mail, ten or twelve and sometimes more, but the other, B, never got one. He used to watch A enviously as he took his bundle and started to read; he hankered to have a letter, just one letter; and one day, when they were expecting the mail, he said to A: “Look here, you always have a packet of letters and I never get any. I’ll give you five pounds if you’ll let me have one of yours.”“Right-ho, ”said A, and when the mail came in he handed B his letters and said to him: “Take whichever you like.”B gave him a five-pound note, looked over the letters, chose one and returned the rest. In the evening when they were having whisky and soda before dinner, A asked casually: “By the way, what was that letter about?”“I’m not going to tell you, ”said B. A, somewhat taken aback, said: “Well, who was it from?”“That's my business, ”answered B. They had a bit of an argument, but B stood on his rights and refused to say anything about the letter he had bought. A began to fret, and as the weeks went by he did all he could to persuade B to let him see the letter. B continued to refuse. At length A, anxious, worried, and curious, felt he couldn’t bear it any longer, so he went to B and said: “Look here, here's your five pounds, let me have my letter back again.”“Not on your life, ”said B.“I bought it and paid for it, it's my letter and I’m not going to give it up.”

In A Writer's Notebook I added: “I suppose if I belonged to the modern school of story writers I should write it just as it is and leave it. It goes against the grain with me. I want a story to have form, and I don’t see how you can give it that unless you can bring it to a conclusion that leaves no legitimate room for questioning. But even if you could bring yourself to leave the reader up in the air you don’t want to leave yourself up in the air with him.”The facts as my correspondent gave them to me intrigued a good many people, and a magazine in Canada and The New Statesman in England, independently of one another, offered prizes to their readers for the best conclusion to the story. I don’t know that the results were particularly successful.

I read once an article on how to write a short story. Certain points the author made were useful, but to my mind the central thesis was wrong. She stated that the“focal point”of a short story should be the building of character and that the incidents should be invented solely to“liven”personality. Oddly enough she remarked earlier in her article that the parables are the best short stories that have ever been written. I think it would be difficult to describe the characters of the Prodigal Son and his brother or of the Good Samaritan and the Man who fell among thieves. They are in fact not characterized and we have to guess what sort of people they were, for we are only told about them the essential facts necessary for the pointing of the moral. And that, whether he has a moral to point or not, is about all the short-story writer can do. He has no room to describe and develop a character; at best he can only give the salient traits that bring the character to life and so make the story he has to tell plausible. Since the beginning of history men have gathered around the campfire or in a group in the market place to listen to the telling of stories. The desire to listen to them appears to be as deeply rooted in the human animal as the sense of property. I have never pretended to be anything but a storyteller. It has amused me to tell stories and I have told a great many.

I have been writing stories for fifty years. In that long period I have seen a number of bright stars creep shyly over the horizon, travel across the sky to burn with a more or less gem-like flame for a while in mid-heaven, and then dwindle into an obscurity from which there is little likelihood that they will ever emerge. The writer has his special communication to make, which, when you come to analyse it, is the personality with which he is endowed by nature, and during the early years of his activity he is groping in the dark to express it; then, if he is fortunate, he succeeds in doing this and if there is in his personality a certain abundance he may contrive for a long time to produce work which is varied and characteristic; but the time comes at last (if he is so imprudent as to live to a ripe age) when, having given what he has to give, his powers fail. He has fashioned all the stories he himself is capable of digging out of the inexhaustible mine which is human nature and he has created all the characters which can possibly be constituted out of the various sides of his own personality. For no one, I believe, can create a character from pure observation; if it is to have life it must be at least in some degree a representation of himself. A generation has arisen which is strange to him and it is only by an effort of will that he can understand the interests of a world of which he can now be only an observer. But to understand is not enough; the writer of fiction must feel, and he must not only feel with, he must feel in. It is well then if he can bring himself to cease writing stories which might just as well have remained unwritten. He is wise to watch warily for the signs which will indicate to him that having said his say, it behoves him to resign himself to silence.

I have written my last story.

译序

爱迪生和爱因斯坦的大名如雷贯耳，在全世界几乎家喻户晓，而特斯拉一直不为世人关注。但特斯拉的科学成就远远高于前两位，他的十大发明彻底改变了人类的生活和认知，对他所处的那个时代以及现在都产生了不可估量的影响，甚至还会影响到世界的未来。由于他的发明和构想过于超前，所以不能被当时的一些人理解，遭到了所谓的“正统科学”的排斥，他的许多观点被斥为“异端邪说”。可是随着社会的进步和科学的发展，他的构想现今已一一变为现实。无论是海里的潜艇、天上的无人机、街上跑的特斯拉电动汽车以及即将风靡世界的无人驾驶汽车和机器人，还是家家户户都在用的交流电，无一不脱胎于他的发明，或者与他的构想有着千丝万缕的联系。这样一个伟大的科学家，理应获得诺贝尔奖——诺贝尔奖的评委们也是这么想的。可是他居功不傲，11次把获奖机会让给了别人。纵观诺贝尔物理学奖的历史，受他的直接启发从而获奖的科学家占了27％，受他的间接启发从而获奖的人数竟占了65％还多。尽管他从不接受诺贝尔奖，但他在过75岁生日时，收到了8封诺贝尔物理学奖获得者的感谢信。

本书是特斯拉的自传，叙述了他极具传奇色彩的人生经历——有些经历过于“传奇”，可能会给人以“匪夷所思”之感，但它们是确实存在的，并因此产生了“传奇”的发明创造。1856年7月10日，尼古拉·特斯拉在克罗地亚出生，父母都是塞尔维亚人。父亲是个牧师，在这一行干得风生水起，颇有名气，还精通物理学，在文学方面亦出类拔萃，是个妙笔生花的诗人。母亲出身于一个热爱发明的家族，无时无刻不在展现她的天赋，发明了许多奇特的家用品。

少年时期，特斯拉的脑海里经常出现一些影像，还伴有强烈的闪光，使他看不清实物，干扰了他的思维和行动。他咨询过生理学和心理学的学者，但无一人能对这些现象做出令人满意的解释。后来他发现可以充分利用自己这种超凡的想象能力，不需要模型，不需要绘图，也不需要实验，单凭想象就能够进行发明创造。他一旦有了想法，就会立刻在脑海里构图，并对其结构进行修改和完善，其间不接触任何实物，直到将所能想到的一切的合理改进都完成，再也找不出缺陷时，他才会把在脑海里最终形成的产物转化为实物。他的这种“特异功能”20年来从未出现过一次偏差，在工程、电气和机械方面的设计和发明全都取得了很好的效果。正是由于这种“特异功能”，他能在遇到危险时化险为夷。一次在河里游泳，河水突然上涨，威胁到了他的生命。就在这时，他的脑海里出现了一道闪光和一幅逃生图，使他得以躲过了一劫。

特斯拉自小就喜欢鼓捣“小发明”，由于思维方式与普通人不同，他经常有惊人之举。例如，他发明的“钓蛙器”使当地的青蛙几乎遭到了“灭顶之灾”；他的“灭虫器”和自制玩具枪也颇有创意。他的家乡有一位商人购置了一辆崭新的消防车并组织了一支消防队，这位商人还给每位消防队员发了一套制服，指挥消防队训练，准备举行一个检阅仪式。所谓消防车其实就是一个水泵，由16名队员操作。一天下午，消防车被拉到了河边，准备举行正式的检阅仪式。人们倾城而出，赶来看这一盛景。演讲和典礼仪式结束后，一声令下，消防队员开始喷水，可是喷嘴里一滴水也喷不出来。教授和专家们群策群力，却找不出哪里出了毛病。特斯拉赶到现场时，人们正急得像热锅上的蚂蚁。当时他在机械原理方面的知识为零，也不懂得什么空气压力，却本能地感到是水下的抽水管出了问题，抽水管可能堵住了。于是他涉水打通了堵塞处，消防车的喷嘴便突然喷出了水。他被人们扛在肩头游行，一下子成了英雄。

特斯拉上学的时候对物理学研究着了迷，可是父母一心一意想让他将来当牧师。一想到这一点，他心里就发怵。一次放假回到家乡，他不幸染上了霍乱，生命垂危，眼看无药可救。父亲心如刀绞，却束手无策。他对父亲说：“如果你同意我学习工程技术，也许我能恢复健康。”父亲听了，郑重地向他许诺：“我要让你上天下最好的工学院。”后来不知怎的，他病情突然好转，竟从死神的手中挣脱了出来。假期结束后，他被送到了奥地利施蒂里亚州格拉茨市的理工学院学习——那是一所历史悠久、声名卓著的大学，是他父亲专门为他挑选的。他悬梁刺股，每天凌晨3点起床，一直学到夜里11点，星期天和节假日也不例外，结果在各个科目上都拔得头筹。除了自己的专业，他还博览文学方面的书籍。一次读到托尔斯泰的书，他“诧异地发现那个‘怪才’靠一天喝72杯黑咖啡竟然写了近100卷的东西，每一卷的字都密密麻麻”！他和托尔斯泰“较劲”，直至将他的全部著作都看完才罢手。他痴迷于文学，不但借此陶冶情操，还觉得文学作品有治病的功效。一次，他大病一场，情况非常危急，可是看了马克·吐温的几部作品后，竟忘掉了自己危重的病情，最终恢复了健康。25年后，他结识了马克·吐温，把这段往事讲给马克·吐温听，惹得马克·吐温哈哈大笑，把眼泪都笑出来了。

特斯拉十分关心世界形势，热切盼望不再发生战争，实现全世界和平。他认为：“战争是不可避免的，除非引发战争的物质因素得以消除——归根结底，这种物质因素在这个我们赖以生存的星球上是普遍存在的。只有通过消除信息传递、旅客运输、能源供应和输送等各方面的差异，才能有朝一日消除战争，使人与人之间永久地保持友好的关系。我们热切盼望全世界的人与人、国与国之间都能加强联系，增进了解，消除狂热的极端思想和自私的民粹主义，因为历来都是这些因素在兴风作浪，让世界陷入原始的野蛮状态，使得冲突不断。”

特斯拉晚年十分不幸。由于病痛和精神的折磨，他变得性格古怪，经常徘徊于纽约公园，给那儿的野鸽子喂食。1943年1月7日，穷困潦倒的特斯拉在纽约的一家旅馆孤独地离开了人世，享年86岁。翻开这本书，你可以了解许多鲜为人知的秘密以及奇异的现象，从而能客观地看待这位科学巨人……

方华文作于苏州大学

2017年12月31日

第一章　早年的人生

人类社会的发展和进步主要依赖于发明创造，而发明创造是人类富有创造力的大脑最重要的产物。发明创造最根本的目的在于利用自然力满足人类的需求，用智慧掌控物质世界。这是一项艰巨的使命——发明家往往会遭到误解，得不到回报。不过，发明家会得到巨大的补偿，因为他们的能力可喜地有了用武之地，他们知道自己会跻身于特殊的精英群体中。没有这样的群体，在和残酷的大自然的激烈搏斗过程中，人类恐怕早已从地球上消失了。

至于我自己，我从发明创造中收获了无与伦比的兴奋和喜悦，多年来我的生活一直不乏欢乐的成分。有人称赞我是一个极为勤奋的人——如果这指的是思维方面的劳动，那么我当之无愧，因为除了睡眠我几乎把所有的时间都用于思考问题了。但是，如果“劳动”指的是在特定的时间，按特定的规则完成某项任务的活动，那我就是最懒散的人了。但凡强迫性的劳动必定会耗费生命的能量，我却从未为此付出过代价。恰恰相反，我在思考中获益匪浅。

我试图通过系列文章连贯而忠实地记述自己所从事的工作，并在《电气实验者》(1)编辑的帮助下将它们发表于该杂志，阅读群体主要为年轻读者。因而，不管愿不愿意，我都必须讲述一下自己年轻时候的想法、生活环境以及发生的事件——这些决定了我以后的生活。

人们在小的时候，行为处世往往喜欢冲动，想象力如脱缰的野马般无拘无束。随着年龄的增长，一个人会趋于理性，做事越来越有条不紊、计划周密。然而，正是这种早年的“冲动”，虽然不会立竿见影，即刻给我们带来好处，却是一种极为重要的因素，也许可以决定我们未来的命运。说实在的，我觉得如果当年自己能够理解和培养而非压抑那种“冲动”，以后肯定会为世界做出更大的贡献，留下一份有价值的遗产。可是，直到成年之后，我才意识到自己原来是个发明家。

这种情况是由多种原因造成的。首先，我有一个天才的哥哥，他天赋异禀，智力世间罕有——生物学无法解释。他的英年早逝让我的父母郁郁寡欢。我们家有一匹马，一匹血统高贵的阿拉伯纯种马，是一位好友送的。它几乎跟人一样聪明，曾经在一个危急时刻救过父亲的命，所以备受全家人的关心和宠爱。那是一个寒冷的冬夜，父亲应邀去做一次紧急祈祷。在狼群出没的群山里，那匹马突然受惊，撒腿就跑，把父亲重重地摔在了地上。它跑回家时，浑身是血，已累得精疲力竭。可是，给家人报告过险情之后，它立刻就冲了出去，返回到事发地。在搜救的人群离得还很远的时候，父亲就迎了过来——他又恢复了知觉，骑在了马背上，全然不知自己在雪地里躺了好几个小时。正是这匹马摔伤了我的哥哥，使得他英年早逝。我目睹了那场悲剧的发生，虽然过了56年仍记忆犹新，每个细节都历历在目。回忆起他所取得的成就，我的小小所得与之相比简直微不足道。

无论我做什么事情，做得多好，都只会让父母更加怀念我的哥哥。所以，我小的时候十分缺乏自信。不过，从那时候发生的一件事来看（那件事我至今仍记得一清二楚），我绝对不能算是一个笨孩子。有一天，我正和一群孩子在街上玩，几个受人尊敬的市参议员走了过来。这群绅士中的一位年龄最长的有钱人停住脚步，要给我们每人一枚银币。他来到我面前时，突然跟我说：“看着我的眼睛。”我照他说的做了，同时把手伸过去，准备领取那枚珍贵的银币。让我失望的是，他说：“没门，你别想从我这儿得到一分钱，因为你太聪明了。”

还有一件关于我的趣事，总是被人们津津乐道。我有两个姑姑，脸都皱得像老树皮一样。其中的一个姑姑长着两颗龅牙，龇出来如象牙一般，她每次亲我时它们都会扎进我脸上的肉里。当时我最怕被这两个充满爱心的丑亲戚拥抱。一天，母亲把我抱在怀里，两个姑姑问我她们两个谁更好看。我先是把她俩的脸仔细打量了一番，然后指着其中的一个，以深思熟虑的语气说：“这个不比那个更丑。”

自打我呱呱坠地，家里就准备让我将来当牧师，这种想法一直给我很大的压力。我渴望当一名工程师，但父亲固执己见，寸步不让。我的祖父是军官，曾在拿破仑大帝的军队里服役，他还有个兄弟是一名数学教授，执教于一所著名学府。他们都接受过军事教育，可奇怪的是，父亲竟然爱上了牧师这一行，而且干得风生水起。父亲是个博闻强记的才子，不仅是牧师，也是名副其实的物理学家、诗人和作家。据说，他布道时口若悬河，与亚伯拉罕·阿·桑克塔·克拉拉(2)只在伯仲之间。他记忆力惊人，经常用不同种类的语言背诵大段经文。他曾经开玩笑说，假如某些经文遗失，他可以凭记忆默写出来，还原它们。在写作方面，他的风格颇受推崇，词句简洁明快，力透纸背，充满了智慧和讽刺。他说话诙谐幽默、妙语连珠，总是那么别致、独具特色。关于这一点，我举两个例子，从中可窥见一斑。我们家有个叫马尼的仆人是斗鸡眼，他是被雇来干农活的。一天，他挥动斧头劈柴的时候，家父就站在他跟前，心里感到十分不安，于是提醒他说：“看在上帝的分上，马尼，千万别砍你眼睛看到的，而应该砍你心里想砍的！”还有一次，他驾马车和一个朋友外出，那位朋友不小心把自己昂贵的皮大衣蹭在了车轮上。父亲提醒他说：“把你的衣服往上提提，别把我的车轮蹭坏了。”家父有个怪习惯，喜欢自言自语，经常自己跟自己说话，慷慨激昂，还以不同的声音展开唇枪舌剑般的辩论。如果有谁在外边碰巧听见，会以为屋里有好几个人呢。

虽然必须承认，正是受了母亲的影响我才有了发明创造的能力，但父亲对我的训练也功不可没。这种训练包罗万象，其中有猜度人的心理，找出别人仪容或言语上的毛病，复述冗长的句子和进行心算等。这些日常的训练项目，用意在于加强我的记忆力和推理的能力，尤其是为了提高我的鉴别力，这无疑使我获益匪浅。

我母亲出身于乡下的一个极为古老的世家，家族里曾经出过好几位发明家。她的父亲和祖父为了方便家用，发明了许多工具，有农用的，也有其他用途的。母亲是一位真正的伟大女性，具有非凡的能力，勇敢坚韧，经历过无数磨难，敢于面对生活中的风风雨雨。她16岁那年，一场致命的瘟疫席卷了她的家乡。一次，她的父亲被叫去为一位垂死的人主持最后的圣事。父亲走后，她独自一人去帮助一户邻居——那户人家也染上了这种致命的瘟疫。那户人家共有五口人，一个接一个死去。她为逝者沐浴更衣，把他们的遗体摆放整齐，根据当地的习俗用鲜花加以点缀。待父亲归来，她已把所有的准备工作做完，只等着举行基督徒葬礼了。家母是位不同凡响的发明家。要不是与现代社会隔绝，没有那么多的机遇，我坚信她一定会有惊人的发明。她发明和制作过各种各样的工具及设备，用自纺的棉线织出过精美的图案，甚至还亲自播种，培育植物，从中提取纤维。她每天从拂晓时分忙到深夜，不知疲倦地操持家务——我们家里人穿的衣服以及用的家具，大多是她劳动的结晶。年逾花甲时，她仍心灵手巧，能够在一根眼睫毛上打三个结。

我之所以一直未能觉察出自己在发明方面的天分，还有一个更为重要的原因。少年时期，我的脑海里常常出现一些影像，还伴有强烈的闪光，它们模糊了我的视线，使我看不清实物，干扰了我的思维和行动，让我深受困扰。那些影像都是我亲眼见过的画面和场景，并非臆想出来的。当我听到别人说某个词时，我的眼前就会清清楚楚地浮现那个词所指代的影像，以致我有时都无法判断出现在自己眼前的事物是真实的还是仅为幻象。我为此而感到极度不安，忧心忡忡。我咨询过生理学和心理学的学者，但无一人能对这些现象做出令人满意的解释。我觉得这种怪异的现象只发生在我身上，可又认为这样的看法有失偏颇，因为我知道我哥哥也曾遇到过类似的麻烦。经过分析，我得出了这样的结论：这些影像的出现，是在极为兴奋的状态下，大脑对视网膜产生的反射作用。鉴于我在其他方面都很正常，心态也很平和，由此可知，这种影像绝对不是由心理疾病和精神痛苦而导致的幻觉。例如，假如我看到了埋死人或者什么刺激性的场面，等到夜深人静时，这些场面就会逼真地浮现在我眼前，任我怎么赶都赶不走。有的时候，我甚至把手伸到空中去抓它们，而它们竟岿然不动。假如我的推论没有错，那么，将人们想象到的任何事物变成影像投射到屏幕上让人观看，是有可能做到的。一旦这种可能成为现实，将会彻底改变人与人之间的关系。我坚信，这一奇迹有朝一日必将变为现实。顺便提一下，我为了解决这一问题已经进行了深入的思考。

为了摆脱这些折磨人的影像，我千方百计地转移注意力，去想自己看到的其他事物，这样倒是可以暂时缓解痛苦，但要达到这一目的，我就得接连不断地想象出新的影像替代旧影像。没过多久，我发现自己所掌握的影像已经用尽，“影像库”已空空如也，因为我对世界了解得太少，眼光仅局限于家里以及邻近区域的事物。当相同的景象第二次或第三次在我脑海中出现，企图把眼前的影像驱逐开时，它们的缓解效力渐渐消失，以至完全无济于事。于是，出于本能，我开始跳出自己所熟知的小天地，于是看到了一些新的影像。这些影像起初模糊不清，朦朦胧胧，一旦我集中注意力观看，它们就倏然不见了。不过，久而久之，它们渐渐趋于清晰，最终竟将真实物体具象地呈现在我眼前。我很快发现，假如不断扩大自己的视野，不断获取新的印象，就能给我的心灵带来极大的安慰，于是我开始远足（当然指的是思维的远足）。一到夜里（有时是在白天）独处一室，我的思想便云游天下，到各个地区、城市和国家游览，在那儿居住，交朋结友。尽管这像是天方夜谭，然而却是真实情况——那些朋友对我和蔼可亲，跟现实生活中的朋友别无两样，他们栩栩如生，宛如生活在真实世界一般。

就这样，我一直过着神游他方的日子，直至17岁，才正儿八经地将注意力转向了发明创造。这时，我惊喜地发现：我可以充分利用自己的这种超凡的想象能力，不需要模型，不需要绘图，也不需要实验，单凭想象就能把所有细节完美地呈现在脑海中。这样，我便不知不觉地形成了一套新的方法，将发明创造的理念和观点变为现实——虽然这与纯粹的实验性理论背道而驰，而我却觉得我的方法要快捷和有效得多。人们设计某种装置，准备用以验证某种不成熟的想法时，发现自己会不可避免地纠缠于这种装置的细节和缺陷。随着装置的完善和重制，他们的注意力便会愈加分散，甚至忽略掉设计的基本原理，这样也许能取得一些效果，但质量却会大打折扣。

我的设计方法却与之不同。我不会急于求成、匆忙动手，一旦有了想法，我会立刻在脑海里构图，在脑海里修改其结构，改良设计，然后在脑海里进行操作。是在头脑中开动涡轮机还是在车间里对它进行试验，对我而言完全无关紧要。甚至我脑海里设计的涡轮机出了毛病，我也能觉察到。不管怎样，我的想象与实际情况毫无二致，没有任何区别，结果都是一样的。以这种方式，我可以迅速地将一种想法付于实践并加以完善，其间不接触任何实物。直到将所能想到的一切的合理改进都完成，再也找不出缺陷时，我才会把在心里最终形成的产物转化为实物。我设计出的装置，运行情况每次都跟我的构想吻合，试验结果完全符合我的计划，20年来无一例外。怎么可能会有其他情况出现呢？工程、电气和机械，所有的试验结果都符合我的设计计划。从可行性理论到实际数据，所有一切都可以预先在脑海中测试。人们通常的做法是将不成熟的想法付于实践，依我看那纯粹是浪费精力、金钱和时间。

虽然早年经受了精神折磨，但除了以上收获，我还另有所得。持续不断的脑力劳动提高了我的观察力，使我发现了一个极为重要的事实——脑海中出现的影像每次都是对以前见过的场景的反映，一遇到特殊的、不同寻常的情况就会出现，而每一次我都会不由自主地追溯其源头。过了一段时间，这几乎成了一种不假思索的行为，使得我具有了一种超凡的能力，能够将因和果联系在一起。不久，我惊讶地发现自己的每一种构想都是受到外界的影响而产生的。非但如此，我的行为举止无不以同样的方式受到影响。随着时间的推移，我非常清楚地意识到自己只不过是一台会移动的机器，一旦感官受到刺激便做出反应，进行思考和采取行动。由此，我提出了自动遥控机械理论——这一理论在操作层面虽然至今尚不完善，但它的潜力最终一定会显现出来。多年来，我一直致力于设计自动控制机，坚信这样的具有一定智能的机器是可以生产出来的，它势必会在商业和工业领域引发一场革命。

大约12岁的时候，通过艰苦的努力，我终于第一次成功地将影像从脑海里驱逐了出去，但是对上文提到的那种闪光却始终无力加以控制。那种闪光也许是我最奇特的体验，是一个解不开的谜。当我发现自己身处险境，或经历大悲大喜时，经常会出现这样的闪光。有几次，我看到周围到处是燃烧的火舌。随着时间的流逝，这种现象非但没有减弱，反而更加强烈，在我25岁时似乎达到了巅峰。1883年，我在巴黎应一位著名的法国制造商邀请出外打猎。由于长期困守在工厂的小天地里，出外呼吸到新鲜空气让我顿感神清气爽。当晚回城的途中，我觉得极其兴奋，像有一团火在大脑里燃烧。我看到了闪光，就好像脑子里有一轮小太阳在放射光芒。那一整夜，我不断地冷敷我那发烫的脑门。最后，闪光出现得越来越少，也越来越弱，但三个星期后才彻底消失。后来再有人请我去打猎，我都会斩钉截铁地拒绝。

每当我突发灵感，产生新的想法时，时不时地就会出现这种闪光现象。不过这种闪光不再令人感到那么焦灼，强度也会有所减弱。合上眼睛的时候，每次我先看到的都是一片幽深、色彩均匀的蓝色背景，那种蓝色不像是白天晴朗的天空，而像是没有星光的夜空。过上一小会儿，这幅场景就会变得活跃起来，出现无数绿色的闪光点，一层一层的，逐渐向我逼近。随后，这幅场景的右边会出现一个美丽的图案，由两组平行、密集排列的线条组成——两组线条构成直角，五彩缤纷，以黄色、绿色和金色为主。紧接着，线条越来越亮，整个图案密密麻麻布满了闪闪发亮的光点。这幅画面会慢慢地从我眼前经过，大约十秒钟之后从左边消失，留下一片沉闷、让人讨厌的灰色，而这片灰色很快变成翻腾的云海，那云团挨挨挤挤，似乎竭力想变成人形。奇怪的是，在后一段景象出现之前，我怎么也没法给这片灰色的背景添加任何形状。每天入睡之前，都会有人或物的影像从我眼前掠过。看见它们，我就知道自己快要进入梦乡了。看不见它们，就意味着我会彻夜难眠。

幻想对我早年人生产生了某种程度的影响，对此我还有一种奇特的经历可以加以说明。跟大多数孩子一样，我喜欢跳跃，后来产生了强烈的愿望，希望自己能飘浮在空中。有时山里刮来一阵富含氧气的强风，我感到自己身轻如燕，于是便纵身一跳，在空中飘浮很长时间——那是一种教人欣喜若狂的感觉。后来发现这仅仅是幻想，我失望到了极点。

在那段时期，我有许多古怪的个人好恶以及习惯，有些可以归因于受到了外界的影响，有些则无法解释。对于女人的耳环，我极其憎恶，可是对于其他饰品，如手镯等，却比较喜欢，喜欢的程度取决于饰品的设计图案。看到珍珠会令我头昏脑涨，可是我又特别喜欢闪闪发亮的水晶以及带有锐角和平面的物体。除非你用枪逼着我，否则我绝不会用手去触摸别人的头发。看到桃子，我就会发高烧。只要家里有一小片樟脑，无论在什么地方，都能让我坐卧不安。甚至到了今天，我依旧对这些东西过敏，见了就心烦。吃饭的时候，如果汤盘里掉进一小片纸，我就感到嘴里有一股怪异的恶心味道。我走路数步子，吃饭则计算汤盘、咖啡杯的容量以及食物的份数，否则这顿饭就吃不好。我重复过的所有动作或做过的事情，其次数都必须能被三整除，如若不然，我就强迫自己再来一遍，哪怕再花上几个小时也心甘情愿。

8岁之前，我性格懦弱、优柔寡断，缺乏勇气和力量，从未有过坚定的信念，情绪不稳定，经常出现波动，从一个极端走向另一个极端。我杂念丛生，愿望就像神话中的九头蛇(3)，砍掉一个头，又会生出两个。我提心吊胆，害怕生活中的苦难，害怕死亡，对宗教具有恐惧感，常常产生迷信的念头，总是怕恶灵缠身，怕妖魔鬼怪以及其他黑暗世界的魍魉。后来，一个翻天覆地的变化突然来到，彻底改变了我的人生轨迹。

我最大的爱好就是读书。家父有一个很大的藏书室，一有机会我就溜进去找书看，以满足自己强烈的读书欲。家父却不允许我看书，一见我看书就生气，后来发现我偷偷地看，便索性把蜡烛藏起来，生怕我把眼睛看坏。没有蜡烛，我就找来牛油放进锡铁盒当灯油，用几根树枝做灯芯，每天夜里把锁眼和门缝一堵便开始读书，常常会读到次日拂晓时分——此时家人都还在睡觉，只有母亲已经起床，开始了她一天的辛勤劳作。一次，我无意中发现了一本翻译成塞尔维亚语的匈牙利著名作家约西卡的小说《阿巴菲》（《阿巴的儿子》）。这本书不知怎的唤醒了我沉睡的意志力，于是我开始有意识地练习自我控制。最初，我的决心就像四月的雪，很快就会动摇。但没过多长时间，我就克服了自己的弱点，终于可以按照自己的意志做事情了，这让我感到了前所未有的快乐。随着时间的推移，这种高强度的脑力训练成了我的第二天性。开始的时候，我必须强行压制自己的意志，但后来愿望和意志便逐渐达到了一致。经过几年的训练，我达到了完全能够自控的程度，甚至可以以游戏的心态控制自己的爱好，而有些嗜好足以摧毁意志最坚强的人。在某一个年龄段我染上了赌瘾，令父母非常犯愁。坐在牌桌旁赌博，对我而言是天大的乐事。家父的一生堪为人之表率，无法容忍我这般浑噩度日，浪费时间和金钱。我固然有强大的自制力，但人生观却不健康，于是对他说：“只要我愿意，随时都可以停止赌博。但是，这种享受只有用天堂的快乐才能够买得到，让我放弃，这值得吗？”他经常冲我发火，对我的行为表示不满。而母亲则不然，她了解男人的脾气，深知要想让我悬崖勒马，得靠我自己大彻大悟。记得有一天下午，我把自己的钱输了个精光，心里还想赌。只见母亲拿着一沓钱走到我面前说：“去痛痛快快赌个够吧。把家里的钱赌光了，你也就甘心了。我知道你一定会浪子回头的。”她说对了——我立刻便控制住了自己的欲望。假如赌博的欲望再强烈百倍，就更能显现出我的自控力，唯此一点令我感到有点儿遗憾。我不仅遏制住了赌博的欲望，还将它连根拔起，一点儿痕迹也没有留下。自那以后，我对任何形式的赌博都不再感兴趣了，就像我不喜欢剔牙一样。

有一段时期，我抽烟抽得很厉害，严重地威胁到了我的健康，后来凭借意志的力量，我不仅戒了烟，还杜绝了抽烟的欲望。很久以前，我曾患有心脏病，后来发现这是由于每天早晨喝咖啡所致的，于是我就不再喝了。我得承认这可不是件容易的事。以这种方式，我还戒除和控制了其他的一些不良习惯和欲望，非但保住了性命，还从中获得了极大的满足感（大多数人认为这是苦修生活，牺牲了人生乐趣）。

完成了格拉茨理工大学(4)的学业之后，我的精神陷入了彻底崩溃的状态。在这段时期，我观察到了许多奇怪得教人无法相信的现象。

(1) 美国的一个技术科学杂志，每月出版一刊，创刊于1913年5月。1917年8月至1919年7月，特斯拉在该杂志上发表了五篇文章，并在1919年的几期中发表了部分自传。

(2) 17世纪德国牧师，因布道感人而闻名于欧洲。

(3) 希腊神话中的怪蛇海德拉拥有九颗头，其中一颗头要是被斩断，立刻又会生出两颗头来。

(4) 奥地利的格拉茨理工大学建立于1585年，是奥地利教育部认可的18所公立大学中的一所。

第二章　发明创造的最初尝试

那是一段非同寻常的人生经历，容我简单做一个介绍，也许会引起心理学和生理学专家的兴趣。再说，这段令人痛苦的时光对我以后的心路历程以及自己所从事的研究都产生了极为深远的影响。不过，在介绍之前，很有必要回顾一下当时的环境和条件，或许从中可以理出些头绪。

从孩提时起，家里就要求我学会自省。这种要求当时折磨得我不轻，但现在我觉得自己因祸得福，意识到自省无论是对怎样看待人生，还是获得事业的成功都有着不可估量的价值。职业压力和通过知识途径不断涌入我们的意识的来自外界的各种印象，使现代社会在很多方面存在危险。大多数人都是只关注外部世界的是是非非，置自己的内心世界于不顾。数以百万计的人过早地死亡，主要原因就在于此。即便关注内心世界的人当中，也普遍存在着一种错误倾向——能不多想就不多想，对真正的危险视而不见。这种倾向个人有之，一个民族也多多少少有之。你只要看一看禁酒运动就一目了然了。禁酒令即便不违反宪法，也流于草率。它通行全国，严禁人们喝酒，但另一现象却显而易见——人们不喝酒了，却从咖啡、烟草、口香糖以及其他东西中寻找刺激，甚至小孩子也如此，这对国民的身体造成的危害更大，从死亡率便可得知。举例来说，上大学时，我根据维也纳公布的死亡率，发现在喝咖啡的人群中，因患心脏病而死亡的人数，比其他人群有时会高出67％。在茶叶消费量过大的城市可能会有类似的观察结果。这些醇香的饮品会极大地刺激大脑神经，使其逐渐衰竭。它们还会严重地干扰动脉循环，然而由于毒副作用出现得慢，这种情况不为人所察觉，因此饮者会掉以轻心。抽烟可以使你的思维变得轻松愉快，但是却会减弱思维的深度以及强度，而思维的深度以及强度是活跃的原创性智力劳动所必需的。口香糖固然能有一时之用，但很快就会破坏你的腺体系，造成不可修复的损害，就更别提它还会叫人感到恶心了。少量的酒精不失为极好的补品，但酒精过量则会产生毒副作用，至于你喝的是威士忌还是胃液里由糖而转化来的酒精，都无关紧要。不容忽视的是，这些东西都是有效的终结者，是大自然的帮手，协助大自然坚持严格而公正的适者生存的法则。热衷于改革的人也应该注意到人类历来都有任性的一面，所以与其严加管束，还不如遵循“放任主义”。说句实话，根据现在的生活条件，我们的确需要兴奋神经的东西以保持高效率的工作，同时又必须从各方面调整和控制自身的食欲及愿望。多年来我都是这么做的，以此在身体和精神上保持青春的活力。我并不总是喜欢自我节制，但我发现这样做给我带来了丰厚的回报，使我的人生经历轻松愉快。此处不妨讲一两件往事，希望能让一些人相信我的看法和信念。

不久前的一个寒风刺骨的夜晚，由于打不到出租车，我就步行返回下榻的旅馆。路面又湿又滑。后边离我有半个街区远的地方，还有一个人在赶路，他显然跟我一样，也急切想回到住所去。突然，我腾空跳起，就在那一瞬间大脑中闪过一道白光，神经立刻做出反应，肌肉缩紧。我在空中来了个180。的大旋转，落下时双手先着地。然后，我若无其事地继续走路。

后边的那个陌生人赶上来，用审视的眼光打量着我问：“你今年多大了？”

“哦，差不多59岁吧。”我回答说，“怎么啦？”

“是吗？”他说，“我曾经见一只猫做过这样的动作，但从未见过一个人竟能如此灵巧。”

大约一个月前，我想买一副新眼镜，于是就去一位眼科医生那里做例行视力检查。我远远地就可以十分轻松地看清视力表上最小的标识，使得他向我投来疑惑的目光。但我告诉他，我已年过60，这更是惊得他张口结舌。我的朋友们经常评价我穿着得体，衣服非常合身，不宽也不紧。但他们哪里知道，我的衣服都是按35年前的尺码定做的，这一尺码从来就没有变过。在这么长的时间里，我的体重也丝毫未变。

关于这一点，我可以告诉诸位一段有趣的往事。那是1885年冬天的一个晚上，我和爱迪生先生、爱迪生照明公司的董事长爱德华·H.约翰逊以及该公司的经理巴彻勒先生一道走进了第五大道65号（该公司各机构的所在地）对面的一个小处所。有人提议互相猜体重，并让我先站到体重秤上。爱迪生摸了摸我全身说：“特斯拉体重142磅，误差在一盎司以内(1)。”他猜得非常准确。我当时的净体重（不穿衣服）是142磅，现在依然如此。我悄悄地问旁边的约翰逊：“爱迪生怎么可能如此精准地猜出我的体重？”

“这个嘛，”他压低声音说，“我可以把秘密告诉你，但你不许对别人说。他曾经在芝加哥的一家屠宰场干过很长时间，每天要为几千头猪称重。这就是秘诀。”

我尊贵的朋友昌西·米切尔·迪皮尤(2)曾经对一个英国人讲过他早年的一段趣闻。对方听得满脸困惑，一年后才悟出了其中的幽默，乐得开怀大笑。实话实说，我理解约翰逊的笑话花的时间比那个英国人更长。

我现在身体健康，得益于自己谨小慎微、有节制的生活方式。你恐怕想不到，我小的时候曾害过三次大病，病情无望好转，医生们均以为回天乏术呢。除了生病，由于无知和无畏，我还经历过种种艰难及险境，一次次侥幸脱险，才得以劫后余生。有好几次我都差点儿被水淹死。我还差点儿死于被开水烫和被火烧，亦被埋进过土里，迷过路，被冻僵过。我遇见过疯狗、野猪以及其他野兽，每次脱险都是九死一生。经历过那么多可怕的疾病，那么多形形色色、稀奇古怪的危险之后，我仍精神矍铄、饱满，这似乎是个奇迹。但回顾这些往事，我坚信自己能够幸存至今肯定并非偶然。

发明家的所作所为，从根本上来讲，就是挽救生命。无论是控制自然力还是改进器械，抑或为人们提供更舒适和便利的生活，其本质都是在提高人类生活的安全性。而且，在遇到危险时，他们比普通人的自救能力更强，因为他们眼观六路耳听八方，善于随机应变。我在某种程度上就具有这种特质。虽然没有其他直接证据，但我的一些个人经历还是可以证明这一点的。此处我暂举一两例，由读者自己判断好啦。我14岁那年的一天，和几个小伙伴在河里游泳。我想吓吓他们，打算潜到一座长长的水上建筑物之下，从另一端悄悄钻出来。我跟鸭子一样，天生就会游泳和潜水，因而坚信完成这一计划不在话下。于是，我潜入水里，一从小伙伴们的眼前消失，便转过身，迅速地向对面游去。后来我满以为已经安全地游出了那座建筑物的范围，便打算浮出水面，谁知竟意外地撞在了一根椽子上。当然，我又急速朝下潜，拼命划水向前冲，直至气都快透不过来了。这时，我再次上浮，脑袋又撞在了一根椽子上。我都有点儿绝望了，但还是拼尽全力，第三次奋力一搏，结果仍以失败告终。由于缺氧，我感到越来越难以忍受，只觉得头发晕，身子朝下沉。此时此刻，我似乎已完全陷入了无望的绝境。突然，眼前出现了一道闪光，那座建筑物的结构变得十分清晰。不知是亲眼看到还是靠猜度，我发现水面和架在椽子上的木板之间有一点儿空隙，我在几乎失去知觉的情况下浮了上去，把嘴贴近木板，总算吸到了一点点儿氧气。不幸的是，就在这时一个浪头打来，差点儿把我呛死。这时的我宛若身在梦境，一次次进行尝试，直至狂跳不已的心逐渐平静了下来。之后，我又数次下潜寻找生机，结果屡遭失败，完全失去了方向感。不过，就在小伙伴们已经绝望，正在打捞我的尸体时，我总算成功脱险、绝处逢生。

由于鲁莽，那年的游泳季对我而言算是完蛋了，可是我很快就忘记了那次教训，仅仅两年之后便陷入了更为危险的境地。当时我在一座城市里上学，离城不远有一条河，河上有一座拦河大坝和一个大型面粉厂。一般情况下，河水只比堤坝高出两三英寸(3)，在那儿游泳基本不会有什么危险，所以我喜欢在那儿游泳，把它当成了一种体育项目。一天，像往常一样，我又单独到那儿享受游泳的快感。我在游到距离石筑的拦河大坝不远的地方时，惊恐地发现河水已上涨，正在迅速地把我朝下冲去。我试图游开，但为时已晚。不过，幸好我用双手紧紧抓住堤坝，才没有被冲下去。水流巨大的冲击力压在我的胸口，使得我几乎无法把脑袋露出水面。当时看不见一个人在附近，我的呼救声被轰隆轰隆的落水声所淹没。慢慢地，我逐渐耗尽了力气，双手就快抓不住墙壁了。正当我快要撒手，任河水将我冲下堤坝，在坝下的石头上摔个粉身碎骨时，我的眼前突然出现了一道闪光，和一张熟悉的表明水流的压力与受力面积成正比的水压原理示意图。于是，我不由自主地把身体转向左侧，结果水流就好像被施了魔法一样，压力顿时减小。我发现，这种姿势比较容易抗击水流的冲击力。不过，我仍未脱离险境，知道自己早晚都会被冲走，即便有人发现，跑来救我，恐怕也来不及了。我虽然有两只手，但右臂的力量几乎已用尽，只能靠左手了。因而，我不敢把身子转向另一侧休息，已经到了山穷水尽的地步，我只好顺着堤坝慢慢移动。这时，我的脸是朝着面粉厂的，而那儿的水流更急、更深，所以我必须反向移动。那真是一场漫长而痛苦的考验。快到尽头时，我差点儿功亏一篑，因为我面前的堤坝上有一处凹陷。我耗完了最后一丝力气，总算渡过了难关，一到河岸上就昏了过去。后来，人们在那儿发现了我。我身体左侧的皮肤被河水几乎全部撕了下来，过了好几个星期高烧才退，这才彻底康复。这只是诸多例子中的两个，但足以表明：要不是出于发明家的本能，我恐怕活不到今天来讲这个故事了。

很多人对我的发明感兴趣，常常问我是什么时候以及如何开始搞发明的。对此，我只能根据自己的记忆加以回答。记得第一次尝试发明，我的野心是很大的，既想发明一种装置，又想发明一种方法。至于“装置”，已有前人发明在先，而“方法”则是由我首创。事情的经过是这样的：我的一个小伙伴得到了一套钓钩和钓鱼用具，在村子里引起了很大的轰动。第二天一早，所有的小伙伴都跟着他钓青蛙去了，唯独撇下了我，原因是我跟他吵过架。我从未见过钓钩，想象着它一定很神奇，具有奇特的功能，于是对不能参加这次活动十分失望。在一种愿望的驱动下，我找来一截软铁丝，用两块石头将它的一端砸出一个锋利的尖，再弯成钩，绑在一根结实的绳子上。随后，我砍了根竹竿，收集了一些诱饵，便到小溪边青蛙多的地方去了。可是我钓来钓去也没钓到一只青蛙，于是几乎无心再钓了。就在这时，我看见有只青蛙蹲在树桩上，便将空钓钩伸到它面前逗它。起先，它显得萎靡不振，后来渐渐鼓起了眼泡，眼睛里充血，身体也胀得有原来的两倍大，跟着就凶猛地扑上来咬住了钓钩。我立刻把它拉了上来，接着用同样的方法钓了一只又一只，百试不爽。我的小伙伴们虽然装备精良，却一无所获，见我满载而归，羡慕极了。很长一段时间，我对自己的秘诀都三缄其口，独自一人去垂钓，可最终由于过圣诞节心情好，我竟将秘诀公布于众了。这下子，每个小伙伴都学会了这一套，次年夏天给当地的青蛙带来了“灭顶之灾”。

我的第二次尝试是在我最初的本能冲动推动下进行的——正是这种本能冲动日后驱动着我去控制大自然的力量，以造福人类。这次的发明是由“五月臭虫”（美国人称其为“六月臭虫”）引起的——这是一种真正的害虫，灌木丛里黑压压的到处都是，有时数量之多能把树枝都压断。我把四只“五月臭虫”拴在一个十字架上，将十字架放在一根细轴上转动，再把转动的能量传输给一个大圆盘，这样就获得了相当大的“驱动力”。这些虫子十分卖力，一旦开始工作就不知道休息了，转啊转的，一连几个小时都不会停下来，天气越热，它们干得越起劲。一切都很顺利，直到一个不认识的男孩走过来，才出了问题。他是一位奥地利退役军官的儿子。那家伙竟然把我的“五月臭虫”都活活吞吃了，美滋滋的就好像在享用一道味道绝佳的蓝蚝大菜。我见了恶心极了，于是结束了这种前景辉煌的试验，那以后再也没有碰过“五月臭虫”以及其他的虫子。

根据我的回忆，这之后我拿祖父的钟表开刀，进行拆卸和组装。拆卸我干得总是很成功的，组装却屡屡失败。后来，祖父以一种不太文明的方式横加干涉，使我的试验戛然而止。若说再次进行钟表方面的试验，那是30年以后的事了。此事过后不久，我用一根空管、一个活塞和两个插栓组装了一支玩具气枪。射击时，活塞冲向枪体腹部，带有两个抓手的管子受到撞击，猛地向后弹去，而两个插栓之间的空气受到挤压便迅速升温，其中的一个砰的一声巨响射了出去。组装这样的玩具枪，关键在于选择形状合适的空心管。组装这支枪，我大功告成，但因为试验时会威胁到我家的玻璃窗户而遭到抵制，家里人一个劲给我泼凉水。如果没记错，接下来我迷上了用木头刻剑，拿家具上的木板当原料（这种原料唾手可得）。那段时间，我受塞尔维亚爱国诗歌的影响，对英雄们的武艺佩服得五体投地，于是便跑到玉米地里，把玉米秆当作敌人挥剑大砍大杀，一砍就是几个小时，糟蹋庄稼不说，还常常被妈妈打屁股。妈妈打我可不是装装样子，而是真打。

这些事都发生在我6岁之前。后来我在斯米莲村（即我的出生地）读了一年小学。接下来，我们举家迁往附近的戈斯皮奇小城。这次搬家对我而言简直就像是一场灾难。家乡有鸽子、小鸡、绵羊，还有颇为壮观的鹅群——鹅群早出晚归，一到早晨便翱翔蓝天，出外觅食，日落时分从觅食地排着整齐的队列返回，那阵容就是叫现在最优秀的空军看了也会自叹弗如。跟它们告别，我的心都快碎了。在新家，我只不过是个囚犯，整日待在家里透过百叶窗观看外边素不相识的行人。我生性害羞，不愿见人，宁愿面对一头咆哮的狮子，也不愿见那些在街上溜达的城市闲汉。可是，星期天我得穿戴整齐到教堂做礼拜，这让我难受极了，如芒刺在背。在教堂，我遇到了一件事，多年后回想起来还感到心里很不是滋味。那是我在教堂的第二次历险。前不久我被困在了一座古老的教堂里整整一夜，那座教堂位于难以抵达的高山上，每年只开放一次。那是一次可怕的经历，但这次的更糟。小城里有个阔太太，人是个好人，就是有点儿爱慕虚荣，到教堂做礼拜时常常盛装打扮，身穿曳地长裙，仆从们前呼后拥。一个星期天，我到钟楼上敲响了大钟之后，三步并作两步往楼下跑，恰逢这位阔太太经过，结果我不小心踩在了她的曳地长裙上。只听刺啦一声，她的长裙裂开了，声音之大就像是新兵不小心走火闹出的响动。家父气得脸色发青，轻轻地扇了我一巴掌。那是他对我唯一的一次体罚，可是至今我还能感受得到当时的那种滋味。接下来出现的那种令人尴尬和困惑的局面，实在难以用语言表达。我在当地遭到了排斥，后来发生了一件事才让我挽回了面子，令众人对我刮目相看。

小城里有一位年轻有为的商人，他组建了一支消防队，购置了一辆崭新的消防车。这位商人给每位消防队员发了制服并指挥消防队训练，他准备举行一个检阅仪式。所谓消防车其实就是一个水泵，由16名队员操作，漆成黑红两色，十分漂亮。一天下午，消防车被拉到了河边，准备举行正式的检阅仪式。人们倾城而出，赶来看这一盛景。演讲和典礼仪式结束后，一声令下，消防队员开始喷水，可是喷嘴里一滴水也喷不出来。教授和专家们群策群力，却找不出哪里出了毛病。我赶到现场时，人们正急得像热锅上的蚂蚁。我在机械原理方面的知识为零，也不懂得什么空气压力，但却本能地感到是水下的抽水管出了问题，抽水管可能被堵住了。于是我涉水打通了堵塞处，消防车的喷嘴便突然喷出了水，浇到了好几个人的漂亮衣服上。曾几何时，阿基米德(4)在锡拉丘兹街头裸奔，大着嗓门狂呼“我发现啦”，曾引起过轰动，而他引起的轰动恐怕并不比我所引起的大。我被人们扛在肩头游行，一下子成了英雄。

在小城安顿下来后，我进入一所所谓的师范学校，开始了四年的学习，准备考大学（或大学预科班）。在这段时期，我仍孩子气地进行各种尝试和探险，麻烦也如影随形。值得一提的是，我在捕捉乌鸦方面颇有建树，在当地享有“捕乌鸦冠军”之美称。我采用的方法极其简单，只不过是到树林里去，躲在灌木丛中，模仿乌鸦的叫声而已。一般情况下，我会先听到几声回应，过不了多久，就会有一只乌鸦扑棱着翅膀落到我跟前的灌木上。这时，我只需扔出一块纸板转移它的注意力，然后一跃而起，一把抓住它，让它来不及逃离茂密的灌木丛。用这种办法，我想抓多少只就能抓多少只。不过，后来发生了一件事，使得我对乌鸦们敬畏了起来。一次，我抓住了两只很漂亮的乌鸦，跟一位朋友一起回家。谁知一出树林，就见有几千只乌鸦聚在一起，发出震耳欲聋的呱呱叫声。没过几分钟，它们飞过来追我们，将我们团团围住。起初，我还觉得挺好玩，直至后脑勺挨了重重一击，栽倒在了地上。它们对我群起而攻之，吓得我赶快放掉了那两只乌鸦。接着我一头钻进了山洞，与躲在那里的朋友会合，这才松了口气。

学校里的一批机械模型引起了我的兴趣，之后我就开始关注水轮机了。我制作了好多台水轮机模型，并乐此不疲地进行操作。那时的生活简直充满了神奇的色彩，用一个例子可以加以说明。我的叔叔觉得我这种业余爱好派不上用场，不止一次责备过我。我读过一篇关于尼亚加拉大瀑布(5)的报道，不由着了迷，脑海中出现了一个巨大的水轮，幻想着可以用瀑布驱动它。我告诉叔叔，说我将来一定要到美国去实现这一计划。30年后，当我的这一理想在尼亚加拉大瀑布变成现实时，我不由感慨万分，觉得人的大脑真是神秘莫测啊！

除此之外，我还发明制造了很多其他的装置，其中最棒的要算弓弩了。我的弩箭射得很远，远得让你看都看不见，而近距离则可射穿一英寸厚的松木板。我由于不断练习拉弩射箭，所以腹肌发达，肚子上的皮厚得堪比鳄鱼的皮。我常常暗自思忖：通过这样的练习，我就是吞下小石子，也能消化得了！另外，投掷石头也是我的一门绝技，此处不能略过不提，若是拿到竞技场上露一手，一定能叫观众惊叹不已。接下来我要讲一件往事，看看我是怎样凭借这一门独步天下的绝技创下丰功伟绩的，读者听了恐怕会难以置信。一天，我和叔叔在河边散步——那时候，我随时随地都要练习我的绝技——但见夕阳西沉，鲑鱼在河里嬉戏，不时跃出水面，闪着亮光，在远处礁石的映衬下其轮廓一清二楚。当然，在这种条件有利的情况下，不管谁用石头砸鲑鱼恐怕都能砸得中。不过，我要做的事情却难得多，并且把我的意图预先详尽地告诉了叔叔。我说我要用石头砸鲑鱼，砸得它贴在礁石上，让它身首异处。我话音刚落，一扬手便完成了这一壮举。叔叔望着我，惊得几乎连魂都没有了，大呼：“你是魔鬼，快滚开！”他接下来一连几天都没有跟我说话。这样的光辉事迹将会被淹没在历史的长河里，但我觉得它们给我带来了荣耀，足够我心安理得地回味终生。

(1) 磅与盎司皆为英美制质量或重量单位。一磅等于16盎司，合0.4536千克。

(2) 美国参议员。

(3) 英美制长度单位，一英寸等于一英尺的1/12。

(4) 古希腊哲学家、数学家、物理学家。

(5) 位于加拿大安大略省和美国纽约州的交界处。

第三章　再接再厉续新篇——发现旋转磁场

10岁的时候，我进入了文理高中(1)，这是一所新成立的学校，教学设备非常完善。物理系拥有各种各样非常棒的科学实验仪器，电学方面的以及机械学方面的都有。老师经常用这些仪器做示范和实验，看得我心醉神迷，这无疑成为鼓励我发明创造的强大动力。我对数学也情有独钟，常常因为计算速度快而得到教授的表扬。这得益于我拥有在大脑中将数字形象化并计算的能力，并不是用普通的直观方式进行计算，而是将数字视为有生命的活体。再难的演算，无论是在黑板上列算式还是用心算，对我而言都一样容易。不过，徒手绘图倒是叫我很伤脑筋，而这门课的课时偏偏又很多，这使得我简直受不了。说来也奇怪，我们家大多数人在这方面都是高手。也许，我之所以如此反感徒手绘图，只不过是因为我更偏爱不受干扰地思考吧。要不是班上有几个笨得不能再笨，什么都不会的学生垫底，我这门课的成绩肯定就是最差的了。根据当时的教育制度，徒手绘图是必修课，这成了我的一个棘手的难题，过不了这个坎就会影响我的整个生涯。家父耗尽了心力才算帮助我渡过了这一道难关。

在该校求学的第二年，我产生了一种构想，并为此而着了迷，即利用稳定的空气压力催发连续运动。前面所述的修好消防车的事件让我大受鼓舞，充满青春活力的想象也得到了充分的激发，使我意识到真空可以产生无穷无尽的能量。我如痴如醉，一门心思想掌控这取之不尽用之不竭的能量，但在很长一段时间里我只是在黑暗中茫然地摸索。不过，我的努力方向最终趋于明朗，那就是推出一项发明，做一件前人没有做过的事情。我的设想是：取一个圆柱形的装置，装上两个轴承，使圆柱形装置能够在轴承的作用下自由旋转。圆柱形的一部分套着一个精密配合的矩形槽，槽的开口一侧用一个隔板封上，圆柱形装置的内部被隔板分隔成两部分，中间由不漏气的滑动接头将其完全分开。这两部分中的一部分完全封闭，只要把它里面的空气彻底抽空，另外一部分就会自动敞开，这样，圆柱形的装置就能不停地旋转。至少，我是这样设想的。我做了个木制模型，极其精心地将各部件组装在一起，从一侧用气泵抽气。看到圆柱形的装置开始旋转时，我高兴得简直都快发疯了。能够借助机械在天上飞行，是我另一个想实现的梦想——虽然我曾经手持一把撑开的雨伞从房顶跳下，结果摔得很惨，这成了我的一段令人沮丧的回忆。以前，我每天都希望自己能够腾云驾雾，穿越云层飞行到远方，只是不知如何才能梦想成真。现在，我有了具体的计划——制造一架飞行器，在上面只安装一个转轴和一双上下扇动的翅膀，让它靠永不枯竭的真空能量驱动。一旦大功告成，我就可以乘坐着舒适、豪华的飞行器每天翱翔于蓝天——乘坐这样的飞行器，恐怕只有所罗门国王才够格。数年之后我才明白过来：大气压力是垂直作用于圆柱体表面的，而我所看到的圆柱形装置微微旋转的现象是因为漏气造成的。尽管这一点是我逐渐悟出来的，但它对我的打击还是挺沉重的。我差点儿没能完成文理高中的学业，因为我大病了一场，或者说大病了十几场，情况非常危急，弄得医生束手无策。在这段时间里，我仍然坚持读书，从当地的公共图书馆借书。这家图书馆平时很少有人去，还请我帮忙对图书进行分类并帮着编辑图书目录。一天，图书馆交给我几卷新出版的文学作品叫我编进目录。这几本书跟我以前看过的书迥然不同，十分引人入胜，使我完全忘掉了自己那令人绝望的健康状况。它们是马克·吐温(2)的早期作品。也许是因为看了这几本书，我竟然奇迹般地恢复了健康。25年之后，我结识了克莱门先生，和他建立了友谊。我把这段往事讲给他听，惊奇地看到这个伟大的人物竟哈哈大笑，把眼泪都笑出来了。

后来，我又到了克罗地亚的卡尔洛瓦茨(3)（我的一个姑姑住在那里），在那儿的一所更高一层次的文理高中继续学习。那个姑姑是当地的头面人物，丈夫久经沙场，是个参加过无数次战斗的陆军上校。我在他们家住了三年，那段时光令我终生难忘。他们家的家规甚至比战争时期的军规还要严。我就好像一只被精心饲养的金丝雀，吃的饭菜顿顿都质量高、味道鲜美，但少之又少，只有我正常食量的1/10。姑姑把火腿切成像纸一样的薄片，如果上校往我的盘子上添加食物，她会一把夺走，同时会情绪激动地对少校说：“还是小心点儿好，尼科(4)的饭量很小！”其实我饭量极大，就这样我承受着坦塔罗斯(5)一样的痛苦。

不过，姑姑家洋溢着典雅的气氛，具有浓浓的艺术品位，这在那个时期以及那种历史条件下是极为罕见的。那个地区地势低洼，沼泽密布，我虽然服用了大量的奎宁，但还是摆脱不了疟疾和高烧的纠缠。有时河水上涨，会有成群结队的老鼠涌进民宅，见什么吃什么，甚至连晾晒的干辣椒串也不放过。消灭这些害虫成了我的一种很好的消遣。我使用各种办法大大地减少了它们的数量，在当地赢得了一个不值得羡慕的“灭鼠王”的称号。最后，我终于完成了文理高中的学业，结束了饿肚子的苦难生活，拿到了毕业证，也走到了人生的十字路口。

在那些年里，父母的决心一直没有动摇，一心一意想让我将来当牧师。一想到这一点，我心里就发怵。在学校物理学教授强烈的影响下，我已经对电产生了浓厚的兴趣。那位教授极具创造力，经常发明仪器，用来阐释物理学原理。记得他发明了一个仪器，那是一个可以自由旋转的球状物，外面用锡纸包裹，跟静电起电机连接在一起时会飞速旋转。目睹他展示的这种神奇的景象时，我心潮澎湃，激动万分，那种心情实在无法形容。每一个场景都会在我心里激起千层浪花。对于那种神奇的静电力量，我渴望了解更多，渴望从事这方面的实验和研究，但同时又不得不以痛苦的内心顺从命运的安排。

正当我准备长途跋涉返回家乡时，家父却叫人传来了话，他叫我去参加狩猎。这一要求十分奇怪，因为他历来都是强烈反对这项活动的。但过了几天，我得知了真相——霍乱正在我们家乡肆虐逞凶。我没理会父母的愿望，还是找了个机会返回了戈斯皮奇。这种灾难每隔15年至20年就会蹂躏我们的家乡一次，人们对其起因却一无所知，无知的程度简直匪夷所思。他们以为这种致命的疾病是靠空气传播的，于是就用刺鼻的气味和烟雾消灭空气里的病菌。与此同时，他们却饮用受到污染的水，大批大批地死去。我返回家乡的当天就染上了这种可怕的疾病，后来虽然大难不死，可还是在床上躺了九个月，几乎动弹不得。此时的我体力已完全耗尽，第二次来到了死亡的门口。我的病一次次发作，其中有一次使我生命垂危。父亲冲进了病房（他那苍白的面孔至今仍浮现在我眼前），用他自己都不相信的话语安慰我，叫我振作起来。我说：“如果你同意我学习工程技术，我也许可以恢复健康。”他郑重地向我许诺：“我要让你上天下最好的工学院。”我知道他会说话算话的。于是，我心里的一块大石头总算落了地。不过，要不是喝了用一种很奇异的豆子熬出来的苦汤，产生了起死回生的疗效，家父的许诺也是顶不了用的。结果，就像拉撒路(6)一样，我从死神那儿被拉了回来，让所有的人都惊讶万分。父亲坚持让我到山区过上一年，加强户外锻炼，以此增强体质，我勉强同意了。这一年，我大部分时间都带着猎人的装备和一捆书在群山里转悠，由于跟大自然亲密接触，我不仅增强了体质，心智也大增。我不断地思考和计划，产生了许多构想，但这些构想几乎无一例外都是虚无缥缈的。我的构想倒是很清晰，只苦于对原理的了解十分有限。在其中的一项发明项目里，我提出在海底铺设一根跨海管道，通过一座水泵站将水压压进管道，将信件和包裹放在一个十分结实，足以抵御水压的球形容器里，通过管道利用水流推动进行传送。我对为管道提供水压的水泵站进行了精确的计算和设计，其他的细节也精心规划。后来只是由于一个小小的细节被稍加忽略，这个发明项目便无果而终了。我假定海底的水流为任意速度，并且无限提高这个速度，希望以准确的计算为基础产生最佳效果。然而，经过进一步思索，我还是解决不了管道如何承受强大水流的问题，于是决定将这一发明交给公众，由公众完成。

我还有一个发明项目，建造一个可以无拘无束地悬浮在空中，绕赤道运行的环形悬浮器，它能高速飞行，靠某种反作用力制动。搭乘这样的悬浮器，时速可达1000英里(7)左右，这是火车无法比拟的。对此，读者也许会付之一笑。这个项目难以实现，这我得承认，但还不至于像纽约的那位名教授所提的方案那么荒唐。此人想把热带的空气抽到温带去，全然忘了上帝已经提供了一台巨大无比的机器来实现空气流通。

除此之外，我另有一种构想，一种极为重要也极为有趣的构想，那就是利用地球自转获取能量。我发现：由于地球自转带来昼夜更替，地球表面物体的运动方向与水平方向时而相同，时而相反。人类能够用可以想象的极其简单的方式将这一巨变所产生的能量加以利用，为任何一个有人居住的地区提供动力。后来我才意识到自己跟阿基米德一样陷入了窘境（阿基米德竟然幻想在宇宙找一个支点将地球撬起），当时失望的心情是无法用语言表达的。

假期结束后，我被送到了奥地利施蒂里亚州格拉茨市的理工学院学习——那是一所历史悠久、声名卓著的大学，是父亲专门为我挑选的。我翘首以待的时刻终于到来了，而且我衣食无忧，于是立刻投入到了学习中，一心一意要取得成就。由于父亲的潜心教育以及各种各样的机会，我的基础胜他人一筹。我掌握了几门语言，曾在好几个图书馆里博览群书，从中获取的知识多多少少都是有用的。还有，我可以选择自己喜欢的科目，这可是破天荒第一遭。我再也不用为徒手绘图而焦虑了！我下定决心一定要给父母一个惊喜，头一学年便开始发奋，每天凌晨3点起床，一直学到夜里11点，星期天和节假日也不例外。鉴于大多数同学都不用功，自然而然，我在各个科目上都拔得了头筹。那一学年，我通过了九门考试，教授们都认为给我最高分也不为过。放假后，我拿着写满教授赞语的成绩单回到家，准备稍微休整一下。我满以为这是凯旋，谁知家父对我辛辛苦苦挣来的荣誉竟毫不关心，使我一下子泄了气。这几乎扼杀了我的雄心壮志。他去世之后，我发现了一捆教授们写给他的信，不由心如刀绞——那些信说，如果不让我辍学，我一定会由于过分用功而丧命。从那以后，我把主要精力都用在了物理学、力学和数学上，课余时间则泡在图书馆。我不管做什么事情，总强迫自己坚持到底，常常因此而陷入困境。一次，我着手攻读伏尔泰的著作，诧异地发现那个“怪才”靠一天喝72杯黑咖啡竟然写了近100卷的东西，每一卷的字都密密麻麻。再多也要看完！当看完他的最后一卷书，将其放到一旁时，我感到十分高兴，说道：“我再也不读了！”

我在第一学年的出色表现赢得了好几位教授的赞赏和友谊。他们当中有教代数学和几何学的罗格纳教授，负责物理学理论和实验教学的波伊施尔教授，以及教积分学并对微分方程有深入研究的阿里博士。在所有给我上过课的教授里，阿里博士讲课最为精彩。他特别关心我的进步，常常上完课后仍留(8)教室里为我答疑解惑，一待就是一两个小时——他的讲解令我感到心情愉悦。我曾经向他介绍了自己构想的飞行器，这个构想是以合理的科学原理为基础的，并非不切实际的想象。如今，由于我发明了涡轮机，这个构想已经变成了现实，不久将会面世。罗格纳和波伊施尔两位教授都是很独特的人。罗格纳的表达方式很有特色，无论什么时候，一讲到高潮时就戛然而止，随之而至的就是漫长、令人尴尬的停顿。波伊施尔教授是一位条理清晰、极为务实的德国人。他手脚粗大，宛若熊掌，但做实验历来都是娴熟而精确的，从未有过丝毫的误差。

在第二个学年，一台从巴黎运来的格拉姆发电机(9)被送到了我们学院。这台机器装有马蹄形的叠片磁铁和一个用金属丝缠绕的电枢，而电枢上装有整流器。各个部件接通之后，它就能展示电流的不同效果。波伊施尔教授在演示时，把它当作电动机操作，结果电刷出了毛病，冒出了大量火花。我提出，不要那些附件，机器照样可以运转。他认为那是绝对行不通的，同时叫我阐述了一下我的观点。我讲完后，他说：“特斯拉先生也许能成就伟大的事业，但在这件事上的看法注定行不通——这等于是要改变万有引力那样的稳定的引力，使之成为旋转的力。这是永动机的概念，永远不可能实现。”但是，人的本能是可以超越知识的。毫无疑问，我们大脑中埋藏着一些神奇的神经纤维，当我们的逻辑推理或其他思维方式无能为力时，它们能帮助我们发现真理。在教授的权威论断下，我曾一度发生了动摇，但很快就坚信自己是对的，而且以年轻人的那种狂热和无穷的信心投入到了这项研究之中。

第一步，我先在大脑里构想出一台直流发电机，想象它运转起来的样子，并观察电枢中电流的变化。第二步，我再构想出一台交流发电机，然后按照相同的方式研究它的运作情况。第三步，我构想出几个由电动机和发电机组成的机组，用各种方式操作。我脑海中出现的那些影像非常逼真、非常清晰。在格拉茨的剩余时间里，我一直在进行这项研究，十分紧张，但无果而终。最后，我几乎断定这是一个无法解决的难题。1880年，我去了波希米亚的布拉格，希望能完成父亲的心愿，在那里完成大学学业。在那座城市里，我采取了具有决定性的一个步骤，把发电机的整流器卸下来，从一个新的角度细心观察发电机的运行情况，结果还是一无所获。在接下来的一年中，我对生活的认识突然发生了转变，意识到父母为我做出的牺牲太大了，于是我决定减轻他们的负担。当时，美国的电话热刚刚波及欧洲大陆，匈牙利的布达佩斯打算设立电话局。这似乎是一个理想的机遇，而我家的一个朋友恰恰是电话公司的负责人。进了电话局后，我的神经却达到了完全崩溃的状态（这一点上文提起过）。患病期间的那段经历你可能无法相信。我的视觉和听觉一直都好得出奇。若论视觉，远处别人压根看不见的东西，我却看得一清二楚。谈到听觉，小的时候我好几次隐约听见邻居家有噼噼啪啪大火燃烧的声音（那声音没有将邻居从睡梦中惊醒），便大呼救火，使得邻居家没有被大火吞没。

1899年，我已过不惑之年，正在科罗拉多进行试验。当时，我可以清楚地听见550英里开外的雷声，而我的年轻助手们听觉范围最远不超过150英里。所以说，我的耳朵的灵敏度是普通人的13倍(10)还要多。然而，说起来，这样的听力跟我神经高度紧张时的听力相比，简直就跟聋子一样。在布达佩斯的那段时间，隔着三个房间，我都可以听到钟表的嘀嗒声；屋里如果有苍蝇落在桌子上，我的耳朵会听见砰的一声沉闷的巨响；几英里外有马车驶过，会震得我浑身发抖；二三十英里以外的火车鸣笛，会让我觉得自己坐的板凳或椅子在剧烈摇晃，产生无法忍受的痛苦感。而且，我脚下的地面也在不停地颤抖，为了能睡得着觉，我只好在床下铺了橡胶垫子。远处或近处传来的喧闹声，让我觉得就跟有人冲我喊话一样，如果我不能将那些声音一一分辨清楚，一定会被吓着的。阳光时隐时现，会对我的大脑造成冲击，使我感到头晕目眩。从桥下或其他建筑物下走过，我会感到有千钧之力压在我的头上，这时我就调动起全部的意志力加以抵御。在黑暗中，我的感觉和蝙蝠一样敏锐，能感知到12英尺(11)之外的物体——如果那儿有东西，我的脑门上会产生一种奇异的感觉。我的脉搏极不均匀，有时每分钟只有几下，有时每分钟达260下，身体的各个部位都会随之颤抖、抽搐和哆嗦，而这也许是最叫人难以忍受的。一位名医让我每天服用大量溴化钾，说我得的是一种怪病，是不治之症。无限遗憾的是，当时没有生理学家和心理学家对我的病情进行观察研究。虽然我压根就没有指望能够恢复健康，但我孤注一掷，不愿放弃生命。有谁能相信，就是这样一个身处绝境的病人竟能起死回生，成为一个精力充沛、坚韧不拔，又工作了38年，中间无一天间歇，仍然身体强壮、思维活跃的人？这就是我的经历。我强烈渴望活下去，渴望继续我的事业，再加上一位运动员挚友的倾力帮助，奇迹出现了——我不仅恢复了健康，思维也变得更加活跃了。后来再次回想这段经历，我还真有点儿遗憾呢，觉得那次战斗结束得太早了——我还有许多能量没有用上呢。在和疾病做斗争的时候，我跟普通人的想法不同。对我而言，那是一个神圣的誓言，是一个关系生死存亡的大问题。我情知自己如果失败，就会命丧黄泉。我觉得我是胜出者。其实，在我的内心深处早已有了答案，只是当时未能用语言表达出来而已。一天下午，我和朋友在城市公园一边散步一边背诵诗歌——当时的情景至今仍历历在目。那个年龄的我看书过目不忘，能倒背如流。夕阳西沉，使我想起了歌德的《浮士德》里的一段壮丽的诗句。

太阳西坠，结束了一天的劳累，
急匆匆奔向远方，到新天地去绽放生命的花蕾；
呜呼，只恨我没有翅膀摆脱大地的束缚，
去追踪，去寻觅太阳的光辉！
太阳隐去了身影，却留下了一个梦，光辉不退！
哦！我的身体没有翅膀，
何不给思想插上翅膀，让思想腾飞！

当我背诵这段发人深省的诗句时，好像有一道闪电从我的脑海中划过，让我刹那间想到了问题的解决方法。我马上找了一根树枝在沙地上画起示意图来，六年后我在给美国电机工程学会做报告时把它们展示给了听众。当时陪我散步的那个朋友完全能够看懂我的示意图。我脑海中的影像出奇地清晰和具体，就跟现实生活中的金属和石块一样，于是我便对朋友说：“瞧，这是电动机！看好，我要让它动起来！”我当时的那种激动心情，现在是无法形容的。即便皮格马利翁(12)看见自己的雕塑变成了活人，也不及我当时的感受强烈。就算我偶然发现了一千个大自然的秘密，对我而言也不及这一发现价值大——它是我经历了千难万险，眼看就要进入鬼门关时得来的。

(1) 德国等国家培养学生升入高等学校的高级中学。

(2) 美国著名作家，真实姓名是萨缪尔·兰亨·克莱门，代表作品有小说《百万英镑》《哈克贝利·费恩历险记》和《汤姆·索亚历险记》等。

(3) 克罗地亚西北部城市，设有大学和克罗地亚最古老的图书馆，还有中世纪建的教堂和城堡遗迹。

(4) 尼古拉·特斯拉的昵称。

(5) 希腊神话中宙斯的儿子，后来由于得罪了众神而被打入地狱，过上了饥渴难忍的日子。

(6) 《圣经》中的人物，死后被耶稣救活。

(7) 英美制长度单位，一英里等于5280英尺，合1.6093公里。

(8) 由法国人格拉姆所发明。

(9) 由法国人格拉姆所发明。

(10) 原文是thirteen times（13倍），按理应该是three times（3倍）。

(11) 英美制长度单位，一英尺等于12英寸，合0.3048米。

(12) 皮格马利翁是希腊神话中的塞浦路斯国王，善雕刻，曾雕刻了一座美丽的象牙少女像，并爱上了她。爱神阿芙洛狄忒被他打动，赐予雕像生命，并让他们结为夫妻。

第四章　发明特斯拉线圈和变压器

有一段时间，我在大脑中构想机器的图形，发明各种新机器，陶醉其中，享受着极大的快乐。那是一种心灵的愉悦，我之前也有过体验。我思如泉涌，唯一的困难在于怎样抓住那稍纵即逝的念头。我所构想的种种机器都是实实在在、真真切切的，我对每一个细节都了如指掌，哪怕最细微的标识和磨损痕迹也逃不过我的眼睛。在想象中，我乐于让电动机一刻不停地运转——那样的画面更让人赏心悦目。当天生的兴趣爱好逐渐发展成为一种强烈的欲望时，一个人就会大踏步向自己的目标迈进，犹如穿上了七里格靴子(1)。实际上，在不到两个月的时间里，我就发明了许多种类的电动机，并对之进行改进（如今，这些机器均以我的名字命名）。后来，由于生活的需要，我暂时终止了这种耗费心力的脑力劳动——也许，这是幸运之举。我因为一份不太成熟的电话业研究报告来到了布达佩斯。受到命运的捉弄，他们叫我在匈牙利政府管辖的电报总局当绘图员，无奈之下我也只好接受了这份工作。至于工资嘛，此处不便透露，还是不说的好！幸运的是，我很快就赢得了总监的赏识，另有委任，他让我负责设备安装方面的计算、设计和评估。电话局开始运营后，我仍从事这三方面的工作。这份工作使我积累了宝贵的知识和实践经验，同时我的发明创造才能也得到了充分施展。我对电话总局的装置做了许多改良，还完善了电话中继器（或称信号放大器）——这项技术没有申请专利，也没有公开发布，然而，甚至到了今天这项技术的发明也应该归功于我。布达佩斯电话业的创始人普斯卡斯先生对我高效率的工作非常认可，他结束了这座城市的业务之后，便邀请我到巴黎工作。我高兴地接受了他的邀请。巴黎是座充满奇幻魔力的城市，给我留下的印象极深，令我终生难忘。一连几天我都在城里转悠，流连于巴黎的街头。这儿有看不尽的新奇景象，让人陶醉。各种景观随处可见，都具有难以抵御的魅力，弄得我花钱如流水，工资一到手便花个精光。一次，普斯卡斯先生问我在这个新环境中感觉如何，我准确地描述道：“每个月的后29天是最难熬的！”我的生活紧张有序，按现在的话说，过的是“罗斯福(2)式的生活”。每天清晨，不管刮风还是下雨，我都会从我居住的圣马塞尔林荫大道步行去塞纳河畔的游泳馆，在游泳池里游上27个来回，随后再步行一个小时到伊夫里，那儿是公司工厂的所在地。7点半，我会在厂里吃一顿工作早餐，接下来就满怀希望等着吃中午的那顿饭了。在这期间，我会为工厂的经理査尔斯·巴彻勒先生（此人是爱迪生的好友和助手）解决一些难题。在这里，我结交了几个美国人。因为我台球打得好，他们都非常喜欢我。我向他们推介了自己的发明，机工车间的负责人坎宁安先生提出应该成立一家股份公司。我觉得他的提议荒唐可笑，实在不理解这种想法，以为这就是美国人的做事方式，于是便没有采取任何措施。在后边的几个月里，我老是出差，辗转于法国和德国，为发电厂排除故障。回到巴黎后，我向公司的一位高管罗尔先生提交了一份改进发电机的计划书，得到了他的首肯。结果，我大功告成，让董事们喜出望外，于是他们授权给我，让我研发自动稳压器，而这正是我梦寐以求的。此后不久，阿尔萨斯地区的斯特拉斯堡新火车站的照明装置出了问题。在火车站剪彩仪式上，由于电线短路，照明装置发生了爆炸，把一大段墙都炸塌了，而当时德国的老皇帝威廉一世就在现场。结果，德国政府拒绝使用这一套照明装置，这样一来，我们的法国公司将遭受巨大的损失。考虑到我会说德语，而且经验丰富，公司就派我去解决这一难题，希望能将此事搞定。我临危受命，于1883年初去了斯特拉斯堡。

在斯特拉斯堡市发生的一些事，给我留下了难以磨灭的印象。真是无巧不成书，我在那里遇见了一些杰出人才，而他们日后都成了风云人物。后来，我曾对人说：“那座古老的城市有一种叫作伟大的‘细菌’，别人都‘感染’了，而我却是个例外！”我没日没夜地工作，又是排除设备故障和与各方沟通，又是跟政府官员协商。但只要能挤出一点儿时间，我就会跑到火车站对面的机械车间里，用我从巴黎带来的材料组装简易电动机。不过，有关简易电动机的试验一直耽搁到那年夏天才完成。当我看到这台电动机在没有滑动触点和整流器的情况下，受到不同相位的交流电驱动，仍然可以运转时，心里快慰极了——这跟我一年前构想的一样。我当时喜悦盈怀，但那种心情与后来第一次向世人展示这一成果时的欣喜若狂相比，却又有着天壤之别。

我新结交的朋友中，有一位是斯特拉斯堡的前任市长博赞先生。我向他介绍了我的新设备和其他一些发明，想赢得他的支持。他侠肝义胆，对我很仗义，向好几位阔佬推荐我的规划，令人失望的是，那几位阔佬竟无一人感兴趣。他绞尽脑汁，一心想帮助我。我一直牢记博赞先生对我的知遇之恩。1919年7月1日前夕，我突然想起了他给过我的一种“帮助”——那帮助不是金钱方面的，却仍让我心怀感激。1870年德国人入侵斯特拉斯堡时，他曾把一批1801年酿造的圣埃斯塔菲(3)酒埋在地下藏了起来。他声称，没有人比我更有资格喝这种名贵佳酿了。可以说，跟前边所提到的事情相比，这是最让我难以忘怀的一件事。这位知心的朋友劝我尽可能早日返回巴黎，在那儿寻求资助。我倒是巴不得赶快回巴黎，但我的工作和谈判遇阻，小麻烦不断，久久不能结束，当时的情况很不乐观。

在这里，我想叙述一段有趣的经历，以此说明德国人是怎样一丝不苟和讲求“效率”的。当时，有一条走廊需要安装一盏16烛光功率(4)的白炽灯，我选定了位置，让电工铺设电线。干了一会儿，电工突然提出必须咨询一下工程师，于是我们便征求了工程师的意见。工程师先是这不是那不是地说了些反对的话，但最终同意把灯安在距离我选定的位置两英寸远的地方。接下来，工作继续进行。过了一会儿，那位工程师突然有点儿忧心忡忡，对我说应该请示一下质检员艾沃戴克才行。那位大人物被请来了，他又是测量，又是跟工程师争论，最后决定把灯的位置朝后移2英寸，而这个位置正是我原先选定的。可是，不一会儿，又轮到艾沃戴克感到不安了，说此事他曾向质检督察黑尔罗尼莫汇报过，让我等黑尔罗尼莫的决策。由于琐事缠身，那位质检督察几天后才抽出了空。但他最终还是来了，经过两个小时的讨论，决定把灯的位置再朝外移2英寸。我希望他可以就此一锤子定音，但这一希望还是破灭了。他走后又返了回来，对我说：“冯克委员是很挑剔的。对于这盏灯的位置，没有他的明确批示，我不敢轻易决定。”于是乎，我们作了些安排，一大早就洒扫庭院，擦擦洗洗，整理仪容，准备迎接那位大人物的光临。我还特意戴上了手套。冯克来的时候前呼后拥，受到了隆重的接待。经过两个小时的深思熟虑，他突然大声说：“我必须走了。”然后指了指天花板上的一个位置，命令我把灯就装在那儿——那儿正是我最初选的位置！

事情就这样一波三折，一天一变，但我决心已定，不管付出什么样的代价都要达到目的。功夫不负有心人，我的努力得到了回报！1884年春，所有的分歧都消除了，对方最后终于接受了我方的照明装置。我怀着美好的憧憬回到了巴黎。公司的一位高管曾经对我许诺，如果我促成此事，就发给我一大笔奖金，另外还给我一笔数量可观的钱奖励我对发电机做出的改进。我满怀希望，想着能到手许多钱。公司总共有三位高管，为了方便，我就分别用A、B、C指代。当我去找A要钱时，他告诉我决定权在B那里，而B又认为只有C可以敲定，C则非常肯定地说只有A才有权决定是否给我钱。经过几轮的拉锯战和扯皮，我才意识到所谓的奖金其实不过是一张空头支票。

为研究项目筹集资金的努力也遭到了彻底失败，令我的一颗心沉到了谷底。巴彻勒先生劝我到美国去发展，为爱迪生设计新机型。于是，我决定到那个遍地黄金的地方去碰碰运气。可谁知这次机会也差点儿跟我失之交臂。我变卖了自己那少得可怜的物品，预订了火车票，赶到火车站时却发现车已经开动了。就在这时，我发现口袋里的钱和车票都不见了踪影。怎么办？赫拉克勒斯(5)在决定何去何从时，倒是有充裕的时间从容考虑，而我却不然——我一边追着火车跑，一边必须即刻做出决定。我心里千头万绪，乱成了一锅粥，似冷凝器一般剧烈震荡不已。就在这紧急关头，我灵机一动，决定乘船走——根据以往的经验，乘船虽然不舒服，但很便宜。于是，我带着自己所剩无几的东西登上了前往纽约的航船，那些东西中包括我写的几首诗和几篇文章，还有一捆写满计算题的纸张（那些计算题有的是对不可解积分的答案，有的涉及的则是我发明的飞行器）。途中，大部分时间我都坐在船尾，随时准备救落水之人，对于自身的安危完全置之度外。后来，我懂得了一些美国人务实的世界观，回忆起这段经历不由感到后怕，实在不明白自己当时怎么那么傻。

在此，我想讲一讲我对美国的第一印象。我看过几篇阿拉伯神话故事，它们讲述的是神仙施展神通，将普通人送到了充满梦想的国度，让他们经历了令人兴奋的事件的故事。我的情况恰恰相反——神仙把我从一个充满梦想的世界送到了一个极为现实的世界。我所离开的那个国家风光旖旎，充满了艺术气氛，处处令人心醉，而我在美国看到的却是一个机器驱动的社会，粗野和缺乏吸引力。我看见一个大块头警察在街上巡逻，手持警棍（那警棍在我看来简直就是一根大棒），于是便走上前彬彬有礼地问路。“往前走六个街区，然后向左拐弯。”他回答说，眼睛里却闪出恶狠狠的光。我感到又难过又惊讶，不由暗想：“美国就是这个样子？在文明程度上简直比欧洲落后了一个世纪！”1889年我离开美国时，我则坚信美国比欧洲先进100年，直到现在回来后五年过去了，我还坚持这种看法。

在我的一生中，跟爱迪生结识是一件值得纪念的事情。这个杰出的人才早年没有受过良好的教育，在科学研究方面也没有受过训练，却取得了那么辉煌的成就，实在令我刮目相看。我学习过十几种语言，钻研过文学和艺术，大好年华是在图书馆度过的，在那儿如饥似渴地博览群书，从牛顿的定律到保罗·德·科克的小说无所不看，觉得自己大部分的时间都被浪费掉了。但没过多久我就意识到那样的知识积累是我所干过的最棒的事情。没出几个星期，我就赢得了爱迪生的信任。情况是这样的：

当时最快的蒸汽机客轮“俄勒冈号”由于两台照明发电机都出现了故障，不得不停航。那艘轮船的上层建筑是发电机系统安装好之后才建造的，所以发电机是不能从船上卸下来的。情况很危急，爱迪生十分苦恼。当天傍晚我携带工具登上了那艘轮船，苦干了一夜。发电机损毁严重，多处短路和漏电，但在船员的配合下，我终于成功地排除了所有故障。次日凌晨5点，我穿过第五大道返回工厂，路上碰见了爱迪生，他和巴彻勒等人刚从工厂出来，正准备回住处睡觉。“瞧，咱们的巴黎人在夜里逛大街！”他说道。我告诉他我刚刚从“俄勒冈号”下来，已经把两台机器都修好了，他听后默默地看了看我，然后一声不吭地走开了。可他走了一段距离之后，我听见他说：“巴彻勒，这家伙真棒！”自此，我在工作方面便有了充分的自主权，每天从上午10点半一直干到次日凌晨5点，没有一天的休息，差不多有一年之久。爱迪生对我说：“我有过许多勤奋工作的助手，但你是最好的。”在这段时间里，我利用短磁芯和同样的方案设计了24台不同规格的标准机型，用以取代原来的机型。爱迪生曾许诺，等我完成了这个项目之后就给我五万元的奖金，谁知他的话竟成了玩笑。这对我打击很大，于是便辞职不干了。

我辞职后，立刻就有人找上门来，提议以我的名义组建一家弧光灯照明公司。我觉得终于有机会研发电动机了，于是欣然同意了。可是，当我提出这个方案时，我的新同事说：“这是不行的。我们需要的是弧光灯，对你的交流电设备不感兴趣。”1886年，我研制的弧光灯系统获得了成功，被应用到工厂和市政照明上。这下子我成了自由之身，然而却一无所获，只有一张印刷精美但不能当饭吃的股权证书。接下来的一段时间，我在自己不太熟悉的领域里苦苦奋斗，但我最后还是获得了回报——1887年4月，特斯拉电气公司终于成立了。我有了自己的实验室和设备，并且研制出了电动机——那些电动机跟我以前构想的一模一样。对于以前的设计方案，我没有做丝毫的改动，而只是将脑海里出现过的设计图变为现实，机器运行情况完全符合我的预想。

1888年年初，我跟威斯汀豪斯公司(6)签约，准备大量生产这种电动机。不过，有一些重大难题亟待解决。我设计的机器用的是低频电流，而威斯汀豪斯公司的专家采用的是133周的电流，为的是在变电方面取得优势。他们不愿意放弃自己的标准设备，所以，我必须设法改变我的电动机，以符合他们的标准。除此之外，我还要另外设计一台电动机，利用两根电线在这种低频电流下有效地工作。这可不是一件容易的事。

不过，到了1889年年底，我完成了任务，也就没必要继续留在匹兹堡了。回到纽约后，我在格兰街的一个实验室里继续搞我的试验，并立即着手设计高频机。这是一个尚无人涉足的领域，我遇到的问题千奇百怪，这让我步履维艰。我对感应型电动机不予以考虑，怕的是这种电动机产生的正弦波不稳定，而正弦波对于共振却是至关紧要的。如果不是出于这一考虑，我的工作量会大大降低。高频交流电动机还有另外一个缺点，就是速度不稳定，这可能会对它的实际应用带来极大限制。向美国电机工程学会进行演示时，我注意到该机型有好几次都频率调谐失衡，需要进一步改进——这些都是没有预料到的问题。直到很久之后，我才找到了一种方法，使这种高频交流电动机在恒定速度和极限负载条件下工作时，每旋转一周的速度变化控制在极小范围内。

我又对许多其他的因素进行了综合考虑，认为很有必要发明一种比较简单的可以产生电振荡的仪器。早在1856年，凯尔文男爵(7)就提出了电容器放电的理论，只可惜这一重要理论未用于实践之中。我看出了这一理论的可行性，于是便根据他的理论着手研制感应器。我的研发进展神速，在1891年的一次报告会上我向听众展示了一个能够产生五英寸长的电火花的线圈。会上，我坦率地告诉在场的工程师们，说用这种新方法变换电流也是有缺陷的，即电火花的间隙会出现损耗的现象。后来的研究表明：不管是用空气、氢、水银蒸汽、油液或者电子束作为媒介，这种缺陷都始终存在。这是自然规律，就像机械能量转化也存在类似的规律一样。物体从高处落下，我们可以让它垂直降落，也可以让它沿着曲线降落，这些都不算什么问题。幸运的是，这一缺陷并非致命性的，通过调整共振电路的适当比例，其效率可以达到85％。这一发明公布后，得到了广泛的应用，给许多领域带来了革命性的发展。然而，它的潜力还远远没有发掘出来。1900年，我成功地制造了100英尺的强大放电电弧，并围绕球体产生了人工闪电。这时，我想起了最初在格兰街实验室看到的那个小小的电火花，不由感慨万千，激动程度不亚于我发现旋转磁场时的那种感觉。

(1) 神话故事里的靴子，穿上后一步就能迈出七里格（一里格约等于4.827千米）。

(2) 连任四届的美国总统，也是美国历史上任期最长的总统。

(3) 圣埃斯塔菲是法国的四大酒庄之一，主要生产红葡萄酒。

(4) 旧时的发光强度单位。

(5) 古希腊罗马神话中的大力神。

(6) 1886年1月8日由威斯汀豪斯在美国宾夕法尼亚州创立，总部设在宾夕法尼亚州匹兹堡市。

(7) 格拉斯哥大学工程师兼物理学家。

序言

给一本你很久之前写的书作序并不是一件很难的事情，因为匆匆流逝的这些年已经让你成为一个不同的人，你可以用全新的视角来审视这部作品。你看到书的缺点，然后为了读者的欢娱，你回想起了自己性格里的缺陷，按你的性格这种回想可能会让你可以忍受或者让你气馁，而你的这些性格缺陷就是你的书的缺点产生的原因；或者你会带着因距离而产生的对过去的满足感回顾你写书时的那些情况；你可以美好地描绘一番你的阁楼，或者稍稍得意地细细回想你面对忽视时的坚定沉着。但当你为了引诱读者去购买一本不再新颖的书而开始为你两三年前写的小说作序，这并非易事，因为你发现已经在这本书中详尽讲述了这一话题，且完成后就抛之脑后了。正如没有什么比已经燃尽的爱更加死气沉沉，对作者来说，没什么话题比那些他已经畅所欲言的话题更加无趣。当然你可以跟你的评论家们争吵，但这几乎没有什么意义；某某评论家对他前年阅读的小说的看法只能对一个太脆弱受不起如今这个乱作一团的世界的考验的作家有意义；评论家早已忘记了这书和他写的评论，而大多数读者亦不再对这些评论费心劳神了。

在我最初成为一名职业作家的时候，我习惯将报纸上的评论贴在剪贴簿上，觉得将来有一天再读到时会很有趣，而且我会细心地在每篇评论上端标上日期和刊发它的报纸的名称。但是，随着时间的推移，这些笨重的剪贴簿变得越来越难以处理，而且由于某些原因，我很少会长时间地居住在同一个地方，于是最终我觉得有必要让清洁工来处理掉它们。自那以后，时光荏苒，我就满足于只读有关我的短评而不收藏它们，且心态平和，既不会为那些不赞同的评论感到过分苦恼，也不会为那些称赞之词感到扬扬自得，然后将它们通通扔进我的废纸筐里。我印象里，总的来说，大家对《剧院风情》的评价相当好。然而，有些评论家抱怨我的女主人公朱莉娅·兰伯特不具有崇高的道德品质、伟大的智慧和高尚的灵魂，并推断出她只不过是一位不知名的三流女演员。据我所知，很多知名的女演员都有同样的观点。事实上，有一位上了年纪的女演员对我的评论非常尖刻，她在我还是个孩子的时候就非常有名，现在也依旧因她经常说的那些让人讨厌但逗人笑的话而被很多中年观众念念不忘，这些话通常以伤害与她合作的演员为代价；但我认为她的尖酸刻薄是源于她的误解。我在小说中很努力去明确地展现这一点：不论我的女主人公有任何其他缺陷，但她并不是一个势利眼。这一点自然也妨碍了这位老演员对于我的朱莉娅是位好演员的认可。我们都倾向于认为别人不会拥有我们的美德，除非他们拥有我们的恶习。

伟大是罕见的。在过去五十年，我见过很多女演员成名。我见过很多有天赋的人，很多在自己的领域胜过常人的人，很多拥有魅力、美貌和知识的人，但我想不到第二位我能毫不犹豫地用伟大来描述的女演员。她就是埃莉诺拉·杜丝(1)。或许西登斯夫人(2)也可称为伟大；或许雷切尔也可以；我不知道。我从未见过全盛时期的萨拉·伯恩哈特(3)，那些围绕着她的荣誉，有关她的夸张传说，让我很难清醒地评价她。她时常举止文雅，有时又会像任何演员女王那样咆哮。在她的全盛时期，她可能曾经是伟大的，而我只在她身上看到了伟大的附属物，那皇冠，那权杖，还有那貂皮斗篷——只见中国皇帝的新衣，未见中国的皇帝。除了我提到的那个例外，我只见过在某些角色上表现优秀的女演员，有时让人觉得非常优秀。依我看来，人在这件事情上的看法很大程度上依赖于他受到多少舞台魅力的影响。剧院给很多人带来的兴奋刺激是历久弥新的。对他们来说，那是一个充满神秘和欢乐的世界；剧院让他们进入想象的王国，增加他们生活里的乐趣，剧院所带来的假象为他们单调平凡的日常生活增添浪漫的金色光芒。当他们看着这位有名的女演员，她的美貌因化妆更加突出，她的重要性被聚光灯凸显，她说着似乎都是从她脑子里出来的优美句子，经历着不同寻常的事情并且承受着深刻的感情，他们觉得演员活得更充实；当他们力图描述那些技艺精湛的演员所带给他们的激动之情时，很自然地，他们会稍稍有些夸张。同样自然地，他们会忽略那使他们兴高采烈的表演至少有一部分功劳属于服装师、布景师、电工还有剧作家。

即使在我年轻时，我也没有迷恋舞台；这是由于我天生个性多疑，还是由于我脑子里充满的各种奇思妙想满足了我那浪漫的诉求，我不确定；而自从我的作品开始被搬上舞台后，我甚至连那点曾经对舞台抱有的幻想都失去了。当我发现为了让动作自然流畅需要付出多少努力，当我意识到让观众热泪盈眶的完美语调并非源于女演员的情感而是作者的体验，简而言之，当我明白一部戏剧呈现给观众前所经历的过程有多么复杂后，我发现无法用大众那样的敬畏、景仰之情来看待那些演员，甚至是那些最杰出的演员。另一方面，我看到他们身上有大众并不相信他们能拥有的那些品质。例如，我发现他们几乎无一例外地勤奋、勇敢、有耐心且一丝不苟。虽然完成一天的工作后疲惫不堪，我看到他们会心甘情愿地再排演一遍某个有难度的场景，而这个场景他们当天已经排演了六次；我看到他们虽然病到几乎无法起身，但仍旧进行演出，不愿让大众失望；我发现他们虽然爱摆架子，但当面对如何最好地表演戏剧、表现自己时，他们变得非常通情达理。在他们著名的“脾气”之后，而这所谓的“脾气”是自私和神经过敏的结合，在错误的印象下被或多或少地、有意识地强调是一种艺术感性的证明，他们身上还经常展现超出大众想象的精明、务实。我从未见过不爱炫耀的孩子，而在每个演员身上都保留了一些孩子气；他的许多最让人着迷的天赋也都源于此。他比常人更爱出风头，除了我们中的个别情况，这种癖好在常人身上很普遍，且如果他不具备，那他不应该去做一名演员；用幽默的态度而非鄙夷的态度去看待这种特别的性格特点才更明智。如果必须对长期和舞台接触的过程中形成的对演员的印象说几句的话，我会说他们的美德比他们伪装的更可靠，而他们的缺点是他们从事的这个冒险而严苛的职业的附带品。

从我创作第一部剧到最后一部剧中间隔了三十年，这期间，我和许多卓越的女演员有密切接触。朱莉娅·兰伯特并非她们之中哪一个人的形象。我收集了大家的品质特点，试图创造一个生动的人物形象。由于我并不为我所熟悉的杰出女演员的魅力所动，因此我敢说，我对我想象的人物形象的描述克制而冷静。可能正是这一点让那些无法将女演员和聚光灯分开的读者感到不安，让那些深深着迷于聚光灯以至于真的以为除此以外自己无其他内涵的女演员恼怒。他们并没有发挥自己的实际能力。艺术家的品质取决于人的品质，除了他的特殊天赋，如果他没有高尚的道德情操，也不可能在艺术上有超常的表现；然而，我不否定，这种高尚会以一种让人惊讶而不可思议的形式展现。我认为朱莉娅·兰伯特是真实的。我希望读者能注意到虽然她的仰慕者认为她是伟大的，虽然她贪婪地接受这些奉承，但我个人并没有宣称她异常成功、天赋异禀、认真而勤勉。我想补充说明我对她万分喜爱；我并没有为她的淘气感到震惊，也没有为她的荒谬而感到愤慨；不论她做什么，我都只能宠溺地看待她。

在我写完这篇序之前，我必须要告诉读者，在这本我邀请他细细品读的作品里我犯了两个错误。尽管小说家试图将每个细节都描写准确，但有时他也会犯错，而且不乏有人已经准备好为他指出错误。曾经在我的一部小说中我偶然提到了一片名为曼利的沙滩，这是游泳季节最受悉尼人喜欢的度假胜地，很不幸，我将它拼写为曼雷(4)。这个多余的“e”带给我来自新南威尔士州上百封充满愤怒和嘲笑的信件。你可能会认为，这很可能是印刷带来的小错误，虽然确实是由于我自己的不小心造成的，这是我对英联邦的故意侮辱。事实上，有位女士告诉我，这又一次显示了英国人对英国殖民地人民的无知的傲慢，如果下一次大英帝国卷入一场大陆战争，比起赶快去营救，澳大利亚的年轻人更喜欢静静待在家中，这得由像我这样的人负责。她用一个修辞学的句子结束了自己的信函。她问我，如果一个澳大利亚小说家在写英国的时候将伯恩茅斯多写了个“e”，英国人会怎么想？我的第一反应就是回答我认为英国人压根不会理会，即使它是错的，而事实上多个“e”才是正确的拼法，但我觉得我最好还是默默忍受这位女士的指责。在这本书中我犯了两个错误；我让我的女主人公承认她演不好比阿特丽斯(5)是因为她念不好无韵诗，并且当她谈到拉辛的《费德尔》时我让她抱怨该剧的女主人公直到第三幕才出现。我并没有验证这些事实，而是相信了我的记忆，我的记忆欺骗了我。比阿特丽斯几乎没有说诗句；她所有重要的戏都是以散文形式进行的；如果朱莉娅没有演好这个角色，那也并不是由于她所给出的原因。费德尔在第一幕第三场就出场了。我不明白为什么只有两个人向我指出这些不可辩解的错误；我喜欢认为大部分读者都在称赞我，认为这些错误并非源于我的疏忽，而是出于我的敏锐，且认为通过让朱莉娅用这种随意的语气说话，使得我对她个性的描述增添了一抹色彩。但我可能在过度自夸，很可能读者对随着这些人物出现的著名戏剧的记忆跟我一样模糊，跟我知道得差不多而已。

————————————————————

(1) 杜丝（Eleonora Duse，1858—1924），意大利女演员。

(2) 萨拉·西登斯（Sarah Siddons，1755—1831），英国女演员，著名的悲剧演员。

(3) 萨拉·伯恩哈特（Sarah Bernhardt，1844—1923），法国著名女演员。

(4) 曼利原文为Manly，曼雷原文为Manley。

(5) 比阿特丽斯（Beatrice），莎士比亚戏剧《无事生非》的女主角之一，伶牙俐齿，爱挖苦人。

第一章

门打开了，迈克尔·格斯林抬起头来。朱莉娅走了进来。

“嘿！我不会耽搁太久的。我正在签署一些信件。”

“不着急。我就是来看看给丹诺伦特一家送了什么位置的票。那个年轻人在这里做什么？”

出于一位老到的女演员用动作配合自己对白的本能，她将梳得整齐的头一偏，示意她刚刚经过的屋子。

“他就是那个会计，从劳伦斯—汉弗雷会计师事务所来的。他来这儿三天了。”

“他看起来很年轻。”

“他是一个见习会计师。他看起来很懂行。但他对我们一直以来的记账系统感到惊奇。他跟我说，他从来没有想到一个剧院能经营得如此有条理。他说伦敦城里有些公司的记账方式能让人愁到头发都白了。”

看着丈夫帅气的脸上流露出扬扬自得的神情，朱莉娅笑了。

“他是个会说话的年轻人。”

“他今天就结束工作了。我想我们可以让他同我们一起回去，请他吃个简单的午餐。他很绅士。”

“那就足以邀请他吃午餐了吗？”

迈克尔没有注意到她语气里那一丝嘲讽的意味。

“如果你不愿意的话，我就不问他了。我只是觉得这会令他欣喜万分。他极其崇拜你。这回的戏他都已经看过三遍了。他做梦都想被人介绍和你认识。”

迈克尔按了一个按钮，不一会儿，他的秘书进来了。

“给你这些信，玛格丽。我今天下午有什么安排？”

朱莉娅心不在焉地听着玛格丽口中的预约时间表，漫不经心地看着四周，虽然她对这房间非常熟悉。这是一间与一流剧场的经理非常相配的房间。房间的墙壁由优秀的房屋设计师镶了护墙板（按成本价），墙上挂着佐芬尼和德维尔德的版画，内容是一些舞台场景。扶手椅宽大又舒适。迈克尔坐在一把雕刻繁复的齐彭代尔椅里，虽然是一件复制品，但由一家有名的公司制作。他的齐彭代尔桌的爪球腿大而结实，坚固无比。桌子上摆着一个结实的银色相框，里面是她自己的照片，旁边对称的是他们的儿子罗杰的照片。在这中间有一个华丽的银色墨水台，那是某次迈克尔生日时她送给他的礼物，后面摆放的是一个红色摩洛哥风格的架子，镀了大量的金，架子上放着他的私人信纸，供他想亲笔写信的时候用。信纸上印着西登斯剧场的地址，信封印着他的饰章，一个野猪头，以及下面这句话：犯我者必受惩罚(1)。一束黄色郁金香插在银色碗里——那是他连续三次赢得戏剧高尔夫巡回赛后获得的——显示出玛格丽的小心呵护。朱莉娅看了她一眼。尽管她剪短的头发漂白过，口红又涂得过于厚重，却有一副被认为是完美秘书应该有的中性外表。她跟随迈克尔已经五年了。这么久的时间里，她对迈克尔从里到外肯定相当了解。朱莉娅在想她是否会蠢到爱上迈克尔。

迈克尔突然从他坐的椅子上站了起来。

“好了，亲爱的，我们现在可以走了。”

玛格丽递给迈克尔他的黑色卷边软呢帽，并为朱莉娅和迈克尔打开房门，让他们先出去。当他们走进办公室时，朱莉娅注意过的那个年轻人转身站了起来。

“我想把你介绍给兰伯特小姐。”迈克尔说道。接着，他显示出一副大使向他觐见的宫廷君主介绍随员的气派，说道：“这就是那位非常优秀的绅士，多亏了他，我们乱作一团的账目终于有了些头绪。”

年轻人脸变得通红。他僵硬地笑着回应朱莉娅温暖、现成的微笑，她友善地握了一下他的手，发现他的掌心已都是汗水。他这副困窘的样子令人同情。那是当人们见到萨拉·西登斯时才会有的感受。她想起，当迈克尔提议请这男孩吃顿午餐的时候她对迈克尔有点刻薄。她直视着他的双眼。她自己的眼睛很大，深棕色，炯炯有神。做出这副神情对她来说一点都不费劲，做出稍稍觉得有趣、友好亲切的表情就好像挥去在她身边飞来飞去的苍蝇一样已是她的本能。

“我在想，我们是否能邀请您来我家，和我们一同吃顿便餐。午饭后迈克尔会开车送您回来。”

年轻人再次脸红，他的喉结在他细细的脖子里滚动。

“您对我太好了。”他焦虑地看了一眼他的衣服，“我浑身脏透了。”

“我们到家后您可以梳洗整理一下。”

汽车在剧院后门等待着他们，这是一辆黑色镀铬的长款车，车座由银色皮革包着，车门上不起眼地印着迈克尔的饰章。朱莉娅坐了进去。

“过来跟我一起坐。迈克尔要开车。”

他们住在史坦霍普广场，当他们到达后，朱莉娅让管家带着年轻人去盥洗的地方。她上楼回到会客室。当迈克尔过来找她的时候，朱莉娅正在描唇。

“我已经告诉他，让他一准备好就上楼来。”

“顺便问一句，他叫什么名字？”

“我不知道。”

“亲爱的，我们必须得知道他的名字。我会让他在我们的本子上题词。”

“可恶，他还没重要到那个地步。”迈克尔通常只会请非常重要的有名望的人在本子上题词，“我们再也不会见到他了。”

就在这时，年轻人出现了。在汽车里，朱莉娅努力让他放松下来，但他依旧非常腼腆。鸡尾酒已经备好，迈克尔为大家斟好酒。朱莉娅抽出一根香烟，年轻人划了根火柴为她点着火，但他手抖得非常厉害，以至于朱莉娅认为他根本无法将火凑上她的香烟，所以她握着他的手点着了烟。

“可怜的年轻人，”她心里想，“我想这可能是他人生中最辉煌的时刻。当他将这一经历告诉他的朋友时，他肯定会特别开心。我估计他会成为办公室里那个遭人嫉妒诅咒的小英雄。”

朱莉娅同自己说话和同别人说话的样子非常不同：当她跟自己说话时，她的语言生动有趣。她将第一口烟吸入肺叶，兴致不错。当你仔细想想，能同她共进午餐，并聊上四十五分钟，真是件美事，说不定还能让一个人在他狭小的圈子里变得十分重要。

年轻人强迫自己说了句话。

“这屋子太壮观了！”

朱莉娅给了他一个短暂、开心的微笑，她精致的眉毛稍稍向上一挑，这表情他一定非常熟悉，常常在朱莉娅表演的时候看到。

“我很开心你喜欢它。”她的声音低沉甚至有点沙哑。你或许真的会认为他的评论让她如释重负，“在我们家里，我们都认为迈克尔的品位非常高。”

迈克尔满意地瞥了一眼屋子。

“我有不少经验。我总是为我们的戏剧设计布景。当然，有人会为我做这些粗活，但想法都是我的。”

他们两年前搬进了这屋子，迈克尔和朱莉娅心知肚明，当他们外出巡演的时候，他们把这屋子交给了一个收费昂贵的设计师，并且这设计师许诺，在他们巡演回来的时候，把屋子完全装修好，而且只收取成本费用，以此来换取他们承诺给他的那些剧院里的活儿。但没有必要把这些冗杂的细节告诉一个他们连名字都不知道的年轻人。这房子装修品位极佳，既古典，又不失现代感，迈克尔说一眼就能看出这是一座绅士居住的房子，一点都没错。然而，朱莉娅坚持自己的卧室要按照自己喜欢的样子来，在他们摄政公园的老房子里她有一间喜欢的卧室，战争结束后他们就住在那里，她把那间卧室照搬了过来。床和梳妆台用粉色丝绸包了起来，躺椅和扶手椅是淡青色；床的上方是几个镀金的胖天使，一起悬吊着一盏淡粉色灯罩的灯，在梳妆台的镜子周围也簇拥着镀金的小胖天使。在椴木桌上摆着的是男演员们、女演员们以及皇室成员的签名照，相框华丽繁复。设计师对这屋子挑起了眉毛，不屑一顾，但只有在这间屋子里，朱莉娅才觉得完全放松。她坐在一个镀金的哈姆雷特风格的凳子上，俯在一张椴木桌子上写信。

午饭准备好了，他们走下楼。

“我希望你能吃得饱，”朱莉娅说，“迈克尔和我的胃口都非常小。”

事实上，午饭有烤鳎目鱼、烤牛排、菠菜和炖水果。这是一顿为了满足饥肠辘辘的人而不会产生脂肪设计的饭菜。厨子在玛格丽跟他说了中午会有客人来吃午餐后，匆匆煎了些土豆。土豆看起来清脆可口，闻着很有食欲。只有这个年轻人碰了它们。朱莉娅留恋地看了一眼土豆，然后摇了摇头以示拒绝。迈克尔神情严肃地盯着它们看了一会儿，就好像不认识这道菜似的，然后慢慢地，打破了沉思，说了声“谢谢，不需要了”。他们坐在一张长长的餐桌旁，朱莉娅和迈克尔分别坐在桌子两端硕大的意大利椅子里，年轻人坐在桌子的中间，他的椅子可没有那么舒服，但非常有形。朱莉娅注意到他似乎在看餐柜，她带着迷人的微笑，向前倾了倾身子。

“怎么了？”

年轻人脸变得通红。

“我在想，我能不能吃片面包？”

“当然！”

她意味深长地看了管家一眼；此刻，管家正在为迈克尔倒一杯干白葡萄酒，然后他离开了房间。

“迈克尔和我从来不吃面包。杰文斯犯傻，没有意识到你可能会想吃一些。”

“当然，面包只是一种习惯，”迈克尔说道，“如果你决计不吃它，不久你就会发现你不需要它了。”

“这可怜的小伙瘦得像杆一样，迈克尔。”

“我不吃面包，因为我怕变胖。我不吃它还因为我觉得没意义。毕竟，就我的运动强度而言，我可以吃任何我想吃的东西。”

迈克尔五十二岁了，身材仍然很棒。他年轻的时候，有一头栗色的鬈发，他皮肤白皙，蓝眼睛大而深邃，鼻梁笔直，再加上那对小小的耳朵，他曾是英国舞台上最好看的男演员。唯一美中不足的地方就是他的嘴唇有点单薄。迈克尔只有六英尺高，举止勇猛。正是他那显而易见的美貌让他走向了舞台而不是像他父亲那样成为军人。现在，他那栗色的头发都已灰白，而且剪得很短；他的脸变得松弛，还有不少皱纹；脸蛋也不再像桃花般娇嫩，肤色变得潮红。但以他那美丽的眼睛和尚好的身材来讲，他仍旧是个美男子。自从他在军队里待了五年之后，他便有了军人风度，以至于如果你不知道他是谁（虽然这极其不可能，因为他的照片总是以各种形式出现在画报上），你可能会认为他是一个高级军官。他吹嘘自二十岁起他的体重就再没变过，并且这么多年来，不论刮风下雨，他每天早晨都会在八点的时候换上短裤和运动上衣，绕着摄政公园跑一圈。

“那个秘书告诉我，今早您在排练，兰伯特小姐，”年轻人说道，“是说您要有新剧上演了吗？”

“并不是，”迈克尔回答道，“我们的剧目已经太多了。”

“迈克尔觉得我们演得有点粗糙，所以他安排了一场排练。”

“我非常高兴我安排了这场排练。我发现他们有一些我没有授意的表演小细节悄悄地混了进来，并且台词也被随意修改。我坚持剧作家的原话应该一字不动地被照念，虽然，上帝知道，如今的剧作家写不了多少话。”

“如果你想来看我们的剧，”朱莉娅优雅地说道，“我肯定迈克尔会很乐意给你几张票。”

“我很想再去观看，”年轻人急忙回答，“我已经看过三遍了。”

“都三遍了？”朱莉娅满是惊讶地叫道，尽管她清楚地记得迈克尔已经将此事告诉她了，“当然，这剧还不算差，还算令人满意，但我无法想象有谁会看三遍。”

“我去看并不是为了那剧本身，而是去看您的表演。”

“我总算逼你说出这句话了。”朱莉娅想着，然后她大声说道：“当我们读到剧本的时候，迈克尔对这出剧表示很怀疑。他觉得我的角色不够好。你知道，并不是什么明星角色。但我觉得我能把这角色演出点什么来。当然，我们不得不在彩排的时候砍掉很多另外一个女人的戏。”

“我并不是说我们重写了剧本，”迈克尔说道，“但我跟你讲，现在这出剧跟作者交给我们的有很大不同。”

“您在剧中简直太棒了。”年轻人说道。

（“他有某种魅力。”）“你喜欢我，这让我很开心。”她回答道。

“如果你这么仰慕朱莉娅，我敢说，你走的时候她会给你一张她的照片。”

“会吗？”

他的脸又红了，蓝色的眼睛闪闪发光。（“他真的很可爱。”）他算不上好看，但有一张真诚、坦率的脸，而且他的羞怯很迷人。他有一头淡棕色的鬈发，但被他用发油抹得平平的。朱莉娅想，如果他能利用自己的鬈发梳个漂亮的发型，而不是试图把波浪都弄直，他肯定会好看许多。他气色不错，皮肤也很好，长了一口精致的牙齿。她发现，他的衣服很合身，穿得很得体，这让她对他赞赏有加。他看上去干净漂亮。

“我估计你从未跟剧院内部打过交道吧？”朱莉娅说道。

“从来没有，因此我特别渴望拿到这份工作。您无法想象当我得知我可以来做这份工作的时候，我有多激动。”

迈克尔和朱莉娅朝着他亲切地微笑。他的仰慕让他们觉得自己高高在上，扬扬得意。

“我从来不允许外人来观看排练，但作为我们的会计，你也算得上剧院的人了，而且我不介意为你开此先例，如果你愿意来的话。”

“您对我真的太好了。我这辈子还从未见过一场排练。您会出演下一部戏吗？”

“哦，我想不会吧。我对表演不再那么热衷了。我发现几乎不可能找到一个适合我的角色。你看，在我这个年纪我无法出演年轻的恋人，而且剧作家也不再像我年轻那会儿那样描述这些角色了。就是法国人所谓的说教者。你知道我所指的那类人吧，公爵，或是内阁大臣，或是地位显赫的皇室顾问，他们说些聪明话，动动小手指就能让人围着他转。我不知道现在的剧作家都怎么了。他们似乎写不出好的台词。无米之炊，这就是我们演员如今所面临的困境。他们感激我吗？我是说那些剧作家。如果我告诉你他们中一些人竟然有胆量提出那样的条件，你一定会大吃一惊。”

“事实上，没有他们我们也不行，”朱莉娅笑道，“如果剧本不行，世界上没有什么表演能够拯救一出戏。”

“那是因为公众对剧院没什么真正的兴趣。在英国剧院的黄金年代，人们并不是去看戏剧，他们去看的是演员。他们不会管肯布尔(2)或者西登斯夫人演的是什么。大家都是奔着他们的人去的。即使到现在，虽然我不否认如果剧本不好那演员也就完蛋了，但我认为，如果剧本不错，人们是去看演员的，而不是戏剧本身。”

“我认为没人能否认这点。”朱莉娅说道。

“像朱莉娅这样的女演员所需要的就是一个媒介。把这媒介给她，剩下的她都会完成。”

朱莉娅给了年轻人一个愉悦的却有点不以为然的微笑。

“你千万不能太把我丈夫的话当真。恐怕我们必须承认在关系到我的事情上他无法做到公平公正。”

“除非这位年轻人是个大傻瓜，否则他一定也会觉得在表演方面你无所不能。”

“哦，那只是人们的错觉，因为我只会去做我自己能够胜任的事情。”

迈克尔当即看了看他的手表。

“年轻人，你喝完咖啡后，我们得出发了。”

这男孩大口咽下他杯子里剩余的咖啡，此刻朱莉娅从桌子旁站了起来。

“你不会忘记答应给我照片吧？”

“我想迈克尔的小房间里应该有一些。我们一起去挑一张。”

她带着他去了餐厅后面的一间很大的房间。虽然这应该是迈克尔的私人起居室——“每个男人都想要一间他能随心所欲、抽烟的房间”——它却主要被用作客人们的衣帽间。那里有一张高贵的红木桌子，上面摆着乔治五世和玛丽王后的签名照片。壁炉架上摆着一张老旧的由劳伦斯为饰演哈姆雷特的肯布尔画的肖像复制品。在一张小桌子上堆着一摞剧本打字稿。这房间四面都是书架，下面是橱柜，从其中一间里，朱莉娅拿出一摞她最新的照片，递了一张给年轻人。

“这张还不错。”

“很漂亮。”

“是吗？那我想可能不太像我。”

“但就是你。跟你一模一样。”

她向他展示了另外一种微笑，有点小淘气的样子；她垂下了眼睑，然后又抬了起来，带着她那种被人们形容为天鹅绒般的眼神，她用这种眼神温柔地盯着他看了一会儿。她这么做没有任何目的。如果不是条件反射，就是出于要讨好别人的本能。这男孩如此年轻，又如此腼腆，他看上去心地善良，但她再也不会见到他了。她希望他的那些钱花得很值；她希望他将这一刻作为人生的重要时刻来回忆。她又瞥了一眼照片。她希望自己就是照片里的样子。摄影师在她的帮助下让她摆出了最佳姿势，以展现她最美的那面。她的鼻子有点宽但摄影师通过灯光让它看上去小巧精致，平滑的皮肤上没有一丝皱纹，她漂亮的眼睛含情脉脉。

“好吧，你就拿这张吧。你知道我并不美丽，甚至算不上漂亮。科克兰(3)以前总是说我有魔鬼之美(4)。你懂法语的，对吧？”

“还能够理解这句。”

“我来给你签名。”

她坐在桌子旁，用她粗放流畅的字体写道：你真诚的朱莉娅·兰伯特。

————————————————————

(1) 原文为拉丁文，Nemo me impune lacessit。

(2) 约翰·菲利普·肯布尔（John Philip Kemble，1757—1823），著名的莎剧演员、剧院经理，对舞台艺术和剧场管理做出过许多改革。西登斯夫人是他的姐姐。

(3) 科克兰（Benoît-Constant Coquelin，1841—1909），法国著名戏剧演员兼戏剧评论家。

(4) 原文为法语，beauté du diable。

第二章

等两个男人走后，她又翻阅了一遍这些照片，之后把它们放回原处。

“对于一个四十六岁的女人来说还不错，”她笑道，“我跟照片里一样，没必要否认。”她想在房间里找面镜子照照，但却没有。“可恶的设计师。可怜的迈克尔，难怪他从来不用这间屋子。当然，我始终拍不好照片。”

她有种想看一看她的旧照片的冲动。迈克尔是个整洁、有条理的人，她的照片都保存在一个大纸箱里，标注了日期，并按照时间顺序存放。他本人的照片在那个纸箱的其他盒子里。

“当有人愿意写我们的职业生涯的故事时，他会发现所有他需要的资料都已经准备好了。”迈克尔这样说道。

本着同样值得赞许的目的，他把有关他们俩的媒体报道全都剪下来，按照时间顺序，贴在了一本本簿子里。

那里有朱莉娅儿童时期的照片，少女时期的照片，她饰演第一个角色的照片，她初为人妻的照片，和迈克尔在一起，之后有了罗杰，她的儿子，那时他还是个婴儿。有一张他们一家三口的照片，迈克尔很男人，极其英俊，她自己温婉恬淡地低头看着罗杰，眼神中充满母爱，而罗杰是个一头鬈发的小男孩，这张照片拍得简直太成功了。所有画报都整版刊登了它，他们还曾在节目单中用过，后来缩印成明信片大小，在外省售卖了好多年。让人懊恼的是当罗杰去了伊顿公学后就拒绝跟她一起拍照了。他不想上报纸这件事还真让人觉得好笑。

“人们会以为你变丑了或是发生了其他的事情，”她告诉罗杰，“而且这并不是什么不好的事情。你应该去首演夜看一看，看那些社会人士是如何聚集在摄影师旁边的，内阁大臣，法官，所有人。他们可能假装不喜欢被拍照，但你看看当他们觉得摄影师盯上他们时摆出的姿势就知道了。”

但罗杰很固执。

朱莉娅看到一张她饰演比阿特丽斯的照片。这是她唯一扮演过的莎剧角色。她知道她穿那身戏服并不好看；她无法理解原因，因为没人能像她那样把现代服装穿得光彩照人。她的衣服，不论是舞台的还是私人的，都在巴黎定制，按裁缝的说法，没人比她的订单更多了。她身材姣好，这一点有口皆碑；作为一个女人来说她很高，双腿修长。可惜的是，她从未有机会扮演罗莎琳德(1)，她穿男孩的戏服应该会很好看，当然现在为时已晚，但或许没有冒险尝试也不错。虽然你可能认为，以她的聪明才智、淘气可爱，以及她的幽默感，她一定会呈现完美的表演。评论家从来没有真正喜欢过她演的比阿特丽斯。这都是那可恶的无韵诗搞的鬼。她的声音低沉浑厚，带着令人印象深刻的嘶哑，遇到倾诉情感的台词，会让你的心都揪起来；如果是搞笑的台词，则会添加不少幽默效果。但当她读比阿特丽斯的台词时，感觉完全不对。还有，关于她的吐字，她吐字非常清晰，即使不提高嗓门，也能让楼座最后一排的观众听得清清楚楚；人们说，这声音让诗歌听起来像散文。而在她看来，其实是因为她过于现代。

迈克尔是演莎剧出道的。那会儿她还不认识他。他在剑桥出演过罗密欧，当他离开剑桥在一所戏剧学院待了一年后，本森雇用了他。他在全国巡演，扮演了各种角色。但他认识到莎剧对他职业发展没什么帮助，如果想要成为一名主演他必须获得出演现代戏剧的经验。有个叫詹姆斯·兰顿的人在米德尔普尔经营一个轮演剧目剧团，吸引了不少人关注。迈克尔在本森那儿待了三年，当公司去米德尔普尔巡演的时候，他写信给兰顿，问能不能与他见一面。詹姆斯·兰顿，一个肥胖秃头、满脸红光的四十五岁男人，模样宛如鲁本斯画中殷实的市民，却对戏剧情有独钟。他是一个古怪、自大、活力四射、自负又迷人的家伙。他爱表演，但他的体形让他无法出演太多角色，但所幸他演得也不怎么样。他无法抑制他那炫耀的本性，虽然他出演每个角色都会仔细琢磨，百般研究，但他的表演最后总是怪诞可笑。他夸大每个动作，夸张每个声调。但当他指导他的演员班底进行排练时，又成了另外一副样子——他无法忍受任何浮于表面的表演。他的耳朵非常灵敏，虽然他自己无法说出正确的声调，但他绝不会放过别人声调里的一丝错误。

“不要真的自然，”他告诉他的团员，“舞台不是为了这种东西存在的。舞台是虚假的艺术。但看上去要自然。”

他为他的剧团紧张而努力地工作。团员们每天早晨从十点开始排练，直到下午两点他才会让他们解散，并敦促他们回家研习各自的角色，在晚上正式表演前稍事休息。他威吓他们，朝他们大喊大叫，嘲弄他们。他给他们微薄的工资。但如果他们演好了一出感人的戏，他会像孩子一样大哭；而如果他们按照他想要的样子说了一句有趣的台词，他会哈哈大笑。如果高兴了，他可以单腿在舞台上跳来跳去；如果生气了，他会把剧本扔在地上，踩上几脚，并让愤怒的眼泪在他的脸颊上流淌。整个剧团的员工都嘲笑他，冷落他，又都尽其所能地取悦他。他激起他们一种保护的本能，他们所有人都觉得不能让他失望。虽然他们说他像对待奴隶一样对待他们，他们从来没有自己的时间，连身体都无法忍受这样的工作强度，但顺从他那令人发指的要求带给他们一种变态的满足感。当他紧紧握着一个周薪七英镑的老团员的手说道：“我向上帝发誓，老家伙，你太棒了！”那老团员感觉自己好像是查尔斯·基恩(2)一般。

迈克尔按时赴约，而此刻吉米·兰顿正好需要一个年轻的主角。他已经猜到迈克尔想要见他的原因，因此前一天晚上去看了他出演的戏剧。迈克尔扮演的是茂丘西奥(3)，兰顿并不看好他的表演，但当迈克尔来到他的办公室时，他被迈克尔的美貌打动了。迈克尔穿着棕色外套和灰色法兰绒长裤，甚至没有化妆，他那帅气的外表能让人惊羡得无法呼吸。他举止文雅，说话如谦谦君子。当迈克尔说明他的来意，兰顿一丝不苟地观察着他。如果他会演戏的话，再加上这副外表，这个年轻人一定前程远大。

“我昨晚去看了你演的丘西奥，”他说道，“你自己是怎么看这角色的？”

“糟糕透了。”

“我也这么认为。你多大了？”

“二十五。”

“我估计肯定有人告诉过你，你长得很好看。”

“这是为什么我选择了舞台的原因。否则我会像我父亲那样去参军。”

“天啊！如果我要是有你的外表，我该会是个多么好的演员。”

这次会晤以迈克尔拿到一份合约结束。他在米德尔普尔待了两年。不久，他与剧团成员混熟。他幽默和善，尽力地帮助每一个人，不计麻烦。他的美貌在米德尔普尔引起了一阵轰动，女孩子常常在戏院门口等着见他。她们给他写情书，递鲜花。他将这一切视作观众对演员正常的敬慕，但绝不允许自己被冲昏头脑。他渴望上进，决计不让任何情感纠葛阻碍他职业的发展。最后，仍旧是他的美貌救了他，因为吉米·兰顿很快认识到，虽然他有坚持的毅力和成功的意愿，但他当演员永远不称职。他的声音有点单薄，慷慨激昂时，会更加尖细。这声音所展示的效果是歇斯底里而不是激情四射。但他作为年轻主演最致命的缺点是他无法表演求爱。在念普通的对话时，他还算轻松自如，能够表现出台词的意义，但要表达强烈感情时，似乎有什么东西抑制了他。他感到窘迫，手足无措。

“可恶，不要像抱着一袋土豆一样抱着那女孩。”吉米·兰顿冲他怒吼道，“你亲吻她时就好像你怕你们正站在风口处。你跟那女孩是相爱的。你必须自己感受到你跟她处于恋爱中。就好像你的骨头在你身体里要融化了，即使下一分钟地震将你吞噬，你也会不管不顾，让地震去见鬼。”

但这些都没用。除了他的美貌、他的优雅和他的随和，迈克尔依旧是一个冷漠的爱人。但这并不妨碍朱莉娅疯狂地爱上了他。他们就是在迈克尔加入兰顿的轮演剧目剧团时认识的。

朱莉娅的事业可谓顺风顺水。她出生在泽西岛，她父亲也在岛上出生，是一名兽医。她母亲的妹妹嫁给了一个法国煤炭商人，住在圣马洛(4)，朱莉娅被送到那里与姨妈一起生活，在当地中学读书。她的法语说得与法国女人一般无二。她是天生的演员，而且，自她能记事起，大家就认为她将来一定会登台演出。她的姨妈，法卢夫人，与一位老年女演员“有点关系”，这位女演员曾是法兰西喜剧院的一个成员，现在退休住在圣马洛，靠着她的一个情人在多年的忠诚同居之后与她分手时给她的微薄的赡养费活着。朱莉娅十二岁的时候，这名女演员已是一个性子泼辣、身材臃肿的六十多岁的老女人，但她活力依旧，热爱食物胜过世界上的一切。她笑声爽朗，像男人一样，说起话来声音低沉响亮。是她为朱莉娅上了表演的启蒙课。她把她在艺术学校所学的所有艺术知识都教授给了朱莉娅，她与她讲赖兴贝格到七十岁还在出演天真少女，讲萨拉·伯恩哈特和她的金嗓子，讲穆内·萨利(5)和他的威严，还有科克兰，他是这群演员中最出色的。她用在剧院学会的方法，把高乃依和拉辛慷慨激昂的长篇演说背诵给朱莉娅，并教她以同样的方式念出来。听到朱莉娅用孩子气的嗓音背诵《费德尔》里那些充满激情的演讲简直太有趣了，她会强调亚历山大诗体的节拍，满口的词被她念得装腔作势却又充满戏剧化。这个珍妮·塔特布一定是个做作的女演员，但她教会朱莉娅吐字清晰、如何走路以及如何控制自己，她告诉朱莉娅不要害怕自己的声音，强调时间感的重要性，这也是朱莉娅与生俱来的本能，在她后来的舞台生涯中成了她最厉害的天赋之一。

“不要停顿，除非你有特殊的理由，”她严肃地说道，握紧的拳头重重地砸在她前面的桌子上，“但当你停顿的时候，你就尽可能长时间地停顿。”

朱莉娅十六岁时去了坐落在高尔街上的皇家戏剧艺术学院，彼时她已经知道了那里能教给她的一切。她需要抛弃一些已经过时的技巧，采用更加谈话式的语调来演戏。她赢得了每一个她所能参与的奖项的评选，当她完成学业后，一口流利的法语立刻让她在伦敦获得了一个法国女仆的小角色。一时看来，似乎她的法语技能会让她专门出演那些需要外国口音的角色，在法国女仆这一角色后，她又扮演了一个奥地利服务员。大概在两年后吉米·兰顿发现了她。那时她正在全国巡演一出在伦敦受到好评的情景剧；在这个阴谋诡计最终败露的意大利女骗子的角色里，她正试图呈现一个四十岁女人的样子，有些力不从心。因为剧中的女主角是个金发白肤的成熟女人，却在扮演一个妙龄少女，表演缺乏真实。吉米那时正在休假，而他的度假方式是夜夜去戏院观戏，一个城市的剧院看完接着去下一个城市。在朱莉娅的戏结束后，吉米到后台去见她。以他在戏剧圈的知名度足以让朱莉娅感到受宠若惊，当他邀请她第二天中午共进午餐时，她答应了。

待他们一坐下来，吉米便直奔主题。

“我一宿没合眼，一直在想你。”他说道。

“这太突然了。您的提议是光明正大的还是无耻下流的？”

他并没有在意朱莉娅无礼的答复。

“我在这个圈子里混了二十五年了。我曾做过催场员、置景工、舞台监督、演员、宣传，该死，我甚至做过剧评人。我自从离开寄宿学校就住在剧院，如果还有我不知道的有关表演的事情，那就是不值得我知道。我觉得，你是个天才。”

“您过奖了。”

“别说话。让我来说。你样样具备：合适的身高，漂亮的外形，像天然橡胶一样的脸。”

“您在恭维我，是吧？”

“正是这样。这是一张女演员都想要的脸。一张能展现一切的脸，甚至是美丽，一张能展现任何脑袋中想法的脸。杜丝就有这样一张脸。昨晚尽管你并没有思考你正在做的事情，但你说的那些话时刻都写在你的脸上。”

“这是个糟糕的角色，让我实在无法专注。您听到我说的那些台词了吗？”

“是演员糟糕，并不是角色。你音色很棒，能够抓住观众的心，我不知道你演喜剧的功底，但我打算冒次险。”

“您说这个是什么意思？”

“你演戏的时机很对。这点是无法被指导的，你一定是天生就懂。这可比后天学来的不知好多少。现在让我们讲讲基本事实。我一直在四处打听你。你好像法语说得跟法国女人一样，所以他们总是给你糟糕的英语角色。出演这种角色你不会有前途，你知道的。”

“我只能拿到这种角色。”

“你自己满足于永远扮演这类角色吗？你会陷入这些角色里，大众也不会接受你演其他角色。你只能演次要角色。一周最多挣二十镑，而且你非凡的才华都浪费掉了。”

“我总是期盼有一天我能有机会出演一个正式的角色。”

“什么时候？你可能需要等待十年。你现在多大？”

“二十岁。”

“酬劳多少？”

“一周十五英镑。”

“撒谎。你一周拿十二英镑，而且你并不值这些。你还有很多东西要学习。你的动作太普通。你不知道，每一个手势动作都必须有意义。你不知道如何在你开始说话前让观众都看你。你妆化得太浓。以你这样的脸，妆越少越好。难道你不想成为一位明星吗？”

“谁不想呢？”

“来我这儿吧，我会把你塑造成英国最伟大的女演员。你学东西学得快吗？你这个年龄应该学得很快。”

“我觉得我可以在四十八小时内记住任何角色的台词。”

“你需要的是经验，以及我作为你的经纪人。来我这儿吧，我会让你一年出演二十个角色，易卜生、萧伯纳、巴克、苏徳曼、汉金、高尔斯华绥。你自带磁力，但你却不知道如何运用它。”他咯咯地笑了起来，“上帝，如果你知道这一点，那个老女人也不会让你出演现在的剧了。你得掐住观众的脖子，跟他们说，‘你们这些狗崽子，你们都给我注意了。’你必须镇住他们。如果你没有这点天赋，没人能帮得了你，但如果你有，你可以通过学习明白如何使用它。我告诉你，你有成为一名伟大女演员的一切素养。我这辈子还没有如此肯定过。”

“我知道我需要舞台经验。当然我得仔细考虑一下。我不介意去您那里待一个演出季。”

“见鬼去吧。你认为我能在一个演出季就把你塑造成一名伟大的女演员吗？你认为我会全力以赴就为了让你能在伦敦出演一些微不足道的小角色？你把我当成了什么傻瓜？我会跟你签三年的合同，给你一周八英镑的薪水，而你将像牛马一样地工作。”

“八英镑一周太可笑了。我无法接受。”

“你能。你现在就值这么多，你也就只能拿这么多。”

朱莉娅已经演了三年的戏，学到了不少东西。另外，珍妮·塔特布，一个非严格的道德家，还向她传授了许多其他有用的信息。

“您是不是觉得我会让您跟我睡觉？”

“天哪，你认为我有时间跟我剧团的成员睡觉？比起这个，我有更加重要的事情去做，我的小姐。而且，你会发现，在四个小时的排练和晚上的演出后，如果能将这些事情都能做到令我满意，再加上日常演出，你自己不会有太多时间，或者还有跟别人做爱的精力。当你回到床上，你只会想睡觉。”

但是，关于这一点，吉米·兰顿预测错了。

————————————————————

(1) 罗莎琳德（Rosalind），莎剧《皆大欢喜》的女主角。

(2) 查尔斯·基恩（Charles Kean，1811—1868），著名男演员，萨拉·西登斯的弟弟。

(3) 莎士比亚的《罗密欧与朱丽叶》中的人物，是罗密欧的朋友。

(4) 圣马洛，法国西北部海港城市，为疗养胜地。

(5) 穆内·萨利（Mounet-Sully，1841—1916），法国男演员。

第三章

朱莉娅，被他的热情和慷慨激昂打动，接受了他的提议。起初，他让她出演一些小角色，在他的指导下，她像从未演过戏那样在舞台上表演。他让评论家对她感兴趣，然后对他们恭维奉承，让他们觉得自己发现了一位优秀的女演员，并且允许他们出面建议他让朱莉娅出演马格达。她红极一时，很快他就让她出演了《玩偶之家》中的娜拉，《人与超人》中的安，以及海达·加不勒。米德尔普尔的人们高兴地发现他们之中有一位女演员能让他们吹捧得比任何伦敦的明星都棒，并且出于家乡的荣誉感，都蜂拥去观看她出演的角色和戏剧。伦敦的短评记者也会不时地提到她，不少热情的戏剧赞助人也专程到米德尔普尔去观看她的表演。回来的人们对她赞不绝口，两三位伦敦戏院的经理派遣代表对她进行报道。他们对她持怀疑态度。她在萧伯纳和易卜生的戏剧里表现得非常好，但如果她出演的是一部普通戏剧呢？经理们曾有过不好的经历。他们基于某位男演员在类似的一部别具一格的戏剧中的精彩表演与他签了约，后来却发现在其他类型的剧目中他比其他演员好不到哪里去。

迈克尔加入剧团时，朱莉娅已经在米德尔普尔表演一年了。吉米开始让他出演萧伯纳《康蒂妲》中的马奇班克斯。吉米的这个选择让大家都很满意，因为对于这个角色而言，迈克尔的帅气是个加分项，而他表演缺乏热情也不会变成劣势。

朱莉娅伸手取出第一个纸盒，这里放着迈克尔的照片。她舒服地坐在地上，快速地翻过他早期的照片，寻找他初次来到米德尔普尔时拍的那张；但当她翻到这照片时，她的心被狠狠地刺痛了。她甚至觉得想要大哭起来。照片里的迈克尔就是他那时的模样。当时康蒂妲由一位年长的女人出演，她是一位优秀的女演员，经常出演母亲、老处女或反面角色，而朱莉娅除了一周出演八次外，没什么其他可做的，便观看他们排练。她对迈克尔一见钟情。她从来没有见过比他更帅的年轻小伙子，并且她不遗余力地追求他。没过多久，吉米不顾传统的米德尔普尔人的谴责，把《群鬼》搬上舞台，迈克尔饰演那个男孩，朱莉娅饰演丽贾纳。他们互相听对方背诵台词，排练过后小心翼翼地一起吃午饭，以免剧组其他人说他俩的闲话。很快他们便形影不离了。朱莉娅对迈克尔几乎没有保留，她疯狂地赞美迈克尔。他对自己的美貌并不自负，他知道自己长得很帅，接受相关的恭维，态度并非完全冷漠，而是好像这些赞美之词是对一座已经在他家族中存在很久的不错的老房子发出的。众所周知这座老房子是当时最好的房子之一，值得人们为之骄傲并好好保护，但它就在那儿，拥有它就如同一个人呼吸空气那样自然。他脑子很清醒，也很有抱负。他知道他的美貌是他目前主要的资产，但他知道容颜之美不会持久，因此决意成为一个好演员，这样他就有除了外表以外的东西可以依赖。他打算从吉米身上学习一切他能学到的，然后去伦敦。

“如果我办事精明，我可以让某个上了年纪的女人资助我当剧院经理。每个人都得成为自己的主人。这是赚钱发财的唯一途径。”

朱莉娅很快就发现迈克尔不太喜欢花钱，当他们一起吃午饭或者周日一起出游时，她都会付自己那部分费用。她不介意这个。她喜欢他算着钱用的习惯，而她自己有点大手大脚，总是迟一两周才能付清房租。她羡慕他，因为他讨厌欠债，虽然他挣得不多，但依旧每周都能存下一点。他着急着存够钱，这样在他去伦敦后，便不会因为钱的问题而不得不一有角色提供给他便接受下来，而是可以支撑他等到能让他一鸣惊人的角色。他父亲靠抚恤金生活，为了送他到剑桥读书做出了很大牺牲。他父亲不喜欢他走演员这条路，而且曾经很坚持这一点。

“如果你想成为演员，我可能无法阻止你，”他说道，“但不管怎样，我坚持你必须像上等人那样接受教育。”

当朱莉娅发现迈克尔的父亲是一位上校时相当满足。听迈克尔讲他的祖先在摄政时期如何在怀特府把家产输光让朱莉娅印象深刻，她喜欢迈克尔戴的那枚有野猪头的图章戒指，上面印着：犯我者必受惩。

“我觉得，比起长得像希腊的神，你的家庭更让你感到骄傲。”她开心地告诉他。

“任何人都能长得好看，”他回答道，脸上带着甜蜜的笑容，“但不是每个人都能出生于一个体面的家庭。告诉你实话，我很高兴我老爹是个绅士。”

朱莉娅鼓足了勇气。

“我父亲是个兽医。”

听到这话，迈克尔的脸僵硬了一下，但他立刻恢复原样，大笑起来。

“当然，这与一个人的父亲的职业并没有多大关系。我经常听我父亲谈起他部队的兽医。他当然也是一名军官。我父亲总说他是最好的兽医之一。”

迈克尔念过剑桥，这让朱莉娅很开心。他曾经代表他的学院参加过划船比赛，甚至有传言说他会被选入校划船队。

“我想戴上我的蓝色剑桥标志，应该会对我在台上有所帮助。我可以以此大做宣传。”

朱莉娅无法判断迈克尔是否知道她爱着他。他从不向她表达爱意。他喜欢她的社交圈，当他们跟别人在一起时，迈克尔很少会离开她身边。有时他们会被邀请去参加星期天的聚会，或者吃午餐，晚上吃顿丰盛的冷餐，他似乎认为他们一同赴约一起离开很正常。当他送她到家门口时，他会给她一个吻，但他吻她的样子与他吻那个和他共同出演《康蒂妲》的中年妇女没什么两样。他很友好，风趣幽默，亲切，但令人沮丧的是，对他来说，朱莉娅仅仅是他的伙伴。然而，她也知道，他没有爱上任何其他人。他会咯咯笑着向朱莉娅朗读那些女人写给他的情书，当她们给他献上鲜花，他会立刻转送给朱莉娅。

“真是一群笨蛋，”他说道，“她们这么做到底想得到什么呢？”

“我觉得答案没那么难猜。”朱莉娅冷淡地说道。

虽然她知道他一点都不在意这些，但她还是忍不住会感到生气和嫉妒。

“如果我跟某个米德尔普尔的女人混在一起，我就太蠢了。毕竟，她们大部分都是轻佻女子。在我还不知道怎么回事的时候，就会有气势汹汹的父亲寻过来，让我必须娶了这个女孩。”

朱莉娅试图打探当他在本森剧团时有没有风流韵事。她推测，有一两个姑娘有意和他扯上关系，但他认为与一同演戏的女演员鬼混在一起是一个极大的错误，这样的事一定会导致麻烦。

“你知道剧团的人是怎么说闲话的吧。所有人会在二十四小时里知道所有的秘密。你一旦开始了那样的事情，你无法预测自己会扯上什么事情。我可不会冒那种险。”

当他想找点乐子的时候，他会等他们在伦敦附近时，赶到伦敦，在全球饭店挑个姑娘。当然，这会很贵，而且回头想想，这个钱花得一点不值；此外，他在本森剧团时经常打板球，有机会也玩高尔夫，但这种东西对眼睛不太好。

朱莉娅撒了一个弥天大谎。

“吉米总是说，如果我能有点风流韵事，我会成为比现在更好的女演员。”

“你千万别信。他就是个肮脏的老男人。你说的风流韵事是跟他一起吧，我猜。我的意思是，这就好像是说，如果我会写诗，我就能把马奇班克斯演得更好。”

他们在一起聊了很多，最终，朱莉娅终于知道了迈克尔对于婚姻的看法。

“在我看来，一位选择早早结婚的演员简直就是个蠢货。太多例子说明婚姻会毁掉一位演员的前途。尤其是当他娶了位女演员。他成了一位明星，而她则成了他难以摆脱的重担。她会坚持与他一起演出，如果他是经理，他就不得不把女主角的位置给她；如果他和其他女人演戏，那情况就更糟糕了。当然，这对于女演员来讲也不理智。她可能会怀上孩子，因此不得不拒绝一个好角色。她会从公众眼睛中消失数月，你知道观众是什么德行，除非他们能一直见到你，否则他们就会忘记你的存在。”

婚姻？她在乎什么婚姻呢？她的心早已融化在他那双深邃而充满热情的眼睛里，看着他充满光泽的黄褐色头发她会因为欢快的痛苦而颤抖。只要他开口，她会乐意给他一切。然而，这种想法从未在他那可爱的脑子里出现过。

“他当然喜欢我，”她对她自己说道，“他喜欢我超过其他任何人，他甚至爱慕我，但我在那方面对他没有吸引力。”

她千方百计引诱他，就差钻到他的床上了，而她没有这么做的原因是因为没有机会。她开始害怕他们的关系会因为他们彼此太熟悉而无法有进一步发展，她咒骂自己没有在他们接触之初把关系推向高潮。他现在对她的感情太真诚了，不可能变成她的情人。她打探到他的生日，送给他一个金烟盒，她知道这是他最想要的东西。这礼物花了她不少钱，她很难负担得起，他笑着责备她太奢侈了。他无法想象，能够给他花钱这事儿让她欣喜若狂。她生日的时候他送了她半打长筒丝袜。她立刻注意到这些丝袜质量一般。可怜的家伙，他可舍不得买什么高档货。但她一想到他会送她礼物就情不自禁地哭了起来。

“真是个感情充沛的小东西。”他说道，但看到她流眼泪他很开心，也很感动。

她认为他的节俭是个迷人的特点。他忍受不了把自己的钱四处乱花掉。他并非真的吝啬，但他也不慷慨。有一两次她觉得他给服务员小费给得过少，但他对她的抗议不屑一顾。他就只给百分之十，当他拿不出正好的零钱时，他会让服务员找零给他。

“既不向别人借钱，也不借钱给别人。”他引用波洛涅斯的话。

当剧团的某个成员一时手头不宽裕，向他借钱都是徒劳。而他拒绝得那么坦率，那么诚恳，竟没有人会怪他。

“我亲爱的老朋友，我很想借给你一英镑，但我自己也没钱了。我都不知道这周末怎么付房租。”

有那么几个月，迈克尔对自己的角色太专注了，以至于他都没有注意到朱莉娅是多么棒的女演员。当然他会阅读剧评，看到他们对朱莉娅的赞美，他都一掠而过，直到读到这些评论家对他的评论才会多注意。他们的肯定让他感到开心，但他们的批评并没有让他气馁。他太谦虚了，并不会对一条负面批评感到气愤。

“我想我演得太糟糕了吧。”他发自内心地说道。

他身上最让人迷恋的特质是他的好脾气。他对吉米·兰顿的侮辱泰然受之。当吉米在一场长时间的排练中脾气越来越暴躁时，他却总能维持平静。跟他吵架简直是不可能的。一天他坐在台前观看一场没有他戏份的排练。这场戏以强大而感人的场景结尾，朱莉娅终于有机会好好展现自己的优秀演技。当舞台开始为下一场戏进行布景，朱莉娅穿过后台和舞台之间那扇门，在迈克尔身边坐下来。他没有对她说话，而是眼睛直勾勾地盯着前方。她惊讶地看了他一眼。他既没有对她微笑也没有跟她打招呼，这一点儿也不像他。然后，她看到他正咬紧牙关以防牙齿打战，他的眼睛里布满泪水。

“怎么了，亲爱的？”

“别跟我说话。你这个小婊子，你让我哭了。”

“我的天使！”

此刻，泪水充盈着她的双眼，顺着脸颊流了下来。她感到如此欣喜，如此荣幸。

“哦，可恶，”他抽泣道，“我忍不住！”

他从上衣口袋中掏出手帕，擦干了眼泪。

（“我爱他，我爱他，我爱他。”）

然后，他擤了擤鼻子。

“我感到好一些了。但是，上帝，你击垮了我。”

“这场戏还不错，对吧？”

“这场戏不怎么样，全都是你。你揪住了我的心。那些评论家说得很对，可恶，你是个名副其实的演员，错不了。”

“你是刚刚才发现吗？”

“我知道你很好，但我不知道你演得这么好。你让我们其他人相形见绌。你将会是个大明星。没什么能阻挡你。”

“好吧，那么你将是我戏里的男主角。”

“如果我能在一个伦敦戏院经理那儿得到这样的角色，简直就是天上掉馅饼。”

朱莉娅灵光一闪。

“那么，你自己必须做经理，让我做你戏里的女主角。”

他停顿了一下。他脑子转得没那么快，需要一些时间让这些想法沉淀在他脑子里。然后，他笑了。

“你知道，这个主意不错。”

他们在午饭的时候又把这事儿说了一遍。大部分时间是朱莉娅在说，迈克尔兴趣十足地听着。

“当然，能一直出演体面的角色的唯一途径就是开自己的剧院，”他说道，“我知道的。”

钱是个问题。他们讨论了他们至少需要多少钱才能开始实施计划。迈克尔认为最少得五千英镑。但他们如何才能募集到那么多的钱？当然，米德尔普尔的制造商们财源滚滚，但期望他们投五千英镑在几个只在地方上小有名声的年轻演员身上简直是痴心妄想。此外，他们都嫉妒伦敦。

“你得找你的有钱老太太。”朱莉娅开玩笑道。

其实，她对自己说的话半信半疑，但能和迈克尔讨论一个能增进她和迈克尔关系的计划让她兴奋不已。但迈克尔是非常认真的。

“我不觉得一个人能在伦敦取得成功，除非他已经名声在外。要做的事情应该是先在其他剧团表演三到四年；然后就能摸清楚门道了。这么做的优势在于有时间去读剧本。除非已经有了至少三个剧本，否则经营剧团简直就是疯子之举。而这三个剧本中必须有一个会获得成功。”

“当然如果这么做，就必须两人共同演出，这样公众会习惯于看到两个人的名字同时出现在节目单上。”

“我觉得这个关系不大。最好还是要有过硬的角色。当然，毫无疑问，如果能在伦敦积累一点名声，那么找赞助人会容易许多。”

第四章

复活节即将来临，吉米·兰顿会在节前的那一周关闭剧院。朱莉娅不知道自己要做什么；回泽西岛似乎不太值当。一天早上，她出乎意料地收到一封迈克尔的母亲格斯林太太的来信，信中说如果她能和迈克尔一起来切尔滕纳姆共度一周，这将会使上校和她无比欣喜。当她把这封信拿给迈克尔看时，他满脸是笑。

“我让她邀请你的。我觉得比起我直接带你去，那样会更加礼貌些。”

“你太好了。我当然愿意去。”

她欢欣鼓舞。即将与迈克尔共度整整一周让她欣喜若狂。在得知她假期无所事事的时候，他那副好心肠让他不得不帮着解决她的问题。但她看得出他还有其他事情要跟她说，可又不大说得出口。

“怎么了？”

迈克尔尴尬地笑了笑。

“亲爱的，你知道，我父亲非常传统，像他这样的人，有些事情是无法理解的。当然，我也不希望你撒谎，但我觉得如果他知道你父亲是一个兽医的话，他会觉得可笑。在我写信给他问能否带你前去的时候，我介绍你父亲是名医生。”

“噢，好吧。”

朱莉娅发现上校并没有她预想的那样令人不安。他身形消瘦，个头很矮，满脸皱纹，一头白发修理得极短。他高贵的面貌中透露着苍老，让人联想起一枚使用很久的旧硬币上的头像。他很礼貌，但也很内敛。他既不暴躁也不暴戾，一点不像朱莉娅凭借她的舞台经验所了解的上校那样。她无法想象他那客气得甚至有点冰冷的声音是如何施放号令的。事实上，他的军人生涯极其平凡，最后带着荣誉军衔退了役，许多年来，他都满足地过着在花园里劳作、在俱乐部打牌的生活。他读《泰晤士报》，星期日去教堂，陪着夫人去各种茶会。格斯林太太是一个个子高挑、身形敦实、上了年纪的女人。由于个子比她先生高出不少，她总是给你留下在试图缩小自己身高的印象。她风韵犹存，可以看得出年轻时一定很美丽。她头发中分，在颈背处低低地盘了个髻。她传统的外表再加上高大的身材，初次见面会让人觉得威风凛凛，但很快朱莉娅就发现实际上她非常腼腆。她的行动僵硬笨拙，穿着过于考究，带着一种老式的富态，但其实并不适合她。朱莉娅一点不尴尬，反倒觉得这个老女人不以为然的态度令人同情。她从未跟一个知名女演员说过话，对目前她所处的两难处境不知所措。房子很普通，是一幢位于花园里的独立的拉毛粉饰的房子，周围种满了月桂树。由于格斯林一家在印度待过几年，所以家里还有黄铜大盘子和黄铜碗，以及印度刺绣和雕刻繁复的印度桌子。这些都是廉价的集市货，不禁让人奇怪为什么有人会想把它们搬回家。

朱莉娅很机智。不久她就发现，虽然上校很少说话，格斯林太太也很腼腆，但其实他们都在观察她。迈克尔带她回家难道是为了让他父母审查她？这想法在她脑海中一闪而过。为什么呢？只可能有一个原因，而当她想到这个原因时，心脏怦怦直跳。看得出，他非常希望她能给他们留下一个好印象。她本能地觉得她必须掩饰自己女演员的身份，并且毫不费力地，没有任何做作地，仅仅因为她觉得这样会讨好他们，她扮演了那个简单的、谦虚的、天真的、过了一辈子乡村生活的女孩。她和上校绕着花园走了一圈，当上校说起豌豆或芦笋时，她听得趣味盎然；她与格斯林太太插花，擦洗起居室里塞得满满的各种摆设。格斯林太太跟她谈起迈克尔，告诉她他的表演如何机智，他多么受欢迎，还称赞他的外表。朱莉娅看出格斯林太太为自己的儿子感到非常骄傲，于是灵机一动，觉得如果让格斯林太太看到她神魂颠倒地爱着迈克尔，一定会让格斯林太太非常开心，但她要做得不露痕迹，就好像她希望保守这个秘密但却笨拙地出卖了自己。

“当然我们希望他表现得不错，”格斯林太太说，“我们不是很喜欢他走上舞台演戏；你看，我们双方都是军人家庭，但他很固执。”

“是的，我知道您的意思。”

“我知道，现在这个问题已经不像我年轻的时候那么重要了，但他毕竟生来就是个绅士。”

“哦，但很多出身很好的人现在都上台演戏了，您知道吗？现在不像从前了。”

“是，不像从前了。我很高兴他把你带到这里来。对此我本来有点紧张。我觉得你会化很浓的妆，可能还会有点吵闹。没人能想到你是个演员。”

（“我肯定不会这么认为。过去四十八小时我难道不是完美地出演了村姑吗？”）

上校也开始跟她开玩笑，有时还会开玩笑地捏她的耳朵。

“您可不能跟我调情，上校，”她大声说道，同时淘气、愉悦地看了他一眼，“难道您觉得我是个女演员您就能对我随随便便吗？”

“乔治，乔治。”格斯林太太笑道。然后她对朱莉娅说：“他一直都是个糟糕的调情者。”

（“天，我简直太受欢迎了。”）

格斯林太太跟她讲印度的事情，讲家里的下人们都是有色人种有多奇怪，但那边的社交圈却很美好，只有军人和印度上等人，可仍旧不像家里，以及她回到英国有多开心。

朱莉娅和迈克尔准备于复活节后的周一离开，因为他们那天晚上有演出。周日晚餐后，格斯林上校说他要去书房写一些信件；一两分钟后格斯林太太说她得去看看厨子。当他们都走后，迈克尔背对着壁炉火站着，点了支烟。

“我担心这里有点太安静了；希望你没有感到太无聊。”

“跟天堂一般。”

“你给我的家人留下了完美的印象。他们都非常喜欢你。”

“天哪，为此我付出了多少努力啊！”朱莉娅不禁这样想，同时她大声说道：“你是怎么知道的？”

“哦，我能看出来。爸爸告诉我你很有教养，一点都不像个女演员，妈妈说你非常通情达理。”

朱莉娅害羞地低下头，似乎这些恭维让她愧不敢当。迈克尔走过来，站在她前面。她突然觉得他看起来像一个帅气年轻的男仆在申请一份工作。他出奇地紧张。她的心脏在胸腔中怦怦乱跳。

“亲爱的朱莉娅，你愿意嫁给我吗？”

过去一周她一直在问自己他会不会求婚，现在，当他终于这么做了，她却感到迷茫。

“迈克尔！”

“我并不是说立刻。等我们做出点成绩的时候再结婚。我知道你的表演比我出色，但我们一见如故，而且当我们开始经营剧院的时候，我们会成为非常好的搭档。并且你知道，我确实非常喜欢你。我是说，我还没有遇见能与你相比的其他女人。”

（“这个笨蛋，为什么他要说这些没用的？难道他不知道我疯了一样地想嫁给他吗？为什么他不吻我，吻我，吻我？我在想我敢不敢告诉他我简直像着了魔一样爱着他。”）

“迈克尔，你这么帅气，没人能够拒绝你的求婚。”

“亲爱的！”

（“我最好站起来。他可不知道怎么坐下。天，那场吉米不断让他重复的戏！”）

她站了起来，与迈克尔面对面。他拥抱了她，吻了她的嘴唇。

“我得告诉妈妈。”

他离开了她，奔向门口。

“妈妈，妈妈！”

不久，上校和格斯林太太都走了进来。他们脸上洋溢着快乐而期待的表情。

（“天，简直就是个圈套。”）

“妈妈，爸爸，我们订婚了。”

格斯林太太哭了起来。她迈着笨拙的步子走到朱莉娅面前，伸手抱住了她，然后开始抽泣，亲吻她。上校则像男人那样紧紧握了一下他儿子的手，然后把朱莉娅从他妻子怀抱中拉出来，也亲吻了一下。他被深深地感动了。所有这些情感让朱莉娅激动，虽然她开心地微笑，但眼泪顺着脸颊流了下来。迈克尔看着这动人的场景，感同身受。

“我们来开香槟庆祝一下如何？”他说道，“我看妈妈和朱莉娅都太激动了。”

“女士们，上帝保佑她们。”上校在斟满酒后说道。

第五章

此刻，朱莉娅翻到了她穿婚纱的照片。

“上帝，我的样子看起来真怪。”

他们决定不对外公开他们订婚的消息，除了吉米·兰顿和两三个剧团里的女孩还有她的服装师，朱莉娅谁都没说。虽然她让他们发誓保守秘密，但这消息还是在四十八小时内传遍了整个剧团。朱莉娅非常开心。她对迈克尔的爱更加强烈了，甚至愿意此时此刻就开心地举办婚礼。但迈克尔一直都很理智。现在，他们不过是一对地方上的演员，若是作为一对结了婚的夫妻，这对他们征战伦敦可没什么好处。朱莉娅非常明确地暗示迈克尔，她很愿意做他的情人，但他拒绝了。他是个正人君子，不愿意占她便宜。

“亲爱的，如果我不崇尚荣誉，我不会这么爱你。”他引用道。

他非常确定，如果在结婚前他们就住在一起，结婚后一定会后悔。朱莉娅为迈克尔的节操感到很骄傲。他是个亲切而深情的爱人，但不久迈克尔就不再把她当回事儿了；他的举止，友好但很随意，会让你觉得他们已经结婚好多年了。但他允许朱莉娅向他示爱。她喜欢蜷在他身边，让他的胳膊搂着自己的腰，脸贴着脸，而她最幸福的时刻就是将自己充满渴望的嘴唇贴压在他那有点单薄的嘴唇上。当他们并排坐着，虽然他更喜欢讨论他们所演的角色或者一起为未来作打算，但这仍旧让她非常开心。对于赞美他的外表，她从不感到厌倦。当她告诉迈克尔他的鼻子多么精致，他那一头拳曲的黄褐色头发多么可爱时，朱莉娅能感受到他更加用力的拥抱并看到他眼中的柔情，这对她来讲如天堂一般美妙。

“亲爱的，你会让我像孔雀那样忘乎所以的。”

“但假意说你没那么帅气是多么愚蠢的事情啊。”

朱莉娅确实这么认为，她这么说自然是因为她喜欢这样表达，但同时也是因为她知道他喜欢听这些。他对她也有感情和崇拜，他与她相处轻松，对她有信任感，但她很清楚他并不爱她。她安慰自己，迈克尔已经尽他所能地爱她了，而且她觉得当他们结婚后，睡在一起，她会用她的热情感染他，激发起他同样的热情。同时，她不断练习自己的机智圆滑和自我控制。她知道她不能让他觉得自己无趣。她也知道她绝不能让他感到自己是个负担或者是一份责任。他可能会为了一场高尔夫游戏或是为了与一个偶然相识的人吃顿午餐就对她不管不顾，然而，她丝毫不会让他感受到自己心中的不悦。当她察觉到她作为一位女演员所取得的成功会强化他对她的感情时，朱莉娅便更加努力地演好戏。

在他们订婚一年后，一个正寻找演员的美国经理听说了吉米·兰顿的轮演剧目剧团后，来到米德尔普尔，便被迈克尔吸引。他递给迈克尔一张便条，邀请他第二天下午到自己所在的酒店见面。迈克尔激动得不能呼吸，当即拿了纸条给朱莉娅看；这唯一的解释就是那位美国经理会邀请他出演一个角色。她的心沉了下来，但她假装跟他一样兴奋，第二天和他一起来到酒店。当迈克尔和那位伟人见面的时候，她在酒店大厅等着。

“祝我好运，”当他转身离开朱莉娅走进电梯的时候，他悄悄说道，“这简直太好了，都不像是真的。”

朱莉娅坐在一个大的皮制扶手椅中，满心希望那个美国经理所提供的角色会遭到迈克尔的拒绝，或者工资太低让迈克尔无法接受。或者他会让迈克尔朗读那个角色的台词，然后发现迈克尔无法诠释这个角色。但半小时后，当她看到迈克尔朝她走来，双眼发亮，步履轻快，她就知道他成功了。那一刻她感到自己要吐了，当她强迫自己展现一个热情洋溢的微笑时，她感到自己的肌肉都是僵硬的。

“一切都很好。他说这是一个非常棒的角色，饰演一个男孩，十九岁。会在纽约上演八到十周，然后是巡演。会跟约翰·德鲁一起工作四十周。一周二百五十美金。”

“哦，宝贝，对你来说这简直太好了。”

很明显他很快就接受了这个邀请。拒绝这个想法从来没有在他脑子里出现过。

“那我，我，”她想，“即便有人一周给我一千美金，如果需要我跟迈克尔分开，我也不会同意的。”

浓重的绝望笼罩了她。她什么都做不了。她必须假装和他一样开心。他激动得甚至无法安静地坐着，拉着她走入外面拥挤的街道。

“这是个绝佳的机会。当然，美国花费高，但一周五十美金应该够我花销了，他们说美国人都非常好客，那么我应该能吃到不少免费餐食。我觉得这四十周里我能存下八千美金，这是一千六百英镑啊。”

（“他不爱我。他一点都不在乎我。我恨他。我想杀了他。让那美国经理见鬼去吧。”）

“如果他第二年还聘用我，我一周会有三百美金。这就是说只用两年我就能存四千英镑了，几乎够开剧院的钱了。”

“第二年！”朱莉娅差点失去控制，她的声音带着浓重的哭腔，“难道你说你会离开两年吗？”

“哦，当然我明年夏天会回来。他们会付我回来的路费，这样我就可以住在家里，没有什么开销。”

“我不知道没有你我怎么办。”

她说这些话时语气欢快，听起来像是奉承，但口吻很随意。

“夏天我们会有不少时间在一起，而且你知道的，在外面一两年时间会一晃而过。”

迈克尔漫无目的地走着，但朱莉娅神不知鬼不觉地把他领到她希望他去的地方，现在他们来到剧团门口。她停了下来。

“我们一会儿见。我得去找吉米。”他的脸沉了下来。

“你现在不能离开我！我必须找人说会话。我以为趁戏还没开始我们可以一起去吃点东西。”

“我十分抱歉。吉米要见我，你知道他是什么样的人。”

迈克尔冲她甜蜜而和蔼地笑了笑。

“好吧，那你去吧。我不会因为一次让我失望就生你的气的。”

他径直走入剧院，而她从后台入口也进入剧院。吉米·兰顿在屋顶下给自己安排了一个极小的公寓，从阳台可以进去。她按响门铃，吉米为她开了门。他有点惊讶，但很高兴见到她。

“你好，朱莉娅，请进。”

她一句话也没说，径直从他身旁走过。当他们来到杂乱无比的客厅时，发现四处都是剧本文件、书和其他垃圾，桌子旁的餐盘上还有他剩余的简单午餐。她转过身，面对着他，下巴绷得紧紧的，眉头紧蹙。

“你这个魔鬼！”

她动作敏捷地走向他，双手抓住了他解开的衬衫领子，用力摇晃他。他试图从她手里挣脱，但朱莉娅很强壮凶猛。

“停下来。停下来！”

“你这个魔鬼，畜生，肮脏下流的男人。”

他挥拳出击，摊开手掌重重地扇了她一巴掌。她本能地松开了抓着他的双手，捂着脸颊，她被他打疼了，顿时大哭起来。

“你这个畜生。你竟然卑鄙下流到对一个女人动手。”

“亲爱的，收起你那些废话。你难道不知道，如果有个女人打我，我肯定会还手的吗？”

“我没有打你。”

“你他妈的差点掐死我。”

“你活该。上帝啊，我简直想要杀了你。”

“现在，坐下来，我给你倒点酒，你平静一下。然后，你可以告诉我到底怎么了。”

朱莉娅在四周寻找一张能让她轻松地陷进去的大椅子。

“上帝，这地方就像个猪圈。你为什么就不能找个做家务的女人来收拾一下？”

她生气地把堆在椅子上的书全部推到了地板上，然后一屁股坐下，开始伤心地哭起来。吉米为她倒了一杯烈性威士忌，加了一点苏打水，让她喝了下去。

“朱莉娅，所有这些托斯卡(1)似的行为到底是为了什么？”

“迈克尔要去美国了。”

“是吗？”

她挣脱了他搭在她肩上的胳膊，“你怎么能这么做？你怎么能这么做？”

“这跟我一点关系都没有。”

“一派谎言。我想你甚至不知道那个可恶的美国经理来到米德尔普尔了吧。当然是你搞的鬼。你这么做就是为了故意拆散我们。”

“哦，亲爱的，你误解我了。事实上我不介意告诉你，我跟他说的是他可以从剧团里挑选任何他喜欢的人，除了迈克尔·格斯林。”

当吉米说这些话的时候，朱莉娅并没有看他的眼神，但如果她看了的话一定会想为什么吉米看上去那么开心，仿佛他的小诡计得逞了一样。

“包括我？”她说道。

“我知道他不会选女演员的。他们已经有很多女演员了。他们想要男演员，那种能展示他们的戏服并且不会在客厅随地吐痰的男演员。”

“哦，吉米，别让迈克尔走。我受不了。”

“我如何阻止得了？他的合同到这个演出季末就结束了。而且对他来说这是个千载难逢的好机会。”

“但我爱他。我想要他。假设他在美国遇到其他人呢。假设某个美国有钱的女继承人爱上了他呢。”

“如果他不再像我想象的那样爱你，你最好离开他。”

这句话又激起了朱莉娅的怒火。

“你这个恶心的太监，你对爱情知道什么？”

“这些女人啊，”吉米叹气道，“如果你试图跟她们上床，她们说你是肮脏的老男人；如果你不跟她们上床，她们说你是恶心的老太监。”

“你不明白。他那么英俊，她们会一批批地拜倒在他脚下，可怜的家伙，他那么容易被奉承话影响。两年里什么都有可能发生。”

“怎么是两年？”

“如果他成功的话，他会再待一年。”

“那你千万别为这个担心。他会在演出季结束的时候回来的，而且是永远回来。那个经理只看过他出演《康蒂妲》。这是唯一他演得还说得过去的角色。我的话搁在这里，用不了多久他们就会发现他们签了一个木偶。他会让他们大跌眼镜的。”

“关于表演你又懂什么？”

“一切。”

“我想挖出你的眼睛来。”

“我警告你，如果你再动我一下，我就不会只是扇你嘴巴了，我会给你下巴来一记重拳，让你至少一周都不能舒服地吃饭。”

“上帝，我相信你能做得出来。你还能算得上一位绅士吗？”

“即便我喝醉也不会是位绅士。”

朱莉娅咯咯笑了，这让吉米觉得最糟糕的场面已经过去了。

“现在你同我一样清楚，你的演技远远在他之上。我告诉你，你将是继肯德尔夫人(2)之后最伟大的女演员。为什么要让一个永远会是你负担的男人阻碍你？如果你经营剧院，他会想跟你演对手戏。亲爱的，他永远配不上你。”

“他有帅气的外表。我会带着他。”

“你对自己很有信心是吗？但你错了。如果你想成功，你就不能让一个不够格的男主角跟你搭档。”

“我不在乎。比起成功然后嫁给别人，我宁愿嫁给他然后失败。”

“你是处女吗？”

朱莉娅又咯咯笑了。

“我不知道这关你什么事，但我确实是。”

“我也觉得你是。那么，除非你有什么顾虑，在我们停演后，为什么你不跟他一起去巴黎待两周？他到八月才会去美国。这样你就可以对他放心了。”

“他不会的。他不是那种人。你看，他是个正人君子。”

“即使是上等人也要繁衍后代。”

“你不明白。”朱莉娅傲然地说。

“我敢打赌你也不明白。”

朱莉娅不屑于回答他。她非常不开心。

“我跟你讲，离开他我无法生活。当他离开了，我自己怎么办？”

“继续跟着我。我会与你签一年合同。我有很多新角色想让你尝试，而且我已经找到一个年轻演员，是个新秀。当你跟一个与你有回应有共鸣的家伙一起演戏，你会惊奇地发现表演原来这么容易。你一周可以拿十二英镑。”

朱莉娅向他走去，目光锐利地盯着他的眼睛。

“你是不是为了让我再待一年而这么做的？你是不是故意伤我的心、毁了我的生活，就是为了让我待在你这腐朽的剧院里？”

“我发誓我没有。我喜欢你，钦佩你。我们的生意从未像过去两年里这样好。但该死的，我不会对你玩那么肮脏的手段。”

“你这个骗子，肮脏的骗子。”

“我发誓这都是事实。”

“证明给我看。”她激动地说。

“我如何证明给你看？你知道我是很体面的人。”

“给我一周十五英镑，我就信你。”

“一周十五英镑？你知道我们的收入是多少。我如何能给你那么多？好吧。但我会自己掏腰包给你那三英镑。”

“我才不管呢。”

————————————————————

(1) 托斯卡（Tosca）是意大利歌剧作家普契尼（Giacomo Puccini，1858—1924）所作同名歌剧中的女主人公。罗马画家马里奥·卡瓦拉多西因掩护政治犯安格洛蒂而被捕受刑，歌剧女演员托斯卡正热恋着他。警察总监斯卡皮亚被托斯卡迷住，答应让她的恋人获得自由。作为回报，她得委身于他。托斯卡被迫假意顺从，在警察总监刚写完假处决的命令后，趁其不备用刀刺死了他。黎明时，马里奥被带到刑场，托斯卡告诉他这只是假处决，谁料这是警察总监耍的花招，马里奥真的被处决了。这时刺死总监一事已经被人发现，并认定斯卡尔亚是托斯卡所杀。托斯卡陷入绝境并跳城墙自杀。

(2) 肯德尔夫人（Mrs. Kendal，1848—1935），英国著名女演员。

第六章

经过两周的排练后，原定由迈克尔出演的角色不再需要他饰演，之后的三四周他无所事事，等待有什么角色能够让他演。没过多久他就登台演出了，但那部剧只在纽约上演不到一个月。这部剧原本也要进行巡演；但由于不景气被撤掉了。在又一轮等待后，剧团让他出演一部戏剧中的角色，这样他好看的外表能发挥最大优势，而他的冷冰冰的表演则不太会被注意到，他以这部剧结束了这个演出季。没有人提起过要与他续约的事情。事实上，雇用他的那位经理对他的评价很刻薄。

“天，我得给那个兰顿点颜色看看，狗娘养的，”他说道，“当他把那根木头杵给我的时候，他很清楚自己在做什么。”

朱莉娅经常给迈克尔写信，长篇的情话和闲话，而迈克尔一周回一封信，不长不短端端正正就四页纸。他总是以致她最好的爱结尾，并在签名前写上“你亲爱的”，但信件的其他部分更多是告知性的，缺乏情感。然而，她还是在痛苦的焦虑中等待这些信的到来，然后把它们读了一遍又一遍。虽然他写得很开心，几乎不说戏院的事情，除了他们给他的角色都很糟糕，要出演的那些戏剧都不值一提，但戏剧界消息传得很快，朱莉娅知道他的进展并不顺利。

“我这么想可能很恶毒，”她想，“但谢天谢地，谢天谢地。”

当迈克尔告诉她回程的日期时，她简直无法抑制自己内心的喜悦。她让吉米把她的演出安排好，以便她能去利物浦接他。

“如果船到晚了，我可能会待一晚。”她告诉吉米。

他讽刺地笑了笑。

“我想你肯定认为借着回家的兴奋之情你能实施你的诡计了。”

“你真是个可恶的小人。”

“别装了，亲爱的。我给你的建议就是，把他灌醉，然后把你同他锁在一间屋子里，告诉他除非让你成了他的女人，否则你不会让他出去的。”

朱莉娅启程时，吉米陪她去了车站。当她要上火车时，他握着她的手，拍了拍。

“紧张吗，亲爱的？”

“哦，亲爱的吉米，我欣喜若狂，同时又万分焦虑。”

“那么，祝你好运。千万别忘了，他一点都配不上你。你年轻，漂亮，还是英国最棒的女演员。”

当火车驶离车站，吉米去了车站的酒吧，要了一杯威士忌苏打。“上帝，这些凡人何等愚蠢。”他叹息道。朱莉娅站在空空如也的车厢里，看着镜子里的自己。

“嘴巴太大，脸太肥，鼻子肉太多。谢谢上帝，我眼睛还算漂亮，腿也长得不错。非常精致的腿。我是不是妆化得有点浓。他不喜欢下了舞台还化妆。不涂腮红的话我看上去就太惨了。我的睫毛还可以。管它呢，我看起来还不错。”

因为直到最后一刻都不能确定吉米会不会让她休假，朱莉娅并没有告诉迈克尔她会去接他。见到朱莉娅，迈克尔感到很意外，也非常开心。他那双漂亮的眼睛充满快乐的光芒。

“你比之前更加可爱了。”她说道。

“哦，别说这傻话了，”他笑道，深情地捏着她的胳膊，“你可以吃完晚饭后再回去，是吗？”

“我可以明天再回去。我已经在阿德尔菲酒店订了两个房间，这样晚饭后我们可以好好谈谈。”

“阿德尔菲酒店有点过于奢侈了吧，不是吗？”

“哦，你又不是天天从美国回来。管它花多少钱呢。”

“你真是个奢侈的小东西。我不知道我们什么时候到岸，所以我告诉我家人等我到了切尔滕纳姆我会给他们发电报。我会跟他们说我明天去那儿。”

当他们到达酒店，迈克尔来到朱莉娅的房间，像朱莉娅建议的那样，这样他们能安静地说会话。她坐在他膝盖上，胳膊缠绕在他的脖子上，她的脸紧贴着迈克尔的脸。

“哦，回到家真是太好了。”她感叹道。

“不用你说。”他说道，并没有理解她指的是他的怀抱，而不是他的到来。

“你还喜欢我吗？”

“当然。”

她温柔地亲吻他。

“哦，你不知道我是如何思念你。”

“我在美国的表现让人大跌眼镜，”他说道，“我没有在信里告诉你，因为我想这会让你担心。他们认为我的演技糟糕透了。”

“迈克尔。”她叫道，好像无法相信他刚刚说的话。

“事实上，我觉得我可能太英式了。他们不愿再跟我续签一年的合同。我不认为他们会跟我续签，但我还是按惯例问了问他们是否愿意，他们坚决地拒绝了我，任何价钱都不考虑。”

朱莉娅沉默了。她看起来非常担心，但她的心脏因狂喜而怦怦欢跳。

“我真的不介意，你知道的。我不喜欢美国。当然，不可否认，我碰了一鼻子灰，但唯一能做的就是笑一笑然后忍耐。要是你认识我必须要打交道的那些人就好了。因为与他们之中的一些人相比，吉米·兰顿是个很好的绅士。即使他们想和我续约，我也会拒绝的。”

虽然他将这件事说得很轻巧，但当时朱莉娅还是感到他受到了沉重的打击。他肯定忍受了不少不愉快的事情。她讨厌看到他被折磨得这么不开心，但，天哪，她如释重负。

“你现在打算怎么办？”她静静地问道。

“我打算先回家，然后整理一下头绪。然后我会去伦敦，看看能否拿到一个角色。”

她知道让他回到米德尔普尔没有意义。吉米·兰顿不会要他。

“我想，你不会想跟我一起去吧？”

朱莉娅简直不相信自己的耳朵。

“我？亲爱的，你知道我会跟你去这世界上任何一个地方。”

“你的合同得到这个演出季末才结束，如果你想换个地方你一定得去伦敦尝试一下。在美国，我存下我能存的每一分钱，他们叫我吝啬鬼，但我不在意，他们尽管去说。我带回来差不多一千两百到一千五百英镑。”

“迈克尔，你究竟是怎么存了这么多钱的？”

“我不怎么花钱，你知道的，”他开心地笑了笑，“当然，这点钱不够开剧场，但足够结婚了。我是说，如果我们无法一下子就有角色或者我们几个月没有工作，我们至少还有这些钱可以用着。”

朱莉娅花了一两秒才明白他的意思。

“你是说，我们现在就结婚吗？”

“当然这么做有点冒险，未来一片空白，但人总得时不时冒冒险。”

朱莉娅双手捧着迈克尔的脸，亲吻了他的唇。然后，她叹了口气。

“亲爱的，你太好了，你同希腊之神一样美好，但你是我这辈子认识的最大的傻瓜。”

当晚他们去剧院看了表演，晚饭的时候喝了香槟，庆祝他们的重逢，为他们的未来干杯。当迈克尔送她回到她房间时，她冲他抬起头。

“你想让我在走廊里跟你说晚安吗？我就进去待一会儿。”

“最好不要，亲爱的。”她庄重而娴静地说道。

她感觉自己如同大家闺秀一般，要维护古老望族的所有传统；她的纯洁如同一颗价格不菲的珍珠；她还感到自己给迈克尔留下了一个非常好的印象：他当然是正人君子，“该死”，她自然也应该是位高贵的淑女。她对自己的表现满意极了，当她走进自己的房间，锁门的时候发出一些响动。她开始在房间里大摇大摆地走来走去，优雅地向想象中的那些奉承的随从点头致意。她伸出自己如百合般雪白的手，让颤抖的老仆人亲吻（当她还是婴儿的时候，他总是把她放在膝盖上逗弄），当他那苍白的嘴唇贴上她的手时，她感到什么东西掉在了手上。那是一滴眼泪。

第七章

幸亏迈克尔性情冷淡，否则他们结婚第一年就应该已经吵得不可开交了。只有在迈克尔获得一个角色或者前天晚上欢快的聚会上他喝了几杯香槟后，才能让迈克尔那满脑子的务实思想转变成谈情说爱的思维。如果第二天与别人有约或者是要打高尔夫，他需要保持大脑清醒，那么任何谄媚和诱惑对他都不起作用。朱莉娅在他面前歇斯底里。她嫉妒他的那些绿屋俱乐部的朋友，嫉妒那些把他从她身边带走的体育运动，还嫉妒他打着建立人脉的名义而参加的男人们的聚餐。最让她怒不可遏的是当自己泪流满面大哭大闹的时候，他却极其平静地坐在那里，握着双手，帅气的脸上呈现好脾气的微笑，好像她做的一切只不过是让自己看起来无理取闹。

“你不会觉得我在追求别的女人吧？”他问道。

“我怎么知道？很明显你一点都不在乎我。”

“你知道在我的世界里唯一的女人就是你。”

“上帝！”

“我不知道你想要什么。”

“我想要爱。我以为我嫁给了全英国最帅的男人，而实际上我嫁了一个布偶。”

“别犯傻了。我与其他正常的英国男人没什么两样。我不是意大利的街头手风琴师。”

她在家里走来走去。他们在白金汉门附近有一套小公寓，虽然空间不大，但她极尽所能将它布置得漂亮一些。她朝天空张开双臂。

“我难道是斜眼或是驼背吗？我老到五十岁了吗？我就这么对你没有吸引力？乞求被爱简直是奇耻大辱。痛苦，痛苦。”

“这个动作很好，亲爱的，活像你在投板球。记住这个姿势。”

她瞥了他一下，眼神中充满不屑。

“你就只会想这些。我的心碎了，而你却在讲我偶然间做出的一个动作。”

但他从她的表情看出，她正在将这个姿势添加到记忆里。他知道，时机合适时，她会巧妙地利用到这个动作。

“毕竟爱情不是一切。当时机、地点合适时，爱情非常美妙。我们蜜月的时候很开心，那就是蜜月的意义，但现在我们必须开始工作。”

他们很幸运，设法在同一部剧中拿到了不错的角色，这部戏剧后来很成功。其中，朱莉娅有一场戏让她大显身手，赢得了满堂喝彩，而迈克尔令人震惊的美貌也引起了观众的注意。凭借他的绅士风度和谈笑风生的温雅气质，迈克尔让他们俩获得不少曝光机会，他们的照片被刊登在一些画报上。他们还接到很多宴会的邀请。虽然迈克尔非常节俭，花钱款待那些可能对他们有帮助的人却从不犹豫。朱莉娅对他在这些场合表现出的慷慨大方印象深刻。一位演员兼剧院经理邀请朱莉娅出演他下部戏的女主角，没有给迈克尔角色，朱莉娅想拒绝这个邀请，但迈克尔没有应允。他说，工作上他们不能感情用事。最终，他在一部古装戏里获得一个角色。

战争爆发时他们都在演出。让朱莉娅感到既骄傲又痛苦的是，迈克尔即将入伍。他父亲的一位老战友在战争办公室身居要职，于是在他父亲的帮助下，迈克尔很快就拿到了委任状。当他远赴法国前线，朱莉娅为曾经对他的那些责骂深深后悔，并下定决心，如果他战死疆场，她便自杀。她想成为一名护士，这样便能一起去法国，至少可以同他在一片土地上，但迈克尔让她明白，国家需要她继续表演，而她无法拒绝这个或许是他死前的最后愿望。迈克尔在战争中如鱼得水。他在团部集体中很受欢迎，旧部队的军官们很快就接纳了他，一点都不嫌弃他曾是个演员。似乎军人家庭的背景已经给他烙上了印记，他本能地就像职业军人那样做事和思考。他行为缜密，性格随和，又懂得如何灵活地运用关系；因而他势必成为某位将军的参谋部成员。他展现了出色的组织能力，在总司令部里度过了战争的最后三年。最后他被晋升为少校，荣获战功十字勋章和荣誉军团勋章。

与此同时，朱莉娅演了一连串重要的角色，已经被公认为最优秀的年轻女演员。整个战争期间，剧院非常繁忙，由于她出演长期上演的戏剧，获益不少，工资上涨。在迈克尔的建议下，她让极不情愿的剧院经理付给她八十英镑的周薪。迈克尔会在假期的时候回到英国，那时，朱莉娅会极度开心。虽然他在法国并不比在新西兰放羊更危险，但朱莉娅每次都会将这些时光当作迈克尔在这世上的最后时光来度过。她对他更加的温柔体贴、宽容，就好像他刚刚从战壕中回来一样。

然而，就在战争结束之前，她对他的爱意消失了。

那时她怀孕了。迈克尔认为把孩子生下来的做法不明智，但她已经快三十岁了，如果他们想要小孩，就不能再拖延了；她在这一行里已站稳了脚跟，消失几个月应该没什么问题，再加上迈克尔随时可能客死他乡——虽然他说过他非常安全，但他这么说仅仅是为了安慰她，而且有的时候连将军们也会死掉——如果她想在迈克尔战死后继续活下去，她必须有他们的孩子作为依靠。这个婴儿会在年底出生。

她从未像这样期待过迈克尔放假回英国。虽然她自我感觉良好，但她极其渴望感受他的拥抱，她感到有点迷茫、无助，她想要迈克尔保护她。他回来了，穿着合身的制服，肩章上的红标和皇冠格外显眼，他看起来英俊极了。总司令部的艰难困苦让他长胖了不少，他的皮肤晒黑了。剪短的头发，风趣的个性，还有军人的举止，让他各个方面看起来都像极了军人。他心情很好，不仅因为可以回家待几天，还因为战争即将结束。他打算尽快离开部队。当你还有点影响力的时候，如果不利用它，那它又有什么用？那么多年轻演员离开舞台去参军，要么出于爱国情结，要么被国内人民的爱国情结胁迫，于是这些主角角色就落在不适合服兵役或者严重受伤不得不被遣返的人的头上。此刻出现了一个绝佳的空档时期，迈克尔知道，如果他能尽快复员，他就能选择自己喜欢的角色。当他再次回到公众的视线时，他们就可以开始寻找一家剧院了，凭借朱莉娅目前的名望，他们可以开始自己经营了。

他俩聊到深夜，然后上床睡觉。她放荡地蜷缩在他怀里，他双手抱住了她。三个月的禁欲让他欲火焚身。

“你是最棒的妻子。”他喃喃道。

他把嘴贴到她的嘴上。她突然有了一阵淡淡的反感。她不得不强忍着才没把他推开。之前，在她多情的鼻孔里，他的身体，那年轻美丽的身体，似乎有鲜花和蜂蜜的香味，这是她迷恋他的原因之一。然而，现在，这种味道奇怪地消失了。她意识到，他闻起来不再像个少年，而是个男人。她感到有点恶心。她无法回应他的热情，她希望他的欲望能尽快得到满足，然后扭过身去睡觉。她躺在床上，久久未能入睡。她感到失望沮丧。她的心沉了下去，因为她知道，她丢失了对她而言非常珍贵的东西，她可怜自己，有大哭的冲动；但同时，她内心充满胜利的感觉，似乎是对曾经他给她带来那么多不愉快的一种报复；她终于摆脱了迷恋他的感情束缚，扬扬得意起来。现在，她可以和他平起平坐了。她在床上伸了伸腿，如释重负地叹了口气。

“上帝啊，做自己的主人真好。”

他们在屋里吃了早饭，朱莉娅靠在床上，迈克尔坐在她身边的一张小桌子旁。她看着他读报纸。三个月的时间可能让他发生这么大的变化吗？要不就是这么多年来，她还一直把他视为那个刚来米德尔普尔舞台上排练的英俊少年，自那时起她便被迷得神魂颠倒？他仍旧很潇洒，毕竟他只有三十六岁，但他不再是个男孩了；一头短发，经受了风吹日晒的皮肤，细细的皱纹开始爬上他光洁的额头和眼睛下方，他绝对已经是个男人了。他失去了那小马般的魅力，他的行为也已定型。虽然每次的变化都很小，但放到一起后，在她那敏锐、精明的双眼里，就成了巨大的变化。他是一个中年男人了。

他们还住在刚来伦敦时住的那套小公寓里。虽然朱莉娅挣了不少钱，但那时迈克尔在服兵役，也就没有任何搬家的需求。但现在他们要迎来一个婴儿，这个公寓显然太小了。朱莉娅在摄政公园附近找了一所她非常喜欢的房子。她想赶紧搬过去，在那里坐月子。

房子面朝花园。一层是会客厅，二层有两间卧室，三层的两间屋子可以改成白天和夜间的婴儿房。迈克尔对一切都很满意；连价格他都认为合理。在过去四年里，朱莉娅挣的钱比迈克尔多了不知多少，因而她主动提出要自己掏钱装修房子。他们站在一间卧室里。

“我可以用原来卧室的家具凑合，”她说道，“我会去梅谱尔家具店给你置办一套好家具。”

“我不想花太多钱，”他笑道，“我估计不会太经常使用它，你知道的。”

他想和她睡在一张床上。虽然没有激情，但他是温柔亲切的，而且他对他们肉体相依有种动物般的欲望。很长的时间里，这是她最大的慰藉。现在，这想法却让她愤怒不已。

“哦，我觉得在孩子出生前我们不能再乱来了。直到我生完孩子，我打算让你自己睡。”

“我没想到这点。如果你觉得这样对孩子好的话……”

第八章

迈克尔在战争结束的那一刻就复员了，紧接着就接演了一个角色。再次回到舞台的他，比起离开舞台时，演技大有长进。他在军队中练就的风趣在舞台上很有效。他是个身体健壮、生气活泼的正常人，总是笑容满面，有时哈哈大笑。他很适合出演发生在会客室的喜剧。他那轻柔的声音让一句挑逗的台词有了特殊效果，虽然他从未让求爱戏看起来逼真，但他能很好地演绎打趣的爱情戏，把求婚演得像笑话，或者讲一段爱情告白时更像是在自我嘲笑，他的表演方式让观众们产生兴趣。他从不试图表演除他以外的人。他擅长演花花公子、绅士般的赌棍、禁卫军官兵和生性善良的年轻坏蛋。经理们也喜欢他。他工作非常努力，并且听从指挥。只要他能接到角色，他并不在意演的是什么。他力争他认为合适的薪金，但如果达不到，那么少些也行，总比闲着强。

他仔细地做自己的计划。战争结束后的第一个冬天暴发了一场流感。他的父亲和母亲都在流感中死亡。他继承了大约四千英镑，再加上他和朱莉娅的储蓄，他们有了七千英镑。但剧院的租金同时也上涨了许多，演员的工资和舞台工作人员的薪水也都增加了，这意味着经营剧院的花销比战前多了许多。原本足够开剧院的钱现在却显得捉襟见肘。唯一的方法就是找一个有钱人和他们一起入伙，这样即使一开始出现一两次失败的经历也不会把他们逐出这圈子。据说，你总能在城市里找到个傻瓜开张数目不小的支票让你制作一部戏剧，但当你谈到实际问题时，你发现，他们的一个重要条件是得让他们感兴趣的某位漂亮女演员来出演主角。多年前，迈克尔和朱莉娅开玩笑说会有个有钱的老女人爱上迈克尔并出钱让他开剧院。他早就知道，没有哪个富有的老女人会出钱让一个妻子是个女演员的年轻男演员经营剧院的，尤其是他对妻子还绝对忠诚。最后，确实有一位有钱的女人掏了这笔钱，然而她并不老，让她感兴趣的人也不是迈克尔，而是朱莉娅。

德·弗里斯太太是个寡妇。她矮小敦实，长着精致的犹太人的鼻子和眼睛，充满活力，性格既奔放又懦弱，还有些男子汉的气概。她对舞台充满热情，在吉米·兰顿的轮演剧目剧团看似要被迫关门的时候几次慷慨解囊。于是，在朱莉娅和迈克尔决定在伦敦碰碰运气时，吉米·兰顿写信给她，希望她能给予他们帮助。她在米德尔普尔看过朱莉娅的表演。她为他们举办宴会，让这对年轻的演员有机会认识剧院经理，并邀请他们在她吉尔福德附近的豪华大房子里住下来，他们在那里享受到做梦都没想过的奢侈生活。她不太喜欢迈克尔。朱莉娅经常收到多莉·德·弗里斯送来的鲜花，她用鲜花填满朱莉娅的公寓和化妆间，她还送朱莉娅很多礼物，例如包包、小手袋、次等宝石串成的项链、胸针等。朱莉娅自然很开心，但她只把多莉的慷慨归因于她喜欢她的才华。当迈克尔去了前线，多莉提出让朱莉娅搬到她在蒙塔古广场的别墅中居住，朱莉娅拒绝了，并表达了她极度的感谢之情。多莉叹了口气，掉了滴眼泪，更加爱慕她。当罗杰出生时，朱莉娅请她做孩子的教母。

有段时间，迈克尔一直在想多莉·德·弗里斯出这笔钱的可能性，但他非常明白，虽然她会为了朱莉娅同意这么做，但是朱莉娅不会为了他而这么做。朱莉娅拒绝向她求助。

“她对我们已经非常好了，我真的不能再去向她提更多要求，而且如果她拒绝了该多丢人啊。”

“这个险值得一冒，而且即使她亏了这笔钱，她也不会在乎。我相信你一定能说服她，如果你肯尝试一下。”

朱莉娅很清楚自己能说服多莉。迈克尔在某些方面头脑很简单；而她也不愿意告诉他已经明摆着的事实。

然而，一旦迈克尔认定了某件事情就不可能轻易放弃。周六晚上的表演结束后，他们开着朱莉娅在迈克尔生日时送给他的车，准备去吉尔福德与多莉共度周末。这是个美妙而温暖的夜晚。迈克尔已经购买了——虽然写支票的时候心痛不已——三部他们俩都喜欢的剧本，并且他已经打听到一家条件合理的剧院。一切都已准备好了，除了钱。他让朱莉娅这周末抓住机会向多莉提及此事。

“你自己问吧，”朱莉娅不耐烦地说道，“我跟你说，我不会去的。”

“我去问，她不会同意的。你动动小指就能让她跟着你转。”

“现在我们也大概对投资戏剧有了些了解。人们投资戏剧有两种原因，要么他们想要名声，要么他们爱上了某个人。很多人谈论艺术，但很难看到有人会为了艺术真的出钱，除非他们自己会从中得利。”

“那么，我们就给多莉她想要的知名度。”

“那不是她想要的。”

“你什么意思？”

“你猜不出来吗？”

他明白了，惊讶得不得了，以至于连车速都降了下来。朱莉娅怀疑的会是真的吗？他从来没有想过多莉有多么喜欢他，至于多莉爱上了他——这种想法从来没有在他脑子里出现。当然朱莉娅有双犀利的眼睛，几乎什么都逃不过她这双眼，但她是个爱嫉妒的小东西，她总是觉得女人们都力图博得他的宠爱。虽然多莉曾经在圣诞节的时候送过他一副袖扣，但他以为多莉这么做只是避免让他感到被冷落，因为她送给朱莉娅一个至少花了两百镑的胸针。那可能只是多莉的诡计。他可以发誓，他从未做过任何让多莉误解他们之间可能会有什么事情发生的事。朱莉娅笑了。

“不，亲爱的，她爱的并不是你。”

朱莉娅看出他在想什么，这让他觉得不安。你几乎无法向她隐瞒什么。

“那你为什么要让我这么想？我乞求上帝，你能表达得清楚一些吗？这样别人才能明白你的意思。”

朱莉娅这么做了。

“我从未听过这种无稽之谈，”他喊道，“你的思想太肮脏了，朱莉娅！”

“别胡说八道，亲爱的。”

“我不相信你刚刚说的有一句是真话。毕竟我头上也长了眼睛。难道你想说我就从未注意到吗？”这是她认识迈克尔这么久以来，他最暴躁的一次，“即使你说的是真的，我也相信你能照顾好自己。这是个千载难逢的好机会，我觉得如果不抓住的话简直就是愚昧至极。”

“《一报还一报》中的克劳第奥和伊莎贝拉。(1)”

“说什么混账话，朱莉娅。上帝啊，我是个绅士。”

“‘犯我者必受惩。’”

他们在暗藏着暴风雨的沉寂中开车走完了剩下的路途。德·弗里斯太太还在等待他们。

“我不想还没见到你就去上床睡觉了。”她说道，拥抱了朱莉娅并亲吻了她两个脸颊。然后，她和迈克尔轻快地握了握手。

第二天，朱莉娅在床上读着星期日的报纸，度过了一个愉快的早晨。她先读了有关剧院的消息，然后是八卦专栏，之后读了关于女人的部分，最后瞧了一眼世界新闻的头条。书评被直接忽略，她搞不懂为什么这部分要占据那么大的篇幅。住在隔壁的迈克尔进来说了一声早安后就去花园了。现在，她门外有人小心翼翼地敲门，然后多莉走了进来。她那双又大又黑的眼睛闪着光芒。她坐在床上，握住了朱莉娅的手。

“亲爱的，我已经跟迈克尔谈过了，我会出钱让你经营剧院的。”

朱莉娅的心脏突然狂跳不止。

“哦，你千万别这么做。迈克尔本就不该去问你。我不会同意的。你对我们已经非常非常好了。”

多莉俯下身来，亲吻了朱莉娅的嘴唇。她的声音比平常还要低沉，带着点微微的颤音。

“哦，我的宝贝，难道你不知道这世上没什么是我不会为你做的吗？一切都会非常美好；它将让我们的关系更加密切，而且我会为你感到非常骄傲。”

她们听到迈克尔在走廊里吹口哨，当他走进房间时，多莉转身面向他，泪眼蒙眬。

“我刚刚告诉了她。”

他兴奋得眉飞色舞。

“多么伟大的女人啊！”他坐在床的另一边，握着朱莉娅另外那只手，“你说呢，朱莉娅？”

她朝他瞥了一眼，心事满满。

“‘这原是你要这样做的，乔治·当丹。’”(2)

“你说什么？”

“莫里哀。”

在合作协议签署完成、迈克尔办妥了剧院秋天营业的手续之后，他立刻雇用了一个宣传代理人。报纸上刊登了多篇报道宣布这一新投资，迈克尔和这个宣传代理人还为他和朱莉娅准备了媒体采访。他们的照片刊登在各种周刊上，其中有单人照还有合照，有罗杰出镜的以及没有罗杰出镜的。家庭信息中最有价值的都被利用了起来。他们无法决定买下的三部剧中首先上演哪一部。某天下午，当朱莉娅坐在卧室读小说时，迈克尔手里拿着剧本走了进来。

“看这里，我想要你立刻读这个剧本。这是刚刚从一个中介那里得来的。我觉得棒极了。只是我们必须现在就做决定。”

朱莉娅放下小说。

“我现在就读。”

“我在楼下。你读完了告诉我，我会上来跟你讨论。这剧本有一个非常精彩的角色给你。”

朱莉娅读得很快，迅速浏览她不感兴趣的部分，但女主角的部分，也就是她要演的部分，她读得非常仔细。当她翻到最后一页，她拉响铃铛，让女仆（也是她的服装师）告诉迈克尔她在等他。

“你怎么想？”

“这个剧本不错。我看不出为什么会不成功。”

他听出她声调中的怀疑口吻。

“那么有什么问题？角色很精彩。我是说，这正是你最擅长演的角色，你会比世界上任何其他演员演得好。有很多喜剧部分，还有你想要的一切情感。”

“我知道女主角是不错的角色，我说的是男主角。”

“也是个非常好的角色。”

“我知道；但他已经五十岁了，如果你让他变得年轻点，那所有的意义就都消失了。而你肯定不想演一个中年男人。”

“但我没有想着要饰演那个角色。只有一个男人适合这个角色。蒙特·弗农。我们可以请到他。我演乔治。”

“但那是个非常小的角色，你不能演那个。”

“为什么不能？”

“但我以为我们经营剧院的目的就是能一起演主角啊。”

“哦，我一点都不在乎那个。只要我们能找到适合你演主角的剧本就行，我无所谓。也许下个剧本中会有个不错的角色适合我。”

朱莉娅靠到她的椅子上，泪水充满了她的双眼，顺着脸颊流下。

“哦，我真是个禽兽。”

他笑了笑，他的笑容还如同以往一样迷人。他走到她身边，跪了下来，拥抱了她。

“老天爷保佑，这位老太太现在怎么样啦？”

朱莉娅这会儿注视着迈克尔，心里想着，他以前究竟是用什么唤醒了她心中火热的激情。想到曾与他发生过的性关系，这让她感到恶心。幸运的是，他对朱莉娅为他布置的床非常满意。他并不是一个把性生活看得很重的人，因而当他发现朱莉娅不再对他有任何要求，这让他松了口气。他想一定是婴儿的出生让她平静下来，他早就想到可能会这样，现在他觉得没早点儿要小孩是个遗憾。当他有那么两三次，更多地出于友好而非欲望，建议恢复性关系，她借口拒绝了。要么是因为太累，身体不适，要么是第二天有两场演出，更不用说早上还要去试穿服装，他平静地接受了她的理由。朱莉娅比以前好相处了许多，她不再吵闹，而他从未像现在这样开心过。他的婚姻简直太幸福了，当他看到别人的婚姻时，他无法抑制地想自己属于幸运者中的一个。朱莉娅为人善良又聪明，像猴子那样聪明；你能同她讲世界上任何事情。她是一个人所能得到的最理想的伴侣。他甚至不会介意这么说，比起打一轮高尔夫，他宁愿和朱莉娅待上一整天。

朱莉娅惊讶地发现自己对迈克尔有一种怜悯之情，因为她已不再爱他。她是个善良的女人，她明白如果迈克尔知道自己对她毫不重要，这对迈克尔将会是一个痛苦的打击。她继续恭维他。她注意到，很久以来，他听到她称赞他那精致的鼻子和美丽的眼睛时都会扬扬得意。她想看看他能受得了多少赞美，这成了她自己的小消遣。她竭力夸奖他。但现在她更多地注意到他那张单薄没有曲线的嘴巴。随着他渐渐变老，迈克尔的嘴越来越难看，当他真正成了一个老人时，这张嘴将只剩下一条生硬冰冷的直线。他的节俭，早年的时候被认为有趣，是一个令人感动的特点，现在让她感到厌恶。当人们陷入困境时，尤其是舞台上的人们经常会遇到这样的情况，迈克尔会奉上亲切友好的慰问之词，却几乎从不给钱。当他捐了一基尼硬币，他都会觉得自己非常慷慨，捐献五英镑对他来说是极度奢侈的。他很快发现朱莉娅持家挥霍无度，坚持要从她手中接管过这个工作，以免除她的麻烦。在那之后，家里没什么浪费了。每一分钱都花得很值。朱莉娅想不明白为什么仆人们还会待在他们家里。那是因为迈克尔对他们非常和蔼可亲。迈克尔那真诚、欢乐、平易近人的态度让他们急于讨好他，当厨娘发现从某个屠夫那里买肉会一斤省下一分钱的时候，迈克尔和她都喜笑颜开，非常满意。一想到他对节俭的热情和他在舞台上呈现的那些满不在乎、挥霍无度的人物形成的反差，朱莉娅忍不住大笑。她时常以为迈克尔无法有慷慨的冲动；现在，就好像是这世上最自然的事情一样，他已经准备好站到一边，让她去抓住自己的机遇了。她感动得说不出话来。对于长期以来她对他不好的想法，朱莉娅感到强烈的自责。

————————————————————

(1) 在莎士比亚的喜剧《一报还一报》中，克劳第奥因未婚与情人生了孩子而被判处死刑，他姐姐修女伊莎贝拉为他向摄政安哲鲁恳求赦罪，安哲鲁见美色而起淫心，向伊莎贝拉提出若她能依从，便同意赦免她的弟弟。伊莎贝拉将这件事告诉狱中的弟弟，他竟要求姐姐牺牲贞操救他性命。

(2) 法语，“Vous l'avez voulu, Georges Dandin.”，引自莫里哀的喜剧《乔治·当丹》。